<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">      <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">The First Canticle (Exodus 15)</language><language id="Indonesian">Hoos Pertama (Keluaran 15)</language>         <language id="Arabic">الهوس الأول (خروح ١٥)</language>         <language id="Coptic">Tote afhwc n~je Mwu~c/c...</language>      </Title>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Tote afhwc n~je Mwu~c/c nem nens/ri m~Pic#l# e~taihwd/ n~te P[oic ouoh afjoc eyroujoc: je marenhwc e~Po#c#: je qen ouw~ou gar af[iw~ou.         </language>         <language id="English">            Then Moses and the children of Israel sang this song to the Lord, and spoke saying, “Let us sing to the Lord for He has triumphed gloriously.”         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Musa dan bangsa Israel </div><div>nyanyikan lagu ini bagi Tuhan dan berkata/, “Mari nyanyi bagi Tuhan </div><div>s'bab Ia t’lah menang dengan gemilang."</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            حينئذ سبح موسى وبنو اسرائيل بهذه التسبحة للرب وقالوا فلنسبح للرب لانه بالمجد قد تمجد.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouh~yo nem ou[acih~yo afberbwrou e~v~iom: oubo/~yoc nem ourefhwbc e~bol hijwi: afswpi n/i n~oucwt/ria~.         </language>         <language id="English">            The horse and its rider, He has thrown into the sea. The Lord is my strength and song, and He has become my salvation.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kuda dan penunggang-nya, Dia telah  lempar ke laut. Tuhan itu kekuatanku dan mazmurku, </div><div>Ia telah menjadi kes’lamatanku.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            الفرس وراكبه طرحهما فى البحر معينى وساترى صار لى خلاصآ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Vai pe Panou] ]na]w~ou naf: V] m~paiwt ]na[acf.         </language>         <language id="English">            He is my God and I will glorify Him, my father’s God and I will exalt Him.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dia Allahku ku ‘kan muliakan Dia, Dia Alla~h Bapaku dan ku ‘kan tinggikan Dia.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            هذا هو إلهى فأمجده أله أبى فأرفعه.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Po#c# petqomqem n~nibwtc: Po#c# pe pefran: nibere[woutc n~te Varaw~ nem tefjom t/rc afberbwrou e~v~iom.         </language>         <language id="English">            The Lord is a man of war, the Lord is His name. Pharaoh’s chariots and his army He has cast into the sea.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tuhan Dialah yang berperang, Tuhanlah nama-Nya Kereta Firaun dan pasukannya Dia lempar ke laut.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            الرب مكسر الحروب الرب إسمه مركبات فرعون وكل قوته طرحهما فى البحر.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Hancwtp n~a~nabat/c n~t~rictat/c afjolkou qen v~iom n~sari.         </language>         <language id="English">            His chosen captains also drowned in the Red Sea.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kapten pilihannya juga tenggelam di Laut Merah.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            ركبانا منتخبين ذى ثلاث جنبات غرقهم فى البحر الأحمر.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Afhwbc e~h~r/i e~jwou n~je pimwou: auwmc e~q~r/i e~pets/k m~v~r/] n~ouw~ni.         </language>         <language id="English">            The depths have covered them; they sank to the bottom like a stone.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kedalaman tutupi m’reka m’reka tenggelam ke dasar s’perti batu</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            غطاهم الماء أنغمسوا إلى العمق مثل الحجر.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Tekoui~nam Po#c# ac[iw~ou qen oujom: tekjij n~oui~nam Panou] actake nekjaji.         </language>         <language id="English">            Your right hand, O Lord, has become glorious in power. Your right hand, O Lord, has dashed the enemy in pieces.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tangan kanan-Mu, ya Tuhan, Mulia berkuasa. Tangan kanan-Mu, ya Tuhan, hancurkan musuh-Mu</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            يمينُك يارب تمجدت بالقوة يدك اليمنى ياإلهى أهلكت أعداءك.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Qen p~a~sai n~te pekw~ou akqomqem n~n/et]oub/n: akouwrp m~pekjwnt afouo~mou m~v~r/] n~hanrwoui~.         </language>         <language id="English">            And in the greatness of Your excellence, You have overthrown those who rose against You. You sent forth Your wrath, it consumed them like stubble.          </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengan keluhuran-Mu yang besar, Kau runtuhkan m’reka yang melawan-Mu, Kau kirimkan api murka-Mu, Yang memakan m’reka bak jerami</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            بكثرة مجدك سحقت الذين يقاوموننا أرسلت غضبك فأكلهم مثل الهشيم.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ebolhiten pip#n#a# n~te pekm~bon afo~hi e~ratf n~je pimwou: au[ici n~je nimwou m~v~r/] n~oucobt: au[wc n~je nijol qen y~m/] m~v~iom.         </language>         <language id="English">            And with the blast of Your nostrils the waters were gathered together, the flood stood upright like a heap, and the depths congealed in the heart of the sea.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengan hembusan nafas-Mu, air berkumpul, berdiri tegak bak tembok, dan membeku di kedalaman tengah laut</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            وبروح غضبك وقف الماء وارتفعت المياء مثل السور وجمدت الأمواج فى وسط البحر.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Afjoc gar n~je pijaji: je ]na[oji n~tataho: n~tavws n~hanswl: n~tat~cio~ n~ta'u,/: n~taqwteb qen tac/fi: n~te tajij ero#c#.         </language>         <language id="English">            The enemy said, “I will pursue, I will overtake, I will divide the spoil, my desire shall be satisfied on them, I will draw my sword, and my hand shall destroy them.”         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kata Musuh, ku ’kan kejar, kususul, kubagi jarahan, Ku puaskan nafsuku, ku hunuskan pedangku dan tanganku ‘kan hancurkan mereka."</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            قال العدو  انى أسرع فأدرك  وأقسم الغنائم وأشبع نفسى  وأقتل بسيفى ويدى تتسلط.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Akouwrp m~pekp#n#a# afhobcou n~je v~iom: auwmc e~pec/t m~v~r/] n~outath qen hanmwou euos.         </language>         <language id="English">            You blew with Your wind, the sea covered them, they sank like lead in the mighty waters.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kau tiup denga~n topan-Mu, laut menu-tu-pi m’reka, M’reka tenggelam s’perti timah di perairan yang kuat.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أرسلت روحك فغطاهم البحر  وغطسوا الى أسفل كالرصاص فى مياه كثيرة.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Nim eto~ni m~mok qen ninou] Po#c#: nim eto~ni m~mok: e~au]w~ou nak qen n/e#y#u# n~tak: euers~v/ri m~mok qen ouw~ou: eki~ri n~hans~v/ri.         </language>         <language id="English">            Who is like You, O Lord, among the gods? Who is like You, glorified in His saints, amazing in glory, performing wonders?         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Siapa s’perti-Mu, ya Tuhan di antara para allah? Siapa s’perti-Mu, mulia di antara para kudus-Nya, dahsyat dalam kemuliaan, melakukan keajaiban..</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            من يشبهك فى الآلهة يارب من يشبهك ممجدا فى قديسيك متعجبا منك بالمجد صانعا عجائب.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Akcouten tekoui~nam e~bol afomkou n~je p~kahi: ak[imwit qajwf m~peklaoc qen oumeym/i: vai e~takcotpf ak]jom naf qen teknom]: euma n~emton efouab nak.         </language>         <language id="English">            You stretched out Your right hand, the earth swallowed them. You, in Your mercy, have led forth the people whom You have redeemed. You have guided them, in Your strength, to Your holy habitation.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kau ulurkan tangan kanan-Mu, bumi telan m’reka. Dalam kasih setia-Mu Kau memimpin m’reka yang telah Engkau tebus, Kau bimbing m’reka dengan kuat-Mu, ke tempat kudus-Mu..</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            مددت يمينك فابتلعتهم الأرض  هديت شعبك بالحقيقة  هذا الذى اخترته وقويته بتعزيتك  الى موضع راحة قدسك.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Aucwtem n~je haneynoc ouoh aujwnt: hannakhi au[i n~n/etsop qen Nivulictim.         </language>         <language id="English">            The people will hear and be afraid; sorrow will take hold of the inhabitants of Palestine.         </language><language id="Indonesian">Bangsa-bangsa men-dengarnya dan takut, kegentaran ‘kan menguasai  penduduk Filistin.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            سمعت الأمم وغضبت  والمخاض أخذ سكان فلسطين.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Tote aui/c m~mwou n~je nih/gemwn n~te Edwm: niar,wn n~te Nimwa~bit/c ouc~yerter pe e~taf[itou.         </language>         <language id="English">            Then the chiefs of Edom will be dismayed, the mighty men of Moab, trembling, will take hold of them.          </language><language id="Indonesian">Lalu pemimpin Edom jadi heran, orang Moab yang perkasa Jadi gemetar.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            حينئذ أسرع ولاة أدوم  ورؤساء المؤابيين أخذتهم الرعدة.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Aubwl e~bol n~je ouon niben etsop qen &lt;anaan: afi~ e~h~r/i e~jwou n~je ouc~yerter nem ouho].         </language>         <language id="English">            All the inhabitants of Canaan will melt away; fear and dread will fall on them.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Penduduk Kanaan akan luluh, takut dan gentar akan menimpa m’reka.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            ذاب كل سكان كنعان  وأتت عليهم الرعدة والخوف.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Qen p~a~sai n~te pekj~voi marouerw~ni: satefcini n~je peklaoc Po#c# satefcini n~je peklaoc: vai e~takj~vof.         </language>         <language id="English">            By the greatness of Your arm, they will be as still as a stone, till Your people pass over, O Lord, till Your people pass over whom You have purchased.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Oleh hebatnya tangan-Mu mereka terdiam s’perti batu, sampai umat-Mu lewat ya Tuhan, sampai umat-Mu lewat, M’reka yang telah Engkau beli..</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            بكثرة ساعدك فليصيروا           كالحجر حتى يجتاز شعبك يارب حتى يجتاز شعبك هذا الذى اقتنيته.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Anitou e~qoun tojou hijen outwou n~te tekk~l/ronomia~: nem e~qoun e~pekman~swpi etcebtwt: vai e~takerhwb e~rof Po#c#.         </language>         <language id="English">            You will bring them in, and plant them in the mountain of Your inheritance, in the place, O Lord, which You have made for Your own dwelling.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bawalah m’reka masuk </div><div>dan tanamlah di gunung pusaka-Mu, di tempat yang t’lah Kau siapkan untuk-Mu berdiam ya Tuhan.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أدخلهم وأغرسهم على جبل ميراثك  وفى مسكنك المعد  هذا الذى صنعته يارب.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Pekma e#y#u# Po#c# v/e~taucebtwtf n~je nekjij: Po#c# ekoi n~ouro sa e~neh nem icjen p~e~neh ouoh e~ti.         </language>         <language id="English">            Your sanctuary, O Lord, which Your hands have established, the Lord shall reign forever and ever.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Di tempat kudus-Mu ya Tuhan yang tangan-Mu telah dirikan, Ya Tuhan, kau ‘kan memerintah selamala-manya..</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            موضعك المقدس يارب الذى أعددته يداك  يارب تملك منذ الأزل والآن والى الأبد.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Je aui~ e~qoun e~v~iom n~je nih~ywr n~te Varaw~ nem nefbere[woutc nem nef[acih~yo.         </language>         <language id="English">            For the horses of Pharaoh went with his chariots and his horsemen into the sea.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sebab telah masu~k ke laut kuda-kuda Firaun Kereta dan penunggangnya</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            لأنه قد دخل الى البحر خيل فرعون ومركباته وفرسانه.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            APo#c# en pimwou n~te v~iom e~h~r/i e~jwou: nens/ri de m~Pic~ra/l naumosi qen petsouw~ou qen y~m/] m~v~iom.         </language>         <language id="English">            And the Lord brought back the waters of the sea on them, but the children of Israel went on dry land in the midst of the sea.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan Tuhan kembalikan air laut ke atas mereka, tetapi bangsa Israel lewati tanah yang kering</div><div>di tengah laut.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            والرب غمرهم بماء البحر  أما بنو اسرائيل فكانوا يمشون على اليابسة فى وسط البحر.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ac[i de nac n~je Mariam ]p~rov/t/c t~cwni n~Aa~rwn m~pikemkem qen necjij: ouoh aui~ e~bol camenh/c n~je nihio~mi t/rou qen hankemkem nem hanhwc.         </language>         <language id="English">            Then Miriam the prophetess, the sister of Aaron, took the timbrel in her hand, and all the women went out after her with timbrels and with praises.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan Miryam, nabiah, saudari Harun, ambil rebana di tangannya, dan semua wanita ikuti dia dengan rebana dan pujian.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            فأخذت مريم النبية أخت هرون الدف بيديها وخرج فى إثرها جميع النسوة بالدفوف والتسابيح.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Acerh/tc de qajwou n~je Mariam ecjw m~moc: je marenhwc e~Po#c#: je qen ouw~ou gar af[iw~ou.         </language>         <language id="English">            And Miriam answered them, saying, “Let us sing to the Lord for He has triumphed gloriously.”         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan Miryam memimpin m’reka berkata: Mari nyanyi bagi Tuhan, S’bab Dia telah menang </div><div>dengan gemilang."</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            وبدأت مريم فى مقدمتهن تقول فلنسبح الرب لأنه بالمجد قد تمجد.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouh~yo nem ou[acih~yo afberbwrou e~v~iom: je marenhwc e~Po#c#: je qen ouw~ou gar af[iw~ou.         </language>         <language id="English">            “The horse and its rider He has thrown into the sea. Let us sing to the Lord for He has triumphed gloriously.”         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kuda dan penunggangnya, Dia lempar ke laut. "Mari nyanyi bagi Tuhan, s’bab Dia telah menang dengan gemilang."</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            الفرس وراكب الفرس طرحهما فى البحر  فلنسبح الرب لأنه بالمجد قد تمجد.         </language>      </text>   </section>      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">      <Title data-section-header="true">                  <language id="English">Psali Adam (Lobsh) for the First Canticle</language><language id="Indonesian">Psali Adam (Lobsh) untuk Hoos Pertama</language>         <language id="Arabic">مديح آدام</language>         <language id="Coptic">Qen ouswt...</language>      </Title>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Qen ouswt afswt: n~je pimwou n~te v~iom: ouoh v~noun ets/k: afswpi n~oumam~mosi.         </language>         <language id="English">            With the split: the waters of the sea split: and the very deep: became a walkway.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengan terbelahnya, air laut terbelah, Dan tempat terdalam, menjadi jalan setapak.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            قطعا انقطع ماء البحر  والعمق العميق صار مسلكا.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Oukahi n~ayouwnh: a~v~r/ sai hijwf: oumwit n~atcini: aumosi hiwtf.         </language>         <language id="English">            A hidden earth: was shone upon by the sun: and the untrodden road: was walked upon.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bumi yang tersembuni, Disinari matahari, Dan jalan yang tak terinjak </div><div>telah dilalui.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أرض غير ظاهرة أشرقت الشمس عليها  وطريق غير مسلوكة مشوا عليها.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Oumwou efb/l e~bol: afo~hi e~ratf: qen ouhwb n~s~v/ri: m~paradoxon.         </language>         <language id="English">            The flowing water: stood still: by a miraculous: act of wonder.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Air yang mengalir, Tegak berdiri, Oleh mujizat, perbuatan yang ajaib</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            ماء منحل وقف بفعل عجيب معجز.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Varaw~ nem nefharma: auwmc e~pec/t: nens/ri m~Pic#l#: auerjinior m~v~iom.         </language>         <language id="English">            Pharaoh and his chariots: were drowned: and the children of Israel: crossed the sea.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Firaun dan keretanya, Tenggelam, dan bangsa Israel, menyeberangi laut.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            غرق فرعون ومركباته وعبر بنو اسرائيل البحر.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Enafhwc qajwou pe: n~je Mwu~c/c pip~rov/t/c: san~tef[itou e~qoun: hi p~safe n~Cina.         </language>         <language id="English">            And in front of them: was Moses the prophet praising: until he brought them: to the wilderness of Sinai.          </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan di depan mereka, Nabi Musa memuji, sampai dia membawa m’reka, ke padang gurun Sinai.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            وكان موسى النبى يسبح قدامهم حتى أدخلهم برية سيناء.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Enafhwc e~V]: qen taihwd/ m~beri: je marenhwc e~Po#c#: je qen ouw~ou gar af[iw~ou.         </language>         <language id="English">            And they were praising God: with this new psalmody: saying, “Let us sing to the Lord: for He has triumphed gloriously.”         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan mereka memuji Allah, dengan mazmur baru ini, berkata, "Mari nyanyi bagi Tuhan, s’bab Dia telah menang dengan gemilang."</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            وكانوا يسبحون الله بهذه التسبحة الجديدة  قائلين فلنسبح الرب لأنه بالمجد قد تمجد.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Hiten nieu,/: n~te Mwu~c/c piar,/p~rov/t/c: Po#c# a~rih~mot nan: m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.         </language>         <language id="English">            Through the prayers: of Moses the archprophet: O Lord grant us: the forgiveness of our sins.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengan doa Musa, Pemimpin para nabi, Ya Tuhan, berikanlah kami pengampunan untuk dosa kami.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            بصلوات موسى رئيس الأنبياء يارب أنعم لنا بمغفرة خطايانا.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Hiten nip~recbia: n~te ]yeo~tokoc e#y#u# Maria: Po#c# a~rih~mot nan: m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.         </language>         <language id="English">            Through the intercessions of: the Mother of God Saint Mary: O Lord grant us: the forgiveness of our sins.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengan syafaat, Theotokos Santa Maria, ya Tuhan  berikanlah kami pengampunan untuk dosa kami</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            بشفاعات والدة الاله القديسة مريم يارب أنعم لنا بمغفرة خطايانا.         </language>      </text>         <insertdocument path="include/TenouwstSeasonalResponseShort" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>            </section></document>