<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" pascha="true" fixeddatedocument="true">   <forceseason id="Fasts ^ PaschaWeek ^ AdamDays ^ Weekdays ^ Mondays ^ FuneralTune ^ SeasonOfAirAndFruits">      <Title>         <language id="English">Monday Eve (The Ninth Hour)</language><language id="Indonesian">Malam Senin<div>(Jam Kesembilan)</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">ليلة الإثنين (الساعة التاسعة)</language>         <language id="Coptic">Pie~jwrh m~p~c~nau (}ajp 9)</language>      </Title>            <role id="Priest">         <insertdocument path="include/KhenEfranAmen"/>                  <text>            <language id="English">               The prophecies of the Ninth Hour of the eve of Monday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Nubuat-nubuat dari Jam Kesembilan <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Malam </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Senin  pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.</span></div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نبوات الساعة التاسعة، من ليلة الإثنين من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Micah 2:3-11</language><language id="Indonesian">Mikha 2:3-11</language>               <language id="Arabic">ميخا 2: 3-11</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/prophecyIntro/Micah"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eybe vai nai ne n/ e~tef jw m~mwou n~je P[oic je h/ppe a~nok ]namokmek e~han pethwou e~jen tai vul/: nai e~tetennas~w~li an n~netenmo] e~bol n~q/tou: ouoh n~netenmosi e~retencoutwn n~ouho] qen ouho]: je ouc/ou efhwou pe.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Therefore thus says the Lord: "Behold, I am devising evils against this tribe from which you shall not lift up your neck, nor will you suddenly walk upright, for this is a time of evil.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebab itu beginilah firman TUHAN: Sesungguhnya, Aku merancang malapetaka terhadap kaum ini, dan kamu tidak dapat menghindarkan lehermu dari padanya; kamu tidak dapat lagi berjalan angkuh, sebab waktu itu adalah waktu yang mencelakakan.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  مـن أجـل ذلك هكذا ما يـقوله الرب. هأنذا أفكر بالشرور على هذه القبيلة. ومن ثم لا تقدرون أن ترفعوا أعناقكم منها ولا تمشون متشامخين. لأنه زمان ردئ.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Qen pie~hoou e~tem~mau eue~[i n~ouparabol/ e~jen y/nou: ouoh eue~erh/bi n~ouh/bi qen ouhwc eujw m~moc: je qen outalepwria~ acertalepwrin:               </language>               <language id="English">                  In that day a parable shall be taken up against you, and a dirge will be wailed, saying, 'In misery we have suffered hardship.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Pada hari itu orang akan melontarkan sindiran tentang kamu dan akan memperdengarkan suatu ratapan dan akan berkata: "Kita telah dihancurluluhkan!               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ذلك اليوم يتخذ عليكم مثل وينوحون نوحاً بتسبيح قائلين: لقد شقيت شقاء.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ttoim~palaoc aurasc m~v~noh ouoh ne m~mon petsws m~mof pe eyreftacyo: neten iohi aurasou: neten messo] auvasou:               </language>               <language id="English">                  The portion of my people has been measured out with a measuring line, and there was no one who was able to stop Him. Our fields have been divided among them.'               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Bagian warisan bangsaku telah diukur dengan tali, dan tidak ada orang yang mengembalikannya, ladang-ladang kita dibagikan kepada orang-orang yang menawan kita."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ونصيب شعبى قاسوه بالحبل. ولم يكن من يحوله ليرجع. قاسوا حقولكم وأقتسموا بقاعكم               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eybe vai n~nefswpi nak n~je v/eynahioui n~ounoh qen ouk~l/roc. Mperrimi qen han ermwoui~ qen ]ekkl/cia n~te[oic P[oic:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Therefore there will be no one to put out a measuring line for a lot for you in the assembly of the Lord.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebab itu tidak akan ada bagimu orang yang melontarkan tali dengan undian di dalam jemaah TUHAN.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  من أجل هذا لا يكون لك من يلقى حبلاً فى نصيب ميراث.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Oude m~pen y~routaouo erm/ e~bol e~jen vai: ou gar n~nef,w m~p~sws n~cwf n~je v/etjw m~moc:                </language>               <language id="English">                  "Do not shed tears, nor even weep over these things; for He will not dismiss the reproaches who says,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Janganlah ucapkan nubuat," kata mereka itu, "orang tidak mengucapkan nubuat seperti itu! Noda tidak akan menimpa kita."                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لا تبكوا بدموع فى كنيسة الرب. ولا تسكبوا العبرات على هذا لأنه لا يترك التعيير عنه القائل:                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  P/i n~Iakwb af]jwnt m~Pip~neuma n~te P[oic: m/ nai an ne nef hb/oui~ etsop naf: m/ nef caji naneu naf an ouoh aumosi eucoutwn:               </language>               <language id="English">                  'The house of Jacob has provoked the Spirit of the Lord; are these not His practices? Are not His words good with Him, and have they not proceeded as predicted?               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Bolehkah hal itu dikatakan, keturunan Yakub? Apakah TUHAN kurang sabar? Atau seperti inikah tindakan-Nya? Bukankah firman-Ku baik terhadap orang yang benar kelakuannya?               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أن بيت يعقوب أغضب روح الرب. أليست هذه أعماله الكائنة معه. أليس كلامه صالحاً نحو من يسلك بالإستقامة وقام               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh afohi e~ratf hit~h/ n~je palaoc eumetjaji oube tefhir/n/: pefsar auraqtf ep~jinw~li n~ouhelpic n~ouqomqem n~te oupolemoc.               </language>               <language id="English">                   And previously, for enmity my people resisted against His peace. They flayed his skin to remove hope in the ravages of war.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Tetapi kamulah yang bangkit sebagai musuh terhadap umat-Ku. Kamu merebut jubah dari orang-orang yang suka damai, yang berjalan lewat dengan tenteram, yang tidak cenderung kepada perang.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  شعبى بالعداوة قبالة سلامته. سلخوا جلده لينزع الرجاء من إنكسار الحرب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eybe vai nihugoumenoc n~te palaoc eue~hitou e~bol qen ni/i n~te p~ounof eybe nouh~b/oui~ ethwou auhitou e~bol.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Therefore those leading my people will be cast out of their luxurious homes; they have been driven out because of their wicked practices.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Para isteri di antara umat-Ku kamu halau dari rumah kesayangannya, kamu mengambil untuk selama-lamanya, semarak yang telah Kuberikan kepada mereka.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  من أجل ذلك مدبرو شعبى يطرحون خارجاً من بيوت نعيمهم: من أجل أعمالهم الشريرة طردوا.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Qwnt e~han twou n~e~neh:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Draw near to the everlasting mountains.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mendekatlah kepada gunung yang kekal.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  اقتربوا إلى الجبال الدهرية               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Twnk masenak je vai pe pekm~ton an e~reten e~tako qen outako eybe ou[wqem. a~reten vwt m~mon v/et[oji n~ca y/nou.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Arise and depart, for this is not a final resting place for you on account of uncleanness; you have been utterly destroyed by corruption. You were pursued by no one pursuing!               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Bangkitlah dan pergilah, sebab ini bukan tempat perhentian bagimu! Oleh karena kenajisan maka kamu akan dibinasakan dengan kebinasaan yang tidak terpulihkan.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  قم انطلق لأنه ليست هذه هى راحتك. لقد هلكتم هلاكاً من أجل النجاسة وهربتم وليس من يطردكم.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ProphecyConclusion"/>         </section>      </role>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Introduction to the Paschal Praise</language><language id="Indonesian">Pendahuluan Pujian Paskah</language>            <language id="Arabic">مقدمة تسبحة البصخة</language>         </Title>               <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PropheciesConclusion"/>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The doxology of the Ninth Hour of the eve of Monday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Doksologi dari Jam Kesembilan Malam Senin pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  تسبحة الساعة التاسعة، من ليلة الإثنين من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="include/LordsPrayerNoTitle"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/Doxology.1"/>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Psalm 17:6,1</language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur 17:6,1</language>               <language id="Arabic">مزمور 17: 6 ,1</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PsalmOfDavid"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Anok aiws e~bol je akcwtem e~roi: rek pekmasj e~roi ouoh cwtem e~nacaji:                </language>               <language id="English">                  I cried out, because You listened to me, O God; incline Your ear to me, and hear my words.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Aku berseru kepada-Mu, karena Engkau menjawab aku, ya Allah; sendengkanlah telinga-Mu kepadaku, dengarkanlah perkataanku.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أنا صرخت لأنك قد سمعتنى يا الله. أمل يارب أذنيك و أنصت لكلامى.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  {ic~m/ Vnou] e~tameym/i: ouoh mah~y/k e~pa]ho: all/louia.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Listen, O Lord of my righteousness; attend to my supplication. Alleluia.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dengarkanlah, TUHAN, perkara yang benar, perhatikanlah seruanku; berilah telinga akan doaku, dari bibir yang tidak menipu. Alleluia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أستمع يا الله عدلى واصغ إلى طلبتى الليلويا.               </language>            </text>         </section>      </role>               <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Mark 8:27-33</language><language id="Indonesian">Markus 8:27-33</language>            <language id="Arabic">مرقس 8: 27-33</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/KeEperto"/>         <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroMark"/>         <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh afi~ e~bol n~je I/couc nem nefmay/t/c e~ni]mi n~te kecria~ n~te Vilp~pe ouoh qen pimwit nafsini n~nefmay/t/c efjw m~moc nwou je a~re nirwmi jw m~moc je a~nok nim:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Now Jesus and His disciples went out to the towns of Caesarea Philippi; and on the road He asked His disciples, saying to them, “Who do men say that I am?”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kemudian Yesus beserta murid-murid-Nya berangkat ke kampung-kampung di sekitar Kaisarea Filipi. Di tengah jalan Ia bertanya kepada murid-murid-Nya, kata-Nya: "Kata orang, siapakah Aku ini?"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ثم خرج يسوع و تلاميذه إلى قرى قيصرية فيلبس. وفى الطريق كان يسأل تلاميذه قائلاً من تقول الناس أنى أنا.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  N~ywou de aujoc naf eujw m~moc je Iwann/c piref]wmc han ke,wouni de je ?liac hanke,wouni de je ouai n~te nip~rov/t/c:               </language>               <language id="English">                  So they answered, “John the Baptist; but some say, Elijah; and others, one of the prophets.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Jawab mereka: "Ada yang mengatakan: Yohanes Pembaptis, ada juga yang mengatakan: Elia, ada pula yang mengatakan: seorang dari para nabi."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أما هم فقالوا له يقولون أنك يوحنا المعمدان وآخرون أيليا وآخرون أنك أحد الآنبياء.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh n~yof nafsini m~mwou je n~ywten de teten jw m~moc e~roi je a~nok nim afe~rouw~ n~je Petroc pe jaf je n~yok pe Pi,~rictoc.               </language>               <language id="English">                   He said to them, “But who do you say that I am?” Peter answered and said to Him, “You are the Christ.”                </language><language id="Indonesian">Ia bertanya kepada mereka: "Tetapi apa katamu, siapakah Aku ini?" Maka jawab Petrus: "Engkau adalah Mesias!" </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أما هو فسألهم وقال وأنتم من تقولون أنى أنا؟ أجاب بطرس وقال أنت هو المسيح.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh afer e~pitiman nwou hina n~ces~tem joc n~h~lieyb/tf:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then He strictly warned them that they should tell no one about Him.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Lalu Yesus melarang mereka dengan keras supaya jangan memberitahukan kepada siapa pun tentang Dia.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فزجرهم لكي لا يقولوا لاحد شيئاً من أجله,               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh aferh/tc n~]c~bw nwou je hw] pe n~te p~s/ri m~v~rwmi [ioum/s n~qici ouoh n~tousosf e~bol hitotou n~ni p~recbuteroc nem niar,/e~reuc nem nicaq ouoh n~touqoybef ouoh menenca somt n~e~hoou n~teftwnf:                </language>               <language id="English">                  And He began to teach them that the Son of Man must suffer many things, and be rejected by the elders and chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and after three days rise again.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kemudian mulailah Yesus mengajarkan kepada mereka, bahwa Anak Manusia harus menanggung banyak penderitaan dan ditolak oleh tua-tua, imam-imam kepala dan ahli-ahli Taurat, lalu dibunuh dan bangkit sesudah tiga hari.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وابتدأ يعلمهم أنه ينبغى لإبن الإنسان أن يتألم كثيراً من الشيوخ ورؤساء الكهنة والكتبة ويقتلونه وبعد ثلاثة أيام يقوم,               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh nafcaji m~picaji qen ouparr/cia~ ouoh afa~moni m~mof n~je Petroc ouoh aferh/tc n~ere~pitiman naf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  He spoke this word openly. Then Peter took Him aside and began to rebuke Him.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Hal ini dikatakan-Nya dengan terus terang. Tetapi Petrus menarik Yesus ke samping dan menegor Dia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان يقول هذا القول علانية فأمسكه بطرس وابتدأ ينهاه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  N~yof de e~tafvonhf ouoh e~tafnau e~nefmay/t/c afere~pitiman m~Petroc ouoh pejaf naf                </language>               <language id="English">                  But when He had turned around and looked at His disciples, He rebuked Peter, saying,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Maka berpalinglah Yesus dan sambil memandang murid-murid-Nya Ia memarahi Petrus, kata-Nya:                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأما هو فالتفت ونظر إلى تلاميذه وزجر بطرس وقال له                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je masenak cavahou m~moi p~catanac je ,~meui an e~na Vnou] alla e~na nirwmi.               </language>               <language id="English">                  “Get behind Me, Satan! For you are not mindful of the things of God, but the things of men.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">"Enyahlah Iblis, sebab engkau bukan memikirkan apa yang dipikirkan Allah, melainkan apa yang dipikirkan manusia.“</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أذهب خلفى يا شيطان لانك لا تفكر فيما لله بل فيما للناس.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/BowDownBeforeTheHolyGospel"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelConclusionEve"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Exposition</language><language id="Indonesian">Komentari</language>            <language id="Arabic">الطرح</language>         </Title>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The exposition of the Ninth Hour of the eve of Monday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Komentari dari Jam Kesembilan Malam Senin pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طرح الساعة التاسعة، من ليلة الإثنين من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  While Jesus and His disciples were on the road to Caesarea Philippi, He started to talk to them overtly about what will happen to Him in Jerusalem.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ketika Yesus dan murid-murid-Nya sedang dalam perjalanan menuju Kaisarea Filipi, Ia mulai berbicara kepada mereka secara terbuka tentang apa yang akan terjadi kepada-Nya di Yerusalem.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لما فرغ الرب أن يسأل تلاميذه فى طريق قيصرية فيلبس. ابتدأ يقول لهم علانية من أجل الذى سيحصل له فى أورشليم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  He must fulfill what is written: That the Son of man will have lots of pains. He will be rejected from the scribes and the elders of the Jews.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ia harus menggenapi apa yang tertulis: Bahwa Anak Manusia akan menanggung banyak penderitaan dan akan ditolak oleh ahli-ahli Taurat dan tua-tua orang Yahudi.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أنه ينبغى أن يكمل المكتوب إن إبن الإنسان ينال آلاماً كثيرة. ويرذل من الكتبة ومشائخ اليهود.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  And after the sufferings He will endure, He will rise on the third day.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan setelah semua penderitaan yang akan dialami-Nya, Ia akan bangkit pada hari ketiga.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ومن بعد الآلام التى سيقبلها يقوم من الأموات فى اليوم الثالث               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  This is the stone that the builders rejected as the scriptures say: He will descend with great anger upon them and His rage will destroy them. He will pour the shame upon their faces because they rewarded charity with evil. And for those who obey Him, and believe in Him, He will give eternal happiness.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Inilah batu yang ditolak oleh tukang bangunan seperti yang tertulis dalam Kitab Suci: Ia akan turun ke atas mereka dengan murka yang besar dan murka-Nya akan membinasakan mereka. Ia akan mencurahkan aib ke atas wajah mereka, karena mereka membalas kebaikan dengan kejahatan. Dan bagi mereka yang menaati-Nya dan percaya kepada-Nya, Ia akan memberikan kebahagiaan kekal.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  هذا هو الحجر الذى رذله البناؤون كقول الكتب فسيهبط عليهم غضبه العظيم ويهشمهم الرجز. هو يصب الخزى على وجوههم لأنهم جازوا الإحسان بالأساءة. والذين يسمعون ويؤمنون به سيعطيهم فرحاً لا يفنى إلى الأبد.               </language>            </text>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ExpositionConclusion"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/EveningLitaniesAndConclusionLink"/>   </forceseason></document>