<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Title>      <language id="English">Hymn of the Intercessions</language><language id="Indonesian">Himne Dengan Syafaat</language>      <language id="Coptic">Hiten nip~recbia...</language>   </Title>   <insertdocument path="include/hiten/StMary"/>   <insertdocument path="include/hiten/HymnOfTheIntercessions.1"/>        <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Hiten nip~recbia n~te pisasf n~ar,iaggeloc nem nitagma n~e~pouranion: P[oic a~rih~mot nan m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.      </language>      <language id="English">         Through the intercessions of the seven archangels, and the heavenly orders, O Lord, grant us the forgiveness of our sins.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dengan syafaat Tujuh Penghulu Malaikat dan Pasukan Surga: Ya Tuhan, berikanlah pengampunan untuk dosa kami.</language>      <language id="Arabic">         بشفاعات رؤساء الملائكة السبعة والطغمات السمائية، ياربُ أنعم علينا بمغفرة خطايانا.      </language>            </text>      <insertdocument path="include/hiten/HymnOfTheIntercessions.2"/>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Hiten nieu,/ n~te na[oic n~io] n~a~poctoloc nem p~cepi n~te nimay/t/c: P[oic a~rih~mot nan m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.      </language>      <language id="English">         Through the prayers of my lords and fathers, the apostles, and the rest of the disciples, O Lord, grant us the forgiveness of our sins.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dengan doa tuan dan bapa kami para rasul dan para Murid lainnya: Ya Tuhan, berikanlah pengampunan untuk dosa  kami.</language>      <language id="Arabic">         بصلوات سادتي الآباء الرسل وبقية التلاميذ، ياربُ أنعم علينا بمغفرة خطايانا.      </language>            </text>      <insertdocument path="include/hiten/HymnOfTheIntercessions.3"/>      <group>      <season id="DisplayNonCustomaryPrayers">         <section>            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Combined Intercessions for the Male Martyrs</language><language id="Indonesian">Syafaat Kombinasi untuk Martir Laki-laki</language>            </Title>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Hiten nieu,/ n~te niaylovoroc m~marturoc pa[oic p~ouro Gewrgioc: Yeo~dwroc pic~tratilat/c: Vilopat/r Merkourioc: abba M/na n~te niVaiat: P[oic a~rih~mot nan m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Through the prayers of the struggle-bearers and martyrs, my lord Prince George, Theodorus the general, Philopater Mercurius, Abba Mena of Vayat: O Lord, grant us the forgiveness of our sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Dengan doa para pejuang dan para martir, Tuanku Pengeran Georgios, Theodorus Sang Jendral, Philopater Merkurius, Abba Mina dari Vayat: Ya Tuhan, berikanlah kami pengampunan untuk dosa kami.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  بصلوات الشهداء المجاهدين، سيدي الملك جاورجيوس، الأمير تادرس محب الأب مرقوريوس وآفا مينا البياضي، ياربُ أنعم علينا بمغفرة خطايانا.               </language>                </text>              </section>            </season>   </group>      <insertdocument path="include/hiten/HymnOfTheIntercessions.4"/>      <group>      <season id="DisplayNonCustomaryPrayers">         <section>            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Combined Intercessions for the Female Martyrs</language><language id="Indonesian">Syafaat Kombinasi untuk Martir Perempuan</language>            </Title>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Hiten nieu,/ n~te niselet n~te Pi,~rictoc ]a~gia  m~m/i Barbara nem Iolia~n/ nem Dumian/ nem Marin/ nem Ir/n/ nem Anacimon nem Ar'~ima nem Anactacia: P[oic a~rih~mot nan m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Through the prayers of the brides of Christ, Saints Barbara and Juliana and Demiana and Marina and Irene and Anasimon and Aripsima and Anastasia: O Lord, grant us the forgiveness of our sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dengan doa para pengantin Kristus, Santa Barbara and Juliana and Demiana dan Marina dan Irene dan Anasimon dan Aripsima dan Anastasia: Ya Tuhan, berikanah kami pengampunan untuk dosa kami.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  بصلوات عرائس المسيح القديسة بربارة ويوليانة ودميانة ومارينا وايريني وآنا سيمون واريبسيما واناسطاسيا، ياربُ أنعم علينا بمغفرة خطايانا.               </language>                </text>              </section>      </season>   </group>      <insertdocument path="include/hiten/HymnOfTheIntercessions.5"/>      <group>      <season id="DisplayNonCustomaryPrayers">         <section>            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Combined Intercessions for the Saints</language><language id="Indonesian">Syafaat Kombinasi untuk Para Kudus</language>            </Title>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Hiten nieu,/ n~te nenio] eyouab m~patriar,/c abba Ayanacioc pia~poctolikoc: nem abba Kurilloc pic~tulloc n~te pinah]: nem Diockoroc t~q/bc n~]oryodoxia: P[oic a~rih~mot nan m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Through the prayers of our holy fathers the patriarchs, Abba Athanasius the apostolic  and Abba Cyril the pillar of faith and Dioscorus the lamp of Orthodoxy: O Lord, grant us the forgiveness of our sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dengan doa para Bapa Kudus kami, Para Patriark, Abba Athanasius Sang Apostolik, dan Abba Cyril Sang Pilar Iman and Dioscorus Sang Lentera Ortodoksi: Ya Tuhan, berikanlah pengampunan untuk dosa kami</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  بصلوات الآباء القديسين البطاركة أنبا اثناسيوس الرسولي و أنبا كيرلس عمود الدين و أنبا ديوسقورس مصباح الاورثوذوكسية، ياربُ أنعم علينا بمغفرة خطايانا.               </language>                </text>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Hiten nieu,/ n~te na[oic n~io] m~mainous/ri: abba Antwnioc nem abba Paule: nem Paqwmioc: nem pisomt eyouab Makarioc: abba Senou] piar,/mand~rit/c: P[oic a~rih~mot nan m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Through the prayers of my masters the fathers who loved their children, Abba Antony, and Abba Paul, and Pachomius, the three saints Makarios, Abba Shenouda the archimandrite: O Lord, grant us the forgiveness of our sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dengan doa tuan kami Bapa yang mengasihi anaknya, Abba Antony, Abba Paul, and Pachomius, tiga orang kudus Makarius, Abba Shenouda sang arkhimandrite: Ya Tuhan, berikanlah kami pengampunan untuk dosa kami</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  بصلوات سادتي الآباء محبى اولادهم، الأنبا أنطونيوس و الأنبا بولا و باخوميوس و الثالثة مقارات القديسين و الأنبا شنودة رئيس المتوحدين، ياربُ أنعم علينا بمغفرة خطايانا.               </language>                </text>                             <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Hiten nieu,/ n~te na[oic n~io] m~mainous/ri: abba Piswi nem abba Paule nem pijwri eyouab: abba Mwc/ abba ?c/dwroc pip~recbuteroc: Maximoc nem Dometioc abba Arcenioc abba Iwann/c pikoloboc abba Camou/l pio~mologit/c: P[oic a~rih~mot nan m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Through the prayers, of my masters and fathers who loved their children, Abba Pishoy and Abba Paul, and the strong Saint Abba Moses, Abba Isidore the priest, Maximus and Dometius, Abba Arsanios, Abba John the short, Abba Samuel the Confessor: O Lord, grant us the forgiveness of our sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Dengan doa tuan kami Bapa yang mengasihi anaknya, Abba Bishoy and Abba Paula, Orang Kudus yang Kuat Abba Moses, Abba Isidorus sang Imam, Maximus dan Dometius, Abba Arsanius, Abba Yohanes yang Pendek, Abba Samuel Sang Pengaku Iman: Ya Tuhan, berikanlah kami pengampunan untuk dosa kami.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  بصلوات سادتي الآباء محبي اولادهم الأنبا بيشوي و الأنبا بولا و القوي القديس الأنبا موسى و الأنبا ايسيذوروس القس، مكسيموس و دوماديوس، الأنبا ارسانيوس، و الأنبا يوحنا القصير و الأنبا صموءيل المعترف، يا رب انعم علينا بمغفرة خطايانا.               </language>                </text>              </section>      </season>   </group>      <insertdocument path="include/hiten/HymnOfTheIntercessions.6"/>      <comment>      <language id="English">                  The verse for the saint of the church is added here, if not already mentioned above.      </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Syair untuk Orang Kudus Gereja ditambahkan disini, jika belum disebut diatas.</language>   </comment>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Hiten nieu,/ n~te n/eyouab n~te paie~hoou piouai piouai kata pefran: P[oic a~rih~mot nan m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.      </language>      <language id="English">         Through the prayers of the saints of this day, each one according to their names, O Lord, grant us the forgiveness of our sins.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dengan doa semua orang kudus, hari ini setiap yang namanya disebut : Ya Tuhan, Berikanlah kami pengampunan untuk dosa kami.</language>      <language id="Arabic">         بصلوات قديسي هذا اليوم، كل واحد باسمِه، ياربُ أنعم علينا بمغفرة خطايانا.      </language>            </text>      <insertdocument path="include/hiten/HymnOfTheIntercessions.7"/>      <comment>      <language id="English">                  In the presence of a bishop or metropolitan, the following verse is added.      </language><language id="Indonesian">Ketika Uskup atau Metropolitan hadir, syair berikut ditambahkan.</language>   </comment>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Hiten noueu,/ a~reh e~p~wnq m~peniwt ettai/out n~dikeoc abba (nim) pie~pickopoc (pim/tropolit/c): P[oic a~rih~mot nan m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.      </language>      <language id="English">         Through their prayers, keep the life of our honored and righteous father, Abba (…) the bishop (metropolitan), O Lord, grant us the forgiveness of our sins.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dengan doa mereka ya Tuhan, lindungilah hidup Bapa yang dihormati Uskup/Metropolitan Abba Reweis: Ya Tuhan, berikanlah pengampunan untuk dosa kami</language>      <language id="Arabic">         بصلواتهم إحفظ حياة أبينا المكرم البار أنبا (…) الاسقف (المطران) ياربُ أنعم علينا بمغفرة خطايانا.      </language>            </text>      <insertdocument path="include/TenouwstSeasonalResponse"/></document>