<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" Baptism="true" LoosingTheGirdle="true">   <Title>      <Language id="English">Loosing of the Girdle of Those Who Have Been Baptized</Language>      <Language id="Arabic">صلاة حل زنار المعمدين</Language>   </Title>   <Comment>      <Language id="English">         That is a prayer over those that have been baptized, after the washing, on the eighth day.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         تقال على المعمدين بعد الحميم في اليوم الثامن من العماد      </Language>   </Comment>   <Comment>      <Language id="English">         A basin is set containing clean water and around it are set lit candles. Then the priest says the Prayer of Thanksgiving and offers Incense by the Mystery of the Pauline Epistle. The chanters say “Glory be ...” and “Our Father…” followed by psalm 50 and the pauline epistle:      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         يوضع إناء فيه ماء، وتوقد حوله الشموع، ثم يبتدئ الكاهن بصلاة الشكر ويرفع البخور وهو يقول أوشية سر البولس. ويقول المرتلون: (ذكصابتري) وأبانا الذي.. والمزمور الخمسين ثم يقرأ البولس.      </Language>   </Comment>   <InsertDocument path="include/StartOfService"/>   <InsertDocument path="include/ThanksgivingPrayer"/>   <InsertDocument path="include/PrayerOfIncenseForPaulineEpistle"/>      <Role id="Deacon">      <BibleReference reference="1 Corinthians 10:1-5" type="section"/>   </Role>         <InsertDocument path="include/trisagion/Seasonal"/>   <InsertDocument path="include/LitanyOfTheGospel"/>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Gospel Response         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            مرد الانجيل         </Language>      </Title>      <Role id="People">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               “This is My beloved Son / in whom My soul is well pleased; / He has done My will; hear Him / for He is the Life-Giver.”            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Je vai pe Pas/ri pamenrit: e~ta ta'u,/ ]ma] n~q/tf: aferpaouws cwtem n~cwf: je n~yof pe Pireftanqo.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               "هذا هو إبني حبيبي، الذي به سرت به نفسي، وصنع إرادتي فأسمعوا له، لأنه هو المحيي."            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>   </Section>      <InsertDocument path="include/litanies/ThreeShort"/>      <Role id="Priest">      <Comment>         <Language id="English">            Then the priest says the following prayer of the laying of hand after communion of the holy Mysteries:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثم يقول الكاهن هذه الصلاة لوضع اليد بعد التناول من الأسرار المقدسة:         </Language>      </Comment>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            O Master, Lord, our God, Giver of peace and blessing, to whom alone belongs goodness and love-of-mankind.           </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            Vn/b P[oic Pennou] Vref] n~]hir/n/ nem nic~mou va ]meta~gayoc m~mauatf nem ]metmairwmi.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أيها السيد الرب إلهنا مانح السلام والبركة، ذو الصلاح وحده محب البشر.           </Language>      </Text>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            Who have blessed us and sanctified us and enlightened us with the light of His Godhead.           </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/e~tafc~mou e~ron: afera~giazin m~mon: aferouwini e~ron qen v~ouwini n~te tefmeynou].         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي باركنا وقدسنا وأضاء علينا بنور لاهوته.           </Language>      </Text>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            Who has made His servants worthy to receive the ineffable light from on high of Your Christ Jesus, our Savior.         </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/e~tafy~renef e~biaik erp~emp~sa eyrou[i m~piouwini etcap~swi n~atcaji m~mof n~te Pek,~rictoc I/couc Pencwt/r.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي جعل عبيده مستحقين أن ينالوا النور الذي من فوق، غير الموصوف، الذي لمسيحك يسوع مخلصنا.         </Language>      </Text>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            Enlighten them with the light of the blessing, purify them, bless them, and renew them by Your grace, through the Baptism they have received in the power of Your life-giving Holy Spirit.          </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            Eke~erouwini e~rwou qen ououwini n~c~mou: eke~toubwou eke~c~mou e~rwou: eke~aitou m~beri qen pekh~mot: hiten piwmc e~tau[itf: qen ]jom n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab n~reftanqo.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أنر عليهم بنور البركة. طهرهم. باركهم. جددهم بنعمتك من جهة الصبغة التي نالوها بقوة روحك القدوس المحيي.         </Language>      </Text>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            O You who have purified them from every defilement of the body and the soul.         </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/e~taftoubwou e~bol ha ywleb niben n~te ]carx nem ]'u,/.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يا مَنْ طهرتهم من كل دنس الجسد والنفس.         </Language>      </Text>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            Yes, O our Master, the Holy One, bless them with Your blessing and confirm them in Your orthodox faith unto the end.         </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            Ce Penn/b V/eyouab c~mou e~rwou qen pekc~mou: matajrwou qen peknah] n~oryodoxoc sa e~bol.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            نعم يا سيدنا القدوس باركهم ببركتك. ثبتهم في إيمانك الأرثوذكسي إلى الإنقضاء.         </Language>      </Text>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            Bring them to maturity and adulthood. May they be gaurded by good angels unto the end.         </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            Anitou e~ousi n~te ]mai/~ nem ]hul/kia: marouswpi eurwic e~rwou n~je hanaggeloc n~a~gayoc sa e~bol.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ات بهم إلى حد القامة والبلوغ. وليكونوا محروسين من ملائكة صالحين إلى الإنقضاء.         </Language>      </Text>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            Fill them with knowledge and every understanding. Keep their life that they may please You.           </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            Mahou e~bol qen pie~mi nem ka] niben: a~reh e~poujinwnq euranak.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إملأهم من المعرفة ومن كل فهم. احفظ حياتهم ليرضوك.           </Language>      </Text>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            Bless them, O our Master with Your holy blessing and take away from their heart the spirit of tremble and every spirit of error.           </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            Cmou e~rwou Penn/b qen pekc~mou m~makarion ouoh w~li e~bol qen pouh/t m~pip~neuma n~te pis~yorter: nem p~neuma niben m~p~lanoc.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            باركهم يا سيد ببركتك الطوباوية. انزع من قلوبهم روح القلق وكل الأرواح الْمُضِلَّة.           </Language>      </Text>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            May their heart be enlightened by the light of Your lordship. Make them worthy of the eternal life and the kingdom of the heavens, in Christ Jesus our Lord.         </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            Mareferouwini e~pouh/t n~je v~ouwini: n~te tekmet[oic. Aritou n~emp~sa m~piwnq n~e~neh: nem ]metouro n~te niv/oui: qen Pi,~rictoc I/couc Pen[oic         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وليضئ قلبهم نور ربوبيتك. اجعلهم مستحقين الحياة الأبدية وملكوت السموات، بالمسيح يسوع ربنا.           </Language>      </Text>   </Role>         <Role id="Priest" silent="true">      <InsertDocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusionEnding"/>   </Role>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">A Commentary</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">طرح</Language>      </Title>            <Role id="People">         <Comment>            <Language id="English">               A commentary that is chanted in the Hosanna Sunday tune for those who have been baptized on the day of Baptism after the crowning and before the commandment, or after the communion, or after eight days from the Baptism:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               طرح يرتل لأجل المعمدين بطريقة الشعانين في يوم العماد بعد وضع الأكاليل قبل الوصية، أو بعد التناول، أو في اليوم الثامن من العماد:            </Language>         </Comment>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Magnify the Lord with me, and let us exalt His name together, for the grace which has been received by this blessed child (...).             </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ma oumetnis] m~P[oic nem/i: ouoh maren[ici m~pefran hi oucop: kata pih~mot e~tafsopf e~rof: n~je pai kouji (nim) etc~marwout.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               عظموا الرب معي، ولنرفعن إسمه جميعاً، من أجل النعمة التي نالها هذا الطفل (...) المبارك.             </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               And let us proclaim openly with a voice of rejoicing, saying, “Be glad and rejoice in the Lord, O blessed child            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ouoh n~tenws e~bol r/twc: qen ouc~m/ n~te p~yel/l: je rasi ouoh yel/l qen P[oic: w~ pia~lou etc~marwout.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلنصرخ جهراً بصوت التهليل قائلين "إفرح وتهلل بالرب أيها الطفل المبارك.            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Jesus Christ has given you confirmation and fruit, and peace be unto you O child (...).”             </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               I/couc Pi,~rictoc efe~] nak: n~oucemni nem oukarpoc: nem ouhir/n/ ece~swpi nak: w~ pikouji (nim).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يسوع المسيح يمنحك ثباتاً وثمراً، وليكن لك السلام أيها الطفل (...)."            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Let us gather together, O our spiritual fathers, and our orthodox brethren, that we may sing in praises and doxologies, and spiritual songs,            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Marenywou] w~ nenio] m~p~neumatikon: nem nenc~n/ou n~oryodoxon: hina n~tener'alin qen nihwc nem nidoxologia: nem nijw m~p~neumatikon.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلتجتمع أيها الآباء الروحانيون والأخوة الأرثوذكسيون لنرتل بالتسابيح والتماجيد والأناشيد الروحية.            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               in the catholic and apostolic, orthodox Church, for the divine joy which has come to this blessed son (...) who is of pure Christian seed.            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Qen ]ekkl/cia n~oryodoxia: ouoh n~kayolik/ n~a~poctolik/: eybe pairasi n~nou] e~tafswpi m~pais/ri etc~marwout (nim): v/e~te e~bol qen y~nouni ettob/out n~,~rictianoc.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               في الكنيسة الأرثوذكسية الجامعة الرسولية، من أجل هذا الفرح الإلهي الذي صار لهذا الإبن المبارك (...) الذي من النسل الطاهر المسيحي.              </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Who has been crowned with the heavenly crown, of the grace of holy Baptism, through Christ the Lord, to whom is glory, who was baptized in the Jordan river            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Vai e~tau]hiwtf n~,~lom n~te t~ve: n~te pih~mot m~piwmc eyouab e~bol hiten Pi,~rictoc P[oic piw~ou naf: v/e~taf[iwmc qen v~iaro m~Piiordan/c.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الذي لبس الإكليل السماوي الذي لنعمة المعمودية المقدسة، من قِبَل المسيح الرب له المجد، الذي اعتمد في نهر الأردن.            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               at the hand of the baptizer and forerunner, John the Baptist, the priest the son of the priest, the relative of Immanuel.            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ebol qen t~jij m~pip~rodromoc: m~baptict/c Iwann/c piref]wmc: piou/b p~s/ri m~piou/b: picuggen/c n~Emmanou/l.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               من يد السابق الصابغ يوحنا المعمدان الكاهن إبن الكاهن نسيب عمانوئيل.            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Hail to you, O John, son of Zacharias, who was worthy to lay your hand, on the head of our good Savior.              </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ Iwann/c: p~s/ri n~Za,ariac: v/e~takerp~emp~sa n~,a tekjij: e~h~r/i e~jen t~a~ve m~Pencwt/r n~a~gayoc.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               السلام لك يا يوحنا بن زكريا الذي استحققت أن تضع يدك على رأس مخلصنا الصالح.            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               You are higher than the patriarchs, honored above all the prophets, for our Savior lauded you, with His holy mouth saying,            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               K[oci e~nipatriar,/c: k~ta/iout e~nip~rov/t/c t/rou: je a~ Pencwt/r eregkwmiazin nak: e~bol qen rwf eyouab efjw m~moc.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أنت متعال أكثر من رؤساء الآباء، وأجل من كافة الأنبياء، لأن مخلصنا مدحك من فمه الطاهر قائلاً:            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               “Among those born of women, no one is like you, nor greater than you, O John the Baptist.”            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Je m~pe ouon twnf qen nijinmici: n~te nihiomi efo~ni m~mok: oude peynaaf e~rok: w~ Iwann/c piref]wmc.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               "إنه لم يقم في مواليد النساء مَنْ يشبهك، ولا أعظم منك يا يوحنا المعمدان."            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Hail to him who has seen the heavens open, and heard the voice of the Father, proclaiming and saying, “This is My beloved Son in whom I am pleased.”            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere v/e~tafnau e~niv/oui euou/n: ouoh afcwtem e~t~c~m/ n~te Viwt: ecws e~bol ecjw m~moc: je vai pe Pas/ri pamenrit e~tai]ma] n~q/tf.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               السلام للذي رأى السموات مفتوحة، وسمع صوت الآب يصرخ قائلاً: "هذا هو إبني الحبيب الذي به سررت."            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               And the Son standing, in the Jordan river, and the Holy Spirit coming down, on His head like a dove.            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ouoh e~Ps/ri efo~hi e~ratf: qen v~iaro n~te Piiordan/c: ouoh e~Pip~neuma eyouab efn/ou e~pec/t: e~h~r/i e~jen tefa~ve m~v~r/] n~ou[rompi.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               والإبن قائم في نهر الأردن، والروح القدس نازل على رأسه شبه حمامة.            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               And you said, O John, concerning Him, “Behold the Lamb of God, who takes away the sin of the world.”              </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ouoh akjoc n~yok Iwann/c eyb/tf: ic Pihi/b n~te Vnou]: v/eynaw~li m~v~nobi n~te pikocmoc.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد قلت أنت يا يوحنا من أجله: "هذا هو حمل الله الذي يرفع خطية العالم."              </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               You witnessed again to Him saying, “This is He of whom I spoke, ‘He who comes after me is preferred before me, for He was before me.’”            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Akermeyre on eyb/tf ekjw m~moc: je vai pe v/e~taijoc eyb/tf: je v/eyn/ou menencwi afersorp e~roi: je ne ousorp e~roi rw pe.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وشهدت أيضاً من أجله قائلاً: "هذا الذي قلت عنه أن الذي يأتي بعدي كان قبلي، لأنه أقدم مني."            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               And the Lord Christ, to Him be the glory, said with His pure mouth, “We must perfect every righteousness.” He also said to His pure disciples, “Go therefore and make disciples of all the nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit; and every one that believes and is baptized shall be saved.” Thus this washing is handed down from the Lord Christ, and His successors, our masters the pure Apostles in the holy Baptism. For in it is forgiveness of sins, and entry into the kingdoms of the heavens, for it is the key to the heavenly Paradise. Therefore, let us laud, this child with a joyful voice, saying,            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               والسيد المسيح له المجد، قال بفمه الطاهر: "يجب علينا أن نُكَمِّل كل بر." وقال أيضاً لتلاميذه الأطهار: "أمضوا إلى كل الأمم وبشروهم بالإنجيل، وعمدوهم بإسم الآب والإبن والروح القدس، وكل مَنْ آمن واعتمد، خَلُصَ." فصار هذا العماد متوارثاً من السيد المسيح وخلفائه سادتنا الرسل الأطهار بالمعمودية المقدسة. لأن بها غفران الخطايا والدخول إلى ملكوت السموات، لأنها مفاتيح الفردوس السمائي. فلنمدح إذن الإبن بصوت الفرح هكذا قائلين:            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Worthy, worthy, worthy, is (...), the Christian.            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Axioc: axioc: axioc: (nim) ou,~rictianoc.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مستحق مستحق مستحق (...) المسيحي            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Rejoice, therefore, O Christian brethren, for this divine grace of which your children have become worthy of. That is the grace of the holy Baptism and their partaking of the divine Mysteries, the Body and Blood of Christ, the only-begotten Son, the Creator of every creature, which He has poured out for Adam and his race. This grace, which includes Baptism and the communion of the life-giving and divine Mysteries, is established to last to the end of the ages for the forgiveness of sins and being the divine seal, the pledge of eternity in the dwellings of light. Therefore, let us laud this beloved child, saying, “Worthy, worthy, worthy.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               افرحوا أيها الأخوة المسيحيون بهذه النعمة الإلهية التي إستحقها أولادكم، التي هي نعمة المعمودية المقدسة، وتناولهم من الأسرار الإلهية التي هي جسد ودم المسيح، الإبن الوحيد، خالق كل البَرِيَة، اللذان اهرقهما عن الجبلة الآدمية. وصارت هذه النعمة التي للمعمودية والتناول من الأسرار المحيية الإلهية إلى آخر الأدهار لمغفرة الخطايا. والخاتم الإلهي عربون الخلود في المساكن النورانية. فلنمدحن هذا الإبن الحبيب هكذا قائلين (مستحق مستحق مستحق).            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Worthy, worthy, worthy, is (...), the Christian.            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Axioc: axioc: axioc: (nim) ou,~rictianoc.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مستحق مستحق مستحق (...) المسيحي            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Let us praise with Moses the prophet, saying, “Praise the Lord for He has triumphed gloriously.” And let us sing with David the Chanter in the psalm, saying, “Therefore God, Your God, has anointed You With the oil of gladness more than Your companions.” For the oil of gladness is the oil of Chrism, the oil of the divine seal. Receive then the Holy Spirit, you who have received the divine grace that is to holy Baptism. Receive the crowns, full of glory, from Jesus Christ, the King of kings and Lord of lords. Receive the grace of the All-Holy Spirit, the Paraclete. Receive the angelic crown and the spiritual pledge. And you, O baptized one, have received the pledge of the kingdoms of the heavens in truth, and have become a vessel for the Holy Spirit. Let us laud you, saying,            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلنسبح إذن مع موسى النبي قائلين: "سبحوا الرب لأنه بالمجد قد تمجد." ولنرتل مع داود المرتل بالمزمور قائلين: "لذلك مسحك الله إلهك بدهن الفرح أفضل من رفقائك." فدهن الفرح هو دهن المسحة، دهن الخاتم الإلهي. اقبلوا إذن الروح القدس يا مَنْ قد نلتم النعمة الإلهية التي للمعمودية المقدسة. إقبلوا الأكاليل المملوءة مجداً، من قِبَل يسوع المسيح ملك الملوك ورب الأرباب. إقبلوا نعمة الروح القدس المعزي، الكلي القدس. إقبلوا الإكليل الملائكي والعربون الروحي. وأنت أيها الْمُعَمَّد قد أخذت عربون ملكوت السموات حقاً، وصرت إناء للروح القدس. فلنمدحك قائلين:            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Worthy, worthy, worthy, is (...), the Christian.            </Language>            <Language id="Coptic">               Axioc: axioc: axioc: (nim) ou,~rictianoc.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مستحق مستحق مستحق (...) المسيحي            </Language>         </Text>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Let us worship the Holy Trinity, and let us entreat His great goodness, that this blessed child may grow in goodness; and that He may grant him a profitable and prosperous age, and give him increase in days and raise him in works pleasing to Him. +(And that he may be promoted to the priestly ranks). May He assemble the children of the orthodox Church, in harmony and spiritual love, and that her children may grow with a growth that is good and well pleasing; that they may be like a good, fruitful and ever-growing tree. May He incline the hearts of those who rule over us towards us and bring to naught the counsels of our adversaries, and everyone that meditates against us evil thoughts.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلنسجد للثالوث الأقدس ونسأل عِظَم صلاحه أن ينشيء هذا الإبن المبارك نشأة صالحة ويمنحه زماناً ناجحاً. ويعطيه العمر الطويل، وينميه في الأعمال المرضية، +(وليرتق إلى الدرجات الكهنوتية). ويجمع شتات أولاد الكنيسة الأرثوذكسية، بالألفة والمحبة الروحية وينشيء أولادها النشأة الصالحة المرضية، ليكونوا كالشجرة المثمرة الطيبة النامية. ونسأله أن يعطف قلوب المتولين علينا. ويبدد مشورة المعاندين لنا، وكل من يفكر فينا أفكاراً رديئة.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Comment>            <Language id="English">               + Said if the child is male            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               + تقال لو كان الطفل ذكراً            </Language>         </Comment>               <Text>            <Language id="English">               Through the intercessions of the Lady, the pure Virgin Saint Mary, the undefiled, and all the angels of light, and Saint John, who baptized in the river Jordan and the all the fathers and the prophets, and all those who do the works of pleasing (to the Lord) and our masters the pure Apostles, and all the martyrs and righteous saints, now and at all times and unto the age of all ages. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بشفاعة السيدة العذراء الطاهرة مريم البتول الزكية وكافة الملائكة النورانية. والقديس يوحنا الْمُعَمِّد في المياه الأردنية. وجميع الآباء والأنبياء وكافة ذوى الأعمال المرضية. وسادتنا الرسل الأطهار. وجميع الشهداء والقديسين الأبرار. الآن وكل أوان إلى دهر الدهور. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>   </Section>      <InsertDocument path="include/ThreeAbsolutions"/>      <Role id="Priest">      <Comment>         <Language id="English">            And the priest signs the water in the form of the holy Cross three times, and says,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يرشم الكاهن الماء بالصليب المقدس ثلاث مرات وهو يقول:         </Language>      </Comment>         <InsertDocument path="include/OneIsTheHoly"/>   </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/psalm150/Psalm150"/>      <Role id="People">      <Comment>         <Language id="English">            Then they shall say,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويقولون هذا اللحن         </Language>      </Comment>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            Behold, John the Baptist testified, “I baptized the Lord in the waters of the Jordan.         </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            H/ppe afermeyre n~je Iwann/c pibaptict/c je ai]wmc m~P[oic qen pimwou n~te Piiordan/c.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ها قد شهد يوحنا المعمدان أني قد عمدت الرب في مياه الأردن.         </Language>      </Text>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            And I heard the Father’s voice crying out, saying, “This is My Son, My beloved, in whom I am well pleased.”         </Language>         <Language id="Coptic">            Ouoh aicwtem e~t~c~m/ n~te Viwt ecws e~bol je vai pe Pas/ri pamenrit e~tai]ma] n~h/tf.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وسمعت صوت الآب صارخاً: هذا هو إبني حبيبي الذي به سررت.         </Language>      </Text>      </Role>      <Role id="Priest">      <Comment>         <Language id="English">            And he bathes the child in the water, and his girdle (zennar), and his baptismal robe that is on his or her body. Thereafter, the water should be poured into the sea or a river or a planted field.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثم يحمون الطفل في الماء، هو وزناره والقميص الذي تعمد فيه، ثم يطرحون الماء في البحر أو في النهر أو في حقل طاهر.         </Language>      </Comment>   </Role></Document>