<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik" baptism="true" bathingprayer="true">      <Title>      <language id="English">The Prayer of the Bathing</language><language id="Indonesian">Doa Pembasuhan</language>      <language id="Arabic">صلاة الحميم</language>   </Title>   <comment>      <language id="English">         Commonly known as the Prayer of the Basin.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Umumnya dikenal sebagai Doa Baskom.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         المعروفة بصلاة الطشت.      </language>   </comment>   <comment>      <language id="English">         This an optional prayer for those who wish to rejoice for the child’s birth. On the seventh day after the birth and before the baptism, water is poured into a basin (washtub) with a little salt and a little oil, and seven candles lit around it.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Ini merupakan doa opsional bagi mereka yang ingin bersukacita atas kelahiran sang anak. Pada hari ketujuh setelah kelahiran dan sebelum pembaptisan, air dituangkan ke dalam baskom (bak mandi) dengan sedikit garam dan sedikit minyak, dan tujuh lilin yang dinyalakan di sekelilingnya.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         هذه صلاة إختيارية للذين يريدون الفرح بالمولود الجديد. في اليوم السابع، قبل المعمودية، يوضع ماء في طبق مع قليل من الملح والزيت وتضاء سبع شمعات.      </language>   </comment>   <insertdocument path="include/StartOfService"/>   <insertdocument path="include/ThanksgivingPrayer"/>      <insertdocument path="include/PrayerOfIncenseForPaulineEpistle"/>      <role id="People">      <insertdocument path="include/TenouwstSeasonalResponse"/>   </role>      <role id="Deacon">      <biblereference reference="Hebrews 1:5-12" type="section">   </biblereference></role>      <insertdocument path="include/trisagion/Seasonal"/>   <insertdocument path="include/LitanyOfTheGospel"/>      <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Gospel Response</language><language id="Indonesian">Respon Injil</language>                     <language id="Coptic">Je piatcarx af[icarx...</language>      </Title>      <role id="People">         <insertdocument path="include/gospelResponse/Nativity.1"/>      </role>   </section>      <insertdocument path="include/litanies/ThreeShort"/>      <role id="Priest">      <text>         <language id="English">            O God, the Great, the Eternal, the Lord, the Pantocrator, through Your Logos, our Lord Jesus Christ,  THE BEING from the beginning and forever,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Allah, Yang Mahabesar, Yang Kekal, Tuhan, Sang Pantokrator, melalui Logos-Mu, Tuhan kami Yesus Kristus, DIA yang ada sejak semula sampai selamanya,         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Vnou] pinis] pisae~neh P[oic Pipantokratwr v/e~te e~bol hitotf m~f/e~te vwk n~logoc Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc: v/etsop icjen h/ nem sa e~neh.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            يا الله العظيم الأبدي، الرب الضابط الكل، الذي من قِبَل كلمتك، ربنا يسوع المسيح، الكائن منذ البدء وإلى الأبد.         </language>      </text>            <text>         <language id="English">            You have created the world in Your unsearchable wisdom. You created man after Your own image and Your likeness.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Engkau telah menciptakan dunia dengan hikmat-Mu yang tak terselami. Engkau menciptakan manusia menurut gambar dan rupa-Mu.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh menenca y~rekyamio m~pikocmoc qen tekcovia n~ataur/jc: akyamio m~pirwmi kata y/e~te ywk n~hikwn nem kata peki~ni.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            خلقت العالم بحكمتك التي لا تستقصى، وكَوَّنْتَ الأنسان مثل صورتك ومثالك.         </language>      </text>            <text>         <language id="English">            You have filled him with the mercy of Your goodness and have adorned him with all splendor. You have given him a spirit of wisdom and rational understanding and gave him authority over all things. You have appointed him to work all day that he may bless You.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Engkau telah memenuhi dia dengan kemurahan dari kebaikan-Mu dan menghiasinya dengan segala kemegahan. Engkau telah memberi dia roh hikmat dan pengertian yang rasional dan memberinya kuasa atas segala sesuatu. Engkau telah menetapkan dia untuk bekerja sepanjang hari agar ia dapat memuliakan Engkau.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Akmahf e~bol qen v~nai n~tekmeta~gahoc: akcelcwlf e~bol qen metcaie niben: ak] naf n~oup~neuma n~covia nem ouka] n~no/~ton ak] ersisi naf e~jen en,ai niben: ak,af e~erhwb m~pie~hoou t/rf: ouoh je n~tefc~mou e~rok.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وملأتة من رحمة صلاحك، وزينته بكل بهاء، وأعطيته روح حكمة وفهماً عقلياً، وسلطته على كل شىء، وتركته ليعمل كل النهار ويباركك.         </language>      </text>            <text>         <language id="English">            Therefore, we ask and entreat Your goodness for Your servant (...) the son/daughter of (...) and (...), bless him/her with all heavenly blessings. Bless also, O Lord, his/her birth. May his/her days be lengthened according to Your grace.            </language><language id="Indonesian">            Oleh karena itu, kami meminta dan memohon kebaikan-Mu untuk hamba-Mu (...) putra/putri dari (...) dan (...), berkatilah dia dengan segala berkat surgawi. Berkatilah juga, ya Tuhan, kelahirannya. Kiranya hari-harinya dipanjangkan sesuai dengan anugerah-Mu.            </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Eybe vai ten]ho ouoh tentwbh m~mok pia~gayooc hijen pekbwk (nim) p~s/ri pa (nim) nem ya (nim). Cmou e~rof qen c~mou niben n~e~poranion: c~mou e~perjinmici on P[oic: marefjem a~hi kata v/e~te vwk n~h~mot.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            من أجل هذا نسأل ونتضرع إلى صلاحك عن عبدك (...) بن (...) و (...). باركه بكل البركات السمائية، وبارك أيضاً يارب ميلاده وليطل عمره كنعمتك.         </language>      </text>            <text>         <language id="English">            Let him/her grow and increase a hundred fold and sixty fold and thirty fold.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Biarkan dia bertumbuh dan bertambah seratus kali lipat, enam puluh kali lipat, dan tiga puluh kali lipat.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Marefaiai n~tefa~sai n~h~r/i qen r# nem x# nem l#.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            حتى ينمو ويكثر ثلاثين وستين ومائة.         </language>      </text>            <text>         <language id="English">            May his/her parents rejoice and be glad for his/her birth like Zacharias and Elizabeth unto whom You have granted John the prophet.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Biarlah orang tuanya bersukacita dan bergembira atas kelahirannya seperti Zakharia dan Elisabet yang kepada mereka Engkau karuniakan Yohanes sang nabi.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ere pefio] rasi euyel/l e~h~r/i e~jen pefjinmici m~v~r/] n~Za,ariac nem Elicabet: e~takerh~mot nwou m~pip~rov/t/c Iwann/c.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وليفرح به أبواه ويسرا بميلاده مثل زكريا وأليصابات اللذين وهبت لهما يوحنا النبي.         </language>      </text>            <text>         <language id="English">            And at the appointed time, may he/she be worthy of the washing of the new birth, unto forgiveness of his/her sins, preparing him/her to be a temple for Your Holy Spirit.            </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dan pada waktu yang telah ditentukan, kiranya ia layak untuk menerima pembasuhan kelahiran baru, untuk pengampunan dosanya, mempersiapkan dirinya untuk menjadi bait Roh Kudus-Mu.            </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh qen pikec/ou ety/s marefp~emp~sa m~pijwkem n~te piouahm~mici e~p~,w e~bol n~te nefnobi: ekcob] m~mof n~ouervei n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وفي الزمان المحدد فليستحق حميم الميلاد الجديد لغفران خطاياه. أعده هيكلاً لروحك القدوس.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <role id="Priest" silent="true">      <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusion"/>   </role>      <role id="People">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1" antiphonestart="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Psalm 148</language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur 148</language>            <language id="Arabic">المزمور ١٤٨</language>         </Title>               <insertdocument path="include/praises/Psalm148Content"/>      </section>            <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Psalm 149</language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur 149</language>            <language id="Arabic">المزمور ١٤٩</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="include/praises/Psalm149Content"/>         <insertdocument path="include/Alleluia3"/>      </section>      </role>      <insertdocument path="include/ThreeAbsolutions"/>      <role id="Priest">      <comment>         <language id="English">            Then the priest signs the water and says:         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kemudian imam memberi tanda salib pada air dan berkata:         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ثم يرشم الماء قائلا:         </language>      </comment>      <insertdocument path="include/OneIsTheHoly"/>         <comment>         <language id="English">            Then he bathes the child with the water while the people sing:         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kemudian imam memandikan anak itu dengan air sementara umat bernyanyi:         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            و يقول الشعب التوزيع:          </language>      </comment>   </role>   <insertdocument path="include/psalm150/Psalm150"/>   <insertdocument path="include/conclusion/ConclusionOfService"/>   </document>