<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik" baptism="true">      <Title>      <language id="English">The Holy Baptism</language><language id="Indonesian">Baptisan Kudus</language>      <language id="Arabic">ترتيب المعمودية المقدسة</language>   </Title>   <role id="Priest">      <comment>         <language id="English">            The priest says the following absolution on the mother of the child.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Imam mengucapkan absolusi berikut ini untuk sang ibu dari si anak. </language>         <language id="Arabic">            يقول الكاهن هذا التحليل على أم الطفل.         </language>      </comment>   </role>      <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Absolution</language><language id="Indonesian">Absolusi</language>         <language id="Arabic">التحليل</language>      </Title>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               O Master, Lord, God the Pantocrator, Creator of the ages, who commanded His servant Moses in the Law, and showed him the ordinance of the purification concerning women who shall bear children, that they should be made to wait those few days which You have appointed to them, and not touch any of Your holy things, but did keep them apart that they should be saved.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Junjungan Agung, Tuhan, Allah Sang Pantokrator, Pencipta segala zaman, yang telah memerintahkan hamba-Nya Musa melalui Hukum Taurat, dan menunjukkan kepadanya peraturan tentang penyucian bagi wanita yang akan melahirkan anak, bahwa mereka harus menunggu beberapa hari seperti yang telah Engkau tetapkan bagi mereka, dan dia tidak boleh menyentuh apa pun yang kudus dari-Mu, tetapi Engkau memisahkan mereka supaya mereka dapat diselamatkan.</div></language>            <language id="Coptic">               Vn/b P[oic Pipantokratwr Pirefyamio n~nie~wn: v/e~tafouahcahni m~pefbwk Mwu~c/c qen pinomoc: aftamof e~p~yws m~pitoubo et[i e~qoun e~c~himi niben eynamici eyrouo~hi n~hankouji n~e~hoou nai e~takyasou nwou: e~s~tem[i nem h~li n~te n/eyouab n~tak alla aka~reh e~rwou eyrounohem.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيها السيدُ الربُ الإلهُ الضابط الكل، خالق الدهور، الذي أمرَ عبدَه موسى في الناموسِ، وعَرَّفَه حدودَ الطهارةِ الواجبةِ على كلِّ النساءِ اللواتي يلدنَ، أن يلبثنَ أياماً قلائل كما رسمتَ لهنَ لكي لا يمسسنَ شيئاً من قدسِكَ، بل حفظتَهنَ ليخلصنَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               So now also, O our Master, we ask and entreat Your goodness for Your handmaid who has kept Your Law and fulfilled Your commandments.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Maka sekarang juga, ya Guru kami, kami meminta dan memohon kebaikan-Mu untuk hamba-Mu yang telah memelihara Taurat-Mu dan memenuhi perintah-Mu.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Pair/] on Penn/b ten]ho ouoh tentwbh n~tekmeta~gayoc e~h~r/i e~jen tekbwki: yai e~taca~reh e~peknomoc acjwk e~bol n~nekentol/.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               كذلك أيضاً يا سيدَنا نطلبُ ونتضرعُ إلى صلاحِكَ عن أمَتكَ، هذه التي حفظتْ ناموسَكَ، وأكملتْ وصاياكَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               She desires to enter into Your holy place, to worship before Your temple, desiring to partake of Your life-giving Mysteries.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dia rindu masuk ke dalam tempat kudus-Mu, untuk menyembah di hadapan bait-Mu, dan mengambil bagian dalam Misteri-Mu yang memberi hidup.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Acere~piy/min e~i~ e~qoun e~pekma eyouab: e~ouwst nahren pekervei: ec[isswou e~[i e~bol qen nekmuct/rion n~reftanqo.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               واشتهتْ أن تدخلَ إلى موضعِ قدسِكَ، وتسجدَ أمامَ هيكلِكَ مشتاقةً إلى التناولِ من أسرارِكَ المحييةِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               We ask and entreat You, O Good One and Lover of Mankind, bless Your handmaid and purify her, cleanse her from every defilement that is alien to Your purity.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kami meminta dan memohon kepada-Mu, wahai Yang Maha Baik dan Pengasih Umat Manusia, berkatilah pelayan-Mu dan sucikanlah dia, bersihkanlah dia dari segala kenajisan, yang adalah asing bagi kesucian-Mu.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ten]ho ouoh tentwbh m~mok pia~gayoc ouoh m~mairwmi: c~mou e~tekbwki ouoh matouboc: a~ritc n~remhe e~bol ha [wqem niben etoi n~semmo e~pektoubo.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسألُ ونطلبُ إليكَ أيها الصالحُ محبَ البشرِ: باركْ عبدتَكَ وحاللها وطهرها من كلِّ نجاسةٍ غريبةٍ من طهرِكَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               May she be worthy of the communion of Your holy Mysteries, without falling into condemnation.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kiranya dia layak menerima komuni dari Misteri-Mu yang kudus, tanpa jatuh ke dalam penghukuman.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Marecerp~emp~sa n~]koinwnia n~te nekmuct/rion eyouab: a[ne hioui~ e~p~hap.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ولتستحقَ شركةَ أسرارِكَ المقدسةِ، بغيِر وقوعٍ في دينونة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               Likewise also, O our Master, this little child who has been born of her, bless him/her, purify him/her, and bring him/her to full age and stature, that he/she may grow up according to Your holy will.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Demikian juga, ya Guru kami, anak kecil yang telah dilahirkan olehnya, berkatilah dia, sucikanlah dia, dan bawalah dia sampai pada usia dan pertumbuhan yang penuh, supaya dia bertumbuh sesuai dengan kehendak-Mu yang kudus.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Pair/] on Penn/b paikouji n~a~lou e~taumacf e~bol n~q/tc: c~mou e~rof: matoubof: a~nitf e~p~swi n~]mai/~ nem ]hul/kia n~tefa~sai kata pekouws eyouab.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               هكذا أيضاً يا سيدَنا هذا الطفل المولود منها باركه وقدسه، وأت به إلى حدِ القامةِ والبلوغِ، ولينمو كمشيئتِكَ الطاهرةِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               Establish him/her in Your orthodox faith and Your hope and Your love, through Your only-begotten Son, Jesus Christ our Lord.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Teguhkanlah dia di dalam iman ortodoks-Mu dan pengharapan-Mu serta kasih-Mu, melalui Putra-Mu yang tunggal, Yesus Kristus, Tuhan kami.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Matajrof qen peknah] n~oryodoxoc nem tekhelpic nem teka~gap/: hiten pekmonogen/c n~S/ri I/couc Pi,~rictoc Pen[oic            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ثبته في إيمانِكَ الأرثوذكسي ورجائكَ ومحبتِكَ، بإبنِكَ الوحيد يسوع المسيح ربنا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <role id="Priest" silent="true">         <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusionEnding"/>      </role>   </section>      <insertdocument path="include/litanies/Catechumens"/>   <insertdocument path="include/LetUsPray"/>      <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Litany</language><language id="Indonesian">Litani</language>         <language id="Arabic">الطلبة</language>      </Title>         <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               O Master, Lord Jesus Christ, who bowed the heavens and came down to earth, whose word smites the rocks more mightily than swords, before whose face the waters were troubled and fled backwards.               </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ya Tuan, Tuhan Yesus Kristus, yang telah menekuk langit dan turun ke bumi, yang firman-Nya menghantam batu karang dengan lebih dahsyat daripada pedang, yang di hadapan-Nya air menjadi gentar dan bergulung ke belakang.               </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Vn/b P[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc v/e~tafrek niv/oui: afi~ e~pec/t e~p~kahi v/e~ta pefcaji hioui~ n~ca nipetra e~hote hanc/fi v/e~ta nimwou c~yerter qa tefh/ ouoh auvwt e~vahou.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيها السيدُ الربُ يسوع المسيح، الذي طأطأ السمواتِ ونزلَ إلى الأرضِ. الذي يحطمُ كلامُه الصخورَ أكثر من السيوفِ، الذي ارتعدتْ منه المياهُ ورجعتْ إلى خلف.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               Heal these children (or this child) who come to be made catechumens.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Sembuhkanlah anak-anak ini (atau anak ini) yang akan dijadikan katekumen.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Arivaqri e~naia~lwoui~ (ie paia~lou) eyn/ou e~qoun e~erkat/,oumenoc.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               اشفْ هؤلاءَ الأطفالَ (أو هذا الطفلَ) الداخلينَ ليوعظوا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               Show them (or him) the way in which it is meet for them to walk, instruct them in the grace of Your Holy Spirit that they may abide in the imperishable gift of Your Holy Spirit, and grant them the forgiveness of their sins,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Tunjukkanlah  jalan yang sesuai bagi mereka (atau dia) untuk berjalan, ajarlah mereka dalam anugerah Roh Kudus-Mu sehingga mereka dapat tinggal dalam karunia Roh Kudus-Mu yang tidak dapat binasa, dan berikanlah mereka pengampunan atas dosa mereka,            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Eeke~ouwnh nwou (ie naf) e~bol m~pimwit: e~tecemp~sa n~toumosi hiwtf a~rikat/,in m~mwou m~pih~mot n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab e~p~jintouswpi qen ]dwrea~ n~attako n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab ouoh n~tekerh~mot nwou m~p~,w e~bol n~te nounobi             </language>            <language id="Arabic">               اكشف لهم الطريقَ الذي ينبغي أن يسلكوا فيه. عظهُم بنعمةِ روحِكَ القدوس ليكونوا في الموهبةِ غيرِ الفاسدةِ التي لروحِكَ القدوس. انعم عليهم بغفرانِ خطاياهم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               and grant them by Your grace that they may be healed from the destroying sin,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               dan dengan anugerah-Mu,  berilah mereka kesembuhan dari dosa yang membinasakan,            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh n~tekt/ic nwou qen pekh~mot eyroutaho m~pital[o: e~bol ha v~nobi n~reftako.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وامنحهم بنعمتِكَ أن يدركوا الشفاءَ من الخطيئةِ المهلكةِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               that they may be made worthy of the holy Baptism of the new birth, that they may receive also the washing of the spotless Baptism of Your Holy Spirit,              </language><language id="Indonesian">               supaya mereka layak menerima kelahiran kembali dari baptisan kudus, supaya mereka juga menerima pembasuhan dengan baptisan Roh Kudus-Mu yang tak bercacat,              </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Eyrouerp~emp~sa m~piwmc eyouab n~te pouahm~mici: hina n~tou[i hwou m~pijwkem n~te piwmc n~ata[ni n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ويستحقوا العمادَ الطاهرَ الذي للميلادِ الجديدِ. وينالوا حميمَ العمادِ الذي بغيرِ عيبٍ بروحِ قدسِكَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               that they may see with holy vision unto sure understanding, and may give glory to You, O God, for Yours is the glory with Your good Father and the Holy Spirit, for ever. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               supaya mereka dapat melihat dengan penglihatan yang kudus sampai kepada pengertian yang pasti, dan memuliakan Engkau, ya Allah, karena bagi-Mulah kemuliaan bersama Bapa-Mu yang baik dan Roh Kudus sampai selamanya. Amin.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ep~jintounau m~bol qen ounau efouab e~pika] etc~mont: ouoh n~tou]w~ou nak Vnou] je piw~ou vwk pe nem Pekiwt n~a~gayoc nem Pip~neuma eyouab sa e~neh: a~m/n.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وينظروا نظراً طاهراً إلى الفهمِ الثابتِ. ويمجدوكَ يا الله. لأن لك المجدُ مع أبيكَ الصالح والروح القدس إلى الأبد آمين.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LetUsPray"/>   </section>      <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            A Prayer Over the Oil of the Catechumens         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Sebuah Doa Atas Minyak Katekumen</language>         <language id="Arabic">            صلاة على دهن الموعوظين         </language>      </Title>      <role id="Priest">         <comment>            <language id="English">               There are three oils used in the Coptic Church: the oil of catechumens, the Hagielaion (the oil of gladness), and the Myron.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ada tiga minyak yang digunakan dalam Gereja Koptik: minyak katekumen, Hagelaion (minyak sukacita), dan Mairon.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               يوجد في الكنيسة القبطية ثلاثة أنواع من الزيت: زيت الموعوظين، وزيت الغاليلون (أو الفرح)، وزيت الميرون.            </language>         </comment>               <comment>            <language id="English">               The priest takes the vessel of the oil of catechumens and says the following prayer on it,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Imam mengambil bejana minyak katekumen dan mengucapkan doa berikut di atasnya,            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               يمسك الكاهن قارورة الزيت الموعوظين ويصلي عليها قائلاً:            </language>         </comment>            <text>            <language id="English">               O Master, Lord God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ.             </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ya Junjungan Agung, Tuhan Allah Sang Pantokrator, Bapa dari Tuhan, Allah dan Juruselamat kami, Yesus Kristus.             </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Vn/b P[oic Vnou] Pipantokratwr Viwt m~Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh Pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيها السيدُ الربُ الإلهُ ضابط الكل أبو ربنا وإلهنا ومخلصنا يسوع المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               We ask and entreat Your goodness, O Lover of Mankind, the One, only, and true God with Your only-begotten Son Jesus Christ, our Lord, and the Holy Spirit,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kami meminta dan memohon kebaikan-Mu, ya Pengasih Umat Manusia, Allah yang Esa, satu-satunya, dan yang benar melalui Putra-Mu Yang Tunggal, Yesus Kristus, Tuhan kami, dan Roh Kudus,            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ten]ho ouoh tentwbh n~tekmeta~gayoc Pimairwmi: Piouai m~mauatf Vnou] n~tav~m/i nem pekmonogen/c n~S/ri I/couc Pi,~rictoc Pen[oic nem Pip~neuma eyouab.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسألُ ونتضرعُ إلى صلاحِكَ يا محبَ البشرِ، الواحد الوحيد الإله الحقيقي، وإبنك الوحيد يسوع المسيح ربنا، والروح القدس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               to look upon Your creation, this oil, and let it become for the casting out of demons and their magic, sorcery and all idolatry,            </language><language id="Indonesian">lihatlah ciptaan-Mu, minyak ini, dan biarlah minyak ini menjadi pengusir setan, sihir, ilmu tenung dan semua penyembahan berhala,            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Hopwc qen oujoust n~tekjoust e~jen pekcwnt: paineh vai ouoh n~teky~refswpi e~oubwl e~bol n~te handemwn nem noumagia nem nouvarmagia nem metsamse i~dwlon niben.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               لكي تنظر نظراً إلى جَبلَتِكَ – هذا الزيت – وتجعله أن يحلَ أعمالَ الشياطين وسحرَهم وكلَّ عبادةِ الأوثانِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               and change it and manifest it as an oil for the anointing of catechumens, to make the soul believe in Christ Jesus our Lord.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               dan ubahkan dan nyatakanlah minyak ini untuk pengurapan bagi para katekumen, supaya jiwa percaya kepada Kristus Yesus, Tuhan kita.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh ouoybef ouoh ouonhf e~ouneh n~ywhc n~kat/,/cic: e~p~jiner ]'u,/ m~pic~t/ qen Pi,~rictoc I/couc Pen[oic.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وانقله واظهره ليكونَ زيتَ مسحةٍ وموعظةٍ لكي يجعلَ النفسَ مؤمنةً بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِنا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <role id="Priest" silent="true">         <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusionEnding"/>         </role>         <insertdocument path="include/LetUsPray"/>   </section>      <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Another Prayer Over the Oil         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Doa Lainnya Untuk Minyak</language>         <language id="Arabic">            صلاة أخرى على الزيت         </language>      </Title>      <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               O Master, Lord, God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ, Your only-begotten Son and Logos, who was crucified for as under Pontius Pilate, and confessed the good confession.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ya Tuhan, Tuhan, Allah Pantokrates, Bapa Tuhan, Allah, dan Juruselamat kami, Yesus Kristus, Anak-Mu yang tunggal dan Logos, yang telah disalibkan di bawah pemerintahan Pontius Pilatus, dan yang telah memberikan pengakuan yang baik.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Vn/b P[oic Vnou] Pipantokratwr Viwt m~Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh Pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc pekmonogen/c n~logoc: v/e~tauer-c~taurwnin m~mof e~h~r/i e~jwn nahren Pontioc Pilatoc: e~afero~mologin n~]o~mologia eynanec.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيها السيدُ الربُ الإلهُ ضابط الكل، أبو ربِنا وإلهنا ومخلصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ، وحيدك الكلمة، الذي صُلِبَ عنا على عهدِ بيلاطس البنطي، وإعترف الإعترافَ الحسنَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               We ask and entreat Your goodness, O Lover of Mankind, send Your holy power upon this oil;            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kami meminta dan memohon kebaikan-Mu, wahai Pengasih Umat Manusia, kirimkanlah kuasa-Mu yang kudus ke atas minyak ini;            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ten]ho ouoh tentwbh n~tekmeta~gayoc Pimairwmi ouwrp n~tekjom eyouab e~h~r/i e~jen paineh vai.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسألُ ونطلبُ من صلاحِكَ يا محبَ البشرِ: أرسلْ قوتَكَ المقدسةَ على هذا الزيتِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               make it become oil of catechumens, given against all the works of the adversary, all witchcraft, all sorcery and all idolatry, and for the overthrow of all evil things.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               jadikanlah ini minyak urapan, yang diberikan untuk melawan segala pekerjaan musuh, segala sihir, segala tenung dan segala penyembahan berhala, dan untuk meruntuhkan segala sesuatu yang jahat.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Marefswpi n~ouneh n~kat/,/ceoc: ef]oube e~nergia niben n~te piantikimenoc: nem meta~,w niben nem metvarmagoc niben nem metsamse i~dwlon niben e~oujintacyo e~vahou n~te hwb niben ethwou.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ليصيرَ دهنَ موعظةٍ يبطل كلَّ أفعالِ المضادِ، وكلَّ سحرٍ وكلَّ تعزيمٍ وكلَّ عبادةِ الأوثانِ. ويردَ إلى خلفٍ كلَّ شيءٍ ردىءٍ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               Through Your only-begotten Son, our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ.              </language><language id="Indonesian">               Melalui Putra-Mu Yang Tunggal, Tuhan, Allah, dan Juruselamat kami, Yesus Kristus.              </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ebol hiten pekmonogen/c n~S/ri Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh Pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               بإبنك الوحيد ربنا وإلهنا ومخلصنا يسوع المسيح.             </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               For Yours is the glory and the dominion, with Him and the Holy Spirit forever. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Bagi-Mulah kemuliaan dan kuasa, bersama dengan Dia dan Roh Kudus sampai selamanya. Amin.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Piw~ou nem pia~mahi vwk nemaf: nem Pip~neuma eyouab: sa e~neh: a~m/n.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               لك المجد والعزة معه ومع الروح القدس إلى الأبد. آمين.            </language>         </text>               <comment>            <language id="English">               Here the priest examines the condition of the children, whether there be earrings in their ears, or ornaments on their feet, or rings on their fingers or armlets, and he asks for their removal.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Di sini, imam memeriksa kondisi anak-anak, apakah ada anting di telinga mereka, atau perhiasan di kaki mereka, atau cincin di jari mereka atau gelang tangan, dan dia meminta untuk melepaskannya.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               هنا يفحص الكاهن الأطفال، ويأمر بخلع كل شيء من أذانهم وارجلهم وأياديهم.            </language>         </comment>               <comment>            <language id="English">               He then takes the vessel of oil and begins anointing the males and then the females.              </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dia kemudian mengambil bejana berisi minyak dan mulai mengurapi yang laki-laki dan kemudian perempuan.              </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ثم يأخذ وعاء الزيت ويرشم الأطفال الذكور ثم الإناث.            </language>         </comment>               <comment>            <language id="English">               He anoints the forehead, saying,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dia mengurapi dahi, sambil berkata,            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               يدهن جبهته قائلاً:            </language>         </comment>            <text>            <language id="English">               I anoint you (...), in the name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, one God,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Aku mengurapi engkau (...), dalam nama Bapa dan Putra dan Roh Kudus, Allah yang esa,            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ceywhc m~mok (nim) qen v~ran m~Viwt nem Ps/ri nem Pip~neuma eyouab Ounou] n~ouwt.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أدهنُكَ يا (...) بإسم الآب والإبن والروح القدس الإله الواحد.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               [with] oil of catechumens for (...) in the one, holy, catholic and apostolic Church of God. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               (dengan) minyak katekumen untuk (...) dalam Gereja Allah yang satu, kudus, katolik dan apostolik. Amin.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Elaion kat/,/ceoc (nim) en t/ a~gia mon/ kayolik/ ke a~poctolik/ ekkl/cia tou Yeou: a~m/n.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               زيت عظةٍ لـ (...) في كنيسةِ الله الواحدةِ المقدسةِ الجامعةِ الرسوليةِ. آمين.            </language>         </text>               <comment>            <language id="English">               He anoints the chest, the hands and the back, saying,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dia mengurapi dada, tangan dan punggung, sambil berkata,            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ثم يدهن قلبه ويديه وظهره قائلاً:            </language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="English">               May this oil bring to naught all assaults of the adversary. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kiranya minyak ini membuat semua serangan musuh menjadi sia-sia. Amin.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Paineh vai n~tefkwrf n~antia niben n~te piantikimenoc: a~m/n.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               هذا الزيتُ يبطلُ كلَّ مقاومةِ المضادِ. آمين            </language>         </text>      </role>   </section>      <insertdocument path="include/LetUsEntreat"/>      <role id="Priest">      <text>         <language id="English">            Blessed are You, O our Master, Lord, the Pantocrator. Blessed is Your only-begotten Son, Jesus Christ our Lord.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Terpujilah Engkau, ya Tuan kami, Tuhan, Sang Pantokrator. Terpujilah Putra-Mu <span style="background-color: rgba(66, 98, 142, 0.1);">Yang Tunggal</span>, Yesus Kristus Tuhan kami.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Kc~marwout Penn/b P[oic Pipantokratwr. Fc~marwout n~je pekmonogen/c n~S/ri I/couc Pi,~rictoc Pen[oic.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            تباركتَ يا ملكَنا الربُ ضابطَ الكلِّ. مباركٌ هو إبنُكَ الوحيد يسوع المسيح ربنا.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Through whom You have drawn all the nations out of darkness, to the true and wonderful light, and from error and vanity of idols to the knowledge of the truth.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Melalui Dia Engkau telah menarik semua bangsa keluar dari kegelapan kepada terang yang benar dan ajaib, dan dari kesalahan dan kesia-siaan berhala kepada pengenalan akan kebenaran.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Vai e~te e~bol hitotf akywhem n~nieynoc t/rou e~bol qen p~,aki e~qoun e~piouwini m~m/i etoi n~s~v/ri: nem e~bol qen oup~lan/ nem oumete~v~l/ou n~te nii~dwlon e~qoun e~p~couen ]meym/i.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            هذا الذي من قِبَلِه دعوتَ كلَّ الأممِ من الظلمةِ إلى النورِ الحقيقي العجيبِ. ومنَ الضلالةِ وأباطيلِ الأوثانِ إلى معرفةِ الحقِ.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/LetUsPray"/>      <role id="Priest">      <text>         <language id="English">            You have called Your servants by Your holy and blessed name.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Engkau telah memanggil hamba-hamba-Mu dengan nama-Mu yang kudus dan terpuji.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Neke~biaik nai n~yok akyahmou qen pekran eyouab ouoh etc~marwout.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أنتَ دعوتَ عبيدَكَ هؤلاء بإسمِكَ القدوسِ المبارك.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Write their names in Your book, count them with Your people and those who fear You.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Tuliskanlah nama mereka di dalam kitab-Mu, hitunglah mereka bersama umat-Mu dan orang-orang yang takut akan Engkau.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Cqe pouran qen pekjwm: o~pou nem peklaoc nem n/eterho] qa tekh/.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            اكتبْ أسماءَهم في كتابِكَ واحسبْهُم مع شعبِكَ وخائفيكَ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Graciously grant them to grow in the faith, and forgiveness of sins, preparing them to be a temple of Your Holy Spirit, through Your only-begotten Son, Jesus Christ our Lord.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dengan murah hati, berikanlah mereka pertumbuhan dalam iman dan pengampunan dosa, persiapkanlah mereka menjadi bait Roh Kudus-Mu, melalui Putra-Mu Yang Tunggal, Yesus Kristus, Tuhan kami.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Arikataxioin e~erh~mot nwou e~[imai/~ qen v~nah] nem p~,w e~bol n~te hannobi: ekcob] m~mwou n~ouervei n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab hiten pekmonogen/c n~S/ri I/couc Pi,~rictoc Pen[oic.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            تفضل أن تنعمَ عليهم بالنموِ في الإيمانِ وغفرانِ الخطايا. أعدهُم هيكلاً لروحِكَ القدوس، بإبنِكَ الوحيد يسوعَ المسيحِ ربنا.           </language>      </text>   </role>      <role id="Priest" silent="true">      <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusionEnding"/>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/LetUsEntreat"/>      <role id="Priest">      <comment>         <language id="English">            The priest asks for the names of those who are to be baptized, and prays over them, saying,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Imam menanyakan nama-nama mereka yang akan dibaptis dan mendoakan mereka, dan berkata,         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            يسأل الكاهن عن أسماء المعتمدين ويصلي قائلاً:         </language>      </comment>            <text>         <language id="English">            Again, let us ask God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Sekali lagi, marilah kita memohon kepada Allah Sang Pantokrator, Bapa dari Tuhan, Allah, dan Juruselamat kita, Yesus Kristus,         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Palin on maren]ho e~Vnou] Pipantokratwr Viwt m~Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh Pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وأيضاً فلنسألُ الله ضابطَ الكلِّ أبا ربِنا وإلهِنا ومخلصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            for Your servants who have presented their names, and entered into the faith by Your grace, that You make them worthy to attain the grace for which they have presented themselves,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            bagi hamba-hamba-Mu yang telah mempersembahkan nama mereka, dan masuk ke dalam iman oleh anugerah-Mu, kiranya Engkau melayakkan untuk memperoleh anugerah yang telah mereka persembahkan,         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Eybe neke~biaik e~tau] n~nouran e~qoun: n/e~taui~ e~qoun qen pinah] qen pekh~mot: hina n~teky~ouerp~emp~sa n~sasni e~pih~mot e~tau] m~pououoi e~rof.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            من أجلِ عبيدِكَ الذين قُدِمَت أسماؤهُم ودخلوا في الإيمانِ بنعمتِكَ، لكي تجعلَهُم أهلاً أن يفوزوا بالنعمةِ التي تقدموا إليها.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            and that they may be purified from the sin that is in the world, and may be delivered from the slavery of corruption.           </language><language id="Indonesian">            dan supaya mereka disucikan dari dosa yang ada di dalam dunia, dan dibebaskan dari perbudakan kehancuran.           </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh n~toutoubo e~bol ha v~nobi et qen pikocmoc ouoh n~touerremhe e~bol ha ]metbwk n~te p~tako.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ويتطهروا من الخطيئةِ التي في العالمِ، ويُعْتَقُوا من عبوديةِ الفسادِ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            For the authority of mercy is with You, O Pantocrator, the Lord our God.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Sebab otoritas belas kasihan ada bersama-Mu, ya Pantokrator, Tuhan Allah kami.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Je n~yok pe v/e~tere p~ersisi m~pinai ,/ n~totk Pipantokratwr P[oic Pennou].         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            لأن سلطانَ الرحمةِ بيدِكَ أيها الضابط الكل الرب إلهنا.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <role id="Deacon">      <text>         <language id="English">            Pray for those who have presented their names, that the Lord may make them worthy of holy Baptism unto the forgiveness of their sins.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Berdoalah bagi mereka yang telah menyerahkan nama mereka, agar Tuhan membuat mereka layak untuk menerima baptisan kudus untuk pengampunan dosa-dosa mereka.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Twbh e~jen n/e~tau] n~nouran e~qoun: eyre P[oic aitou n~emp~sa m~piwmc eyouab e~p~,w e~bol n~te nounobi.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            اطلبوا عن الذينَ قُدِمَت أسماؤهُم لكي يجعلَهم الربُ مستحقينَ العِمَاد المقدس لغفرانِ خطاياهم.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>      <role id="Priest">      <text>         <language id="English">            O Master, Lord, God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ. We ask and entreat Your goodness, O Lover of Mankind, have mercy on Your servants who have presented their names.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Junjungan Agung, Tuhan, Allah Sang Pantokrator, Bapa dari Tuhan, Allah dan Juruselamat kami, Yesus Kristus. Kami meminta dan memohon kebaikan-Mu, ya Pengasih Umat Manusia, kasihanilah hamba-hamba-Mu yang telah mempersembahkan nama mereka.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Vn/b P[oic Vnou] Pipantokratwr Viwt m~Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh Pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc. Ten]ho ouoh tentwbh n~tekmeta~gayoc Pimairwmi: neke~biaik e~tau] n~nouran e~qoun: nai nwou.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أيها السيدُ الربُ الإلهُ ضابط الكلِّ أبو ربِنَا وإلهنا ومخلصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ. نسألُ ونطلبُ من صلاحِكَ يا محبَ البشرِ، عبيدك الذين قُدِمَت أسماؤهم، إرحمهم.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Make them worthy of the grace for which they have presented themselves, that they may receive of Your Holy Spirit, and may be filled with Your divine power,         </language><language id="Indonesian">Layakkanlah menerima anugerah dimana telah mereka persembahkan diri mereka sendiri, sehingga mereka dapat menerima Roh Kudus-Mu, dan dipenuhi dengan kuasa ilahi-Mu,         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Aritou m~p~emp~sa m~pih~mot e~tau] m~pououoi e~rof. Eyrou[i e~bol qen Pekp~neuma eyouab ouoh n~toumoh e~bol qen tekjom n~nou].         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            إجعلهم مستحقينَ للنعمةِ التي تقدموا إليها، لينالوا من روحِ قدسِكَ، ويمتلئوا من قوتِكَ الإلهيةِ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            and may take the likeness of Your only-begotten Son, becoming one with Him, who is our Lord Jesus Christ.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            agar menjadi serupa dengan Putra-Mu <span style="background-color: rgba(66, 98, 142, 0.1);">Yang </span><span style="background-color: rgba(66, 98, 142, 0.1);">Tunggal</span>, dan menjadi satu dengan Dia, yaitu Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Eyrouswpi euo~ni m~pekmonogen/c n~S/ri euoi n~ouai nemaf: n~yof pe Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ويكونوا متشبهين بإبنِكَ الوحيد ربنا يسوع المسيح صائرينَ واحداً معه.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Grant them a purified mind and godly thoughts.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Berikanlah kepada mereka akal budi yang murni dan pikiran yang saleh.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ari,arizecye nwou n~ounouc eftoub/out nem oulogicmoc n~euceb/c.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أنعم عليهُم بعقلٍ نقيٍ وفكرٍ طاهرٍ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            And grant Your servants to be guarded through the grace of Your Holy Spirit, and lead them to the hope of Your eternal benefits.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dan jagalah hamba-hamba-Mu melalui anugerah Roh Kudus-Mu, dan pimpinlah mereka kepada pengharapan keuntungan kekekalan bersama-Mu.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh m/ic n~neke~biaik eyrouswpi eua~reh e~rwou hiten pih~mot n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab: ouoh [imwit qajwou e~qoun e~]helpic n~te neka~gayoc n~e~w~nion.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وامنح عبيدَك أن يكونوا محفوظينَ بنعمةِ روحِكَ القدوس. واهدهم إلى رجاءِ خيراتِكَ الأبديةِ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Through Your only-begotten Son, Jesus Christ our Lord.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Melalui Putra-Mu <span style="background-color: rgba(66, 98, 142, 0.1);">Yang </span><span style="background-color: rgba(66, 98, 142, 0.1);">Tunggal</span>, Yesus Kristus, Tuhan kami.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Hiten pekmonogen/c n~S/ri I/couc Pi,~rictoc Pen[oic.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            بإبنِكَ الوحيد يسوع المسيح ربنا.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <role id="Priest" silent="true">      <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusionEnding"/>   </role>      <comment>      <language id="English">         Then they kneel.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Kemudian mereka berlutut.</language>      <language id="Arabic">         يحنو الشعب ركبهم.      </language>   </comment>   <insertdocument path="include/LetUsEntreat"/>      <role id="Priest">         <comment>         <language id="English">            The priest prays over them, saying,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Imam mendoakan mereka dengan berkata,         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            يطلب الكاهن عنهم قائلاً:         </language>      </comment>            <text>         <language id="English">            Again, let us ask with great fervor and entreat God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Sekali lagi, marilah kita meminta dengan penuh semangat dan memohon kepada Allah Sang Pantokrator, Bapa dari Tuhan, Allah, dan Juruselamat kita, Yesus Kristus,         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Palin on maren]ho qen ou[wlk n~houo~ ouoh tentwbh m~Vnou] Pipantokratwr Viwt m~Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh Pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وأيضاً فلنطلبُ بإلحاحٍ كثيرٍ، ونسأل الله ضابطَ الكلِّ، أبا ربِنا وإلهِنا ومخلصِنا يسوعَ المسيح.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            for His servants who have presented their names, that He open the ears of their heart, and kindle within them a light of knowledge, and persuade their hearts to know the certainty of the words with which they have been instructed—He is the Lord our God, the Pantocrator who has  the authority of mercy.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            bagi hamba-hamba-Nya yang telah menyebutkan nama-nama mereka, agar Dia membuka telinga hati mereka, dan menyalakan di dalam diri mereka cahaya pengetahuan, dan membujuk hati mereka untuk mengetahui kepastian firman yang telah diajarkan kepada mereka - Dialah Tuhan, Allah kita, Sang Pantokrator yang memiliki otoritas belas kasihan.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Eybe nefe~biaik e~tau] n~nouran e~qoun hopwc n~tefouwn n~nimasj n~te pouh/t ouoh n~teferouwini n~q~r/i n~q/tou n~ououwini n~te p~e~mi ouoh n~tefywt m~pouh/t e~p~jincouen p~tajro n~nicaji e~tauerkat/,in m~mwou n~q/tou n~je v/e~tere p~ersisi m~pinai ,/ n~totf Pipantokratwr P[oic Pennou].         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            من أجلِ عبيدِه الذين قُدمَت أسماؤهُم، لكي يفتحَ مسامعَ قلوبِهم، ويضيءَ عليهُم بنورِ المعرفةِ، ويطيبَ قلوبَهم لمعرفةِ ثباتِ الكلامِ الذي وُعِظُوا به. الذي بيدِه سلطانُ الرحمةِ، الضابطٌ الكل الربُ إلهنا.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/LetUsPray"/>      <role id="Priest">      <text>         <language id="English">            O Master, Lord, God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ. We ask and entreat Your goodness, O Lover of Mankind, that through the invocation of Your holy name, all powers and all hostile and evil spirits may be cast out.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Tuhan, Tuhan, Allah Sang Pantokrator, Bapa dari Tuhan, Allah dan Juruselamat kami, Yesus Kristus. Kami meminta dan memohon kebaikan-Mu, ya Pengasih Umat Manusia, agar dengan menyebutkan nama-Mu yang kudus, segala kuasa dan perseteruan dan semua roh jahat dapat diusir.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Vn/b P[oic Vnou] Pipantokratwr Viwt m~Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh Pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc. Ten]ho ouoh tentwbh n~tekmeta~gayoc Pimairwmi: hopwc e~bol hiten ]e~pik~l/cic n~te pekran eyouab n~toubwl e~bol n~je jom niben nem p~neuma niben n~antion ouoh ethwou.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أيها السيدُ الربُ الإلهُ ضابط الكلَّ أبو ربِنا وإلهنا ومخلصِنا يسوع المسيح. نسألُ ونطلبُ من صلاحِكَ يا محبَ البشرِ، لكي من قِبَلِ استدعاءِ إسمِكَ القدوس تنحَلُ كلُّ القواتِ وكلُّ الأرواحِ المقاومةِ الشريرةِ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Rebuke them and drive them out. For You have called Your servants, who come from darkness into light, from death to life, from error to the knowledge of the truth, from idolatry to the knowledge of You, the true God.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Tegurlah mereka dan usirlah mereka. Karena Engkau telah memanggil keluar hamba-hamba-Mu dari kegelapan kepada terang, dari kematian kepada hidup, dari kesesatan kepada pengetahuan akan kebenaran, dari penyembahan berhala kepada pengenalan akan Engkau, Allah yang benar.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Tahno m~mwou ouoh a~ria~yetin m~mwou: je n~yok pe e~takywhem n~neke~biaik nai: eyn/ou e~qoun e~bol qen p~,aki e~ouwini: e~bol qen oumou e~ouwnq: e~bol qen oup~lan/ e~p~jincouen ]meym/i: e~bol qen oumetsam se i~dwlon e~qoun e~oujincouwnk Vnou] m~m/i.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            إمنعها وارفضها، لأنكَ أنتَ الذي دعوتَ عبيدَكَ هؤلاءَ الداخلين منَ الظلمةِ إلى النورِ، ومن الموتِ إلى الحياةِ، ومن الضلالةِ إلى معرفةِ الحقِ، ومن عبادةِ الأصنامِ إلى معرفتِكَ يا الله الحقيقي.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Search the chambers of their hearts, O You who searched Jerusalem with a candle. Let no evil sprit conceal himself within them.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Selidikilah bilik-bilik hati mereka, ya Engkau yang telah memeriksa Yerusalem dengan lilin. Jangan biarkan roh jahat menyembunyikan diri di dalam mereka.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Moust n~nitamion n~te pouh/t: v/e~tafmoust n~Ieroucal/m qen ouq/bc: m~per,a oup~neuma efhwou ecrefhwp n~q~r/i n~q/tou.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            فَتِّشْ خزائنَ قلوبَهُم يا مَنْ فَتَّشَ أورشليمَ بسراجٍ. لا تدعْ روحاً رديئاً يختفي فيهُم.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Grant them a saving purity, and bestow upon them eternal salvation.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Berilah mereka kemurnian yang menyelamatkan, dan anugerahkanlah kepada mereka keselamatan yang kekal.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Eke~er,arizecye nwou n~oujintoubo n~oujai ouoh a~rih~mot nwou n~oucw] n~e~w~nion.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أنعمْ عليهُم بطهارةٍ وخلاصٍ، وهب لهم خلاصاً أبدياً.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            And renew their birth a second time by the washing of the new birth and the forgiveness of their sins; preparing them to be a temple of Your Holy Spirit, through Your only-begotten Son, Jesus Christ our Lord.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dan perbaharuilah kelahiran mereka untuk kedua kalinya melalui pembasuhan kelahiran baru dan pengampunan dosa mereka; persiapkanlah mereka menjadi bait Roh Kudus-Mu, melalui Putra-Mu <span style="background-color: rgba(66, 98, 142, 0.1);">Yang </span><span style="background-color: rgba(66, 98, 142, 0.1);">Tunggal</span>, Yesus Kristus, Tuhan kami.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh j~vwou n~kecop hiten piouahm~mici n~te pijwkem nem n~,w e~bol n~te nounobi: ekcob] m~mwou n~ouervei n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab hiten pekmonogen/c n~S/ri I/couc Pi,~rictoc Pen[oic.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ولدهُم مرةً أخرى بحميمِ الميلادِ الجديدِ ومغفرةِ خطاياهُم. أعدَهُم هيكلاً لروحِكَ القدوس بإبنِكَ الوحيدِ يسوعَ المسيحِ ربِنا.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <role id="Priest" silent="true">      <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusionEnding"/>   </role>      <role id="Priest">      <comment>         <language id="English">            Then the priest lays his hands upon them, saying,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kemudian imam menumpangkan tangannya ke atas mereka dan berkata,         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ثم يضع الكاهن يده عليهم قائلاً:         </language>      </comment>      <text>         <language id="English">            In the name of the only-begotten Son, Jesus Christ, I purify and prepare beforehand this body.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dalam nama Putra Tunggal, Yesus Kristus, aku menyucikan dan mempersiapkan tubuh ini.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Qen v~ran m~pimonogen/c n~S/ri I/couc Pi,~rictoc: ]toubo ouoh ]ersorp n~cob] m~paicwma vai.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            بإسم الإبن الوحيدِ يسوعَ المسيحِ، اُطَهِّر واسبق أهيئ هذا الجسد.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            In the name of the only-begotten Son, Jesus Christ, may it be delivered from every demon and every uncleanness.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dalam nama Putra Tunggal, Yesus Kristus, kiranya dibebaskan dari segala roh jahat dan kecemaran.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Qen v~ran m~pimonogen/c n~S/ri I/couc Pi,~rictoc mareferremhe e~bol ha demwn niben nem [wqem niben.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            بإسم الإبن الوحيدِ يسوعَ المسيحِ، فليعتق من كافةِ الشياطين، ومن سائرِ الأدناسِ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Let all darkness flee from this body, and let all unbelieving thoughts flee from this soul.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Biarlah semua kegelapan meninggalkan tubuh ini, dan biarlah segala pikiran yang tidak percaya meninggalkan jiwa ini.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Marouvwt e~bol qen paicwma vai ,aki niben: nem meui niben n~te oumetaynah] marouvwt e~bol qen tai'u,/.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وليهرب من هذا الجسدِ كلُّ ظلمةٍ. وكلُّ فكرِ قلةِ الإيمانِ فليهرب من هذه النفس.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            In the name of the only-begotten Son, Jesus Christ, our Lord, you shall be purified, and be delivered from all demons forever. Amen.         </language><language id="Indonesian">Dalam nama Putra Tunggal, Yesus Kristus, Tuhan kita, engkau disucikan dan dibebaskan dari semua setan selamanya. Amin.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Qen v~ran m~pimonogen/c n~S/ri I/couc Pi,~rictoc Pen[oic eke~toubo eke~erremhe e~bol ha demwn niben sa e~neh: a~m/n.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            بإسم الإبن الوحيدِ يسوعَ المسيحِ ربِنا، تُطَهِر وتَعتَق من جميعِ الشياطين إلى الأبدِ. آمين.         </language>      </text>         <comment>         <language id="English">            At this time, those to be baptized are stripped and look towards the west, with their right hand raised, and say the following.            </language><language id="Indonesian">            Pada saat ini, mereka yang akan dibaptis ditanggalkan pakaiannya dan melihat ke arah barat, dengan tangan kanan terangkat, dan mengatakan hal berikut.            </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ثم يكشف الذي يعتمد وينظر إلى الغرب ويده اليمنى مرفوعة ويقول ما يأتي.         </language>      </comment>         <comment>         <language id="English">            If he or she is a child, the father or the mother or the sponsor says the following on his or her behalf,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Jika dia adalah seorang anak, ayah atau ibu atau walinya mengatakan  berikut atas namanya,         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وأن كان طفلاً، فليقل عنه أبوه أو أمه أو إشبينه:         </language>      </comment>   </role>      <role id="Sponsor">      <text>         <language id="English">            I renounce you Satan, and all your unclean works, and all your wicked angels and all your evil demons,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Aku menolakmu setan, dan semua perbuatanmu yang najis, dan semua malaikatmu yang jahat dan semua setanmu yang jahat,</language>         <language id="Coptic">            }era~potazecye m~mok Pcatanac nem nekh~b/oui~ t/rou etcwf: nem nekaggeloc t/rou m~pon/~ron: nem nekdemwn t/rou ethwou.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أجحَدُكَ أيها الشيطانُ، وكل أعمالِكَ النجسةِ، وكل جنودِكَ الشريرةِ، وكل شياطينِكَ الرديئةِ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            and all your power, and all your abominable service, and all your evil cunning and error, and all your army, and all your authority and all the rest of your impieties.           </language><language id="Indonesian">            dan semua kekuatanmu, dan semua pelayananmu yang keji, dan semua kelicikan dan kesesatanmu yang jahat, dan semua bala tentaramu, dan semua kekuasaanmu, dan semua kelalimanmu yang lain.           </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Nem tekjom t/rc nem peksemsi t/rf m~bo] nem nekkotc t/rou ethwou ouoh m~p~lan/ nem tekc~t~ratia t/rc nem pekersisi t/rf nem p~cwjp t/rf n~te nekmetaceb/c.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وكل قوتِكَ، وكل عبادتِكَ المرذولةِ، وكل حِيَلِكَ الرديئةِ والْمُضِلَّةِ، وكل جيشِكَ، وكل سلطانِكَ. وكل بقيةِ نفاقِكَ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            I renounce you. I renounce you. I renounce you.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Aku menolakmu. Aku menolakmu. Aku menolakmu.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            }jolk e~bol: ]jolk e~bol: ]jolk e~bol         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أجحدُكَ. أجحدُكَ. أجحدُكَ.         </language>      </text>      </role>      <role id="Priest">      <comment>         <language id="English">            Then, the priest breathes into his or her face and says the following three times,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kemudian, imam menghembuskan napas ke wajahnya dan mengucapkan sebanyak tiga kali,         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ثم ينفخ الكاهن في وجهه وهو يقول ثلاث مرات.         </language>      </comment>            <text>         <language id="English">            Come out O unclean spirit.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Keluarlah, hai roh jahat.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Amou e~bol pip~neuma n~a~kayarton.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أخرج أيها الروحُ النجسُ.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <role id="Sponsor">      <comment>         <language id="English">            Then, they turn to the East, with both of their hands uplifted, and say,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kemudian, mereka berpaling ke arah Timur, dengan kedua tangan terangkat, dan berkata,         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            بعد هذا يحولـه إلى الشرق ويده مرفوعة إلى فوق ويقول:         </language>      </comment>            <text>         <language id="English">            I confess You, O Christ my God, and all Your saving laws, and all Your living service, and all Your life giving works.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Aku mengakui Engkau, ya Kristus, Allahku, dan semua hukum-Mu yang menyelamatkan, dan semua pelayanan-Mu yang menghidupkan, dan semua karya-Mu yang memberi hidup.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            }ercuntazecye nak Pi,~rictoc Panou]: nem neknomoc t/rou n~oujai: nem peksemsi t/rf n~reftanqo: nem nekh~b/oui~ t/rou n~ref] m~p~wnq.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أعترفُ لك أيها المسيحُ إلهي، وكلُّ نواميسِكَ الْمُخْلِصَةِ، وكلُّ خدمتِكَ المحييةِ، وكلُّ أعمالِكَ المعطيةِ الحياةِ.         </language>      </text>         <comment>         <language id="English">            Then the priest teaches him or her the faith.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kemudian imam mengajarkan iman kepadanya.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ثم يلقنه الإيمان قائلاً:         </language>      </comment>   </role>      <role id="Priest">      <text>         <language id="English">            I believe in one God, God, the Father, the Pantocrator, and His only-begotten Son, Jesus Christ, our Lord, and the Holy Spirit, the Giver of Life, and the resurrection of the flesh, and the one, only, holy, catholic and apostolic Church. Amen.         </language><language id="Indonesian">Aku percaya kepada Allah Yang Esa,  Bapa, Sang Pantokrator, dan Putra Allah Yang Tunggal, Yesus Kristus,Tuhan kita, dan Roh Kudus, Sang Pemberi Hidup, dan kebangkitan tubuh, dan Gereja yang satu, satu-satunya, kudus, katolik and apostolik. Amin.</language>         <language id="Coptic">            }nah] e~Ounou] n~ouwt: Vnou] Viwt Pipantokratwr: nem pefmonogen/c n~S/ri I/couc Pi,~rictoc Pen[oic: nem Pip~neuma eyouab n~reftanqo: nem ]a~nactacic n~te ]carx nem ]oui~ m~mauatc eyouab n~kayolik/ n~a~poctolik/ n~ekkl/cia: a~m/n.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أؤمن بإلهٍ واحدٍ، الله الآبِ ضابطِ الكلِّ، وإبنِه الوحيدِ يسوعَ المسيحِ ربِنا، والروحِ القدسِ المحيي، وقيامةِ الجسدِ، والكنيسةِ الواحدةِ الوحيدةِ المقدسةِ الجامعةِ الرسوليةِ. آمين.         </language>      </text>         <comment>         <language id="English">            And he asks him or her three times, saying,           </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dan dia bertanya kepadanya tiga kali, dengan berkata,           </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ثم يسأله ثلاث مرات قائلاً:         </language>      </comment>         <text>         <language id="English">            Do you believe?         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Apakah engkau percaya?</language>         <language id="Coptic">            Aknah].         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أمنتَ؟         </language>      </text>   </role>      <role id="Sponsor">      <comment>         <language id="English">            And he or she answers each time with,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dan setiap kali dia menjawab dan berkata,</language>         <language id="Arabic">            فيجاوبه ثلاث مرات قائلاً:         </language>      </comment>            <text>         <language id="English">            I believe.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Aku percaya</language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ainah].         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أمنتُ.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/LetUsEntreat"/>      <role id="Priest">      <text>         <language id="English">            O Master, Lord, God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Junjungan, Tuhan, Allah Sang Pantokrator, Bapa dari Tuhan, Allah, dan Juruselamat kita, Yesus Kristus,         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Vn/b P[oic Vnou] Pipantokratwr: Viwt m~Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh Pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أيها السيدُ الربُ الإلهُ ضابط الكلِّ أبو ربِنا وإلهنا ومخلصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            who have created every thing, Lord of heaven and earth; who brought the knowledge of Himself to those who dwell on earth through His only-begotten Son, our Lord, Jesus Christ;         </language><language id="Indonesian">            yang telah menciptakan segala sesuatu, Tuhan atas langit dan bumi; yang telah membawa pengenalan akan diri-Nya kepada mereka yang diam di bumi melalui Putra-Nya Yang Tunggal, Tuhan kita, Yesus Kristus;         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            V/e~tafyamio n~hwb niben P[oic n~t~ve nem p~kahi: v/e~tafi~ni m~pefe~mi n~n/etsop hijen p~kahi e~bol hitotf m~pefmonogen/c n~S/ri Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            الذي خَلَقَ كلَّ شيءٍ، ربُ السماءِ والأرضِ، الذي أعطي معرفتَه للكائنينَ على الأرضِ، من قِبَلِ إبنِه الوحيد، ربنا يسوع المسيح.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            who has prepared the heavens for them through the calling, and has confirmed them in His power.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            yang telah mempersiapkan surga bagi mereka melalui panggilan, dan telah mengukuhkan mereka dalam kuasa-Nya.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            V/e~tafcob] n~niv/oui nwou e~bol: hiten piywhem ouoh aftajrwou qen tefjom.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            الذي هَيَّأ لهم السمواتِ بالدعوةِ، وثَبَتَهُم بقوتِه.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Confirm the profession of these Your servants, let power dwell in them that they turn not back again to the things they have left.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Teguhkanlah pengakuan hamba-hamba-Mu ini, biarlah kuasa tinggal di dalam diri mereka sehingga mereka tidak kembali lagi kepada hal-hal yang telah mereka tinggalkan.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Matajre ]hupotak/ n~te neke~biaik nai: mare oujom swpi n~q/tou: hina n~tous~temtacywou n~kecop e~n/e~tau,at n~cwou.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ثَبِّتْ طاعةَ عبيدِكَ هؤلاء، ولتكن فيهم قوةٌ لكي لا يَعُودوا دفعةً أخرى إلى ما قد تركوه.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Confirm their faith that nothing may separate them from You.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Teguhkanlah iman mereka agar tidak ada yang dapat memisahkan mereka dari-Mu.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Matajre pounah]: hina n~tes~tem h~li vorjou e~rok.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وطد إيمانُهم لكي لا يفرقهم مِنكَ شيءٌ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            And establish them upon the foundation of Your apostolic faith, and call them into Your holy light, and make them worthy of this great grace of Yours.            </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dan tetapkanlah mereka di atas dasar iman apostolik-Mu, dan panggillah mereka ke dalam terang-Mu yang kudus, dan jadikanlah mereka layak dari anugerah-Mu yang agung ini.            </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh cemn/tou hijen ]cen] n~te peknah] n~a~poctolikon: ouoh yahmou e~qoun e~pekouwini eyouab: ouoh a~ritou n~emp~sa m~painis] n~h~mot n~tak.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            رتبهُم على أساسِ إيمانِكَ الرسولي. وادعهُم إلى نورِكَ الطاهرِ وإجعلهُم أهلاً لنعمتِكَ العظيمةِ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Strip them of their old condition, and renew their life. Fill them with the power of Your Holy Spirit unto oneness and union with Your only-begotten Son;         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Tanggalkanlah keadaan mereka yang lama, dan perbaharuilah hidup mereka. Penuhilah mereka dengan kuasa Roh Kudus-Mu menuju kesatuan dan persatuan dengan Putra Tunggal-Mu;         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Basou e~bol n~toumeta~pac: ouoh a~ripouwnq m~beri: mahou e~bol qen ]jom n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab: e~oumetouai nem oujinywt n~te pekmonogen/c n~S/ri.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            عرهُم من عتيقِهُم. وجددْ حياتَهم. املأهُم من قوةِ روحِكَ القدوسِ، بوحدانيةِ وعزاءِ إبنِكَ الوحيد.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            that they be no more sons of the flesh, but sons of the truth, and become wise and faithful servants, through Christ Jesus our Lord.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            supaya mereka bukan lagi anak-anak daging, tetapi anak-anak kebenaran, dan supaya mereka menjadi hamba-hamba yang bijaksana dan setia melalui Kristus Yesus, Tuhan kita.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Hina n~tous~temswpi je n~hans/ri n~te hancwma: alla hans/ri n~ta ]meym/i ouoh n~touswpi n~hane~biaik n~cabeu ouoh m~pictoc: qen Pi,~rictoc I/couc Pen[oic.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            لكي لا يكونوا بعد أبناءَ الجسدِ بل أبناءَ الحقِ. ويصيروا عبيداً حكماء وأمناء. بالمسيحِ يسوع ربنا.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <role id="Priest" silent="true">      <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusionEnding"/>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/BowYourHeads"/>      <role id="Priest">      <comment>         <language id="English">            He or she kneels and the priest prays over them, saying,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dia berlutut dan imam mendoakan mereka dengan mengatakan,         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            يحنون ركبهم ويطلب الكاهن عنهم قائلاً:         </language>      </comment>         <text>         <language id="English">            O Master, our Savior, the Lover of Mankind, the beneficent, to You alone is this mystery perfected.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Guru, Juruselamat kami, Pengasih umat manusia, Yang Maha Pemurah, kepada-Mu sajalah misteri ini disempurnakan.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Vn/b Pencwt/r Pimairwmi n~referp~eynanef: n~yok m~mauatk pe e~touwk m~paimuct/rion nak e~bol.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أيها السيدُ مخلصُنا محب البشرِ، صانع الخيراتِ، أنتَ وحدكَ الذي يَكمُلُ لك هذا السر.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            To You all knees bow, those in heaven and those on earth, and those which are beneath the earth, and all tongues confess to You, saying, “Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God, the Father.”         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kepada-Mu bertekuk lutut semua yang ada di langit dan di atas bumi dan di bawah bumi, dan semua lidah mengaku kepada-Mu: “Yesus Kristus adalah Tuhan, kemuliaan bagi Allah, Bapa!”         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Nyok pe e~tere keli niben kwlj nak: na t~ve nem na p~kahi: nem n/etcapec/t m~p~kahi: ouoh e~re lac niben ouwnh nak e~bol eujw m~moc: je P[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc euw~ou m~Vnou] Viwt.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أنتَ الذي تجثو لكَ كلُّ ركبةٍ، ما في السماءِ وما على الأرضِ، وما تحتِ الأرضِ، وبِكَ يعترفُ كلُّ لسانٍ قائلاً: "إن الربَ يسوعَ المسيحِ لمجدِ الله الآب."         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            And Your servants who have fled to You, bowing their knees to You.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dan hamba-hamba-Mu yang telah berlari kepada-Mu, bersujud kepada-Mu.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh neke~biaik e~tauvwt harok aukwlj nak n~noukeli.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وعبيدُك الذين إلْتَجَأوا إليكَ، أحنوا لكَ ركبَهُم.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Therefore we ask and entreat You, O Lover of Mankind, search the chambers of their souls and enlighten the eyes of their understanding with the light of knowledge.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Oleh karena itu, kami meminta dan memohon kepada-Mu, wahai Pengasih Umat Manusia, selidikilah bilik-bilik jiwa mereka dan cerahkanlah mata pengertian mereka dengan cahaya pengetahuan.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Eybe vai ten]ho ouoh tentwbh m~mok Pimairwmi: moust n~nitamion n~te nou'u,/ ouoh a~riouwini e~nibal n~te pouka] m~piouwini n~te p~e~mi.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            فلهذا نسألُ ونطلبُ منكَ يا محبَ البشرِ: فَتِّشْ خزائنَ نفوسِهم واضئ عيونَ إفهامِهم بنورِ المعرفةِ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            All magic, all sorcery, all the work of Satan, chase from them; all traces of idolatry and unbelief, cast out of their heart.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Semua sihir, semua tenung, semua pekerjaan Iblis, jauhilah mereka; semua jejak penyembahan berhala dan ketidakpercayaan, buanglah dari hati mereka.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Magia niben: varmagia niben: e~nergia niben n~te Pcatanac: [oji n~cwou e~bol harwou: cwjp niben n~te oumetsamse i~dwlon nem oumetaynah]: hitou e~bol qen pouh/t.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            كلَّ سحرٍ وكلَّ تعزيمٍ وكلَّ فعلٍ شيطانيٍ، اطرده عنهُم. وكلَّ بقايا عبادةِ الأوثانِ وعدمِ الإيمانِ اطرحها من قلوبِهم.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Prepare their souls for the reception of Your Holy Spirit.           </language><language id="Indonesian">            Persiapkanlah jiwa mereka untuk menerima Roh Kudus-Mu.           </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Cob] n~nou'u,/ e~p~jinswp e~rwou m~Pekp~neuma eyouab.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            هيئ أنفسَهُم لكي يقبلوا روحَكَ القدوسَ.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            And let them be worthy of the washing of the new birth, of the garment of incorruption and of forgiveness of sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dan biarlah mereka layak menerima pembasuhan kelahiran baru, jubah kebangkitan dan pengampunan dosa.            </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh marouerp~emp~sa m~piouahm~mici n~te pijwkem nem ]hebcw n~te ]metattako nem p~,w e~bol n~te ninobi.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وليستحقوا حميمَ الميلادِ الجديدِ. واللباسَ غير الفاسدِ، وغفرانَ الخطايا.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="English">            Preparing them to be a temple for Your Holy Spirit, according to the pleasure of Your good Father and the Holy Spirit, now and at all times and unto the age of all ages. Amen.         </language><language id="Indonesian">Persiapkan mereka menjadi bait Roh Kudus-Mu, sesuai dengan perkenanan Bapa-Mu yang baik dan Roh Kudus, sekarang dan selamnya dan dari segala abad hingga segala abad. Amin.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ekcob] m~mwou n~ouervei n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab qen p~]ma] m~Pekiwt n~a~gayoc nem Pip~neuma eyouab: ]nou nem n~c/ou niben nem sa e~neh n~te nie~neh t/rou: a~m/n.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            إذ تَعِدّهُم هيكلاً لروحِكَ القدوسِ، بمسرةِ أبيكَ الصالحِ والروحِ القدسِ، الآن وكلِّ أوان وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ كلِّها. آمين.         </language>      </text>         <comment>         <language id="English">            Then the priest takes the Hagielaion and anoints him or her on the chest, the arms, over the heart from behind, and between his two hands in the sign of the cross, saying,            </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kemudian imam mengambil Hagelaion dan mengurapinya di dada, lengan, di atas jantung dari belakang, dan di antara kedua tangannya dengan tanda salib, sambil berkata,            </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ثم يأخذ الكاهن الزيت المقدس (الغاليلاون) ويدهن به الذي يعتمد في قلبه وذراعيه وقدام قلبه إلى خلف ووسط يديه بعلامة الصليب قائلاً:         </language>      </comment>      <text>         <language id="English">            I anoint you (...) with the oil of gladness, given against all works of the adversary, unto your grafting into the sweet olive tree of the holy, catholic, and apostolic Church of God. Amen.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Aku mengurapimu (...) dengan minyak sukacita, yang diberikan untuk melawan semua pekerjaan musuh, agar engkau dicangkokkan ke dalam pohon zaitun yang manis dari Gereja Allah, yang kudus, katolik dan apostolik. Amin.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Ceywhc m~mok (nim) n~ouneh n~yel/l: ef]oube e~nergia niben n~te piantikimenoc: e~p~jinerkunt~rizin m~mok e~]bw n~jwit n~notem: n~te ]a~gia n~kayolik/ n~a~poctolik/ n~ekkl/cia n~te Vnou]: a~m/n.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أدهنُكَ يا (...) بدهنِ الفرحِ، مضاداً لكلِّ أفعالِ المضادِ. لتغرسَ في شجرةِ الزيتونِ اللذيذةِ، في كنيسةِ الله المقدسةِ الجامعةِ الرسوليةِ. آمين.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <role id="Deacon">      <text>         <language id="English">            Amen.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Amin.         </language>         <language id="Coptic">            Am/n.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            آمين.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            The Prayer of the Laying of Hands on the Catechumens         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Doa Penumpangan Tangan ke atas Para Katekumen</language>         <language id="Arabic">            صلاة رفع يد على الموعوظين         </language>      </Title>      <comment>         <language id="English">            After they are anointed with the Hagielaion         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Sesudah mereka diurapi dengan Hagelaion         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            بعد دهنهم بالغاليلاون         </language>      </comment>      <insertdocument path="include/LetUsEntreat"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               O Master, Lord, God the Pantocrator, we call upon Your holy and blessed name, so that You search out and chase away all adverse and hostile powers.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ya Junjungan Agung, Tuhan, Allah Sang Pantokrator, kami berseru kepada nama-Mu yang kudus dan terpuji, supaya Engkau menyelidiki dan mengusir semua kekuatan yang merugikan dan bermusuhan.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Vn/b P[oic Vnou] Pipantokratwr: tenws oube pekran eyouab ouoh etc~marwout: e~p~jinqotqet ouoh n~tek[oji n~ca jom niben n~a~poctat/c ouoh n~antion.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيها السيدُ الربُ الإلهُ ضابط الكلِّ، نصرخُ نحو إسمِكَ القدوسِ المباركِ، لكي تُفَتِّشَ وتطردَ كلَّ القواتِ المارقةِ والمضادةِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               When we ask You, O our Master, through all Your saints, search out the hearts of Your servants who have presented themselves for the washing of Your grace.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ketika kami meminta kepada-Mu, ya Tuhan, melalui semua orang kudus-Mu, selidikilah hati para hamba-Mu yang telah mempersembahkan diri mereka untuk pembasuhan anugerah-Mu.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Qen p~jiny~ren]ho oun e~rok Penn/b e~bol hiten neka~gioc t/rou: qotqet n~nih/t n~te neke~biaik e~tau] m~p~ououoi e~pijwkem n~te pekh~mot.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               عندما نطلبُ إليكَ يا سيدنا بجميعِ قديسيكَ. فَتِّشْ قلوبَ عبيدِكَ الذين تقدموا إلى حميمِ نعمتِكَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               If there be any guile of the Devil hidden within them, disclose it and let it reveal itself, and chase it away from the souls and bodies of Your servants who believe on Your holy name, and renew their life.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Jika ada tipu daya Iblis yang tersembunyi di dalam diri mereka, nyatakanlah dan biarkanlah ia menampakkan dirinya, dan usirlah ia dari jiwa dan tubuh hamba-hamba-Mu yang percaya kepada nama-Mu yang kudus, dan perbaharuilah hidup mereka.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Eswp ouon oukakia n~te Pidiaboloc h/p n~q~r/i n~q/tou: yai e~t~ak[orpc e~bol marecouonhc e~bol: ouoh [oji n~cwc e~bol ha ni'u,/ nem nicwma n~te neke~biaik eynah] e~pekran eyouab: ouoh a~ripouwnq m~beri.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وان كان شرُ الشيطانِ مخفياً فيهُم، اكشفه، وليُعْلَن. أطرده من نفوسِ وأجسامِ عبيدِكَ المؤمنيَن بإسمِكَ القدوسِ، وجددْ حياتَهم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               And make them worthy, in spotlessness and purity, to receive the light and the seal of Your Christ, and the gift of Your Holy and co-essential Spirit,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan jadikanlah mereka layak, dalam kekudusan dan kemurnian, untuk menerima terang dan meterai Kristus-Mu, dan karunia Roh-Mu yang kudus dan sehakekat,            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh a~ritou m~p~emp~sa qen oumetata[ni nem outoubo: eyrouswp e~rwou m~piouwini nem ]c~v~ragic n~te Pek,~rictoc nem ]dwrea~ n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab ouoh n~o~mooucioc nemak.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               واجعلهُم أهلاً بغيرِ عيبٍ وبطهارةٍ أن يقبلوا إليهُم النورَ وخاتمَ مسيحِكَ وموهبةَ روحِكَ القدوسِ المساوي لكَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               and that they may receive a garment of light, and be clothed with the vestment of salvation, and the armour of faith which is invincible and unconquerable to those who fight against us.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               dan supaya mereka menerima jubah terang dan mengenakan jubah keselamatan, yaitu perlengkapan senjata Allah yang tak terkalahkan dan tak tertaklukkan oleh mereka yang memerangi kita.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh n~touswpi n~ouent/ma n~ouwini: ouoh n~tou]hiwtou n~ouhebcw n~oujai: ouhoplon n~te ounah] n~at[ro e~rof ouoh n~atbwtc e~rof e~bol hiten n/et] oub/n.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ويصيروا حلةً نورانيةً. ويلبسوا لباسَ الخلاصِ، الذي هو سلاحَ الإيمانِ الذي لا يُغلَبُ، الذي لا يُقَاوَمُ من المضادينَ لنا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               May they be sheep in Your flock, and sons of Your heavenly bridal chamber, and heirs of Your incorruptible and eternal kingdom, in Christ Jesus our Lord.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kiranya mereka menjadi domba-domba dari kawanan-Mu, dan menjadi anak-anak dari kamar pengantin-Mu di surga, dan menjadi ahli waris dari kerajaan-Mu yang tak terbinasakan dan yang kekal, di dalam Kristus Yesus, Tuhan kami.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh marouswpi n~e~cwou n~te peko~hi: ouoh n~s/ri n~te pekman~selet n~e~pouranion ouoh n~k~l/ronomoc n~te tekmetouro n~attako ouoh n~e~w~nion qen Pi,~rictoc I/couc Pen[oic.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وليصيروا خرافاً ضِمْنَ قطيعِكَ، وبنيناً لخِدْرِكَ السمائي، ووارثينَ لملكوتِكَ غيرِ الفاسدِ الأبدي، بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِنا.            </language>         </text>         </role>         <role id="Priest" silent="true">         <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusionEnding"/>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LetUsPray"/>         <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               O You, THE BEING, Master, Lord, God, who formed man in His image and His likeness; who has given us the privilege of everlasting life.            </language><language id="Indonesian">Ya Engkau, Sang, Junjungan Agung, Tuhan, Allah, yang membentuk manusia menurut gambar dan rupa-Nya; yang telah memberi kami hak istimewa untuk hidup yang kekal.</language>            <language id="Coptic">               V/etsop Vn/b  P[oic Vnou] v/e~taferp~lazin m~pirwmi kata tefhukwn nem kata pefi~ni: v/e~taf] nan m~piersisi n~te p~wnq eym/n e~bol.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيها الأزليُ السيدُ الربُ الإلهُ الذي جَبَلَ الإنسانَ كصُورتِهَ ومثالِه، الذي أعطانا سلطانَ الحياةِ الدائمةِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               And then, when he fell through sin, You have not abandoned him, but have prepared the salvation of the world through the Incarnation of Your only-begotten Son, our Lord, Jesus Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan kemudian, ketika ia jatuh ke dalam dosa, Engkau tidak meninggalkannya, tetapi telah menyediakan keselamatan bagi dunia melalui Inkarnasi Putra-Mu Yang Tunggal, Tuhan kami, Yesus Kristus.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ita e~tafhei v~nobi: m~pek,af n~cwk: alla akeroikonomin m~pioujai m~pikocmoc: hiten p~jinerrwmi m~pekmonogen/c n~S/ri Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ثم لما سَقَطَ في الخطيئةِ، لم تتركه، بل دَبِّرْتَ خلاصَ العالمَ بتأنسِ إبنِكَ الوحيدِ ربِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               On these, O Lord, who are also Your creation, have mercy. Deliver them from the slavery of the enemy. Receive them into Your kingdom.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kepada mereka ini, ya Tuhan, yang juga ciptaan-Mu, kasihanilah mereka. Bebaskanlah mereka dari perbudakan musuh. Terimalah mereka ke dalam kerajaan-Mu.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Nyok P[oic nai kep~lacma n~tak nai: cotou e~bol ha ]metbwk n~te pijaji: sopou e~rok e~qoun e~tekmetouro.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أنتَ يارب أنقذْ أيضاً جبلتَكَ هؤلاء من عبوديةِ العدوِ. أقبلهُم في ملكوتِكَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               Open the eyes of their heart, that they may be enlightened with the light of the Gospel of Your kingdom.               </language><language id="Indonesian">               Bukalah mata hati mereka, sehingga mereka dapat diterangi dengan terang Injil kerajaan-Mu.               </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Aouwn n~nibal n~te pouh/t eyrou[iouwini qen v~ouwini m~pieuaggelion n~te tekmetouro.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               إفتح أعينَ قلوبِهم ليستضيئوا بضياءِ إنجيلِ ملكوتِكَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               Let the angels of light accompany their life, to save them from the attacks of the adversary            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Biarlah para malaikat terang menemani hidup mereka, untuk menyelamatkan mereka dari serangan musuh            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Marouers~v/r e~pouwnq n~je hanaggeloc n~te v~ouwini e~nohem m~mwou e~bol ha e~pibol/ niben n~te piantikimenoc.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ولتصحبَ حياتَهم ملائكةُ النورِ، ليُخَلِّصُوهُم من كلِّ مؤامرةِ المضاد.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               and from all evil assaults, and from the demon of midday, and from the arrow that flies by day, and from that which walks in darkness, and from phantoms of the night.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               dan dari semua serangan jahat, dan dari setan tengah hari, dan dari panah yang terbang di siang hari, dan dari yang berjalan dalam kegelapan, dan dari hantu-hantu malam.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Nem e~bol ha oua~pant/ma efhwou: nem ouiq n~te hana~meri: e~bol ha ouoynef efhalai m~pie~hoou: nem e~bol ha ouhwb efmosi qen p~,aki: nem e~bol ha ouvanatcia n~te pie~jwrh.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ومن المصادفةِ الرديئةِ، ومن سهمٍ طائرٍ في النهارِ، ومن شيطانِ الظهيرةِ، ومما يسلكُ في الظلمةِ، ومن خيالِ الليلِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               Cast out of their heart: every defiled spirit, the wicked spirit that troubles their heart, the spirit of error and every evil,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Usirlah dari dalam hati mereka segala roh yang najis, roh jahat yang mengganggu hati mereka, roh kesesatan dan setiap kejahatan,            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Hioui~ e~bol qen pouh/t m~p~neuma niben n~a~kayarton: pip~neuma m~pon/~ron ouoh ets~yorter m~pouh/t: pip~neuma n~te ]n~lan/ nem pon/ria niben.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               إنزع من قلوبِهم كلَّ الأرواحِ النجسةِ، الروحَ الخبيثَ الذي يقلقُ قلوبَهم، وروحَ الضلالةِ وكلَّ خبثٍ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               the spirit of love-of-money and of idolatry, the spirit of falsehood and every defilement which works after the teaching of the Devil.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               roh cinta uang dan penyembahan berhala, roh kepalsuan dan setiap kecemaran yang bekerja menurut ajaran Iblis.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Pip~neuma n~te ]metmaihat: nem ]metsamse i~dwlon: pip~neuma n~te ]meynouj nem a~kayarcia niben e~touerhwb e~rwou kata ]dackalia n~te Pidiaboloc.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               روحَ محبةِ الفضةِ وعبادةِ الأوثانِ، روحَ الكذبِ وكلَّ نجاسةٍ تصنعُ كتعليمِ إبليس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               And make them sheep of the holy flock of Your Christ,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan jadikanlah mereka sebagai domba-domba dari kawanan domba-Mu yang kudus,            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh a~ritou n~e~cwou n~te pio~hi eyouab n~te Pek,~rictoc.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               إجعلهم خرافاً للقطيعِ المقدسِ الذي لمسيحِكَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               purified members of the catholic Church,            </language><language id="Indonesian">anggota Gereja Katolik yang telah dimurnikan,</language>            <language id="Coptic">               Hanmeloc eutoub/out n~te ]kayolik/ n~ekkl/cia.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أعضاءً نقيةً للكنيسةِ الجامعةِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               purified vessels, sons of the light, and heirs of Your kingdom.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               bejana yang dimurnikan, anak-anak terang, dan pewaris kerajaan-Mu.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Hanc~keuoc eutoub/out: hans/ri n~te piouwini hank~l/ronomoc n~te tekmetouro.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أواني طاهرةً، أبناءَ النورِ، وارثينَ لملكوتِكَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               That they may strive according to the commandments of Christ, and guard the seal unbroken, and keep the garment unspotted, and may attain the blessedness of Your elect, in Christ Jesus our Lord.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Supaya mereka berjuang sesuai dengan perintah Kristus dan menjaga agar meterai itu jangan sampai rusak, dan jubah itu jangan sampai ternoda, dan supaya mereka memperoleh berkat-Mu sebagai orang-orang pilihan-Mu, di dalam Kristus Yesus, Tuhan kami.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Hina n~touerpoli-teuecye kata nientol/ n~te Pi,~rictoc: ouoh n~tourwic e~]c~v~ragic n~atkolpc ouoh n~toua~reh e~]hebcw n~atlwm n~tousasni e~]metmakarioc n~te nekcwtp qen Pi,~rictoc I/couc Pen[oic.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               لكي يجاهدوا كوصايا المسيحِ، ويحرسوا الخاتمَ من أي سارقٍ، ويحفظوا اللُبِاسَ بغيرِ إضمحلالٍ، ويفوزوا بطوباويةِ أصفيائكَ بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِنا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <role id="Priest" silent="true">         <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusionEnding"/>      </role>   </section>   </document>