<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation – Proverbs 3:5-14         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير – أمثال 3: 5-14         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Trust in the Lord with all your heart,” means that the individual should not place his or her trust in temporal possessions or lean on their own strengths, but instead trust in the Lord wholeheartedly, so that God may fulfill the best for him or her.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "توكل على الرب بكل قلبك". يعني يجب على الإنسان ألا يتوكل في هذه الحياة الدنيا على مال أو جاه. بل يجعل اتكاله على الرب بكل قلبه. فيكمل له كل شيء صالح.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As the Lord Jesus, to Him be the glory, said, “But seek first the kingdom of God and His righteousness” from all your hearts “and all these things shall be added to you.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كما قال المسيح له المجد: "اطلبوا أولاً ملكوت الله وبره. من كل قلوبكم. وهذا كله يزاد لكم".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And lean not on your own understanding,” meanings that if an individual is wise, and proud of his or her own wisdom, then he or she is actually weak and rejected. As the apostle said: “For the wisdom of this world is foolishness with God,”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وعلى فطنتك لا تعتمد" يعني أن الإنسان إذا كان حكيماً وافتخر بحكمته فهو عاجز ومرذول. كما قال الرسول: "إن حكمة هذا العالم هي عند الله جهالة".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            and “he who glories, let him glory in the Lord.” For God is the One who gives wisdom to the foolish. “Let no one deceive himself, if anyone among you seems to be wise in this age, let him become a fool that he may become wise.” And God will add wisdom to him and exalt him among men.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقال أيضا: "من افتخر فليفتخر بالرب". لأن الرب هو المعطي لجهلاء الحكمة. "فلا يخدعن أحد نفسه. إن حسب أحد منكم أنه حكيم في هذا الدهر فليصر جاهلاً ليكون حكيماً". ويزيده الله حكمة وتعظمه الناس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The wise individual should not be a miser with his wisdom, but should share it with others and should not turn it into a buried treasure that will not benefit him or anyone else; so that he may be favored by his Creator, and receive a great reward.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كما وأنه ينبغي على الحكيم ألا يبخل على غيره بحكمته. ويجعلها كالكنز المدفون الذي لا ينفع به. بل يجتهد في إفادة أبناء جنسه ليحظى بالثواب من خالقه. ويكون أجره عظيماً.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As the Lord, to him be the glory said, “But whoever does and teaches them, he shall be called great in the kingdom of heaven.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كما قال السيد له المجد: "وأما الذي يعمل ويُعلّم فهذا يُدعي عظيماً في ملكوت السموات".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “In all your ways acknowledge Him” meaning that God will forgive the individual who confesses his sins. As the prophet said: “I said, I will confess my transgressions to the Lord, and You forgave the iniquity of my sin.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وفي كل طرقك أعرفه" يعني الرجل المعترف بسقطاته يغفرها له الرب كما قال النبي: "قلت أعترف للرب بذنبي وأنت رفعت آثام خطيئتي".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            For if the sinner repents, turns to God with all his heart, and recalls that which he had done, then God will erase his sins and forget them, for He is merciful and generous.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن الخاطئ إذا تاب إلى الرب بكل قلبه وكان متفكراً فيما فعله فإن الله يترك له خطاياه ولا يذكرها له. لأنه رحوم كثير الإحسان.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “He shall direct your path,” means He will guide you on your path to salvation. “And your foot will not stumble” means if you are steadfast in Him, He will not let you slip at all but will guard you from humiliation. As the prophet said, “Uphold my steps in Your paths, that my footsteps may not slip.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله: "يقوم سبلك" أي يهديك إلى طريق الخلاص. قال: "ولا يعثر رجلك" يعني أنك إذا ثبتت فيه فإنه لا يدعك تسقط أبداً. بل تحرصك معونته لئلا تزل. كما قال النبي: "تمسكت خطواتي بآثارك فما زُلت قدماي"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Fear the Lord and depart from evil,” means that avoiding evil is not enough to satisfy the Lord. We must also do good.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "اتق الله وتجنب كل شر". أي أن الله لا يقنع من الإنسان بترك الشر بل وأن يفعل الخير أيضا.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “It will be healthy to your flesh, and strength to your bones.” If the person avoids evil, does good and despises worldly pleasures, then his body will be comforted and his soul will grow in virtue.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "حينئذ تكون الصحة في عضلك. والري في عظامك". يعني أن الإنسان غذا ترك الشر وصنع الخير وازدرى بكل شهوات العالم فإن جسده يستريح ونفسه تنمو في عمل الفضيلة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Honor the Lord with your possessions and with the first fruits of your increase; so your barns will be filled with plenty, and your vats will overflow with new wine.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وقدم له البكور من أثمار برك. فتمتلئ أهراؤك من كثرة القمح. وتفيض معاصرك من الخمر".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Meaning that if God increased the man’s wealth, then man should offer the oblations from it on his own behalf to God. Also, supporting the weak in God will increase an individual’s wealth, protect him from all evil and bless his barns.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يعني إذا كثر رزق الإنسان فيجب عليه أن يقدم منه القرابين عن نفسه لله تعالى. ويواسي الضعفاء فإن الله يكثر رزقه ويحفظه من كل الأسواء. وتمتلئ أهراؤه من بركاته.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            An individual should not begin any of his worldly tasks before offering prayers with a pure heart to God, asking for His mercy and help. For He will give him what he asks and that which is good for him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كما وأنه واجب على الإنسان ألا يبدأ بأي عمل من الأعمال الدنيوية إلا بالصلاة لله ويسأله الرحمة والمعونة بقلب نقي. فإنه تعالى يعطيه ما يطلب وما فيه خير نفسه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “My son do not despise the chastening of the Lord,” meaning, do not complain or think of the hardships that befall you,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "يا ابني لا تحتقر تأديب الرب". يعني لا تضجر أيها الإنسان إذا ما ابتليت بشدة ولا تكفر.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            because sorrow is the gateway to heaven. If you thank God in patience, His grace will comfort you quickly, and you will be double blessed. As He did with Job the righteous, when He saw his patience and thanksgiving when he faced temptations and tribulations.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن الأحزان باب السماء. وإذا كنت صبوراُ على البلوى شاكراً لله تعالى، فإن معونته تدركك عاجلاً. وتضاعف عليك نعمته. كما فعل بأيوب الصديق لما رأى صبره ورجاحة شكره على المحن والتجارب.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “For whom the Lord loves He corrects.” This means that God, in His wisdom, tests His saints to try their patience toward others and to compensate them with rewards in this world and in eternity. Their longsuffering and patience will benefit others.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لأن من يحبه الرب يؤدبه". يعني أن الرب سبحانه وتعالى يجرب قديسيه ويمتحنهم ليظهر صبرهم للغير ويحسن جزاءهم في الدنيا والآخرة. وتنتفع الناس بجميل صبرهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Happy is the man who finds wisdom,” the wise man blesses those who believe in Christ because they witnessed what many wished to see but did not.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "طوبى للإنسان الذي يجد الحكمة". أعطى الحكيم الطوبى للمؤمنين بالمسيح لأنه كان يشتهي أن ينظر شيئاً من الذي نظره المؤمنون بالمسيح فلم ينظر.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Therefore the Lord said to His disciples: “But blessed are your eyes for they see, and your ears for they hear; for assuredly, I say to you that many prophets and righteous men desired to see what you see, and did not see it, and to hear what you hear, and did not hear it.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولذلك قال الرب لتلاميذه: "طوبى لعيونكم لأنها تُبصر. ولآذانكم لأنها تسمع. فإني الحق أقول لكم أن أنبياء وأبرار كثيرين اشتهوا أن يروا ما أنتم ترون ولم يروا. وأن يسمعوا ما أنتم تسمعون ولم يسمعوا".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “For her proceeds are better than the profits of silver, and her gain than fine gold. She is more precious than ruby.” Truly, faith in Christ is more precious than anything because He transcends us to the perfect joy.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لأن تجارتها خبز من تجارة الفضة. وربحها أفضل من كنوز الذهب. وأكرم من الحجارة الثمينة". وبالحقيقة إن الإيمان بالمسيح أفضل من كل شيء لأنه يوصل الإنسان إلى كمال السعادة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Glory be to God forever Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والمجد لربنا دائماً أبدياً. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>       </Document>