<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><text>      <language id="Coptic">         &lt;ere ne ten]ho e~ro: w~ y/e#y#u# eymeh n~w~ou: e~toi m~paryenoc n~c/ou niben: ]macnou] y~mau m~P,#c#.      </language>      <language id="English">         Hail to you. We ask you, O saint, full of glory, the ever-virgin, the Theotokos, the Mother of Christ,      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Salam bagimu, kami mohon kepadamu, ya santa, penuh kemuliaan, perawan selamanya , Theotokos , Bunda Kristus.</language>      <language id="Arabic">         السَّلامُ لَكِ، نَسْألُكِ أيَّتُها القِدّيسَةُ الممْتَلِئةُ مَجْداً، العَذْراءُ كلَّ حينٍ، والِدةُ الإلَهِ، أمُّ المسيحِ:      </language>   </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Anioui~ n~tenp~roceu,/: e~p~swi ha pes/ri m~menrit: n~tef,a nennobi nan e~bol.      </language>      <language id="English">         Lift up our prayers unto your beloved Son, that He may forgive us our sins.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Naikanlah doamu kepada Putramu terkasih, kiranya Dia mengampuni dosa kami.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         اصْعدي صَلَواتِنا إلى ابْنِكِ الحَبيبِ، ليغْفِرَ لَنا خَطايانا.      </language>   </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         &lt;ere y/e~tacmici nan: m~piouwini n~tav~m/i: P,#c# Pennou]: ]paryenoc e#y#u#.      </language>      <language id="English">         Hail to the holy Virgin, who has brought forth unto us the true Light, Christ our God.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Salam bagi Perawan Kudus yang telah memberikan kami Terang Sejati, Kristus Allah kami.</language>      <language id="Arabic">         السَّلامُ لِلَّتي وَلَدَتْ لَنا النّورَ الحَقيقيَّ المسيحَ إلَهَنا. العَذْراءُ القدّيسَةُ.      </language>   </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Ma]ho m~Po#c# e~h~r/i e~jwn: n~teferounai nem nen'u,/: n~tef,a nennobi nan e~bol.      </language>      <language id="English">         Ask the Lord on our behalf, that He may have mercy on our souls, and forgive us our sins.      </language><language id="Indonesian">          Mohonlah kepada Tuhan demi kami, kiranya Ia mengasihani jiwa kami dan mengampuni dosa kami.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         اسْألي الرَّبَّ عنّا ليَصْنَعَ رَحْمَةً مَعَ نُفوسِنا، ويغفِرَ لَنا خَطايانا.      </language>   </text>