<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik" firstprostration="true" fixeddatedocument="true">   <forceseason id="Feasts ^ FeastsOfTheLordPeriods ^ MajorFeastsOfTheLordPeriods ^ MajorFeastsOfTheLord ^ PentecostWeek7 ^ PentecostPeriod ^ Pentecost ^ AdamDays ^ Weekend ^ Sundays ^ SeasonOfAirAndFruits">      <Title>         <language id="English">First Prostration</language><language id="Indonesian">Sujud Pertama</language>         <language id="Arabic">السجدة الأولى</language>      </Title>            <comment>         <language id="English">            Prayed in the second chorus of the church in the festive tune.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Didoakan pada korus kedua dari gereja dengan nada sukacita.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            تصلى فى الخورس الثانى باللحن الفرايحى         </language>      </comment>            <comment>         <language id="English">            A pottery vessel should be prepared and filled with charcoal to be ready so the priest may put four spoonfuls of incense in the vessel during the Verses of the Cymbals while mentioning the departed.          </language><language id="Indonesian">            Sebuah bejana tembikar harus disiapkan dan diisi dengan arang agar siap sehingga imam dapat menaruh empat sendok penuh dupa ke dalam bejana tersebut selama ayat-ayat Simbal sambil menyebutkan nama mereka yang telah meninggal.          </language>         <language id="Arabic">            يجب تحضير وعاء من الفخار وملءه من الفحم ليكون جاهزا للكاهن ليضع اربعه معالق من البخور في الوعاء خلال ارباع الناقوس وحينما يذكر المنتقل أثناء السجدتين الاولتين.فقط          </language>      </comment>            <insertdocument path="include/StartOfService" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <insertdocument path="include/ThanksgivingPrayer" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>            <forceseason id="Matins">         <insertdocument path="include/ProcessionOfIncense" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </forceseason>            <insertdocument path="include/versesofthecymbals/VersesOfTheCymbals" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <insertdocument path="include/Psalm50AndGloryBeToOurGod" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>            <role id="People">         <insertdocument path="include/DoxaPatriAlleluia" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <biblereference reference="Deuteronomy 5:22-6:3" type="section" self-closing="true"> </biblereference>            </role>            <insertdocument path="include/PrayerOfIncenseForPaulineEpistle" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>            <role id="People">         <insertdocument path="include/TenouwstSeasonalResponse" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <biblereference reference="1 Corinthians 12:28-13:12" type="section" self-closing="true"> </biblereference>            </role>            <insertdocument path="include/trisagion/Seasonal" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <insertdocument path="include/LitanyOfTheGospel" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Adam Exposition</language><language id="Indonesian">Komentari Adam </language>               <language id="Arabic">طرح أدام</language>            </Title>                        <text>                <language id="English">                  The Apostles preached the teaching of the Holy Gospel, not by writing the Book but by the renewal of the Holy Spirit. The indication of that was  they spoke in the different languages with tongues of fire.                </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Para Rasul mengkhotbahkan ajaran Injil Kudus, bukan dengan penulisan Kitab tetapi dengan  pembaharuan oleh Roh Kudus.  Indikasinya adalah: mereka berbicara dalam berbagai bahasa dengan lidah-lidah api.  </div><div><br self-closing="true"> <br/></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  كان الرسل يبشرون بالتعليم المقدس الإنجيلي. لا بكتابة الكتاب بل تجديد الروح القدس. وعلامة ذلك أنهم نطقوا بكافة لغات الألسن بألسنة نارية.               </language>            </text>                        <text>                <language id="English">                  But the Jews who remained in their iniquities, disdained them saying that they were drunk. The Jews unknowingly uttered the truth with their own mouths, because the grace of the Holy Spirit is the new wine which filled the Apostles and made them speak with all purity in tongues of fire.                </language><language id="Indonesian">Tetapi orang-orang Yahudi yang tetap dalam kesalahan mereka, meremehkan para rasul, mengatakan bahwa mereka sedang mabuk. Orang-orang Yahudi tanpa sadar mengucapkan kebenaran dengan mulut mereka sendiri, karena anugerah Roh Kudus adalah anggur baru yang memenuhi para rasul dan membuat mereka berbicara dengan segala kemurnian dalam bahasa lidah api.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فاما اليهود الذين تعتَّقوا في إثمهم كانوا يهزأون قائلين أن هؤلاء سكارى من سلافة. وليس بإختيارهم قالوا الحق بأفواههم. لأن نعمة الروح هي خمر جديد. هذا الذي منه الرسل إمتلأوا. وبطهارة كانوا ينطقون نارية.               </language>            </text>                        <text>                <language id="English">                  Through their prayers, purify us also, O our Master, from the evil of the old man. And make us worthy of the fellowship of Your Holy Spirit, O Lover of Mankind. Through the prayers of our fathers the Apostles, O Lord, grant us the forgiveness of our sins.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Melalui doa-doa mereka, ya Tuhan kami, sucikanlah kami juga dari kejahatan manusia lama. Dan layakkanlah kami menerima persekutuan dengan Roh Kudus-Mu, wahai Sang Pengasih umat manusia.  Melalui doa-doa bapa kami para rasul, ya Tuhan, berikanlah kami pengampunan untuk dosa kami.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  بصلواتهم طهرنا نحن أيضاً يا سيدنا من شر الإنسان العتيق. واجعلنا مستحقين لشركة روحك القدوس أيها الرب المحب البشر، بصلوات آبائنا الرسل. يا رب انعم لنا بغفران خطايانا.               </language>            </text>         </section>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/gospelResponse/GospelResponse" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>               <insertdocument path="include/StandardPrayerIntro" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <insertdocument path="include/litanies/Sick" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <insertdocument path="include/litanies/Travelers" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <insertdocument path="include/litanies/Seasons" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <insertdocument path="include/cyril/litanies/Place" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>            <comment>         <language id="English">            The congregation bows down after the deacon says:         </language><language id="Indonesian">            The congregation bows down after the deacon says:         </language>      </comment>            <insertdocument path="include/WorshipGodInFear" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>         <role id="Priest">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">First Prostration Prayer</language><language id="Indonesian">Doa Sujud Pertama</language>            </Title>                        <text>               <language id="English">                  O Lord, who is without blemish, the Undefiled, without beginning, the Invisible, the Incomprehensible, the Unchangeable and the Omnipresent, who is not evil or spiteful, who alone is immortal, dwelling in incomprehensible light.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Tuhan, Yang Tidak Bercacat, Yang Tidak Tercela, Tanpa Awal, Yang Tak Terlihat dan Yang Tak Dapat Dimengerti, Yang Tak Berubah dan Yang Mahahadir, yang tidak jahat atau pendendam, yang satu-satunya adalah kekal, yang berdiam dalam terang yang tak dapat dipahami.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يا الله الذي بلا عيب، الغير الدنس، الغير المبتدئ، الغير المرئي، الغير المدرك، الغير المفحوص، الذي لا يتغير ولا يستحيل، الذي يشبه ولا يحد، الغير الشرير، الغير الحقود، الحائز وحده صفة عدم الموت، الساكن في النور الذي لا يدرك.               </language>            </text>                         <text>               <language id="English">                  Who created the heaven, the earth and the sea and all that therein. Who gives all people their request before they ask Him. We ask and entreat You, O our King, the Lover of Mankind, God, the Father of our Lord, our God and Savior Jesus Christ.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Yang menciptakan langit, bumi dan laut dan segala yang ada di dalamnya. Yang memberi semua orang permintaan mereka, sebelum mereka meminta kepada-Nya. Kami meminta dan memohon kepada-Mu, ya Raja kami, Sang Pengasih Umat Manusia, Allah, Bapa dari Tuhan Allah dan Juruselamat kami Yesus Kristus.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  الذي خلق السماء والأرض والبحر وكل خلقة فيها. الذي يعطي كل الناس طلباتهم قبل أن يسألوه. نسأل ونطلب منك يا ملكنا يا محب البشر، يا الله أبو ربنا وإلهنا ومخلصنا يسوع المسيح.               </language>            </text>                         <text>               <language id="English">                  Who for us men and for our salvation, came down from heaven, and was incarnate of the Holy Spirit and of the Virgin Saint Mary, the Theotokos, Mother of God. Who taught us first through words and then by granting us His salvation which He performed with His honored sufferings.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Yang demi kita manusia dan demi keselamatan kita, turun dari surga dan berinkarnasi dari Roh Kudus dan dari Perawan Santa Maria, Theotokos, Bunda Allah. Yang pertama-tama mengajari kami melalui perkataan dan kemudian dengan memberikan kami anugerah keselamatan-Nya, yang Dia lakukan melalui penderitaan-Nya yang berharga.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  الذي من أجلنا نحن البشر ومن أجل خلاصنا نزل من السماء وتجسد من الروح القدس ومن مريم العذراء القديسة والدة الإله. هذا الذي علمنا أولاً بالقول، وأخيراً أولانا خلاصه الذي صنعه بألآمه الكريمة.               </language>            </text>                         <text>               <language id="English">                  Grant us, we who are humiliated by our sins and are unworthy to be Your servants, to send up our supplications to You, and bow down our heads and our knees before You for the sake of our sins and for the ignorance of Your people. You are abundant in mercy and the Lover of Mankind.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mampukanlah kami, yang dipermalukan oleh dosa-dosa kami dan tidak layak menjadi hamba-Mu, untuk dapat menaikkan permohonan kami kepada-Mu, dan menundukkan kepala dan lutut kami di hadapan-Mu karena dosa-dosa kami dan karena kebodohan umat-Mu. Engkau yang melimpah dalam belas kasih dan Pengasih Umat Manusia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أعطي لنا علامة نحن المذلولين بالخطايا والغير المستحقين أن نكون عبيداً لك لنرفع طلباتنا ونخضع لك بأعناقنا وركبنا من أجل خطايانا وجهالات شعبك. أنت الكثير الرحمة والمحب للبشر.               </language>            </text>                              <text>               <language id="English">                  Listen to us on this day on which we call upon you; this Day of Pentecost which is after the Ascension of our Lord Jesus Christ into the heavens and His sitting at the right hand of His Father. He sent His Holy Spirit upon His holy disciples and He descended on each one of them.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengarkanlah kami pada hari ini, saat kami memanggil-Mu; pada Hari Pentakosta ini, yaitu setelah kenaikan Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus ke surga, dan duduk-Nya di sebelah kanan Bapa-Nya. Dia mengirimkan Roh Kudus-Nya ke atas para murid-Nya yang suci, dan Dia turun ke atas mereka masing-masing.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إستجب لنا في هذا اليوم الذي ندعوك فيه. سيما هذا اليوم الذي لعيد الخمسين. هذا الذي من بعد صعود ربنا يسوع المسيح إلى السموات وجلوسه عن يمين أبيه. أرسل روحه القدوس على تلاميذه القديسين وحل على كل واحد فواحد منهم.               </language>            </text>                         <text>               <language id="English">                  They were all filled with the infinite grace and they spoke in different tongues and prophesied of Your greatness, O God. Now also, O Master, listen to us. We, being humiliated by our sins and cast down under condemnation, ask You to free our captive souls by Your great kindness.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Lalu, mereka semua dipenuhi dengan anugerah yang tak terbatas dan berbicara dalam bahasa lidah yang berbeda dan bernubuat tentang kebesaran-Mu, ya Allah. Sekarang juga, ya Guru, dengarkanlah kami. Kami, yang dipermalukan oleh dosa-dosa kami dan terlempar di bawah penghukuman, memohon kepada-Mu untuk membebaskan jiwa-jiwa kami yang tertawan, dengan kebaikan-Mu yang besar.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فإمتلأوا جميعاً من النعمة التي لا تفرغ وتكلموا بألسنة أخرى وتنبأوا بعظائمك يا الله. فالآن أيضاً إستجب لنا يا سيدنا نحن الطالبين إليك، المذلولين بالخطايا المنطرحين تحت الحكم، رُد سبيْ أنفسنا لأن عِظَم حنوك يتضرع إليك من أجلنا.               </language>            </text>                         <text>               <language id="English">                  We ask You to accept us, we who are bowing down before You, crying out to You and saying "We have sinned for You have left us since the beginning." You are our God since we were in our mothers' wombs. Our days have passed by in vain and we have been naked of Your help and are unable to give a reason for our deeds,               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kami meminta-Mu agar menerima kami, yang bersujud di hadapan-Mu, berseru kepada-Mu dan berkata, "Kami telah berdosa terhadap-Mu,  dan Engkau telah meninggalkan kami sejak awal (sejak saat bapa kami Adam jatuh dalam dosa). Engkaulah Allah kami sejak kami masih berada dalam kandungan ibu kami. Hari-hari kami telah berlalu dengan sia-sia dan kami menjadi telanjang dari pertolongan-Mu dan tidak mampu memberikan sebuah alasan atas perbuatan kami,               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إقبلنا نحن الجاثين لك ونصرخ: أخطأنا لأنك تركتنا منذ البدء من الحشاء، أنت هو إلهنا منذ كنا في بطون أمهاتنا. لكن من أجل أن أيامنا فنيت بالباطل وتعرينا من معونتك، عاجزين عن كل جواب.                </language>            </text>                              <text>               <language id="English">                  but we trust in Your lovingkindness and cry out to You, saying: "Do not remember the sins of our youth and our ignorance." Cleanse us, O Lord, from our hidden impurities. Look at our humility and save us and forgive us our sins. Do not abandon us in our old age.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  tetapi kami percaya pada kasih sertia-Mu, dan berseru kepada-Mu, mengatakan: "Janganlah ingat dosa-dosa masa muda kami dan masa kebodohan kami." Bersihkanlah kami, ya Tuhan, dari ketidakmurnian kami yang tersembunyi. Lihatlah kerendahan kami dan selamatkanlah kami dan ampunilah dosa kami. Janganlah membuang kami pada masa tua kami.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لكننا واثقون برأفتك. إذ نصرخ قائلين: خطايا صبانا وجهلنا لا تذكرها. طهرنا يا رب من خفاياتنا. انظر إلى تواضعنا وخلصنا وإغفر لنا جميع خطايانا. ولا ترفضنا في زمن الشيخوخة.               </language>            </text>                              <text>               <language id="English">                  Do not leave us if we stray but grant us repentance before we return to dust. Look upon us with Your grace. Measure our sins with Your kindness. Place the multitude of our repentance in the depth of Your compassion. Behold Your people, O Lord, from Your high holy place; these who bow down their heads waiting for the multitude of Your great mercies.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Janganlah tinggalkan kami saat tersesat, tapi berilah kami pertobatan sebelum kami kembali menjadi debu. Bersegeralah melihat kami dengan anugerah-Mu. Timbanglah dosa kami dengan kebaikan-Mu. Tempatkanlah banyaknya pertobatan kami pada ke dalaman belas kasihan-Mu. Lihatlah umat-Mu, ya Tuhan, dari tempat kudus-Mu yang tinggi; mereka yang menundukkan kepalanya menunggu banyaknya belas kasihan-Mu.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وعند فناء أنفسنا لا تتركنا. هِب لنا رجعة قبل أن نعود إلى الأرض وإلتفت إلينا بهدوء ونعمة، ووازن خطايانا بتحننك، وكثرة ندامتنا ضعها بعمق رأفتك. إطلع يا رب من علوك المقدس على شعبك، هذا المطامن الرأس، المنتظر كثرة رحمتك.               </language>            </text>                              <text>               <language id="English">                  Visit us with Your goodness. Save us from the tyranny of Satan. Strengthen our lives with Your pure power and Your honorable law. Appoint one of Your faithful guardian angels to guard Your people. Bring us all into Your kingdom. Grant forgiveness to Your people who put their trust in You and also forgive us our sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kunjungilah kami dengan kebaikan-Mu. Selamatkanlah kami dari tirani setan. Kuatkanlah hidup kami dengan kuasa-Mu yang murni dan hukum-Mu yang berharga.<div>Tunjuklah salah satu malaikat pelindung-Mu yang setia untuk menjaga umat-Mu. Bawalah kami semua masuk ke dalam kerajaan-Mu. Berikanlah pengampunan kepada umat-Mu yang menaruh kepercayaan kepada-Mu dan juga ampunilah dosa-dosa kami.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إفتقدنا بصلاحك. نجنا من جبروت إبليس. ثبت حياتنا بقوتك الطاهرة وناموسك الكريم. ملاكاً أميناً حافظاً أقمه لحراسة شعبك. أدخلنا جميعاً إلى ملكوتك، هِب صفحاً لشعبك المتكل عليك وإغفر لنا نحن أيضاً خطايانا.               </language>            </text>                              <text>               <language id="English">                  Cleanse us all by the good power of Your Holy Spirit. Loosen us from the bondage of Satan. Truly blessed are You, O Lord, our King, the Pantocrator who enlightens the day with the light of the sun and the night with the rays of the fiery stars. Who made us worthy to see the length of the day and to approach the beginning of the night.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bersihkanlah kami semua dengan kuasa yang baik dari Roh Kudus-Mu. Bebaskanlah kami dari belenggu setan.</div><div>Sungguh diberkatilah Engkau, ya Tuhan, Raja kami, Sang Pantokrator yang menerangi siang dengan cahaya matahari dan malam dengan sinar bintang yang menyala. Yang melayakkan kami untuk melihat panjangnya hari dan mendekati permulaan malam.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طهرنا كلنا بالقوة الصالحة التي لروحك القدوس، حلنا من أوثقة إبليس. تباركت بالحقيقة أيها الرب ملكنا الضابط الكل الذي أنار النهار بضوء الشمس والليل بشعاع النجوم النارية. الذي جعلنا أهلاً لمعرفة طول النهار ونقترب إلى مبدأ الليل.               </language>            </text>                              <text>               <language id="English">                  Listen to our supplications together with the supplications of all Your people and forgive us our sins which we have committed knowingly and unknowingly. Accept our evening praises. Send the multitude of Your mercies and kindness upon Your inheritance. May we be surrounded by pure angels to guard us with the weapons of righteousness. May we be covered with Your justice.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengarkanlah permohonan kami bersama dengan permohonan semua umat-Mu dan ampunilah dosa kami yang telah kami perbuat secara sadar dan tidak sadar. </div>Terimalah pujian malam kami. Kirimkanlah belas kasihan dan kebaikan-Mu yang berlimpah ke atas milik pusaka-Mu. Kiranya kami dikelilingi oleh para malaikat yang murni untuk menjaga kami dengan senjata kebenaran. Kiranya kami diliputi dengan keadilan-Mu. </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إسمع طلباتنا مع كافة شعبك وإغفر لنا خطايانا التي بمعرفة والتي بغير معرفة. إقبل ابتهالاتنا المسائية وأرسل كثرة رحمتك وتحننك على ميراثك ولنفز بملائكة أطهار ليحفظوا منطقنا بأسلحة البر، وليحيط بنا عدلك.               </language>            </text>                         <text>               <language id="English">                  Preserve us with Your power. Save us from every affliction and from every conspiracy of the enemy. Grant us to complete this evening and this coming night with all purity and in peace and justice. May we be without sin, or doubt or fear all the days of our lives, through the prayers of the Theotokos, Mother of God, the Virgin Saint Mary,               </language><language id="Indonesian">Jagalah kami dengan kuasa-Mu. Selamatkanlah kami dari setiap penderitaan dan dari setiap persekongkolan musuh. Mampukanlah kami untuk menyelesaikan sore ini dan malam ini dengan semua kemurnian dan dalam damai dan keadilan. MBiarlah kami tanpa dosa, tanpa keraguan atau ketakutan sepanjang hari-hari hidup kami, melalui doa  Theotokos, Bunda Allah, sang Perawan Santa Maria, </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إحفظنا بقوتك، إنقذنا من كل شدة ومن كل مؤامرة المعاند. إمنحنا أن نكمل هذه العشية، وهذا الليل المقبل أيضاً بطهارة وسلامة وعدل ونحن بلا خطية ولا شك ولا خوف كل أيام حياتنا، بطلبات والدة الإله القديسة مريم،               </language>            </text>                              <text>               <language id="English">                  and all the saints who pleased You since the beginning.               </language><language id="Indonesian">dan semua orang kudus yang telah menyenangkan-Mu sejak dari semula.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وجميع القديسين الذين أرضوك منذ البدء.               </language>            </text>         </section>      </role>            <role id="Priest" silent="true">         <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusion" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </role>   </forceseason></document>