<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Gospels         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير الأناجيل         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            David the prophet said of the devil, “He made a pit and dug it out, And has fallen into the ditch which he made. His trouble shall return upon his own head, And his violent dealing shall come down on his own crown.” He also said, “Let destruction come upon him unexpectedly, And let his net that he has hidden catch himself; Into that very destruction let him fall.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال داود النبي عن الشيطان: "كراً جباً. حفره فسقط في الهوة التي صنع. يرجع تعبه على رأسه وعلى هامته يهبط ظلمه". وقال أيضا: "لتأته التهلكة وهو لا يعلم ولتنشب به الشبكة التي أخفاها وفي التَهلُكة نفسَها ليقع".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            When the devil envied Adam for the glory and authority that God had granted him, he disguised himself as a serpent, tempted Adam, stripped him of his glory and denied him his paradise. He started to brag in front of God of his wile by which he had managed to make Adam fall. He thought that God would not have the provision to save Adam and to restore him to his former glory. The great, wise Creator provided a way for Adam’s deliverance and restoration. Just as the devil hid himself in a serpent to destroy Adam, God hid in man to hide His divinity from Satan, deliver Adam from Satan’s control, and grant him eternal life. God trapped the devil in the net, which he had cast for Adam.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أن الحكيم في الشر لما حسد آدم على الرئاسة والمجد اللذين أعطاهما الله له في الفردوس. استتر في الحية حتى أغوى آدم وعرَّاه من مجده وأبعده من نعيمه. وحينئذٍ صار يتعظَم ويفتخر على الله بما أتاه من الحكمة والتدبير اللذين بهما أسقط آدم. وظن خزاه الله أن ليس عند الله تدبير يخلص به آدم منه ويعيده إلى مجده. فدبَّر الخالق الحكيم في الخير تدبيراً بعٍظم حكمته ورحمته خلَّص به آدم منه. وأعاده إلى مجده. وهو كما أن الشيطان اختفى في الحيَّة وأغوىَ آدم وأسقطه من مجدهِ. كذلك استتر الإله في إنسان حتى أخفى لاهوته عن إبليس واخرج آدم من تحت سلطانه وأورثه حياة الأبد. وعلى ذلك فالشبكة التي عملها الشيطان لآدم أوقع الإله الشيطان فيها.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Because the devil has control over the human race, he started to be nice to those who are inclined towards his evil ways. He charmed people with sin and the earth became full of corruption. Satan took the soul of every dying man to Hades because they were under his control. This situation lasted five thousand and five hundred years until our God was incarnate and born of a woman. The devil thought that He was another naïve individual under his control. The Lord played upon this misunderstanding and combined all His miraculous deeds with a display of human weakness like an entreat or a request of God to hide His divinity from Satan who feared Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما كان الشيطان مستولياً على الجنس البشري. صار يحسن لكل أحد ما يعرف أن هواه مائل إليه. وبذلك قد فتن الجنس البشرى بالخطايا حتى تعبَّد لها إذ عمَّ الفساد كل الأرض. وصار الشيطان بقبض على نفس كل من بموت ويهبطها إلى الهاوية، لأنها بخطيئة آدم تحت سلطانه، وقد استمر حاله على ذلك النظام خمسة آلاف وخمسمائة عام. ولما تجَسد ربنا ووُلِد من امرأة متأنساً ظنه الشيطان إنساناً ساذجاً كبقية الناس الذين تحت سلطانه. فكان السيد إذا عمل معجزاً قرنه بشيء من الضعف البشري كتضرُع أو طلبة. ليخفي بذلك لاهوته عن إبليس.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Each time Satan saw these miracles, he fled, assured that this was God but then the Lord would show him a sign of human weakness, making him believe that He was but a naive man. God intended that when the time to give up His soul comes, the devil would come to capture His soul as he had done with all previous human beings, and God would reveal Himself, in His glory capture Satan, and ask him for a ransom. This ransom was all the human souls that he had previously captured.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن إبليس كان متخوفاً منه وآخذاً منه الحَذرِ. فكان عند مشاهدته تلك الآيات الباهرة يولي الفرار متحققاً أنه الإله لا محالة. فيُظهر له الرب من الضعف البشري ما يجعله يظنه إنساناً ساذجاً. وكان القصد بذلك أنه عندما يريد أن يُسَلِّم نَفسه. ويحضر إبليس للقبض عليها كفعله بنفوس البشر. يكشف الرب عنه الغطاء ويريه مجده ثم يقبض عليه بقوة لاهوته. ويطالبه بالدية. لكي يخلص منه في ديته جميع النفوس المحصورة تحت سلطانه.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            When Satan saw the Lord nailed to the Cross-, he was assured of His humanity and was keen on capturing His soul. He made people humiliate Him, hoping that this will lead to the uncovering of His true nature. When he saw the Lord patient with all of this humiliation, he assumed He was a helpless human. He came close and waited to capture His soul but when he saw darkness cover the face of the earth, he ran away.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فالشيطان لما أبصر الرب وهو مسمراً على الصليب، وَثقَت نفسه بأنه إنساناً ساذج. وكثر طمعه في أخذ نفسه. ثم حرَّك المستهزئين والمعيرين ليستكشف بهم أمره. فلما رأى الرب صابراً على كل ذلك كإنسان ليس له ناصر. قرب منه منتظراً خروج نفسه والقبض عليها. ولما رأى الظلمة قد غشت الأرض كلها ولَّى هارباً         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And about the ninth hour Jesus cried out with a loud voice, saying, "Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani?" that is, "My God, My God, why have You forsaken Me?” The Lord said this to encourage Satan to fight Him and to fulfill David’s prophecy in Psalm 22, “My God, My God, why have You forsaken Me?” This Psalm describes the pain the Lord had endured at the hands of the Jews.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "ونحو الساعة التاسعة صرخ يسوع بصوت عظيم قائلاً إيلي إيلي لما شبقتني أي إلهي إلهي لماذا تركتني" ومراد ربنا من هذا القول تشجيع إبليس وإغراؤه لمقاومته ليتم قوله على لسان داود النبي في المزمور الثاني والعشرين وهو: "إلهي إلهي لماذا تركتني" ويوجد في هذا المزمور وصْف الآلام التي قاساها الرب من اليهود.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord therefore wanted to direct their attention to the biblical prophecies about Him and make them read what followed this verse. He also wanted to set an example for us to heed when we fall in trials. We should only reach out to God’s door, where there is life and mercy. If we do this with a pure intention, we will discover that God’s providence is great. We must also note that Jesus did not say this out of weakness or in request of help but just to confirm His humanity lest people would think it an illusion.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فكان قول الرب هذا ليذكرهم بما قد سبق في الكتاب من أجله. أي اقرءوا ما قد تنبأ به داود من أجلى بعد قوله "إلهي إلهي لماذا تركتني" أنه أراد أن يطرق لنا نحن المؤمنين طريقاً نسلكها متى وقعنا في الشدائد. وهي إننا لا نقصد في شدائدنا إلا باب الآب وحده: لأنه باب الحياة والرحمة. حتى إذا فعلنا هذا بنيات خالصة. كانت عناية الله بنا قوية. هذا ولا يفوتنا أن نقول: أن قوله هذا لم يكن عن ضعف أو تَخليه ولا لطلَب معونة. ولكنه قصد له المجد بذلك تحقيق تأنسه حتى لا يظنوه خيالاً.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Some of those who stood there, when they heard that, said, "This Man is calling for Elijah!" because Eli is close to Elijah in Hebrew. “After this, Jesus, knowing that all things were now accomplished, that the Scripture might be fulfilled, said, "I thirst!"  Now a vessel full of sour wine was sitting there; and they filled a sponge with sour wine, put it on hyssop, and put it to His mouth.  So when Jesus had received the sour wine, He said, "It is finished!" fulfilling David’s prophecy in Psalm 69, “And for my thirst they gave me vinegar to drink.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "فقَوم من الواقفين هناك لما سمعوا قالوا أنه ينادى إيليا" وذلك لمشابهة اسم إيلي "أي الهي" لإيليا في اللسان العبري. "بعد هذا رأى يسوع أن كل شيء قد كَمُلَ فلكي يتم الكتاب قال أنا عطشان. وكان إناء موضوعاً مملوءاً خلاً. فملأوا إسفنجه من الخل ووضعوها على زوفاً وقدَّموها إلى فمه. فلما أخذ يسوع الخل قال قد أكمل" أي قد تم ما تنبأ به النبي داود في المزمور التاسع والستين "في عطشى يسقوني خلاً."         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “The rest said, "Let Him alone; let us see if Elijah will come to save Him." They said this to further humiliate him and rejoice in his agony, “and he bowed his head, and gave up the ghost.” Luke the evangelist says, “And when Jesus had cried out with a loud voice, He said, "Father, 'into Your hands I commit My spirit.' "” and the disciple John says, “And bowing His head, He gave up His spirit.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "وأما الباقون فقالوا أترك. هل يأتي إيليا يخلصه" وكان هذا القول منهم على سبيل التشفي منه والهزأ به "فصرخ أيضا بصوت عظيم وأسلم الروح" ويقول لوقا البشير "ونادى يسوع بصوت عظيم وقال يا أبتاه في يديك استودع روحي ولما قال هذا أسلم الروح" وقال يوحنا "ونكَّس رأسه وأسلم الروح."         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            His scream shows that He willingly died. He said, “Therefore doth my Father love me, because I lay down my life, that I might take it again. No man taketh it from me, but I lay it down of Myself. I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فصراخه يدل على أنه بإيثاره مات لا عن قهر. كما قال له المجد: "إني أضع نفسي لآخذها أيضا ليس أحد يأخذها مني بل أضعها أنا من ذاتي لي سلطان أن أضعها ولي سلطان أن آخذها".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            It is to be noted that philosophically and theologically, the soul and spirit mean the same thing, which is the speaking essence referred to as soul and spirit by theology and reason in philosophy.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            واعلم إن لفظتي الروح والنفس في الاصطلاح الشرعي والفلسفي يترادفان على شيء واحد هو الجوهر الناطق المُشار إليه بالروح والنفس في الشرع وبالعقل في الفلسفة.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            When Satan saw the Lord, “Bowing His head, and gave His spirit” he was pleased and came joyfully to capture His soul because he thought that He was a weak, naïve man, but when he discovered His divinity he ran away but the Lord rebuked and uncovered him. The devil was unable to move because the divine rays surrounded him from all six directions. He then saw all the heavenly authorities restless around the cross and learnt with certainty that He is the Son of God. He remained under siege in the air where he could see all his doings concerning urging the Jews to boldly resent, fight and persecute Jesus. When all of this was revealed, he realized God’s patience with him and knew what he had reaped. He realized the worth of Jesus’ ransom. He said nothing in the heavens or on earth could be worth one minute of Jesus standing in front of Pilate for a second let alone what happened before and after the judgment. God then reduced the heat on him to make him pay the ransom willingly. When he no longer felt the heat, he stood before the Master in humiliation begging for mercy and to remain in his base on earth. He asked that God accept all the souls that were in his power as ransom. God accepted the ransom and delivered Adam and his virtuous offspring from hell and restored him to his first position.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما رأى الشيطان الرب وقد "نكَّس رأسه وأسلم الروح "ابتهج وسُر وتقدَم إليه بفرح مفرط ليقبض على نفسه لأنه ظنه إنساناً ساذجاً ضعيفاً. فلما انكشف له سر لاهوته انثنى هارباً. فزجره الرب وكَشَفَ عنه الغطاء وحينئذ لم يتمكن من أن يبرح لأن شعاع اللاهوت حاصره من الجهات الست. ثم رأى القوات السمائية مُرتجَّة حول الصليب المقدس فتحقَق في ذلك الوقت أنه ابن الله تحقيقاً شافياً. ولبث محاصراً في الجو يلتهب فرقاً. ثم صور له الرب جميع أعماله. وما كان يعتمده في حقه من المقاومات والمناصبات ومن تشديد اليهود فيما قد أقدموا عليه به من الجرأة في أمره. وصار ذلك ظاهراً مكشوفاً. وحينئذ عرف قدر إمهال الله عليه على ما قد جناه واستعظم دية ابن الله. وقال إن السماء وما فيها والأرض وما عليها. لا يقومان بقدر وقوفه قدام بيلاطس لمحة بصر. لاسيما ما كان قبل ذلك وبعده. فخفَفَ الرب عنه الالتهاب ليكون قيامه بالدية عن رضا. ولما خمد التهابه وقف أمام السيد خاضعاً ذليلاً مُتسولاً راغباً في رفع التهلكة عنه. وأن يستمر على قاعدته التي هو عليها على الأرض. وأن يقبل منه في دية دمه الكريم جميع ما هو تحت سلطانه من الجنس البشري. فأجيب إلى سؤاله وحينئذ اصعد الرب آدم من الجحيم وأعاده إلى رتبته الأولى وأجاز معه الأبرار من ذريته.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Although our Lord’s soul departed from His body, this was not in the same way as our souls depart from our bodies because His was still attached to His divinity because His divinity did not separate from His humanity since the annunciation of the angel to the virgin and forever and not even for the twinkling of an eye. The unity means the union of the divinity with the humanity includes body and soul.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وسيدنا وان كانت نفسه قد فارقت جسده إلا أنها لم تكن مفارقة منفصلة كما تفارق نفوسنا أجسادنا على الإطلاق. بل كانت مفارقة متصلة وذلك لأن اللاهوت لم يفارق الناسوت منذ بدء بشارة الملاك للبتول والى أبد الآباد ولا طرفة عين. لأن معنى الإتحاد هو اتحاد اللاهوت بالناسوت. والناسوت يشمل النفس والجسد.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            When the body of our Lord was on the cross, His divinity was attached to it and to the speaking, reasoning soul. Our God died with His sinless body to give us sinners, eternal life. In His mercy and generosity, He accepted our lot which is death and gave us His share which is eternal life and made us heirs with Him in His heavenly kingdom. This is the ultimate generosity of our Lord. Glory be to Him, Forever. Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فلما كان جسد السيد المسيح على الصليب كان اللاهوت متحداً به وبالنفس البسيطة العاقلة الناطقة وقد مات الإله بجسده الذي ليس له خطيئة ليعطينا نحن الخطاة حياة الأبد. لأنه بكرَمِه وكثرة رحمته قَبِل بجسده الكريم ما هو لنا باستحقاق الذي هو الموت. والتي له بحق وهى حياة الأبد أعطاها لنا وصَيَّرَنا بجوده وارثين معه في ملكوته السمائية وحياته الأبدية. وهذا هو الكَرم الفائق الذي هو أقصى غاية كل جود من إلهنا الذي له المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>