<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Title>      <Language id="English">         Holy Great Friday      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         بيان يوم الجمعة العظيمة من البصخة المقدسة      </Language>   </Title>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Brook Kidron         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وادى قدرون:         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            After our Savior ate the Passover with His disciples in Jerusalem, they praised while journeying to Mount Olivet beyond Brook Kidron (Cf. Jn 18:1). This deep brook, also named the Black Brook, is located between Jerusalem and Mount Olivet. Its stream starts about one and a half miles northwest of Jerusalem and flows southeast until it reaches the northeastern corner of the city wall, at which point, it then streams east of the city. It claims the name Valley of Jehoshaphat (Cf. Joel 3:2) when the city wall is to its west, and Mount Olivet and the Hill of Disobedience are to its east; then, it stretches toward Mar Saba where it bears the name Monk Valley. From there, it extends to Lot’s sea, where it bears the name Fire Creek; it is also known as Cedar (Cedron) Valley. After the obscene image of Maachah (Cf. 1 Kg 15:13; 2 Chr 15:16) was burned, and all the vain worship utensils which profaned the Lord’s temple were cast into this brook (Cf. 2 Chr 29:16; 30:14; 2 Kg 23:4, 6, 12), this brook became a common cemetery (Cf. 2 Kg 23:6). David crossed this brook when he fled from his son Absalom (Cf. 2 Sam 15:23, 30); likewise, the Lord Christ while in Gethsemane (aware that Judas was familiar with this place) did not attempt to hide. Rather, He was prepared to offer Himself as a propitiation for the sins of the world, to the extent that He did not wait for the soldiers to inquire of Him. In anticipation, He went out to meet them, asking, “Whom are you seeking?” (Jn 18:4). This was at midnight on Friday, the 15th day of the month of Nisan.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بعد ما أكل مخلصنا -له المجد- الفصح مع تلاميذه بأورشليم، سبحوا وخرجوا إلى جبل الزيتون الى عبر وادى قدرون (يو 18: 1)، وكان هذا الوادى عميقاً، ويسمى بالوادي الاسود. وكان موقعه بين أورشليم وجبل الزيتون. يبتدئ على بعد ميل ونصف الى الشمال الغربى من أورشليم ويسير الى الجنوب الشرقى الى أن يصل الي زاوية السور الشمالية الشرقية، ثم ينحدر شرقى المدينة. ويسمي وادى قدرون أيضاً "وادى يهوشافاط" (يؤ 3: 2)، وهو بين سور المدينة من الجانب الغربى وجبل الزيتون وتل المعصية من الجانب الشرقى، ثم ينحدر الى "مار سابا" حيث يسمى "وادى الراهب". ومن ثم يمتد إلى بحر لوط وهناك يسمي "وادى النار". ويسمى أيضاً "بوادى الارز"، وفي هذا الوادى أُحرقت تماثيل معكة (1مل15: 13)، (2أخ15: 16)، وطرحت جميع أدوات العبادة الباطلة التى تنجس بها هيكل الرب (2أخ29: 16)، (30: 14)، (2مل23: 4،6،12)، ثم صار ذلك الوادى مكاناً للمقابر (2مل 23: 6). ومم يٌذكر أنه عبر هذا الوادى هرب داود من وجه إبنه ابشالوم (2صم15: 23،30)، ويذكر أيضاً أن السيد المسيح عندما ذهب الى جثسيمانى وهو عالم أن يهوذا كان يعرف هذا المكان لم يرد أن يختفى بعد، بل كان مستعداً أن يقدم ذاته كفارة عن خطايا العالم، حتى أنه لم ينتظر الجند ليسألوا من هو، بل سبقهم وخرج لاستقبالهم وسألهم "من تطلبون؟" (يو18: 4)، وكان ذلك في نصف الليل من ليلة الجمعة الموافقة خمسة عشر نيسان.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            The High Priest’s Court         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            دار رئيس الكهنة:         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The soldiers arrested the Savior; the disciples seeing their teacher bound and led away, forsook Him and fled. But two of them (Peter and John) calmed their fears and followed the multitude to the court of the high priest, Annas (father-in-law of Caiaphas). Customarily, members of this council assembled in one of the temple quarters, but they were also permitted to meet at the high priest’s court. Perhaps, the intended purpose of this meeting was to conceal their conspiracy from the multitude, especially since at that time, the temple quarters were overcrowded with people during the Passover.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لما قبض الجند على المخلص -له المجد- ورأى التلاميذ أن معلمهم قد أُوثِقَ وأُخِذَ فتركوه وهربوا، غير أن إثنين منهم سَكن روعهما وهما بطرس ويوحنا اللذان تبعا الجمع إلى دار رئيس الكهنة "حنان" الذى كان حما "قيافا"، وكان من عادة أعضاء ذلك المجلس أن يجتمعوا فى إحدى ديارات الهيكل، وكان يجوز لهم الإجتماع فى دار رئيس الكهنة. ولعل غاية إجتماعهم هذا اخفاء مشورتهم عن الشعب، لأن ديار الهيكل كانت فى ذلك الوقت غاصة بالناس لأنها كانت أيام الفصح.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            The High Priesthood         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وظيفة رئيس الكهنة:         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As for the occupation of the high priest, the first to assume it was Aaron (Ex 29), and in the first centuries of Israelite history, the eldest descendent was to inherit it (Num 3:10). However with the conquest of the Greek empire, this occupation was sold to anyone paying a substantial amount. Thereafter, with the Roman conquest, the high priest was appointed and discharged according to the empire’s fancy, irrespective of the lineage or qualification of the person. This detestable habit continued from the time of Herod the Great, until the devastation of Jerusalem.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأما عن وظيفة رئيس الكهنة فكان أول من تولاها هو "هرون" (خر 29)، وكان يرثها الأكبر من سلالته (عد3: 10) فى القرون الأولى من تاريخ الاسرائيليين ولما إستولى ملوك اليونان على الإسرائيليين صاروا يبيعون لهم تلك الوظيفة لمن يدفع فيها ثمناً وافراً، وبعد أن إستولى عليهم الرومانيون أخذوا يعزلون الرئيس ويقيمون غيره كما يريدون، غير مراعين أهلية ومقدرة الشخص المرغوب فيه. وإستمرت هذه العادة الممقوتة من عصر "هيرودس الكبير" الى زمان خراب أورشليم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Annas was a very prominent and influential figure, and so managed to attain the position of high priesthood, not only for himself, but also for his son Eleazar, his son-in-law Caiaphas, and four more sons. Each one who held this position was given the title of high priest and sat at the great assembly for the duration of his life, even if deposed.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويظهر أن "حنان" كان ذا سطوة قوية وجاه عظيم حتى حصل على رئاسة الكهنة ليس لإبنه "اليعازر" وصهره "قيافا" فحسب بل بالأكثر لأربعة آخرين من بنيه، وكان يلقب كل من أخذ تلك الوظيفة برئيس الكهنة ويجلس فى المجلس الكبير طول أيام حياته ولو عُزِلَ.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Such was the case with Annas; he retained his title as high priest, although he had been deposed from this position four years before the crucifixion. His name preceded that of Caiaphas because he was older in age and more tenured and experienced in the position. When the Jews arrested the Lord Christ, they first took Him to Annas, to enlist his approval and endorsement of the arrest, and then, they took the Lord of glory bound to Caiaphas (Jn 18:24).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهكذا جرى مع حنان فإنه دُعى رئيس الكهنة مع أنه كان معزولاً من وظيفته وقتئذ [قبل الصلب بأربعة سنوات]. وقُدِمَ إسمه علي إسم قيافا لأنه أكبر منه سناً وأقدم فى الوظيفة وله خبرة واسعة بالأحوال، ولما أمسك اليهود السيد المسيح له المجد قدموه أولا إلى "حنان" إستجلاباً لمصادقته وإرضائه عما فعلوا، ومن ثم أخذوا السيد له المجد موثقاً إلى "قيافا" (يو 18: 24).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Caiaphas         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قيافا         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Joseph, also known as Caiaphas (according to Josephus the historian), was present at the time when the judgment to crucify the Lord Christ was passed (Jn 11:49–61). Being a member of the Sadducees sect, and Annas’ son-in-law, he was also spuriously given the title of high priest (Jn 11:49). Caiaphas is the one who said, “It is expedient for us that one man should die for the people, and not that the whole nation should perish” (Jn 11:49–50). Just as the case with Annas, Caiaphas, too, was deposed as the high priest at the will of the Romans. He was deposed by Vitalious (or Valarius), Pontius Pilate’s successor, as the Roman governor ruling Judea. This occurred six years after the Lord Christ’s crucifixion.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "قيافا" إسمه "يوسف" كما ذكر يوسيفوس المؤرخ، وقد كان حاضراً وقت القضاء علي السيد المسيح بالصلب (يو11: 49-61)، وكان صدوقى المذهب وكان صهر "حنان" و"كان رئيساً للكهنة فى تلك السنة" (يو11: 49)، هو الذى قال: "خير لنا أن يموت واحد عن الشعب ولا تهلك الأمة كلها" (يو11: 49-50)، ولأن الدولة الرومانية فى ذاك الوقت كانت تنصب رئيس الكهنة أو تعزله حسب إرادتها، لذلك كما حدث مع حنان الى عُزل من روما كرئيس كهنة، هكذا قيافا أيضاً عزله فيتاليوس أو فالوريوس سلف بيلاطس فى الحكومة اليهودية وهو القائد الرومانى، وكان ذلك بعد ستة سنوات من صلب السيد المسيح له المجد.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Condemning the Savior at Night         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            محاكمة المخلص ليلاً         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Sanhedrin assembled, and called an unofficial preliminary session. This took place when Annas sent Jesus to Caiaphas (shortly after midnight), where our Savior was first examined. He remained alone before Caiaphas and the council members, who mocked Him until almost dawn, or the time of the cock’s crowing (during which time, Peter denied the Lord Christ three times).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إجتمع أعضاء مجمع السبعين وعقدوا جلسة إستعدادية غير رسمية. ولابد أن يكون مخلصنا قد فحص أولا أمام "قيافا" لما أرسله اليه "حنان" بعد منتصف الليل بقليل، وبقى مخلصنا له المجد أمام قيافا وحده، وأمام أعضاء المجمع إلى قرب الفجر، أو وقت صياح الديك، وفى أثناء ذلك أنكر بطرس السيد المسيح ثلاث مرات، ثم استهزأوا به.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As Friday morning neared, the great council convened in the temple to uphold the ruling of the previous unofficial session that took place during the night in the high priest’s court. The ruling deliberated was the death of Jesus. This was considered merely an expression of the members’ opinions because it contradicted both Jewish law, which prohibits conducting an examination during the night, and also Roman law, which forbids passing a ruling before dawn. This reveals the intensity of the high priests’ wrath towards Jesus, and their dread of His impact on the people. The council met at night in order to fabricate an accusation for His death.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لما كان نهار صباح يوم الجمعة إجتمع المجمع الكبير فى الهيكل وأثبت حكم الجلسة السابقة الغير الرسمية والتى عُقِدت فى الليل فى دار رئيس الكهنة، لأن الحكم علي يسوع بالموت فى تلك الجلسة كان يُعتبر كمجرد تصريح برأى الأعضاء، لأنه كان مخالفاً لشريعة اليهود أن يُجري فحص جناية فى الليل، وكذلك مخالفاً للشريعة الرومانية أن يصدر حكم قبل الفجر. ويَظهر من ذلك أن غضب رؤساء الكهنة كان شديداً على يسوع له المجد، وإنهم كانوا خائفين جداً من تأثير أقواله فى الشعب، لذلك إجتمعوا فى الليل لكى يخترعوا عليه تهماً ملفقة لإماتته.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The high priest deceptively asked Jesus, “I put You under oath by the living God: Tell us if You are the Christ, the Son of God!” (Mt 26:63; Mk 14:61). At Jesus’ reply, Caiaphas displayed disgust and shock, declaring Him blasphemous, and therefore, he needed no further witnesses to rule against Him. They took a unanimous judgment that His punishment is death (Jn 19:7; Mk 14:64), although neither they nor their rulers had authority to carry out such a conviction.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            حينئذ سأله رئيس الكهنة "أستحلفك بالله الحى أن تقول لنا هل أنت هو المسيح إبن الله" (مت 26: 63)، (مر14: 61) فلما أجاب يسوع على السؤال، تظاهر قيافا بالاشمئزاز من جوابه، وحسبه تجديفاً، وقال أنه غير محتاج إلى شهود بعد، فحكموا عليه بالإجماع بالموت (يو19: 7)، (مر 14: 64)، غير أنه لما لم يكن لهم ولا لرؤسائهم قوة تنفيذ هذا الحكم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Thus, they took Jesus to Pilate, the Roman governor, to condemn Christ to be crucified. It is no secret that the great council alone had a lawful right to deliberate on criminal cases and assign its penalty. They had no authority to pass a judgment of death upon anyone, for the Roman authority had suspended this right many years earlier.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لذلك أخذوا يسوع إلى بيلاطس الحاكم الرومانى لكي يأمر بصلبه. ولا يُخفى أن المجمع الكبير كان له وحده الحق الشرعى فى الحكم على الدعاوى الجنائية التى تستوجب القصاص، إلا إنه لم يكن له سلطاناً فى ذلك الوقت أن يُجرى الحكم بالموت على أحد، لأن الحكومة الرومانية كانت قد نزعت منه ذلك السلطان قبل هذا الوقت بعدة سنين.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The chief priest tore his clothes (Mt 26:65), a universal sign of mourning for Jews (2 Kg 18:37; 19:1; Esth 4:1), intending by this to show his disgust at the extent of the blasphemy in his presence. He testified that Jesus was a blasphemer, and incited the council to concur with his ruling against Him. His entire emotional enactment was a hypocritical and deceptive attempt to promote his evil objective. He further added to his iniquity by tearing his clothes, because according to Mosaic Law, the chief priest was forbidden from tearing his clothes (Lev 10:6; 21:10). From that point forward, the priesthood was torn away from the Jewish nation.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما حدث أن رئيس الكهنة مزق ثيابه (مت26: 65)، وكانت هذه هى العلامة المألوفة للحزن عند اليهود (2مل18: 37، 19: 1)، (أس 4: 1)، وكان قد قصد بها رئيس الكهنة أن يُظهر اشمئزازه من فظاعة التجديف، ولكى تكون شهادة علي يسوع -له المجد- بأنه جدف، وحضاً للمجلس بالحُكْم على يسوع كما حَكَمَ هو عليه، إلا أنه كان كل ما أظهره من الإنفعالات رياءً وخداعاً للوصول فقط إلي تتميم بغيته الشريرة، بينما فِعْل رئيس الكهنة هذا أى تمزيقه لثيابه قد زاد من إثمه، لأنه على موجب شريعة موسى كان لايجوز لرئيس الكهنة أن يمزق ثيابه (لا 10: 6، 21: 10)، ومن ذلك الحين نُزِعَت من الأمة اليهودية وظيفة الكهنوت.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            It was the council members’ duty to impartially investigate if what the Lord of glory said was true or not. Instead, they hardened their hearts from hearing the truth and condemned Him, in accordance with Mosaic Law for blasphemers, to be subject to stoning (Cf. Jn 10:31; Lev 24:16).[36]         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان على أعضاء المجلس أن ينظروا فى الدعوى الموجهة ضده ليعلموا أحق هو كل ما قاله السيد له المجد أم لا، ولكنهم صرفوا أذهانهم عن سماع الحقيقة وقرروا تنفيذ الحكم فيه بالموت رجماً على مقتضي شريعة موسى التى أمرت برجم المجدف[36] (يو 10: 31)، (لا24: 16).         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [36] The mention of stoning here refers to previous attempts of stoning Him, although not specified in Scripture as the anticipated method of death.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The council members had two options, they either could have ordered the people to stone Jesus (disregarding the Roman decree, as they later did in the case of Stephen), or they could have obtained authorization from Pilate. They refrained from the latter, in fear that many from the crowd would come to defend Jesus and rescue Him. They resorted to ask Pilate to carry out their charge to kill Jesus. At that time, Roman law passed judgment of crucifixion in cases of blasphemy. This was the Lord of glory’s accusation, and thus, He was to die in the flesh—crucified, and not stoned. These council members were in agreement on their judgment, yet in order to make it lawful, because according to their assembly by-laws it was forbidden to carry out nocturnal judgments against criminals, they had to meet again. Therefore, they met once more after the break of dawn and repeated the charge against Him (Mt 27:3) (this was the last time Jesus stood before the Jewish rulers).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان ممكناً لأعضاء المجلس أن يأمروا الناس برجم يسوع على رغم حكام الرومان، كما فعلوا بعد ذلك باستفانوس، وأن يستأذنوا بيلاطس فى ذلك، ولكنهم لم يفعلوا هذا خوفاً من أن كثيرين من الشعب قد يدافعون عن يسوع وينقذونه من أيديهم، فإستحسنوا أن يسألوا بيلاطس أن يُجرى حكمهم أى أن يقتله. و كان القانون عند الرومانيين يقضى فى مثل هذه الحالات على المجدف بالموت صلباً، وهذه هى علة إختيار السيد له المجد أن يموت بالجسد صلباً لا رجماً. وكان أعضاء ذلك المجمع يعتبرون حكمهم نهائياً، لكنهم إضطُروا أن يجتمعوا أيضاً ليجعلوا هذا الحكم شرعياً، لأنه ممنوع تنفيذ الأحكام التى يصدرونها على المذنبين بالليل حسب قوانين مجلسهم كما ذكرنا قبلاً، فإجتمعوا هذه المرة الثانية بعد طلوع الفجر وكرروا الحكم عليه وأدانوه (مت 27: 3)، وهذه كانت آخر مرة نظرت فيها الدعوى على يسوع أمام قضاة اليهود.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Court Ruling in the Morning         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            جلسة المجمع صباحأ         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            On Friday morning, all the chief priests and elders of the people conspired against Jesus to kill Him. The intention of this session was to affirm the decision taken at the nocturnal meeting, which was contrary to regulations and deemed unlawful according to the Talmud (one of the holiest Jewish books). According to the standards set out in the Talmud, the counsel is prohibited from examining criminal cases at night, especially ones that carry the death penalty. It is necessary for the conviction of death to be passed at the time of trial, and no ruling was to be delivered without self-testimony. Since the counsel broke this fundamental law by trying Jesus at night, they found it necessary to rectify the situation by holding a formal lawful session early in the morning. This session was held in its formal location (in the temple), unlike the nocturnal session, which was held in the court of the high priest. The intended purpose was to question Jesus, and provoke Him to speak blasphemously, in order to procure Pilate’s (the Roman governor) collaboration with their sentence. As all the evangelists recorded, they arrested Him and took Him to Pilate (Mt 27:11-30; Mk 15:6-20; Lk 23:13-32; Jn 19:6-7).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما كان الصباح أى صباح يوم الجمعة تشاور، جميع رؤساء الكهنة وشيوخ الشعب على يسوع حتى يقتلوه، وكان الغرض من إنعقاد هذه الجلسة إثبات ما حكموا به فى إجتماعهم فى الليل. وكان ذلك على خلاف النظام، كما إنه لم يكن شرعياً حسب نص كتاب التلمود الذى هو من أقدس كتب اليهود، لأنه بموجب ذلك الكتاب لم يجُز للمجلس أن يفحص ليلاً دعاوى جنائية يمكن أن يُحكم فيها على من تثبت عليه بالموت، وكان من المُحتم أن يحكم على المدعى عليه بالموت فى ذات الوقت الذى يُحاكم فيه، وألا ينفذ عليه الحكم إلا بمجرد إقراره على نفسه. وبما إنهم كسروا الشريعة التى تنهى عن الحكم فى القضايا الجنائية فى الليل، رأوا أنه من الواجب أن يعقدوا جلسة رسمية شرعية فى الصباح مبكرين فى ذلك بقدر إمكانهم. وعقدت هذه الجلسة طبعاً فى المكان الرسمى فى الهيكل، وليست كالجلسة التى عقدت بالليل فى بيت رئيس الكهنة. وكان المقصود منها إستجواب يسوع وإستماع أقواله، والمشورة بكيفية إجراء توقيع الحكم عليه الذى يقتضى التصديق عليه من بيلاطس الوالى الرومانى كما تقدم، فأوثقوه وأتوا به إلى بيلاطس كما ينص جميع البشيرين (مت27: 11-30)، (مر15: 6-20)، (لو23: 13-32)، (يو19: 6-7).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Judas’ Suicide         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إنتحار يهوذا         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When Judas realized He was condemned, he was remorseful and returned the thirty pieces of silver (Mt 27:3). His remorse, however, was not a true repentance; otherwise; he would have sought and attained forgiveness. True repentance leads the transgressor to Christ; yet, this remorse was not from a heart void of deceit. A true repentant heart leads to life, but false repentance leads to more transgression. We see this in the example of Judas, who furthered his betrayal by committing suicide. His remorse is likened to Cain and King Saul’s, spiraling downward to hopelessness and despair. When Judas’ conscience awoke, he felt the gravity of the crime he committed against his good Master—he had relinquished himself to the devil, who in turn, used him to fulfill his evil intentions and left him without consolation or hope. Furthermore, divine help forsook him, and so in despair, he went and hanged himself, adding to his transgressions.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            حينئذ لما رأي يهوذا أنه قد دين، ندم ورد الثلاثين من الفضة (مت 27: 3)، فندمه هذا لم يكن توبة حقيقية وإلا لحمله على طلب المغفرة فينالها. فالتوبة الصحيحة تقود المذنب الى المسيح، ولكن هذه الندامة لم تكن صادرة عن قلب نقى من الغش، لأن التوبة الحقيقية تقود الى الحياة وأما التوبة الغير حقيقية فتقود الى زيادة الإثم كما هو مشاهد فى قصة يهوذا. فإنه زاد على خيانته قتله لنفسه، وكان ندمه كندم قايين وشاول الملك ملتجئاً الى اليأس والقنوط، وذاك عندما أنبه ضميره وشعر بعظم الجرم الذى إرتكبه فى حق معلمه الصالح، أسلم نفسه للشيطان فإتخذه إبليس آلة فى يده لإتمام مقاصده الشريرة، ثم تركه بلا تعزية ولا رجاء، ومن ثم تخلت عنه المعونة الإلهية فذهب وخنق نفسه وبذلك تضاعف جرمه.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Peter’s Remorse         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ندامة بطرس         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            There is a great difference between Judas’ remorse, and Peter’s remorse. When Peter felt the gravity of his sin, he withdrew from people, sought isolation, and wept bitterly (Lk 22:62) (as the Holy Bible mentions). He did this because of his great shame and sorrow, and for his wrongdoings toward the Savior, and for his weakness, fearfulness, blaspheming of grace, and his transgression in denying Christ by cursing and swearing after boasting of his courage and steadfastness. Truth be told, his transgression was very great because he committed it after having spent three years as a disciple of Jesus: hearing His teachings, witnessing His miracles, seeing His signs, and being chosen over the others as one of the three distinguished disciples. He had dined with Him only a few hours earlier, heard His warning, and vowed saying, “If I have to die with You, I will not deny You!” (Mk 14:31). The trials that set Peter to deny Christ were meager, as he was not threatened by great men, strong forces, or the most distinguished of people, but rather by a maidservant. Peter saw John, who “was known to them as one of Christ’s disciples” (Jn 18:15–16). Therefore, it cannot be said that Peter’s transgression is less than Judas’. But unlike Judas, Peter offered a true repentance. His remorse was not akin to Judas’ remorse because Judas’ remorse was that of hopelessness, while Peter’s remorse led him to seek true repentance. This was exemplified by his isolation, the extent of his remorse, and his regret. His repentance can be likened to David’s repentance. The difference between a hypocrite and a Christian is that the first falls and does not rise, while the latter falls but rises remorsefully, penitently, humbly, and consequentially renewed in his spiritual life.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فيوجد فرق عظيم ما بين ندامة يهوذا وندامة بطرس، فبطرس لما شعر بعظم الخطأ الذى وقع فيه إعتزل الناس وأحب الإنفراد وبكى بكاء مراً (لو22: 62) كما يذكر الكتاب، لخجله وأسفه الشديدين على ما فرط منه فى حق المخلص وعلى ما كان عليه من ضعف وخوف وكفر بالنعمة، وعلى إثمه بأنه أنكر المسيح بحلف ولعن بعد أن كان يفتخر بشجاعته وثباته، والحق أن إثمه كان عظيماً جداً، لأنه إرتكبه بعد أن كان تلميذ يسوع ثلاث سنوات، وبعد أن سمع تعاليمه وشاهد معجزاته ورأى آياته، وكان واحداً من الرسل الثلاث المختصين على غيرهم، وكان قد تعشى معه قبلها ببضع ساعات، وسمع تحذيره له من هذا الإثم ووعد بطرس لمعلمه قائلاً ولو مت معك لا أنكرك (مر 14: 31)، وكانت دواعي هذا الإنكار قليلة إذا لم يُهَدَدْ من أكبر الرجال ولا من أعظم القواد ولا من أشرف الناس بل من جارية خادمة، بينما كان يشاهد هناك يوحنا يتبع معلمه إذ انه كان معروفاً عندهم أيضاً إنه من تلاميذ السيد المسيح (يو18: 15-16)، فكانت خطية بطرس أقل تجاوزاً من خطية يهوذا، ولكنه ندم على ما فرط منه بندامة حقيقية. ولم يكن أسفه كأسف يهوذا، لأن أسف يهوذا كان أسف اليأس بينما أسف بطرس كان أسف التوبة الحقيقية، والدليل على هذا إنفراده وشدة ندمه ودوام تأثيره فكانت توبته كتوبة داود النبى، فالفرق بين المرائى والمسيحى أن الأول يسقط ولا يقوم والثانى يسقط ويقوم نادماً تائباً متواضعاً متجدداً فى الحياة الروحية.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Jesus before Pilate         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يسوع أمام بيلاطس         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When the Savior was sent to the Roman ruler, Pontius Pilate, He was accompanied by the entire great assembly (Lk 23:1; Mt 27:1–2). The intent behind gathering the entire assembly and parading in the morning to Pilates’ court was to sway Pilate and convince him that the accused—Jesus, had committed the greatest, most despicable, repugnant crime. When Pilate was informed that the great council members had arrived with a transgressor, they sent Jesus to Pilate and stood at the doorway (they could not enter into the Praetorium because the law forbade them from entering a house where there is leaven). They did not enter lest they become unclean and be prohibited from eating the Passover. Knowing this, Pilate went out to meet them. They were eager to present their accuser, without mentioning the reasons for which the great assembly had condemned Him, in hopes to establish a hasty conviction. However, their hope was lost when Pilate asked, “What accusation do you bring against this Man?” (Jn 18:29). At this point, they were compelled to declare their fabricated accusation. After hearing this, Pilate declared that he found no reason for condemning Jesus to death (Lk 23:22,14,4; Jn 18:38, 19:6,4), which dampened their hopes of condemning Christ. St. Luke the Evangelist mentions that Pilate publicly confessed three times that he found no justifiable reason for our Savior’s death; he further confessed that Herod also found no reason (Lk 23:14-15).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما أُرسل المخلص له المجد فى المرة الأولى إلى الوالى الرومانى صحبه كل المجمع الكبير (مت 27: 1-2)، (لو23: 1)، ولابد أنهم كانوا يقصدون من تجمهرهم هذا والذهاب بموكب حافل من ادنياء وكبراء أن يموهوا على عقل بيلاطس ويقنعوه بأن يسوع قد إرتكب جناية من أفظع وأشنع الجنايات التى لم يُسمع بمثلها، مبالغين فى إستدانته. ولما أُخبِرَ بيلاطس بأن أعضاء المجلس الكبير أتوه بمذنب، وانهم لا يقدرون أن يدخلوا إلى الوالى فى دار الولاية [تبعاً للقانون الذى يحرم عليهم دخول بيوت فيها خمير] فدفعوا بيسوع إلى بيلاطس، وهم لبثوا بإزاء الباب فى الطريق، ولم يدخلوا لئلا يتنجسوا فيمتنعوا من أكل الفصح إنما خرج هو لمقابلتهم. ولا ريب أنهم كانوا يطمعون فى إثبات حكمهم حالاً بدون ذِكر الأسباب التى دانه عليها المجمع الكبير. غير أنه قد خاب أملهم عند سؤال بيلاطس لهم "أية شكاية تقدمون على هذا الانسان؟" (يو18: 29) فاضطروا إلى أن يقرروا الذنب الموهوم. وأسفرت النتيجة عن أن بيلاطس أعلن أنه لم يجد فيه علة يستوجب عليها الموت (لو23: 4، 14، 22) ، (يو18: 38، 19: 4،6)، [هنا ويذكر معلمنا لوقا البشير أن بيلاطس إعترف وأعلن ثلاث مرات إنه لم يجد فى مخلصنا علة للموت، بل وبالأكثر إعترافه أن هيرودس أيضاً لم يجد فيه علة للموت (لو23: 14-15)].         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Pilate         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بيلاطس         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Pilate was also known as Pontius. Archelaus, the son of Herod the Great, was the last king over Judea.(he was removed from ruling in the year 6 AD). From that time forward, Caesar appointed governors over Judea. Pilate was Tiberius Caesar’s sixth appointed governor over Judea. He governed Judea for ten years (six before Christ’s crucifixion, and four after His Resurrection). He was known to be ruthless, unjust, temperamental, and sought only his personal gain; he did not care for the good of others. The Jews rebelled against his reign often. Consequently, he shed their blood readily to suffocate their insurrections, so much so that the Jews passionately despised him and complained to Caesar several times.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بيلاطس هذا كان يلقب بالبنطى، كان أرخلاوس بن هيرودس الكبير آخر ملك علي اليهودية وكان قد نفى من حكمه سنة ست للميلاد، ومن ذلك الوقت أخذ قيصر يقيم على اليهودية الولاة، فكان بيلاطس سادس والي على اليهودية عينه طيباريوس قيصر، وكان قد تولى اليهودية مدة عشرة سنوات (ستاً منهم قبل صلب السيد المسيح وأربعاً بعد قيامته). وكان قاسياً ظالماً سريع التقلب لا يسعي الا لمنافعه الشخصية ولا يكترث بمصالح الاخرين، وكثيراً ما عصاه اليهود، فسفك دماء كثيرين منهم اخماداً لفتنهم، فأبغضوه أشد البغض وشكوه عدت مرات لقيصر.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Although he could discern truth and justice, he lacked the courage to avenge the wronged and defend the truth when there was resistance. He hated and abhorred the Jews, but he feared their complaints to the emperor. He was removed from his governorate at the same time that Caiaphas was removed from the priesthood.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إلا أنه كان بصيراً فى بيان الحق والعدل لكنه لم تكن له القوة والشجاعة لينصف المظلوم، وليحامي عن الحق عند وجود شغب ومقاومة. فكان بدوره يكره اليهود ويبغضهم لكنه كان يخشى شكواهم إياه للإمبراطور. وكان قد عُزِلَ من ولايته فى الوقت الذى عٌزِلَ فيه قيافا من كهنوته.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The governor’s headquarters was in Caesarea, on the Roman seashore (Acts 23:23–33; 25:1,4,6,13). The governor was tasked with traveling to Jerusalem during the great feasts to make rulings and maintain the peace, by preventing troubles and nuisances evidently of large crowds. The governor’s house in Jerusalem is in the palace called, Herod’s Palace (the Praetorium) on Mount Zion.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كان مركز الوالى في قيصرية علي شاطئ بحر الروم (أع 23: 23-33، 25: 1، 4، 6، 13)، لكنه كان يذهب إلى أورشليم فى أيام الاعياد العظيمة ليمنع الشغب والتشويش الذى كان يحدث من الجمع وليُجرى الأحكام. وكان منزل الوالى فى أورشليم فى القصر الذي يُسمى قصر هيرودس الكبير على جبل صهيون.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Jesus Sent to Herod         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يسوع أُرسل الى هيرودس         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As Pilate was debating on how to sidestep judging the Lord Christ, the mention of Galilee, in passing, gave him the idea that he could pass the burden to Herod Antipas, the tetrarch of Galilee (Lk 3:1), who ruled for 42 years (four years before the Lord Christ’s crucifixion, and thereafter, the remainder). He was the second son of Herod the Great and from his fourth wife, Miltaki. Like his father before him, he craved glory, and indulged in grandeur and extravagance. He is the one the Master called a fox (Lk 13:32). Also, like his father, he had spent grand sums on community buildings. He built Tiberius in honor of the emperor Tiberius Caesar. When his wife, Herodias, urged him to go to Rome to seek the royal title, Emperor Caligula removed him from his position, and exiled him to Leon in Gaul for his trespasses.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">             ولما كان بيلاطس حائراً فى ماذا يفعل ليتخلص من إدانته للسيد له المجد و ذكر أمامه أن المخلص من الجليل، خطر فى باله أنه يمكنه أن يُخلى نفسه من هذه المسؤولية بإرساله إلى هيرودس انتيباس رئيس الربع فى الجليل (لو3: 1). هيرودس هذا كانت مدة وجوده فى الحكم هى أثنين وأربعين سنه (أربعة منها قبل صلب السيد المسيح والباقى بعد صلبه)، وكان ثانى أبناء هيرودس الاكبر من إمرأته الرابعة ملثاكى، وكان مثل أبيه راغباً فى المجد والعظيمة ورغد العيش، وهو الذى سماه ربنا ثعلباً (لو13: 32)، وقد انفق كابيه مبالغ طائلة في المباني العمومية، فبنى "طبرية" إكراماً للامبراطور طيباريوس قيصر. حدث أن حرضته إمرأته "هيروديا" بأن يتوجه إلى رومية لكي يطلب لقب ملك غير أن الامبراطور "كليكولا" عذله من وظيفته و نفاه إلى ليون فى غاليا لسبب ذنوبه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            It has been mentioned at least five times that Herod Antipas has taken the wife of his brother Philip [not Philip the Tetrarch], and John the Baptist rebuked him. Although previously he rejoiced at the teachings of John, he eventually beheaded John in prison and handed his head to Salome, the daughter of Herodias, in order to fulfill his promise to her (Mt 14:11; Mk 6:16–28).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد ذُكر خمس مرات على الأقل أن هيرودس أنتيباس هذا كان قد أتخذ زوجة فيلبس أخيه زوجة له (مت14: 3)، (مر16: 17)، (لو13: 19) ، وبسبب هذا كان يوحنا المعمدان يوبخه بشدة، بالرغم من إنه كان سابقاً يمتدح تعاليمه، لكنه وضعه في السجن الى أن أعطى رأسه الى إبنة هيروديا عندما إضطر لإيفاء وعده لها (مت14: 11)، (مر6: 16-28).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Herod was in Jerusalem for the Passover, and thus, also passed judgment against the Lord Christ. Pilate sent Jesus, being a Galilean, to Herod’s jurisdiction. Herod was very glad to meet the Savior, because for a long time, he had wanted to see Him. He took this opportunity to ask Him many questions, but the Master refused to answer any of his questions (Lk 23:7–12). Herod begged Him to perform a miracle before his eyes, but again, the Lord with His divine wisdom refrained. In turn, Herod and his men of war mocked Jesus, but He maintained His silence—answering nothing.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان هيرودس أحد القضاة عند محاكمة المسيح له المجد لأنه إتفق حضوره إلى أورشليم في ذلك الوقت لعيد الفصح، فأرسل بيلاطس يسوع اليه لانه كان جليلياً تحت سلطانه. أما هيرودس فقبل المخلص بكل فرح لانه كان مشتاقاً من زمن طويل أن يراه. وإذ اشتهى هيرودس أن يعلم عنه شيئاً أخذ يسأله الكثير من الإسئلة لكن السيد المسيح لم يجبه بشئ عما سأله (لو23: 7-12)، وترجاه أن يصنع أمامه آية فلم يصنع حسب ما اقتضت حكمته الالهية، فهزأ به هو وجنوده  أما يسوع فبقى ساكتاً ولم يجبه بشئ.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Herod considered Pilate’s act of sending Jesus to him for judgment as a gesture of respect and honor. This was the cause of reinstating their friendship, which went sour after Pilate killed the Galileans, as mentioned in the Gospel according to St. Luke (Lk 13:1).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد اعتبر هيرودس ارسال يسوع اليه من قبل بيلاطس هى علامة اعتبار من ومحبة. وكان ذلك سبب لارجاع الصداقة بينهما التى كانت قد انحلت عراها بسبب ذبح بيلاطس الجليليين المذكورين فى لوقا (لو13: 1).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Glory to You O Lord, for by Your amazing birth, You brought peace to earth and reconciled us to God Your Father, and at Your death You removed the enmity from the hearts of the kings. Truly, You are the King of reconciliation and peace.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            المجد لك يا رب فى ميلادك العجيب ألقيت سلاما على الارض وصالحتنا مع الله أبيك، وعند موتك نزعت العداوة من قلوب الملوك، حقاً إنك رئيس الصلح والسلام.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Judgment against Jesus         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الحكم على يسوع         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            After Jesus returned from Herod, He was brought again before Pilate. This time, Pilate officially sat on the judgment seat and declared that he had accurately examined Jesus and found not one fault in Him deserving of death, and that Herod had concurred with this same decree. As such, Pilate still insisted on releasing Jesus. He declared he would scourge Him and release Him, hoping this would appease the Jewish nation, especially the priests. This pleased no one, but rather those present shouted loudly, “Crucify this Man and release to us Barabbas!” (Cf. Lk 23:18) (which means son of ‘Abbas’). He was infamous for shedding blood and committing offenses. He was cast into prison for his insurrection and rebellion. It is probable that he was from the faction that abhorred Roman authority, and had set the city in an uproar with his rebellion and murderous ways.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بعد رجوع مخلصنا له المجد من عند هيرودس، أُحضر مرة ثانية أمام بيلاطس الذى كان لم يزل مصمماً على طلاقه. ثم جلس فى هذه المرة على كرسى القضاء رسيماً وأعلن انه قد فحص يسوع فحصاً دقيقاً فلم يجد فيه علة واحدة تستوجب الموت، وقد أقر أيضاً هيروس هذا الاقرار ولذلك قال انه سيؤدبه ويطلقه، آملا بذلك أنه يرضى أمة اليهود وخصوصاً الكهنة. غير إنه لم يرض أحداً منهم بل إرتفع صراخ الموجودين أصلب لنا هذا وأطلق باراباس (لو23: 18)، ومعنى إسم باراباس هو ابن عباس، وهو رجل كان قد اشتهر بسفك الدماء وارتكابه المعاصى، وكان ملقى فى السجن بتهمة إحداث المشاغبات والقلاقل و إهاجة المدينة بعمله الفتن وارتكابه القتل. من المحتمل أن باراباس كان من الحزب الذى يكره السلطان الرومانى.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Ironically, Barabbas was guilty of the exact charge the chief priests falsely laid on the Savior—rebellion. No greater or clearer evidence could be presented, only the demise of the Pharisees and their supports in the hypocritical scheme to fiercely ask the Roman ruler to release the transgressor, Barabbas, and condemn the righteous Savior. “When Pilate saw that he could not prevail at all, but rather that a tumult was rising, he took water and washed his hands before the multitude, saying, ‘I am innocent of the blood of this just Person. You see to it’” (Mt 27:24; Duet 21:6–9). These words did not acquit Pilate. Although, he did truly wash his hands with water, yet this did not wash his heart from transgression—he did deliver to death One whom he had judged as innocent, simply because the cries of the crowd contradicted his conviction. When he could not convince the high priests and rulers of His innocence, he delivered the Savior to scourging first, in hopes that would satiate them, but to his disappointment, it was not enough, and the high priest and rulers demanded the crucifixion, which Pilate was compelled to execute.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            مما يستحق الالتفات، أن باراباس كان مجرماً بذات الجرم الذى ادعى به رؤساء الكهنة كذباً على المخلص وهو الفتنة. لذلك لا يمكن تقديم برهان أكبر من هذا على انحطاط وخبث تلك الامة، وهو بذلهم كل ما فى استطاعتهم ليطلبوا من الحاكم الرومانى اطلاق سراح  باراباس الاثيم وادانة المخلص البار. ”حينئذ لما رأي بيلاطس انه لا فائدة من ذلك بل بالحرى يحدث شغب أخذ ماء وغسل يديه قدام الجمع قائلا: انى برئ من دم هذا البار أبصروا أنتم" (مت27: 24)، (تث21: 6-9)، لم يكن هذا القول مبرراً لبيلاطس، نعم وان كان قد غسل يديه بالماء ولكنه بذلك لم يغسل قلبه من الذنب، لانه سلم للموت من كان قد حكم ببراءته بمجرد سماعه صراخ الشعب بما هو مخالف لاعتقاده، فلما لم يقدر أن يُقنع الكهنة والرؤساء، أَسلمَ المخلص له المجد ليٌجلد أولاً طلباً لإرضائهم، ولما أحبط عندما رأى إنهم لم يستكفوا بالجلد بل طلبوا أن يُصلب، حقق لهم بيلاطس إرادتهم بعد ذلك.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Scourging and Mocking Him         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            جلدوه واستهزأوا به         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Roman scourging was very brutal, much more severe than Jewish scourging. Jews only exposed the upper body part of the one to be scourged, while Romans exposed the whole body. For Jews, the whips had a limit—forty minus one—but the Romans observed no such limit, used extreme severity, and showed no compassion. Void of human emotions, they would whip criminals mercilessly and quite often criminals died under scourging. In fact, scourging was forbidden on Romans, and was designated for slaves and people from other nations under the Roman rule, whom they also classified as slaves (Acts 22:25).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان الجلد عند الرومانيين فظيعاً جداً، بل كان اقسى كثيراً من جلد اليهود، لان اليهود كانوا يعرون فقط الجزء الاعلى من جسد المرغوب فى جلده، أما الرومانيون فكانوا يعرون الجسد كله. كانت عدد الجلدات عند اليهود محدوداً اى اربعين جلدة الا واحدة، واما عند الرومانيين فبلا عدد وبقسوة متناهية. فكانوا يجلدون المجرمين بلا رحمة ولا شفقة وكثيراً ما كان يموت البعض من المجرمين تحت الجلد. لذلك كان الجلد ممنوعاً على الرومانيين، بل خصوا به العبيد واهل البلاد التى تكون تحت سلطانهم، إذ كانوا عندهم بمنزلة عبيد (أع22: 25).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            After the Savior was scourged, they again removed His clothes and dressed Him in a scarlet robe; this is the attire of an army commander. The intention was to mock Jesus for proclaiming Himself a King. All their derision, however, was preordained by God to serve His divine purpose. What they used to mock Jesus, He used to establish Him as a King. The purple and scarlet robe is as a symbol that He is victorious; He was crowned with thorns because He is the King of heaven and earth; and a reed was placed in His hand because He clutches the scepter of sovereignty.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بعد ما جُلد المخلص له المجد نزعوا ثيابه والبسوه ثوباً قرمزياً، وهو ما كان يلبسه رؤساء الجيش، لكنهم البسوه إياه كاحتقار له لانهم زعموا أن مخلصنا له المجد إدَّعى بانه ملك، غير أن ما صنعوه به من استهزاء قد تعين من قبل الله ليدل على معانى إلاهية، وتعيرهم له إستخدم بالأكثر ليثبت إنه ملك: فانهم قد أُلبسوه القرمز والارجوان لأنه غالب. قد كلل بالشوك لأنه ملك السماء والارض. قد وضعت فى يده قصبة لأنه قابض علي صولجان الملك.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Vinegar Mixed with Bitter Herbs         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الخل الممزوج بالمر         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            After the soldiers ridiculed Jesus, they dressed Him in His own clothes and led Him outside the city to crucify Him at the place, called in Hebrew, Golgotha (the skull), which is a round high hill, void of rocks or trees and resembling the human skull. Some say it received this name because of the abundance of skulls of the slain thrown there. It was also said that Adam’s skull was buried there.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبعدما سَخَرَ الجند بيسوع البسوه ثيابه ومضوا به الى خارج المدينة ليصلب فى المكان الذى يسمى بالعبرانيه جلجثة ومعناه الجمجمة، وهو عبارة عن اكمة مرتفعة مستديرة خالية من الصخور والاشجار تشبه جمجمة الانسان. وقال بعضهم سُميت بهذا الاسم لكثرة ما طرح فيها من جماجم القتلى. وقيل أيضاً أن جمجمة آدم كانت مدفونه هناك.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When they arrived at this location, “they gave Him sour wine mingled with gall to drink. But when He had tasted it, He would not drink” (Mt 27:34). Most probably those who gave the Lord of glory this drink were Jews, as this was not a custom for the Romans. Jews offered this drink to whomever was condemned to death at their execution because the rabbis declared this to be godly and righteous, based on the Sage’s advice: “Give strong drink to him who is perishing, and wine to those who are bitter of heart. Let him drink and forget his poverty, and remember his misery no more” (Prov 31:6–7). It seems that the Lord Christ tasted it out of courtesy to the one who offered this good deed, but refrained from drinking it, preferring to thoroughly feel His Passion, not wanting to distort His clarity of mind, and to sense all the pains of His crucifixion with full cognizance: “Shall I not drink the cup which My Father has given Me?” (Jn 18:11). As for the drink, it was of bitter herbs like wormwood mingled with poppy seed juice and acidic wine (differing slightly from vinegar). The intention in blending it with the wine was to provide a potent effect, so that by simply drinking from it, the crucified becomes oblivious to being dead or alive.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فلما وصلوا به الي ذلك المكان أعطوه خلاً ممزوجاً بمرارة ليشرب ولما ذاق لم يرد أن يشرب (مت 27: 34)، ومن المرجح أن الذين قدموا للسيد المسيح له المجد هذا الشراب هم من اليهود لانه لم يكن ذلك من عوائد الرومان، ولان اليهود كانوا يتبرعون به لكل محكوم عليه بالموت عند قتله. ولان الربانيين أعلنوا أنه من أعمال التقوى والبر بناء على قول الحكيم ”اعطوا مسكراً لهالك وخمراً لمرى النفس. يشرب وينسي فقره ولا يذكر تعبه بعد (أم 31: 6، 7)،” ويظهر إن السيد المسيح له المجد ذاقه إكراماً لمن أسدى له هذا المعروف بإعطائه إياه ولكنه أبى أن يشربه لأنه فضل أن يكون له الحس التام بالآمه، ولم يشأ أن يُعكر صفاء عقله، ليكابد جميع آلام الصلب وهو فى حالة الصحو. لأنه الكأس الذى أعطاه الآب ليشربه (يو18: 11)، أما الشراب فكان من الأعشاب المرة كالافسنتين وأمثاله، ممزوج بنقيع بزر الخشخاش وخل حامض يختلف عن الخل قليلاً، وغايتهم من مزج الخمر به ليكون شديد التأثير، حتى إنه بمجرد ما يأخذ منه المصلوب لا يدرى ولا يشعر أن كان ميتاً أو حياً.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Pain of the Cross         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            آلآم الصليب         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “There They Crucified Him” (Lk 23:33). Roman crucifixion is the most agonizing and severest form of torture endured by a transgressor. In addition to the crucifixion and scourging, our Lord endured consistent mockery and derision throughout this horrible ordeal. There was great pain arising from the duration the crucified remained alive (three days or longer), being drenched in sweat, hungry, and feverish (from inflamed wounds). The crucified was placed in such a position that the slightest movement caused extreme sharp pain to penetrate throughout his whole body from the strain of the nails in his hands and feet. Likewise, the blood accumulating in the lungs and pressing on the heart caused indescribable and excruciating pain accompanied by great thirst. Crucifixion was humiliating to the extent that Romans would never execute such a ruling against a Roman; it was reserved for slaves, thieves, the insubordinate, and criminals.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            “حينئذ صلبوا يسوع” (لو 23: 33)، كان الصلب عند الرومانيين من أشد العذابات المبرحة وأوفر القصاصات الآماً للمذنبين لما فيه من التشهير والعار الذى يلحق بالشخص المصلوب، والالآم الشديدة التى تنتج عن طول المدة، فقد يبقى المصلوب معلقاً حياً ثلاثة أيام أو أكثر، فيعتريه جوع وأرق وحمى من إلتهاب الجراح، لأن المصلوب كان يوضع على هيئة بحيث أن أدنى حركة يأتيها تسبب له ألماً شديداً جداً فى كل أجزاء الجسم من شدة المسامير فى اليدين والرجلين. و كذلك الدم الذى يتجمع فى الرئتين ويضغط على القلب كان يسبب ألماً شديداً فوق التصور لا يٌطاق ولا يُحتمل مصحوباً بعطش شديد. وكان الصلب مهيناً حتى أن الرومان لم يقاصوا به البتة رعاياهم من الرومانيين، بل كانوا يعاقبون به فقط الأرقاء واللصوص والعصاة والمجرمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Crucifixion as a Form of Punishment         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            عقوبة الصلب         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Those condemned to crucifixion were first scourged, and then, each carried his cross to the crucifixion site, a specific location outside the city where many people gathered to deride and mock them as an example of deterrence for others. When they reached the crucifixion site, they would strip them and offer them an intoxicant (as described earlier). For Jews, crucifixion was not a form of punishment. It was forbidden for a Jew to crucify a Jew. As for the comment in the Torah about hanging on the wood [“He who is hanged is accursed of God” (Deut 21:23)], it is what is generally known today as hanging. Crucifixion originated in Persia, where it was used as a punishment for Egyptians, Greeks, and Romans. Alexander the Great, in conquering the city of Tyre, crucified 2,000 of its residents. Romans did not decree upon Romans death by crucifixion, but reserved it for slaves, persons committing the vilest crimes, and the inhabitants of countries they conquered (whom they classified as slaves). The Roman ruler, Crispus, decorated the path from the city of Kibeu to the city of Rome with the crosses of those who offended the Roman Empire. Caesar Augustus crucified 6,000 slaves on the Island of Sicily because they disobeyed him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كان المحكوم عليهم بالصلب يجلدون أولا ثم يحملون الصليب الى محل الصلب الذى كان يعين فى مكان مشهور خارج المدينة حيث يجتمع كثيرون من الناس، وذلك لأجل إحتقارهم والإستهزاء بهم ليصبحوا عبرة لغيرهم. وكان متى وصلوا الى محل الصلب يعروهم ثم كانوا يقدمون لهم شرابا مخدرا كما مر. والصلب لم يكن من أنواع العقوبات عند اليهود، وكان من المحال أن يَصلِب يهودي يهوديا، أما ما ورد فى التوراة عن التعليق على خشبة فالمقصود به ما يُعرف عند الجميع بالشنق[35] (تث 21: 23). أصل الصلب كان فى بلاد الفرس وعاقب به كل من المصريين واليونانيين والرومانيين. فالإسكندر الكبير عند افتتاحه لمدينة صور صلب من أهلها الفين. والرومانيون لم يوقعوا علي رومانى حكم الموت بالصلب بل خصوا به العبيد ومن يرتكب أشر الآثام وأهل الولايات التى استولوا عليها لانهم يحسبونهم كالعبيد. وكراسبوس القائد الرومانى سيج الطريق من مدينة كبيو إلى مدينة روميه بصلبان العبيد الذين عصوا الدولة الرمانية. وصلب اغسطس قيصر ستة آلاف عبد فى جزيرة صقلية أي سيسيليا لانهم عصوه.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Method of Crucifixion         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كيفية الصلب         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The crucifix was composed of two perpendicular pieces of wood, with a rod placed at the foot, to bear part of his weight and hold him upright, lest the spot where the nails were inserted tear the skin of the crucified and they fall off the cross. One method was to erect the cross, and lift up the crucified and nail him while in the air. Most often, after removing the crucified’s clothes, they would place the cross horizontally on the ground, and stretch him out on it and nail his hands and feet to the wood of the cross. Often times, they would only nail the hands, and tie the legs to the cross with ropes. They would position the cross vertically, and elevate the person being crucified, crucifying him while suspended above ground. As for our Lord of glory’s crucifixion, it was by nailing the hands and feet (as confirmed in the Gospel according to St. Luke (Lk 24:39–40)). Then they would lift up the cross with the crucified, and erect it vertically into the hole prepared for this sole purpose. Sometimes, they would thrust the cross into the hole with great speed and violently, that it would magnify the crucified’s pain and suffering. The crucified was about one handbreadth above the ground. When the soldiers nailed our Savior to the cross, He prayed saying, “Father, forgive them, for they do not know what they do” (Lk 23:34).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان الصليب يُركب من قطعتين متعارضتين من الخشب فى إحداهما عمود يدخل بين رجلى المصلوب ليحمل بعض ثقله لئلا يتمزق محل مدخل المسامير فيسقط المصلوب. وكانوا ينصبون الصليب رأسياً ويرفعون الشخص المراد صلبه ويسمرونه وهو مرتفع عن الأرض. وغالباً ما كانوا يضعون الصليب أفقياً على الأرض ويمدون المراد صلبه عليه بعدما يعرونه من ثيابه، ثم يسمرون يديه ورجليه بالمسامير على خشبة الصليب. ثم يرفعون الصليب بالمصلوب بعيداً عن الأرض بمقدار زراع واحد، ثم ينصبونه رأسياً فى حفرة يعدونها لذلك، وأحياناً كانوا ينزلون بالصليب فى الحفرة بسرعة وعنف شديدين ليضاعفوا عذاب المصلوب. أما سيدنا له المجد فصُلب بتسمير يديه ورجليه بدليل ماجاء فى بشارة معلمنا لوقا (لو24: 39، 40)، فلما سمر العسكر مخلصنا له المجد على الصليب صلى قائلأ "يا أبتاه إغفر لهم لأنهم لا يعلمون ماذا يفعلون"(لو23: 34).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Title of the Crucified         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            عنوان المصلوب         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            It was custom for the condemned to bear the inscription of his accusation, so when he reached the crucifixion site, it was placed above his head. For Pilate, the accusation against the Lord Christ was: “THIS IS JESUS THE KING OF THE JEWS” (Mt 27:37). Thus, the insignia was written in the three popular languages in Syria at that time: Hebrew, Greek, and Latin. By inscribing this sign, Pilate intended to ridicule and mock the Jews by crucifying their king. The chief priests objected to the inscription, but he did not care for, or pay attention to their protests and said, “What I have written, I have written” (Jn 19:22). Therefore, the title that the wise men gave Christ at His birth glorifying Him, Pilate also gave to Him at His death.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكانت العادة أن يحمل المحكوم عليه بالصلب إعلان العلة التى صُلب لأجلها حتى إذا وصلوا محل الصلب تُوضَع فوق رأسه. فكانت علة السيد المسيح عند بيلاطس (هذا هو يسوع ملك اليهود) (مت 27: 37)، وكَتب هذا العنوان بثلاث لغات كانت شائعة فى سوريا وقتئذ، وهى العبرانية واليونانية واللاتينية. وقصد بيلاطس بذلك العنوان تعيير اليهود بصلب ملكهم والتشهير بهم. فاعترض الرؤساء علي ما كُتب لكن بيلاطس لم يُبال بهم ولم يذعن لقولهم بل قال "ما كتبت قد كتبت" (يو 19: 22)، فما لقَّب المجوس به السيد المسيح عند ميلاده تمجيداً له، لقَّبه به أيضاً بيلاطس عند موته.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Darkness over the Whole Earth         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الظلمة على الأرض         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Jesus was hung on the cross before noon, and from the sixth hour to the ninth hour, there was darkness over the whole earth (Mt 27:34; Mk 15:33; Lk 23:44). This darkness was a miracle because the sun could not eclipse except when the moon is a crescent; it was the 15th of the month and a full moon. This was a total eclipse, not a partial! Nature dressed in mourning over what humanity did to the Creator of Existence, the Coordinator of Creation, the Light of the World, and the Sun of Righteousness.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            علق مخلصنا له المجد على الصليب قبل الظهر. "ولما كانت الساعة السادسة، كانت ظلمة على الأرض كلها الى الساعة التاسعة" (مت27: 34)، (مر15: 33)، (لو23: 44)، فكانت هذه الظلمة معجزة لأنه لا يمكن أن يحصل كسوف للشمس إلا والقمر هلال. وكان يومئذ اليوم الخامس عشر من الشهر. وكان القمر بدراً وكان هذا الكسوف كلياً وليس جزئياً، فقد لبست الطبيعة أثواب الحداد إظهاراً لما فعله البشر بخالق الكون، مدبر الخليقة، نور العالم، وشمس البر.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            He Was Wounded for Our Transgressions         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            مجروح لأجل معاصينا (أش 53: 5)         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Listen, O my beloved, while I mention the shocking pains which our Savior suffered from the Jews. They arrested Him in an inhuman way, treated Him with barbaric cruelty, and bound Him and took Him like a criminal to the council of Caiaphas and Annas, while slapping, beating, and spitting on His honorable face. They branded Him with their unjust judgment and handed Him to Pilate. Pilate, then, dressed Him in white (in the appearance of a lunatic) and sent Him to Herod, who after examining Him and finding no reason deserving of death, sent Him back to Pilate, who was compelled to condemn Him to death after scourging. The Jews bribed the scourgers to kill Him under the whips, so they whipped Him with all their brutality, so much so, that they tore apart His pure body. In staying on course with their viciousness, they placed on His holy head, instead of a diadem, a crown of thorns sharper than nails, which penetrated His forehead; and instead of a royal robe, they placed on His shoulders a red robe; and instead of the scepter of rule, they handed Him a reed.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إسمعوا أيها الأحباء ذكر ما قاساه مخلصنا له المجد من الآلآمات المبرحة من اليهود، فإنهم قبضوا عليه بشكل لا يتفق مع الإنسانية، وعاملوه بقسوة بربرية، فأخذوه موثقاً الى مجلس قيافا وحنان بين لَطْم وضَرْب وبَصْق على الوجه الكريم، وإستهزاء به كمجرم وهو البار القدوس. هناك أصدروا عليه حكمهم الظالم، وسلموه الى بيلاطس، وبيلاطس ألبسه لباساً أبيض كمجنون وأرسله الى هيرودس، ولما فحصه هيرودس ولم يجد فيه علة يستوجب عليها الموت، أعاده ثانية الى بيلاطس فحكم عليه بالموت بعد الجلد. ورشا اليهود الجلادين لكى يميتوه تحت السياط، فجلدوه بكل قسوة حتى مزقوا جسده الطاهر تمزيقاً، وأتموا عملهم البربرى بوضعهم على هامته المقدسة إكليلاً من الشوك أحد من المسامير عوضاً عن التاج فخدش جبينه الطلق، وبدلاً من البرفير وضعوا على كتفه ثوباً أحمر، وعوضاً عن صولجان الملك أمسكوه قصبة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            His body grew feverish due to the wound from carrying the heavy massive cross, trudging through the crowded streets of Jerusalem. On His journey were the mocking of the crowds, the derision of rivals, the attacks of the vulgar, the insults of bandits, and the vengeance of the enemies. He agonized under it at the throes of death, and sometimes fell upon the stones, and rose again—pale faced, drained of strength, and drenched in blood until He reached the Golgotha altar. There, He was laid on the cross to be pierced by the nails penetrating His body to the cross. Thus, Isaiah’s prophecy was fulfilled: “He has no form or comeliness; and when we see Him, there is no beauty that we should desire Him. He is despised and rejected by men, a Man of sorrows and acquainted with grief. And we hid, as it were, our faces from Him; He was despised, and we did not esteem Him. Surely He has borne our griefs and carried our sorrows; yet we esteemed Him stricken, smitten by God, and afflicted. But He was wounded for our transgressions, He was bruised for our iniquities” (Is 53:2-5). Nature was affected by this scene: the sun untimely hid its rays—ashamed to see its Creator hanging naked on the Cross; creation stared at Him as did shameless Ham (Gen 9:22–23); the earth shook in shock and the rocks split in horror over the Lord of glory, as if saying, “Let me swallow the wicked ones who do not know their Creator, by whom they live, move, and have their being” (Acts 17:28), as it swallowed Korah, Dathan, and Abiram (Num 16:31–32).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد أتخن جسده بالجراح من جراء حمل الصليب الضخم الثقيل سائراً به فى شوارع أورشليم، بين سخرية الجمع، وإهانة الخصوم، وتهكم السفلة، وشتائم الاجلاف، وتشفى الاعداء، يئن تحته أنين المحتضر، فيقع تارة علي الحجارة وينهض أخرى، خائر القوى، شاحب الوجه، دامى الاعضاء، حتى بلغ مذبح الجلجلة، وهناك جرى مقتله بحراب المسامير على الصليب، [فكملت نبوة أشعياء قائلاً "لا صورة له ولا جمال فننظر اليه ولا منظر فنشتهيه، محتقر ومخذول من الناس، رجل أوجاع ومختبر الحزن، وكمسَّتر عنه وجوهنا، محتقر فلم نعتد به، لكن أحزاننا حملها، وأوجاعنا تحملها، ونحن حسبناه مصاباً مضروباً من الناس ومذلولاً. وهو مجروح لأجل معاصينا، مسحوق لأجل أثامنا(أش53: 2-5)] فتأثرت الطبيعة من هول هذا المنظر، الشمس حجبت نورها بغير أوان خجلاً من أن ترى مبدعها معلقاً على الصليب عارياً والخليقة تتفرس فيه مثل حام الوقح (تك 9: 22-23). والأرض تزلزلت إضطراباً والصخور تشققت إلتياعاً على رب المجد،. ولسان حالها يقول دعنى أبتلع الأشرار الذين لم يعرفوا خالقهم الذى به يحيون ويتحركون ويوجدون (أع 17: 28)، كما إبتلعت قورح وداثان وأبيرام (عدد16: 31، 32).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            This all happened to our Savior for our sake. Are we fulfilling our duty toward our Creator? The Jews’ crucifixion is not less harsh than ours: some of us add to the weight of His crucifixion, others ridicule Him more than Herod, while others may sell Him with a more piercing betrayal than Judas. Some may whip Him as intensely as the soldiers, some may act like the sharp thorns on His crown placed upon His forehead, still others increase the number of His nails, while others pierce Him, but not with a spear as did His murderers, but with the spears of our sins.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            هذا ماحل بالمخلص له المجد لأجلنا، فهل نحن قائمون بما يجب علينا نحو خالقنا؟ فما صَلْب اليهود له بأكثر قسوة منا، فمنا من أزاد صليبه ثقلاً، ومنا من هزأ به أكثر من هيرودس، ومنا من باعه بأشد خيانة من يهوذا، ومنا من جلده بقساوة افظع من قساوة العسكر والجند، ومنا من غرز فى هامته أشواكاً أحَد من أكليل صالبيه، ومنا من زاد مسامير صلبه عدداً، ومنا من طعنه لا بحربة كقاتليه بل بحراب الخطايا والذنوب         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The One who stirred the thief on His right hand[37] to repentance can alone enlighten our hearts to see the repugnance of sin, and return to Him—our beloved Creator, with a repentant heart.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "اللهم يامن ألهم اللص اليمين التوبة، وهداه الى سبل الرشاد، أنت وحدك القادر أن تنير عيون قلوبنا فنرى شناعة الخطية ونرجع الى خالقنا نادمين على ما إرتكبناه من المعاصي والشرور".         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [37] Tradition ascribes the title, “the thief on the right hand” to the penitent, Demas, though there is no mention of his exact position.         </Language>      </Comment>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            His Cry on the Cross         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الصراخ على الصليب         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            At the ninth hour, Jesus cried out with a loud voice, “Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani,” a Hebrew phrase bearing the meaning, “My God, My God, why have You forsaken Me?” (Mt 27:46; Ps 22:1; cf. Heb 5:7). (It appeared in the Gospel according to St. Mark as, “Eloi, Eloi” (Mk 15:34), a similar expression, except that our teacher, St. Mark, transcribed it in the Syrian language, as the Lord Christ pronounced it). This bitter depression and great anguish pushed our Savior to this horrific outcry: “My God, My God, why have You forsaken Me?” because He felt the extent of the pain that He bore for the sake of our sins while on the Cross. He stood instead of us before Divine Justice to pay our dues. He tasted death for every person (Heb 2:9), and became sin for us, He, who knows no sin, that we might become the righteousness of God in Him (Cf. 2 Cor 5:21). This fulfills what Isaiah said: “Yet it pleased the Lord to bruise Him; He has put Him to grief. When You make His soul an offering for sin… But He was wounded for our transgressions, He was bruised for our iniquities; the chastisement for our peace was upon Him, and by His stripes we are healed” (Is 53:10,5), St. Peter also said: “[Christ] suffered once for sins, the just for the unjust, that He might bring us to God” (1 Pet 3:18).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وفى وقت الساعة التاسعة صرخ يسوع بصوت عظيم قائلاً ”إيلى إيلى لما شبقتني” لفظة عبرانية مكررة معناها "إلهى إلهى لماذا تركتنى" (مت 27: 46)، (مز22: 1)، (عب5: 7) وجاء فى انجيل معلمنا مرقس ”ألوى ألوى” (مر15: 34) وهذا اللفظ أيضاً مثل "إيلى إيلى" إلا أن معلمنا مرقس نقلها بلفظه السريانى كما نطق به السيد المسيح له المجد، إن هذه الكآبة المرة والضيقة الشديدة التى إضطرت مخلصنا له المجد إلى هذا الصراخ المخيف ”إلهى إلهى لماذا تركتني” هو إنه شعر بشدة الآلآم التى تحملها لأجل خطايانا وهو على الصليب وشناعة الخطية التى إرتكبها الانسان، وقيامه نيابة عنا أمام العدل الالهى ليفيه حقه إذ ذاق الموت عن كل إنسان (عب 2: 9)، "لأنه جعل الذى لم يعرف خطية، خطية لأجلنا لنصير نحن بر الله فيه" (2كو5: 21)، وهذا إتمام لقول أشعياء "أما الرب فسُر بأن يسحقه بالحزن. إن جعل نفسه ذبيحة أثم" (أش 53: 10)، "وهو مجروح لأجل معاصينا مسحوق لأجل آثامنا تأديب سلامنا عليه وبحبره شفينا" (أش 53: 5)، وكما قال بطرس أيضاً "فإن المسيح أيضاً تألم مرة واحدة من أجل الخطايا، البار من أجل الاثمة، لكي يقربنا إلى الله" (1بط 3: 18).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            After this, Jesus, knowing that all things were now accomplished, that the Scripture might be fulfilled, said, "I thirst!" Now a vessel full of sour wine was sitting there; and they filled a sponge with sour wine, put it on hyssop, and put it to His mouth. So when Jesus had received the sour wine, He said, "It is finished!" And bowing His head, He gave up His spirit (Jn 19:28-30). After this, Jesus cried out again with a loud voice and gave up the spirit (Mt 27:50; Mk 15:37; Lk 23:46); perhaps, this cry was the shout of joy because He had fulfilled our redemption.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "بَعْدَ هَذَا رَأَى يَسُوعُ أَنَّ كُلَّ شَيْءٍ قَدْ كَمَلَ فَلِكَيْ يَتِمَّ الْكِتَابُ قَالَ: «أَنَا عَطْشَانُ» وَكَانَ إِنَاءٌ مَوْضُوعاً مَمْلُوّاً خَلاًّ فَمَلَأُوا إِسْفِنْجَةً مِنَ الْخَلِّ وَوَضَعُوهَا عَلَى زُوفَا وَقَدَّمُوهَا إِلَى فَمِهِ، فَلَمَّا أَخَذَ يَسُوعُ الْخَلَّ قَالَ: «قَدْ أُكْمِلَ». وَنَكَّسَ رَأْسَهُ وَأَسْلَمَ الرُّوحَ" (يو19: 28-30). وبعد ذلك صرخ يسوع أيضاً بصوت عظيم وأسلم الروح" (مت27: 50)، (مر15: 37)، (لو23: 46)، ولعل هذا الصراخ كان هتاف الفرح لأنه أكمل عمل الفداء.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Crying with a loud voice at His death proves that He did not die out of weakness or fatigue, but was in full strength.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أما صراخه بصوت عظيم على الصليب فهذا دليل على أنه لم يمت بضعف وعياء بل إنه كان فى تمام قوته.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            His Seven Words and His Death         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كلماته السبع وموته         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He uttered seven words while on the cross—three before the darkness and four after:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد نطق مخلصنا له المجد بسبع كلمات وهو على الصليب، ثلاثة قبل الظلمة، وأربعة بعدها وهم:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            1)      Forgiving His crucifiers: “Father, forgive them, for they do not know what they do” (Lk 23:34).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            1-      "يا أبتاه إغفر لهم لأنهم لا يعلمون ماذا يفعلون" (لو23: 34) إشارة الى غفرانه لصالبيه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            2)      Promising the thief [on His right] salvation: “Assuredly, I say to you, today you will be with Me in Paradise” (Lk 23:43).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            2-      "الحق أقول لك إنك اليوم تكون معى فى الفردوس" (لو23: 43) إشارة الى وعده للص بالخلاص.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            3)      Entrusting His mother to the beloved disciple, John: “Woman, behold your son… Behold your mother!” (Jn 19:26–27).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            3-      "يا إمرأة هوذا إبنك" ثم "هوذا أمك" (يو19: 26، 27) إشارة الى تسليم أمه ليوحنا تلميذه ليرعاها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            4)      Crying to God: “My God, My God, why have You forsaken Me?” (Mt 27:46).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            4-      صراخه قائلاً "إيلى إيلى لما شبقتنى أى إلهى إلهى لماذا تركتنى" (مت27: 46).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            5)      “I thirst” (Jn 19:28).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            5-      "أنا عطشان" (يو19: 28).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            6)      “It is finished” (Jn 19:30).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            6-      "قد أكمل" (يو19: 30).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            7)      Giving up His pure spirit to the Father: “Father, into Your hands I commit My spirit” (Lk 23:46).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            7-      أودع روحه النقية للأب "يا أبتاه فى يديك أستودع روحى" (لو23: 46).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            His Divinity Parted Not from His Humanity         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اللآهوت لم يفارق الناسوت         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            We know that at His Incarnation, the Lord Christ was perfect God incarnate: as His Divinity united with His humanity without mixing, mingling, or changing. Therefore, according to His Humanity, He was susceptible to all of life’s difficulties: hunger and thirst (Jn 4:7), weariness (Jn 4:6), crying (Heb 5:7), tears (Jn 11:35), sorrow (Mk 14:34), and all the other effects of the world—except sin (Heb 4:15). Yet, according to His Divinity, He vastly surpassed this: He satiated the hungry (Jn 6:10), quenched the thirsty (Jn 7:37; Mt 26:27; Jn 4:15; Rev 21:6), relieved the exhausted (Mt 11:28), consoled the sorrowful (Jn 11:40–44; 2 Cor 1:3–4), and saved the weak from temptation (Mt 14:28–31; 1 Cor 10:13).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بما إننا قد عرفنا أن السيد المسيح له المجد عند تجسده كان إلهاً كاملا متأنساً، وقد إتحد لاهوته بناسوته بدون إختلاط ولا إمتزاج ولاتغيير، فكان بناسوته قابلاً لكل ما يطرأ عليه من صعوبات الحياة، كالجوع والعطش (يو4: 7) والتعب (يو4: 6) والصراخ (عب5: 7) والبكاء (يو11: 35) والحزن (مر14: 34) وسائر التجارب العالمية ماعدا الخطية (عب4: 15)، وأما بلاهوته فمتعال عن ذلك علواً كبيراً فيهب الشبع للجوعان (يو6: 10) ويروى العطشان (مت26: 27)، (يو4: 15)، (يو7: 37)، (رؤ21: 6)، ويريح من التعب (مت11: 28) ويعزى الحزين (يو11: 40)، (2كو1: 3-4) ويخلص من التجارب (مت14: 28-31)، (1كو10: 13).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Holy Spirit testified to this through the writings of the holy apostles. St. Peter said, “Who Himself bore our sins in His own body on the tree” (1 Pet 2:24). St. Paul said, “God did by sending His own Son in the likeness of sinful flesh, on account of sin: He condemned sin in the flesh” (Rom 8:3). Again, St. Peter declares, “Put to death in the flesh but made alive by the Spirit” (1 Pet 3:18), because it was written of Him: “Who alone has immortality, dwelling in unapproachable light” (1 Tim 6:16).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد شهد الروح القدس بذلك علي أفواه الرسل القديسين، فيقول بطرس الرسول "الذى حمل هو خطايانا فى جسده على الخشبة" (1بط 2: 24)، وقال الرسول "إذ أرسل الله ابنه فى شبه جسد الخطية ولاجل الخطية دان الخطية في الجسد" (رو8: 3)، وبصريح العبارة يبرهن بطرس عن موته بالجسد قائلاً "مماتاً فى الجسد ولكن محيياً في الروح (1بط3: 18)، لأنه مكتوب عنه "الذى وحده له عدم الموت ساكناً فى نور لايدنى منه" (1تي6: 16).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            At His death, He gave up His pure spirit, saying to His Father, “Father, into Your hands I commit My spirit.” Thus, He died according to His Humanity, while His Divinity did not part from His body for a single moment nor a twinkle of an eye, not before crucifixion, during, nor after crucifixion. In declaring this, we say that it is impossible for the Lord Christ to be two persons—one contradicting the other: one born and the other not. One cannot amaze with wonders, while the other receives mockery; neither can one be crucified while the other not crucified. The one born, the wonderworker, and the crucified are all one. This is the apostolic faith, the concurrence of the evangelists, and the fathers’ aphorisms.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فعند موته أسلم روحه الطاهرة قائلا لأبيه: "يا أبتاه في يديك أستودع روحى" وهكذا مات بناسوته ومع ذلك لاهوته لم يفارق ناسوته أى جسده لحظة واحدة ولا طرفة عين لا قبل الصلب ولا حين الصلب ولا بعد الصلب. وإذ تقرر ذلك نقول أنه لايمكن أن يكون فى المسيح شخصان، أحدهما يضاد الآخر، واحد يولد والآخر لا يولد، واحد يبهر بالعجائب والآخر تقع عليه الاهانات، واحد يُصلب والآخر لا يُصلب. بل أن المولود، والصانع العجائب، والمصلوب، هو واحد. هذا هو الايمان الرسولي وإتفاق أصوات البشيرين وأقوال الآباء.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            That He is living and not dead is evinced from a profound sign when the soldier pierced Jesus’s side, and out flowed water and blood from His side. Church history, taken from early tradition, mentions that when Joseph and Nicodemus came to embalm the Master, Joseph held His hand and said, “Would this awesome hand that created all die, and could I now embalm it!” Christ opened His eyes and smiled, at which Joseph cried out, “Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal.” Hence, the Church arranged this chant among her hymns for Passion Week.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ومما يبرهن على عدم موته إنه لما طعنه أحد الجنود بالحربة خرج من جنبه ماء علامه على انه حى ولن يموت. وجاء فى تاريخ الكنيسة الذى أُخِذَ عن التقليد القديم أن يوسف ونقوديموس لما شرعا فى تحنيط السيد المسيح أمسك يوسف يده وقال هذه اليد العظيمة التى خلقت المخلوقات تموت وأنا أحنطها؟ ففتح السيد المسيح عينيه وتبسم فى وجهه، فصرخ عند ذلك يوسف قائلا "قدوس الله، قدوس القوى، قدوس الحي الذى لا يموت". ولذلك قد رتبت الكنيسة هذه التسبحة بين ترنيماتها أيضاً فى إسبوع الالام.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Therefore, it is a fact that our Lord’s acceptance of the passion and death was not with regards to His Divinity. His Divinity is impassible; therefore, the impact did not reach the Divinity, being united with His Humanity (a full personal natural hypostatic union): indivisible, inseparable, and irreproducible.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إذن فليكن معلوماً أن قبول ربنا الآلام والموت لم يكن من حيثية لاهوته الأقدس، إذ أن اللاهوت منزه عن كافة الانفعالات، لذلك لم تتطرق إليه التأثيرات بما أنه متحد بالناسوت إتحاداً ذاتياً طبيعياً أقنومياً لا يقبل الانفصال ولا الافتراق ولا يشوبه تثنية.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            They Have All Turned Aside         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الجميع زاغوا (رو3: 12)         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Before beings were created, and even before the creation of time, God knew by His foreknowledge that man would sin and do evil. Since “the wages of sin is death” (Rom 6:23), God, out of His abundant mercy did not wish the death of man whom He was about to create, so He planned his salvation before Adam appeared on the face of the earth. Salvation could not occur except through the mediation of an unblemished, righteous, Holy One, on whose mouth there is no deceit, who is outside the human race, and without sin. An angel, archangel, prophet, or saint could not fulfill this. The angelic nature differs from the human nature, and the prophets and saints were born with the original sin, which affects the whole human race—no one being is exempted. According to St. Paul, “Therefore, just as through one man sin entered the world, and death through sin, and thus death spread to all men, because all sinned” (Rom 5:12). Also, ‘“There is none righteous, no, not one; there is none who understands; there is none who seeks after God. They have all turned aside; they have together become unprofitable; there is none who does good, no, not one’” (Rom 3:10–12).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قبل أن تُخلق الكائنات، وقبل أن تتعين الازمان، عَلِمَ الله بسابق عِلمه أن الانسان سيخطئ ويعمل الشر على الارض، وبما أن "أجرة الخطية هى موت" (رو6: 23)، وكان الله من فرط رحمته لا يشاء أن يهلك الانسان الذى هو مزمع أن يخلقه. فدبر الله أمر خلاصه قبل أن يظهر فى عالم الوجود. ولما كان ذلك الخلاص لا يتم الا بواسطة بار قدوس لا عيب فيه، ولا يوجد في فمه غش، خارج عن الجنس البشرى، منزه عن الخطية، وبما أن هذا الامر لا يقدر أن يقوم به ملاك أو رئيس ملائكة أو نبي أو قديس، لان طبيعة الملائكة غير طبيعة البشر. وبما أن الانبياء و القديسون مولدون بالخطية الجدية التى عمت جميع النوع الانساني، ولم يستثن منها أحد كقول بولس الرسول "من أجل ذلك كأنما بانسان واحد دخلت الخطية إلى العالم وبالخطية الموت وهكذا إجتاز الموت إلى جميع الناس إذ أخطأ الجميع" (رو5: 12)، كما هو مكتوب أنه "ليس بار ولا واحد، ليس من يفهم، ليس من يطلب الله، الجميع زاغوا وفسدوا معاً، ليس من يعمل صلاحاً ليس ولا واحد" (رو3: 10-12).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Salvation Through the Son         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الخلاص بالإبن         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            A transgressor cannot save a fellow transgressor, nor can a needy person satisfy the wants of a fellow destitute. The Almighty God saw that this redemption could not be fulfilled except through the second hypostasis, through whom the creation was formed, as our teacher St. John the Evangelist testified: “All things were made through Him, and without Him nothing was made that was made” (Jn 1:3). Therefore, it was the responsibility of the One who created all things to be the Savior, and none other. “God sent forth His Son, born of a woman, born under the law, to redeem those who were under the law, that we might receive the adoption as sons” (Gal 4:4–5). Thus, He took the form of a servant, which was defiled by sin, to renew it once more and restore it to its original glory. All three hypostases participated in humanity’s salvation: the Father’s justice was fulfilled; the Son paid the debt for mankind; and the Holy Spirit remitted the sins.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بما إنه لا يقدر المذنب أن يخلص مذنباً مثله، كما وأن المحتاج لا يسد عوز من يشبهه فى الاحتياج، رأى الله -له المجد- أن لايتم هذا الفداء إلا بالاقنوم الثانى الذى بواسطته قد صورت الخليقة كما شهد بذلك معلمنا يوحنا الانجيلى "كل شئ به كان وبغيره لم يكن شئ مما كان"(يو1: 3)، فوجب بمن أوجد الموجودات أن يكون به الخلاص دون سواه فأرسل الله إبنه، مولوداً من إمرأة، مولوداً تحت الناموس ليفتدي الذين تحت الناموس لننال التبنى (غل4: 4-5)، فلبس صورة الانسان التى كانت قد أفسدتها الخطية ليجددها مرة ثانية ويعيد لها مجدها الاول، وكان ذلك باجماع الثلاثة الاقانيم على خلاص الانسان.  فالآب إستوفى عدله، الابن قد قدم عنه الوفاء، والروح القدس غفر الخطايا.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Justice and Mercy         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            العدل والرحمة         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            This is the reason God took the form of a bondservant—to judge sin in the flesh. God was able to save man by a word, as He created him by a word, but because He is just, He saw that there was no forgiveness except by the shedding of blood. Therefore, there was a necessity for this amazing incarnation, one beyond nature, to fulfill Divine Justice: “The soul who sins shall die” (Ezra 18:20). God’s mercy had to fulfill the work of redemption for sinful man. In this way, God is simultaneously just and merciful. Justice received its due by the death of the Son on the wood of the cross, and mercy interceded in fulfilling salvation. Thus, God’s justice and mercy were at equilibrium as each one was affirmed in accordance.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فهذا السبب الذى جعل الله أن يتخذ صورة عبد وجسد انسان خاطئ ليدين الخطية في الجسد وكان الله قادراً أن يخلص الانسان بكلمة كما خلق العالم بكلمة ولكن بما انه عادل رأى أن لا تحصل مغفرة إلا بسفك دم، فلذا لزم هذا التجسد العجيب الذى ما هو فوق الطبيعة وذلك تنفيذاً للعدل الالهى "أن النفس التى تخطئ هى تموت" (عز18: 20 )، وعليه، فقد إقتضت رحمة الله أن تقوم بعمل التكفير عن الانسان المذنب. وبذلك يكون الله عادلاً ورحيماً فى آن واحد. فالعدل قد إستوفى حقه بموت الابن على خشبة الصليب. والرحمة قد توسطت في صنع الخلاص فصار عدل الله ورحمته متساويين إذ كل منهما قد استوفى حقه حتى لا يكون بينهما تفاوت.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            The following section was found in an ancient Pascha book         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            النبذة التالية وجدت بالبصخة القديمة         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As for the bodily death of the Lord Christ, its divine sacred superior purposes are great and tremendously auspicious to us, His servants who believe in Him and have hope in His immense favor and His generous gifts. They are:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أما موت السيد المسيح بالجسد فكان لغايات مقدسة سامية ومفيدة وعظيمة لنا نحن عبيد المؤمنين بإسمه الراجين عفوه المنشود وفضله العظيم وهى:         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Reconciling Us with God         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            مصالحاتنا مع الله         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            We angered God, His Father, by our evil deeds and our insistence on committing sins and transgressions; hence, a firm punishment and a painful torture precedent, and a partition—a dividing barrier existed between Him and us. The death of the Lord of glory wiped out the handwriting against us, broke down the middle wall separating us from God, removed the enmity, brought us closer to Him, and reconciled us via His cross. St. Paul says, “For it pleased the Father that in Him all the fullness should dwell, and by Him to reconcile all things to Himself, by Him, whether things on earth or things in heaven, having made peace through the blood of His cross” (Col 1:19–20). The Apostle Paul tells the Ephesians, “For He Himself is our peace, who has made both one, and has broken down the middle wall of separation, having abolished in His flesh the enmity, that is, the law of commandments contained in ordinances, so as to create in Himself one new man from the two, thus making peace, and that He might reconcile them both to God in one body through the cross, thereby putting to death the enmity. And He came and preached peace to you who were afar off and to those who were near” (Eph 2:14–17). The apostle also writes to the Romans, “For if when we were enemies we were reconciled to God through the death of His Son, much more, having been reconciled, we shall be saved by His life” (Rom 5:10).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أولاً- مع الله أبيه الذى أغضبناه بسوء أفعالنا وإنصبابنا على إرتكاب المعاصى والآثام، فأعد لنا عقاب صارم وعذاب أليم، وصار بيننا وبينه فاصل وحاجز منيع. فبموت السيد له المجد محا الصك الذى كان مكتوباً علينا، ونقض الحاجز المتوسط، بيننا وبين الله، وأزال العداوة وقربنا منه -له المجد- وصالحنا بصليبه، كما يقول بولس الرسول "لأنه فيه سر أن يحل كل الملء وأن يصالح به الكل لنفسه عاملاً الصلح بدم صليبه بواسطته سواء كان ما على الأرض أم مافى السموات" (كو1: 19-20)، وكما يقول أيضاً لأهل أفسس "لأنه هو سلامنا الذى جعل الإثنين واحداً ونقض حائط السياج المتوسط أى العداوة، مبطلاً بجسده ناموس الوصايا فى فرائض لكى يخلق الإثنين فى نفسه إنساناً واحداً جديداً صانعاً سلاماً ويصالح الإثنين في جسد واحد مع الله بالصليب قاتلاً العداوة به. فجاء وبشركم بسلام أنتم البعيدين والقريبين" (أف2: 14-17)، وكما يقول لأهل رومية "لأنه وإن متنا ونحن أعداء قد صولحنا مع الله بموت إبنه، فبالأولى كثيراً ونحن مصالحون نخلص بحياته" (رو5 : 10).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Removing the Curse         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            رفع اللعنة عنا         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He cleared us of the curse resulting from disobeying and breaking the laws: “Cursed is everyone who does not continue in all things which are written in the book of the law, to do them” (Gal 3:10). When no one kept the law, all were accursed; since death on the cross is a curse, He wanted to die the death of the cross to take away our curse, and send us the blessing, as the apostle says, “Christ has redeemed us from the curse of the law, having become a curse for us (for it is written, ‘Cursed is everyone who hangs on a tree’ (Cf. Deut. 21:22-23)), that the blessing of Abraham might come upon the Gentiles in Christ Jesus, that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith” (Gal 3:13–14).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثانيا- ليبررنا من لعنة الناموس التى حلت عينا من جراء مخافتنا وكسرنا للناموس، كما قيل "ملعون كل من لايثبت فى جميع ماهو مكتوب فى كتاب الناموس ليعمل به" (غل3: 10)، ولما لم يحفظ أحد الناموس صار الكل ملعونين، ولأن موت الصليب لعنة فأحب أن يموت موت الصليب ليرفع عنا اللعنة، ويرسل لنا البركة كما يقول الرسول "المسيح إفتدانا من لعنة الناموس إذ صار لعنة لأجلنا لأنه مكتوب ملعون كل من علق على خشبة لتصير بركة إبراهيم للأمم فى المسيح يسوع لننال بالإيمان موعد الروح" (غل3: 13-14).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            The Life of Righteousness         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لكى نحيا للبر         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            So that we might die to sin through His death and live through His life, as St. Peter the Apostle wrote, “Who Himself bore our sins in His own body on the tree, that we, having died to sins, might live for righteousness” (1 Pet 2:24).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثالثاً- لكى نموت نحن عن خطايانا بموته ونحيا بحياته، كما يقول بطرس الرسول "المسيح حمل هو نفسه خطايانا فى جسده على الخشبة لكى نموت عن الخطايا فنحيا للبر" (1بط2: 24).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Freedom from Slavery         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ونعتق من العبودية         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He died that He might taste the pain of death, abolish it, trample it, crush it, and destroy it, as the writer, the Apostle Paul, to the Hebrews states: “Inasmuch then as the children have partaken of flesh and blood, He Himself likewise shared in the same, that through death He might destroy him who had the power of death, that is, the devil, and release those who through fear of death were all their lifetime subject to bondage” (Heb 2:14–15).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            رابعاً- مات لكى يذوق ألم الموت ويبطله ويدوسه ويسحقه ويلاشيه، كما يقول كاتب رسالة العبرانيين "فإذ قد تشارك الأولاد فى اللحم والدم إشترك هو أيضاً كذلك فيهما لكي يبيد بالموت ذاك الذى له سلطان الموت أى إبليس ويعتق أولئك الذين خوفاً من الموت كانوا جميعاً كل حياتهم تحت العبودية" (عب2: 14-15).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            A Copy of a Letter         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            صورة خطاب         </Language>      </Title>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            + Cowper, Harris, The Apocryphal Gospels and Other Documents Relating to the History of Christ. London: Williams and Norgate, 1867, 221-222.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            From Reboleolino, the mayor of Judea in Jerusalem, to the court of Rome’s Caesar,[39] this letter was found in the safe of Prince Sharaweeny of Italy, in which he described the appearance and news of the Lord Christ. These are his words:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            مرسل من ربوليولينو مدير اليهودية بأورشليم إلى محفل قيصر رومية، وهذا الخطاب المذكور وجد فى خزانة الأمير شروينى من ايطاليا يصف فيه شكل وأخبار السيد المسيح وها هو بحروفه:         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [39] This sentence is found in the said book as: “Lentulus, president of the people of Jerusalem, to the Roman Senate and People: Greeting.”         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Your majesty, I have learned that you wish to know what I am about to tell you: There has appeared in our times, and still is, a man of great virtue named Christ Jesus, who is called by the Gentiles a prophet of truth, whom His disciples call the Son of God, raising the dead and healing diseases. He is a man of lofty stature, handsome, having a venerable countenance which the beholders can both love and fear. He has wavy hair, rather crisp, of a tinge, and glossy, flowing down from His shoulders, with a parting in the middle of the head after the manner of the Nazarenes.[40] His forehead is even and very serene, and His face without any wrinkle or spot, and beautiful with a slight blush. His nose and mouth are without fault; He has a beard abundant and reddish, of the color of His hair, not long but forked. His eyes are sparkling and bright. He is terrible in rebuke, calm and loving in admonition, cheerful but preserving gravity, has never been seen to laugh but often to weep. Thus, in stature of body, He is tall; and His hands and limbs are beautiful to look upon. In speech He is grave, reserved, and modest and He is fair among the children of men. He is claimed as the creator of heaven and earth and all that exists therein. Truly, every day we hear amazing news about this Jesus. His appearance overflows with reverence and awe. His eyes are like the rays of the sun, and no one could stare at Him from the brightness of His face. His arms and shoulders are exquisite. As for the meetings, in them he pleases many, yet rarely looks at them, and when He is present with them, He sits with the greatest propriety. So, in His appearance and form, He is the most beautiful person you could imagine, greatly resembling His mother who is the most beautiful young lady to be seen in this area. O king, if your majesty wishes to see Him, please inform me, whereby I will not delay in sending Him to you speedily. He has astonished the whole city of Jerusalem with His knowledge, knowing everything without having studied. Sometimes, He walks barefoot and bareheaded, and many, when they see Him laugh at Him, but in His presence or when speaking to Him, He confounds and astonishes. They say that there has never been heard of such a man in wisdom, and truthfully as the Jews have told me, we have not heard such wisdom from anyone like what this Jesus teaches. Many others come forward complaining to me of Him, saying that He opposes your laws, and you find me very indignant from those evil Jews. They say that He gives them many graces and much health, and in all cases I am ready to obey you; whatever your majesty commands me to do will be done with all speed.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أيها الملك إننى فهمت أنك ترغب معرفة ما أخبرك به الآن. لأنه فى وقتنا هذا وُجِدَ رجل عائش عيشة فاضلة يدعونه رسول الفضيلة، وتلاميذه يقولون انه إبن الله خالق السماء والأرض وكل ما يوجد فيهما، بالحقيقة أن كل يوم نسمع أمورا عجيبة عن يسوع هذا، فهو يقيم الموتى ويشفى السقماء بكلمة واحدة، وهو معتدل القامة وجميل المنظر جداً، ووجهه ذو هيبة هكذا حتى أن الذين ينظرون إليه يشعرون باجتذابهم اليه ويحبوه ويخافوه، شعر رأسه نازل لحد أذنيه ومن أذنيه مستدل على كتفيه، وهو بلون التراب إنما يفوق عليه ضياء، وفى وسط جبينه غرة كعادة الناصريين. أما جبينه فمبسوط ووجهه كثير الصفاء، ليس فيه تجعد ولا علامة البتة. وخداه فى غاية الاعتدال، أنفه وفمه لا يقاسان بحسن فى أحد، منظره يفيض خشوعاً، فرحاً، وورعاً، عيناه كأشعة الشمس فلا أحد يقدر أن يحدق بنظرة اليه من كثرة الضياء. إذا وبخ أرهب، إن نصح أبكى، ويجعل الجميع يحترمونه لأنه ذو سماحة وهيبة. يقولون أنه لم يُنظَر ضاحكاً قط بل باكياً وذراعاه ويداه زائدة الجمال. أما فى الاجتماعات فيُرضى كثيرين، ولكن ينظر إليهم نادراً، وعند وجوده بينهم يجلس بغاية التهذيب. ففى رؤيته وشكله هو أجمل إنسان يمكن تخيله، ومشابه بمقدار عظيم لأمِهِ التى هى أجمل فتاة يمكن مشاهدتها أو تشاهد قط بهذه الجهات. فيا أيها الملك إن رغبت جلالتكم أن تراه فاخبرنى لكى لا أتقاعد عن توجيهه إليك سريعاً. على إنه بالعلوم قد أذهل مدينة أورشليم بأجمعها، فهو يعرف كافة العلوم من غير أن يتعلم، وتارة يمشى حافى الاقدام مكشوف الرأس كمجنون، وكثيرون عند نظرهم اليه يضحكون منه أما فى حضوره أو التكلم معه فأنه يُرهِب ويُذهِل، ويقولون أنه لم يُسمع قط عن رجل هكذا فى الجهات، وبالحقيقة مثل ما يقول لى اليهود إننا لم نسمع قط مشورات حكمة من أحد كمثل ما يُعلِم يسوع هكذا. وكثيرون آخرون يتهكمون ويشتكون لى منه قائلين أنه مضاد لشريعة عظمتكم، وترانى معنفاً جداً من هؤلاء اليهود الأشرار، ويقولون إنه ما أغاظ أحداً قط بل كافة الذين عرفوه وأخبرونى عنه يقولون إنه حاصل لهم منه إنعامات وصحة كثيرة، وفى كل الأمور إنى مستعد لطاعتكم ومن ثم كل ما تأمر به جلالتكم يجرى.          </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [40] The writer has here evidently confounded Nazarenes with Nazirites.         </Language>      </Comment>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            From the Cross to the Tomb         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إنزال السيد المسيح له المجد عن الصليب ووضعه فى القبر         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Romans were in the habit of leaving the bodies of those crucified on their crosses, to be eaten by the vultures, wild animals, or to decompose, but the Jews had a stern command from Almighty God that the body shall not hang overnight on the wood (Deut 21:23), but must be brought down and buried the same day of crucifixion.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">             جرت العادة عند الرومانيين أن يتركوا جثث المصلوبين على صلبانهم حتى تأكلها الجوارح أو وحوش البرية أو تتلاشى من ذاتها. أما اليهود فكان عليهم أمر صريح من الله تعالى ألا تبيت جثة المعلق على الخشبة، بل تُنزل وتُدفن فى ذات اليوم الذي يصلب فيه (تث 21: 23).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            The Valley of Hinnom         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وادى هنوم         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            They used to cast the bodies of the dead in a pit in the Valley of Hinnom. This valley bore many names; the part falling southwest of Jerusalem is called Rabbabba Valley; in the Holy Bible it is called Valley of Hinnom (Josh 15:8; Neh 11:30), Valley of the son of Hinnom (Josh 15:8, 18:16), and Valley of the sons of Hinnom (KJV 2 Kg 23:10). It is a valley descending from the Hebron Gate to Job’s Well, separating Mount Zion from the Mount of Corruption. The southeastern portion of this valley is called Tophet (Jer 7:31; 2 Kg 23:10), or the Valley of Slaughter (Jer 7:32; 19:6), a border separating Benjamin and Judah. Solomon built on the southern crevice overlooking Tophet, the high places for Moab (1 Kg 11:7). Ahaz (2 Kg 16:3; 2 Chr 28:3) and Manasseh (2 Chr 33:6) passed their children through the fire in this valley. Josiah stopped this worship by desecrating the valley and the high places with human bones and other unclean objects, breaking the sacred pillars, and cutting down the wooden images (2 Kg 23:10,13,14). It became a place where all of the city’s rubbish was thrown out, and into where the entire city’s cesspool poured. Looking at what defiled this valley: Molech’s fire, and the fire used to burn the rubbish, the Jews took to calling it Gehinnom [Hades] (land of Hinnom), making it a general location for punishment, throwing the bodies of the two thieves there. Had Joseph not come forward, asking Pilate for the body of the Lord Jesus, He would have been thrown with the thieves, as the Jewish rulers intended.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كانوا يطرحون جثث القتلى فى حفرة فى وادى هنّوم. ويسمى هذا الوادى بعدة أسماء منها الجزء الواقع جنوب غربى أورشليم يدعى "بوادى ربابة". و يسمى فى الكتاب المقدس "وادى هنوم" (يش15: 8)، (نح11: 30)، و"وادى ابن هنوّم" (يش15: 8، 18: 16)، و"وادى بنى هنوم" (2مل23: 10)، وهو وادٍ ينحدر من "باب الخليل" إلى "بئر أيوب" ويفصل "جبل صهيون" عن "تل المؤامرة السيئة". ويسمى الجزء الجنوبى الشرقى من هذا الوادى "توفة" (أر7: 31 )، (2مل23: 10)، أو "وادى القتل" (أر7: 32) ، (19: 6) وكان تخماً بين بنيامين ويهوذا. وكان قد بنى سليمان على الجرف الجنوبى المشرف عليه مرتفعات لموآب (1مل11: 7)، وهو الذى أجاز فيه آحاز ومنسى أولادهما بالنار (2مل16: 3)، (2أخ28: 3، 33: 6) فى هذا الوادى، وفيه أيضاً أبطل يوشيا هذه العبادة بتنجيسه الوادى والمرتفعات بعظام الناس وباشياء أخرى دنسه، وبتكسيره التماثيل، وقطعه السوارى (2مل23: 10، 13، 14) ومن ثم صار متغوطاً تنصب اليه بواليع البلد ومرمى كناساتها. وبالنظر إلى ما تنجس به هذا الوادى من "نار مولك" ومن "النيران المستعملة لاحراق الكناسات"، أخذ اليهود يسمونه جهنم (أى أرض هنّوم)، وجعلوه علماً لموضع العقاب، وفيه طرحت جثتا اللصين. ولولا أن يوسف تقدم إلى بيلاطس وطلب جسد الرب يسوع لطرح مع اللصين كما كان قصد رؤساء اليهود.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Embalming Jesus         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تكفين يسوع         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Joseph took the body, aided by Nicodemus, who followed him, being a Sanhedrin council member, coming with 100 pounds of spices, a mixture of myrrh and aloes. Nicodemus supported Joseph in opposition to the ruling which the Jews passed against Jesus (Jn 7:50–52). They wrapped Him in pure linen which was only done by the rich, noble, and affluent. The linen was a long strip to be wrapped around the body several times. No doubt the spices were placed on the body, mingling with it, and then He was wrapped in the strip and placed in the tomb. As Almighty God previously appointed Joseph the carpenter to care for Jesus during His childhood, He now appointed another Joseph to bury Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فأخذ يوسف الجسد وساعده على ذلك نيقوديموس الذى يماثله لكونه من أعضاء مجلس السبعين، وهو أيضاً كان يوافق يوسف فى الرأى إذ لم يكن موافقاً على الحكم الذى أصدره اليهود ضد يسوع (يو7: 50-52). هذا أتى بمئة رطل طيب من مزيج المر والعود. ولفاه بكتان نقى، وهذا لايفعله إلا الاغنياء والشرفاء وذوى المقامات الرفيعة. وكان ذلك الكتان شقة طويلة تلف علي الجسم جملة مرات، ولابد من أن الاطياب وُضعت على الجسم وضٌمخ بها وبعد ذلك لٌف باللفافة ووضع فى القبر. فكما ان لله تعالى قد عين قبلاً "يوسف النجار" ليعتنى بيسوع فى طفوليته. قد عين الآن "يوسفاً" أخر ليدفنه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            This reminds us of another Joseph, the son of Jacob in the Old Testament, who provided food for the people of Israel in Egypt.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهذا يذكرنا "بيوسف بن يعقوب" فى العهد القديم الذى أعد القوت لشعب إسرائيل فى مصر.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            His Burial         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            دفنه         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Here, we again see God’s mighty care. It was not in the means of the Virgin Mary or the disciples to take the body, but Joseph, who was unknown at that time as a disciple, but as a rich noble man, took it with the greatest ease. Thus, Isaiah’s prophecy was fulfilled: “And they made His grave with the wicked—but with the rich at His death” (Is 53:9). Also, Nicodemus, who came to learn from Jesus three years earlier (Jn 3:2), appeared now accompanying Joseph and helped him in the preparations for burying the Savior. He was placed in a new tomb, in which no one had been placed before, because God had ordained that the One who would not see corruption would not be placed in a tomb with other corrupted bodies (Ps 16:10; Acts 2:31). How amazing are God’s care and economy!         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهنا نرى أيضاً عناية الله العظيمة، فأنه لم يكن فى وسع السيدة مريم العذراء ولا التلاميذ أن يأخذوا الجسد، ولكن "يوسف" الذى لم يكن يٌعرف فى ذلك الوقت كتلميذ، بل كانسان غنى ومشير، أخذه بغاية السهولة وتمت نبوة أشعياء "جعل مع الأشرار قبره ومع غنى عند موته" (أش53: 9)، ثم ان نيقوديموس الذى أتى إلى يسوع قبل الآن بثلاث سنين لكى يتعلم منه (يو3: 2)، ظهر وقتئذ أيضاً كصديق ليوسف وساعده فى الاستعدادات لدفن المخلص له المجد. وقد وضع فى قبر جديد لم يوضع فيه أحد، لان الله قد عين أن الذى لا يرى الفساد لا يوضع فى قبر مع أجساد أخرى تفسد (مز16: 10)، (أع2: 31). فما أعجب عناية الله وتدبيره.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Three Days and Three Nights         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثلاثة أيام وثلاثة ليال         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord’s body was placed in the tomb on Friday before sunset, and rose in the early dawn of Sunday. Thus, the time in which the Lord slept in the tomb was about 36 hours: part of Friday, Saturday (all day and night), and part of Sunday when He rose early. This duration is considered three days and three nights; this is a principle in the Talmud, such that adding one hour to a day counts as another day, and adding a day to a year counts as another year. The same principle was applied in Book of Esther (Esth 4:15–16), and this applies even today in our government. Most governments count one day of the year, a full year. For example, if a child is born on the last day of the year, the whole year is counted for him. Therefore, it is valid to say that the Lord Christ stayed in the tomb for three days and three nights, otherwise the Jews would have objected to the Christians and challenged the veracity of Christ for not fulfilling His promise of rising on the morning of the third day, but they never presented such an objection.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إن جسد الرب قد وضِعَ فى القبر يوم الجمعة قبل غروب الشمس، وقام له المجد فى صباح الأحد باكرا، فتكون المدة التى نامها السيد في القبر نحو ست وثلاثين ساعة، جزء من يوم الجمعة، ويوم السبت بليله، وجزء من يوم الأحد الذى قام فيه باكراً. فقد تُعتبر هذه المدة ثلاث أيام وثلاث ليال، وذلك مبدأ فى كتاب التلمود الذى يُعد أقدس كتاب عند اليهود بعد كتاب الله. وهو إن اضافه ساعة إلى يوم تُحسب يوماً آخر وإضافه يوم إلى سنة يُحسب سنة أخرى. وكذا كان الامر فى أستير (أس 4: 15-16)، وهكذا يجرى هذا الاصطلاح لوقتنا هذا فى حكومتنا، وجميع الحكومات، تحسب يوماً واحداً من السنة سنة كاملة. مثلا إذا ولد طفل فى آخر يوم من السنة، تحسب له السنة كلها. وعلى ذلك فأنه قد يصح القول بأن السيد المسيح قد مكث فى القبر ثلاث أيام وثلاث ليال. ولولا ذلك لاعترض اليهود على المسيحيين وادعوا كذب مسيحهم لعدم اتمام وعده بقيامته صباح اليوم الثالث. ولكنهم لم يأتوا هذا الاعتراض بالمرة.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>