<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Title>      <Language id="English">         Bright Saturday      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         باكر يوم سبت الفرح      </Language>   </Title>      <Text>      <Language id="English">         Romans were in the habit of leaving the bodies of those crucified on their crosses, to be eaten by the vultures, wild animals, or to decompose, but the Jews had a stern command from Almighty God that the body shall not hang overnight on the wood (Deut 21:23), but must be brought down and buried the same day of crucifixion.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         جرت العادة عند الرومانيين أن يتركوا جثث المصلوبين علي صلبانهم حتي تأكلهم الجوارح أو حيوانات البرية أو تتلاشي من ذاتها، أما اليهود فكان عليهم أمر صريح من الله تعالي ألا تبيت جثة المعلق علي الخشبة، بل تُنْزَل وتُدْفَن في ذات اليوم الذي يصلب فيه (تث٢٣:٢١). وكانوا يطرحون جثث القتلي في حفرة في وادي هنوم.      </Language>   </Text>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            The Valley of Hinnom         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وادى هنوم         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            They used to cast the bodies of the dead in a pit in the Valley of Hinnom. This valley bore many names; the part falling southwest of Jerusalem is called Rabbabba Valley; in the Holy Bible it is called Valley of Hinnom (Josh 15:8; Neh 11:30), Valley of the son of Hinnom (Josh 15:8, 18:16), and Valley of the sons of Hinnom (KJV 2 Kg 23:10). It is a valley descending from the Hebron Gate to Job’s Well, separating Mount Zion from the Mount of Corruption. The southeastern portion of this valley is called Tophet (Jer 7:31; 2 Kg 23:10), or the Valley of Slaughter (Jer 7:32; 19:6), a border separating Benjamin and Judah. Solomon built on the southern crevice overlooking Tophet, the high places for Moab (1 Kg 11:7). Ahaz (2 Kg 16:3; 2 Chr 28:3) and Manasseh (2 Chr 33:6) passed their children through the fire in this valley. Josiah stopped this worship by desecrating the valley and the high places with human bones and other unclean objects, breaking the sacred pillars, and cutting down the wooden images (2 Kg 23:10,13,14). It became a place where all of the city’s rubbish was thrown out, and into where the entire city’s cesspool poured. Looking at what defiled this valley: Molech’s fire, and the fire used to burn the rubbish, the Jews took to calling it Gehinnom [Hades] (land of Hinnom), making it a general location for punishment, throwing the bodies of the two thieves there. Had Joseph not come forward, asking Pilate for the body of the Lord Jesus, He would have been thrown with the thieves, as the Jewish rulers intended.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يسمي هذا الوادي بعدة أسماء، منها الجزء الواقع جنوب غربي أورشليم يدعي "بوادي ربابة"، ويسمي في الكتاب المقدس "وادي هنوم" (يش ٨:١٥ )، (نح٣٠:١١)، ووادي ابن هنوم (يش٨:١٥ ، ١٦:١٨)، ووادي بي هنوم (2مل23 : 10)، وهو وادٍ ينحدر من باب الخليل الي بئر أيوب ويفصل جبل صهيون عن تل المؤامرة السيئة. ويسمي الجزء الجنوبي الشرقي من هذا الوادي "توفة" (ار7 : 31) ، (2مل23: 10) أو "وادي القتل" (ار٣٢:٧ ، ٦:١٩) وكان تُخماً بين بنيامين ويهوذا، وبني سليمان علي الجرف الجنوبي المشرف عليه "مرتفعات لموآب" (١مل٧:١١)، وأجاز آحاز ومنسي أولادهما بالنار في هذا الوادي (٢ مل ٣:١٦)، (٢اخ ٣:٢٨ ،٦:٣٣)، وأبطل يوشيا هذه العبادة بتنجيسه الوادي والمرتفعات بعظام الناس وبأشياء أخر دنسه، وبتكسيره التماثيل، وقطعه السواري (2مل١٠:٢٣، ١٣ ،١٤)، (٢اي٤:٣٤ ،٥). ومن ثم صار متغوطاً تنصبُّ اليه بواليع البلد ومرمي كناساتها. وبالنظر الي ما تنجس به هذا الوادي من نار مولك ومن ثم بالنيران المستعملة لإحراق الكناسات، أخذ اليهود يسمونه جهنم (أي أرض هنوم)، وجعلوه عَلَماً لموضع العقاب، وفيه طُرِحت جثتا اللصين. ولولا أن يوسف تقدم الي بيلاطس وطلب جسد الرب يسوع، لطُرِحٍ مع اللصين وهذا ما كان يقصده رِؤساء اليهود.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Embalming Jesus         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تحنيط جسد يسوع         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Joseph took the body, aided by Nicodemus, who followed him, being a Sanhedrin council member, coming with 100 pounds of spices, a mixture of myrrh and aloes. Nicodemus supported Joseph in opposition to the ruling which the Jews passed against Jesus (Jn 7:50–52). They wrapped Him in pure linen which was only done by the rich, noble, and affluent. The linen was a long strip to be wrapped around the body several times. No doubt the spices were placed on the body, mingling with it, and then He was wrapped in the strip and placed in the tomb. As Almighty God previously appointed Joseph the carpenter to care for Jesus during His childhood, He now appointed another Joseph to bury Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أخذ يوسف الجسد وساعده علي ذلك نيقوديموس الذي يماثله في كونه من أعضاء مجلس السبعين. وهذا أتي بمئة رطل طيب من مزيج المر والعود. وهو أيضا كان يوافق يوسف في الرأي ولَم يكن موافقا علي الحُكم الذي أصدره اليهود ضد يسوع (يو٥٠:٧-٥٢)، ولفاه بكتان نقي، وهذا لا يفعله إلا الأغنياء والشرفاء وذوي المقامات الرفيعة. وكان ذلك الكتان شقة طويلة تلف علي الجسم جملة مرات ولابد من أن الأطياب وُضِعتْ علي الجسم، وضُمِخ بها، وبعد ذلك لُفَ باللفافة، ووُضعَ في القبر. فكما أن الله تعالي قد عَينَ قبلاً يوسف النجار ليعتني بيسوع في طفولته، قد عَينَ الآن يوسفاً أخر ليدفنه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            This reminds us of another Joseph, the son of Jacob in the Old Testament, who provided food for the people of Israel in Egypt.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهذا يُذكرنا بيوسف بن يعقوب في العهد القديم الذي أعدَ القوت لشعب إسرائيل في مصر.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            His Burial         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            دفنه         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Here, we again see God’s mighty care. It was not in the means of the Virgin Mary or the disciples to take the body, but Joseph, who was unknown at that time as a disciple, but as a rich noble man, took it with the greatest ease. Thus, Isaiah’s prophecy was fulfilled: “And they made His grave with the wicked—but with the rich at His death” (Is 53:9). Also, Nicodemus, who came to learn from Jesus three years earlier (Jn 3:2), appeared now accompanying Joseph and helped him in the preparations for burying the Savior. He was placed in a new tomb, in which no one had been placed before, because God had ordained that the One who would not see corruption would not be placed in a tomb with other corrupted bodies (Ps 16:10; Acts 2:31). How amazing are God’s care and economy!         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهنا نري أيضاً عناية الله العظيمة فإنه لم يكن في وُسِعْ السيدة مريم العذراء ولا التلاميذ أن يأخذوا الجسد، ولكن يوسف الذي لم يكن يُعرَف في ذلك الوقت كتلميذ بل كإنسان غني ومشير، أخذه بغاية السهولة وتمت نبوة أشعياء "جُعِلَ مع الأشرار قبره ومع غني عند موته" (آش ٩:٥٣)، ثم أن نيقوديموس الذي أتي الي يسوع قَبِلَ الآن بثلاث سنين لكي يتعلم منه (يو٢:٣)، ظهر وقتئْذٍ أيضا كصديق ليوسف وساعده في الإستعدادات لدفن المخلص له المجد. وقد وُضِعَ في قبرٍ جديد لم يوضع فيه أحد لان الله قد عيٓن أن الذي لا يري الفساد لا يوضع في قبر مع أجساد أخري تفسد (مز١٠:١٦)، (أع ٣١:٢). فما أعجب عناية الله وتدبيره.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Three Days and Three Nights         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثلاث أيام وثلاث ليال         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord’s body was placed in the tomb on Friday before sunset, and rose in the early dawn of Sunday. Thus, the time in which the Lord slept in the tomb was about 36 hours: part of Friday, Saturday (all day and night), and part of Sunday when He rose early. This duration is considered three days and three nights; this is a principle in the Talmud, such that adding one hour to a day counts as another day, and adding a day to a year counts as another year. The same principle was applied in Book of Esther (Esth 4:15–16), and this applies even today in our government. Most governments count one day of the year, a full year. For example, if a child is born on the last day of the year, the whole year is counted for him. Therefore, it is valid to say that the Lord Christ stayed in the tomb for three days and three nights, otherwise the Jews would have objected to the Christians and challenged the veracity of Christ for not fulfilling His promise of rising on the morning of the third day, but they never presented such an objection.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أن جسد الرب قد وُضع في القبر يوم الجمعة قبل غروب الشمس، وقام في صباح الأحد باكراً، فتكون المدة التي نامها السيد في القبر نحو ستٍ وثلاثين ساعة، فهى جزء من يوم الجمعة، وجزء من يوم السبت بليله، وجزء من يوم الأحد الذي قام فيه باكراً. فقد تُعتبر هذه المدة ثلاث أيام وثلاث ليالٍ. وذلك مبدأ في كتاب التلمود الذي يُعد أقدس كتاب عند اليهود بعد كتاب الله، وهو أن إضافة ساعة إليّ يوم تُحسب يوماً آخر، وإضافة يوم إليّ سنة يُحسب سنة أخري. وكذا كان الأمر في أستير (آش ١٦:٤ ، ١٥)، وهكذا جارٍ هذا الإصطلاح لوقتنا هذا في حكومتنا السنِية وجميع الحكومات إذ تَحسِب يوماً واحداً من السنة سنة كاملة. فمثلا لو وُلِدَ الطفل في آخر يوم من السنة تُحسب له السنة كلها. وعلي ذلك فانه قد صح القول بأن السيد المسيح قد مكث في القبر ثلاثة أيام وثلاث ليالٍ. ولولا ذلك لإعترض اليهود علي المسيحين وإدعوا كذِب مسيحهم لعدم إتمام وعده بقيامته صباح اليوم الثالث. ولكنهم لم يأتوا هذا الإعتراض بالمرة.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Reasons for Christ’s Death         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            سبب موت المسيح         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The death of the Lord Christ in the flesh was for very sacred, sublime, helpful, and grand purposes for us, His faithful servants who hope for and seek His forgiveness and deep favor:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أما موت السيد المسيح بالجسد فكان لغايةٍ، مقدسةٍ، ساميةٍ، مفيدةٍ وعظيمةٍ جداً لنا نحن عبيده المؤمنين بإسمه الراجين عفوه المنشود وفضله العميم:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The first purpose is to reconcile us with God His Father, whom we had angered by our vile deeds and insistence on committing transgressions. Thus, He had prepared for us severe punishment, painful torment, and an impenetrable barrier separating us from God. Through the death of the Master, to whom is due glory, He blotted out the writing against us, broke the middle barrier between us and God, removed the enmity, brought us closer to Him, and reconciled us through His cross, as the Apostle Paul says, “For it pleased the Father that in Him all the fullness should dwell, and by Him to reconcile all things to Himself, by Him, whether things on earth or things in heaven, having made peace through the blood of His cross” (Col 1:19-20). The same apostle also says in his letter to the Ephesians, “For He Himself is our peace, who has made both one, and has broken down the middle wall of separation, having abolished in His flesh the enmity, that is, the law of commandments contained in ordinances, so as to create in Himself one new man from the two, thus making peace, and that He might reconcile them both to God in one body through the cross, thereby putting to death the enmity. And He came and preached peace to you who were afar off and to those who were near” (Eph 2:14-17). And also saying to the Romans, “For if when we were enemies we were reconciled to God through the death of His Son, much more, having been reconciled, we shall be saved by His life” (Rom 5:10).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أولاً: ليُصالحنا مع الله أبيه الذي قد أغضبناه بسوء أفعالنا وإنصبابنا علي إرتكاب المعاصي والآثام، وبذا فقد أعد لنا عقاباً صارماً وعذاباً أليماً وصار بيننا وبين الله فاصل وحاجز منيع، فبموت السيد له المجد محا الصك الذي كانَ مكتوباً علينا، ونقض الحاجز المتوسط بيننا وبين الله، وأزال العداوة، وقربنا منه تعالي، وصالحنا بصليبه كما يقول بولس الرسول "لأنه فيه سُرَّ أن يحل كل الملء. وأن يُصالِح به الكلَّ لنفسِهِ، عاملاً الصُلحَ بدمِ صليبِهِ بواسطته، سواء كانَ ما علي الأرض أم ما في السموات" (كو١٩:١ ،٢٠ )، وكما يقول أيضاً لأهل أفسس "لأنه هو سلامُنا الذي جَعلَ الاثنين واحداً، ونقضَ حائط السياج المتوسط، أي العداوة. مبطلاً بجسده ناموس الوصايا في فرائض، لكي يخلُق الإثنين في نفسهِ إنساناً واحداً جديداً، صانعاً سلاماً، ويصالح الإثنين في جسدٍ واحدٍ مع الله بالصليب قاتلاً العداوة به. فجاءَ وبشركم بسلامٍ أنتم البعيدين والقريبين (اف ١٤:٢-١٧)، وكما يقول لأهل رومية "لأنه إن كنّا ونحن أعداء قد صُولِحنا مع الله بموتِ إبنهِ فبالأولي كثيراً ونحن مُصالَحون نخلصُ بِحياتِهِ" (رو٥ : 10).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The second purpose is to justify us from the curse of the law that had befallen us as a result of our breach and disobedience to the law, as it is written, “Cursed is everyone who does not continue in all things which are written in the book of the law, to do them” (Gal 3:10). Everyone broke the law, and therefore, everyone became accursed. When death by the cross was installed as a curse, God wanted to die on the cross to lift off the curse from upon us, and to send us the blessing. The Apostle Paul says, “Christ has redeemed us from this curse of the law, having become a curse for us (for it is written, ‘Cursed is everyone who hangs on a tree’), that the blessing of Abraham might come upon the Gentiles in Christ Jesus, that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith” (Gal 3:13-14).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثانياً: ليُبررنا من لعنة الناموس التي حلت علينا من جراء مخالفتنا، وكَسْرِنا للناموس كما قيل "ملعون كل من لا يثبُتْ في جميع ما هو مكتوب في كتاب الناموس ليعْمَل به" (غلا١٠:٣) ولما لم يَحفظ أحد الناموس صار الكل ملعونين، ولما كان موت الصليب لعنة، فأحب الله أن يموت موت الصليب ليرفع عنا اللعنة، ويُرسل لنا البركة كما يقول الرسول "المسيح إفتدانا من لعنة الناموس، إذ صار لعنة لأجلنا، لأنه مكتوب: ملعون كل من عُلِق علي خشبة. لتصير بركة إبراهيم للأمم في المسيح يسوع، لننال بالإيمان موعد الروح" (غل١٣:٣ ، ١٤).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The third purpose is that we may die to our sins by His death, and live through His life, as the Apostle Peter says, “Who Himself bore our sins in His own body on the tree, that we, having died to sins, might live for righteousness” (1 Pet 2:24).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثالثاً: لكي نموت نحن عن خطايانا بموته ونحيا بحياته كما يقول بطرس الرسول "الذى حَمَلَ هو نفسه خطايانا في جسده علي الخشبة، لكي نموت عن الخطايا فنحيا للبر" (١ بط ٢٤:٢).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The fourth purpose is He died that He might taste the pain of death, and nullify, trample, crush, and eliminate it, as the writer Paul of the Epistle to the Hebrews says, “Inasmuch then as the children have partaken of flesh and blood, He Himself likewise shared in the same, that through death He might destroy him who had the power of death, that is, the devil, and release those who through fear of death were all their lifetime subject to bondage” (Heb 2:14-15).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            رابعاً: مات لكي يذوق ألم الموت ويُبطِله ويدوسه ويسحقه ويلاشيه، كما يقول كاتب رسالة العبرانيين "فإذا قد تَشَارك الأولاد في اللحم والدم إشترك هو أيضاً كذلك فيهما، لكي يبيد بالموت ذاك الذي له سلطان الموت، أي إبليس، ويُعتق أولئك الذين خوفاً من الموت كانوا جميعاً كل حياتهم تحت العبودية" (عب١٤:٢ ، ١٥).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>