<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Title>      <Language id="English">         Holy Hosanna Sunday      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         بيان عن أحد الشعانين      </Language>   </Title>      <Text>      <Language id="English">         On Saturday, the ninth of Nisan in the year 5534 of creation, at the house of Simon the Leper, in the well-known village of Bethany (which means “house of misery” or “house of misfortune” [1]), Jesus Christ attended a dinner prepared for Him. Lazarus, whom Jesus raised from the dead, was also present. As mentioned by St. John the Evangelist, this is also when Mary [sister of Lazarus and Martha] anointed the feet of Jesus with pure, precious, fragrant oil, wiping them with the hair of her head: “Then, six days before the Passover, Jesus came to Bethany, where Lazarus was who had been dead, whom He had raised from the dead. There they made Him a supper; and Martha served, but Lazarus was one of those who sat at the table with Him. Then Mary took a pound of very costly oil of spikenard, anointed the feet of Jesus, and wiped His feet with her hair. And the house was filled with the fragrance of the oil” (Jn 12:1–3).[2] Six days before the feast was a Saturday.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         حضر السيد المسيح العشاء الذي أُعِدَ له يوم السبت الواقع في التاسع من نيسان سنة 5534 للخليقة في القرية المعروفة ببيت عنيا ومعناه "بيت البؤس أو النحس"[1]، في بيت سمعان الأبرص، حيث كان لعازر الميت الذي أقامه يسوع من الاموات، وحيث دهنت مريم قدمي يسوع بالطيب الخالص الكثير الثمن ومسحتهما بشعر رأسها كما يقول يوحنا الإنجيلي "ثُمَّ قَبْلَ الْفِصْحِ بِسِتَّةِ أَيَّامٍ أَتَى يَسُوعُ إِلَى بَيْتِ عَنْيَا حَيْثُ كَانَ لِعَازَرُ الْمَيْتُ الَّذِي أَقَامَهُ مِنَ الأَمْوَاتِ. فَصَنَعُوا لَهُ هُنَاكَ عَشَاءً. وَكَانَتْ مَرْثَا تَخْدِمُ وَأَمَّا لِعَازَرُ فَكَانَ أَحَدَ الْمُتَّكِئِينَ مَعَهُ، فَأَخَذَتْ مَرْيَمُ مَناً مِنْ طِيبِ نَارِدِينٍ خَالِصٍ كَثِيرِ الثَّمَنِ وَدَهَنَتْ قَدَمَيْ يَسُوعَ وَمَسَحَتْ قَدَمَيْهِ بِشَعْرِهَا فَامْتَلَأَ الْبَيْتُ مِنْ رَائِحَةِ الطِّيبِ"(يو12: 1-3)[2]، وبالطبع قبل الفصح بستة أيام يكون السبت.      </Language>   </Text>      <Comment>      <Language id="English">         [1] According to Strong’s “Bethany” 846, Bethany means “house of dates or house of misery.”      </Language>   </Comment>      <Comment>      <Language id="English">         [2] Biblical references are taken from the NKJV, unless otherwise indicated.      </Language>   </Comment>      <Text>      <Language id="English">         The following day, Sunday, the tenth of Nisan, is the day on which every Israelite family would choose their Passover lamb from the flock, and keep it until the fourteenth of the month, when they would sacrifice it in the evening (Ex 12:1–36). On this day, Jesus entered Jerusalem publicly (Jn 12:12). Just as the Passover lamb is chosen and kept for a few days in the Holy City, likewise, the Lamb of God, who takes away the sin of the world (Jn 1:29), remained within the walls of Jerusalem, alternating between the temple and Bethany.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         ثم قام في الغد قاصداً الدخول الي أورشليم علانية (يو12: 12)، فكان هذا الغد هو الأحد الموافق 10 نيسان، وهو اليوم الذي كان يأخذ فيه كل جماعة من بني إسرائيل خروف الفصح من وسط القطيع ليحفظونه الي اليوم الرابع عشر من هذا الشهر، ثم يذبحونه في العشية (خر12: 1-36). وكما كانت خراف الفصح تٌفرز وتُوضع تحت الحفظ بضعة أيام في المدينة المقدسة، هكذا بقي حمل الله الذي يَرفع خطايا العالم (يو1 : 29) بين جدران أورشليم متردداً بين الهيكل وبيت عنيا.      </Language>   </Text>      <Text>      <Language id="English">         When the appointed time to fulfill redemption drew near, He entered Jerusalem in a great celebration, just as Zechariah prophesied concerning Him: “Rejoice greatly, O daughter of Zion! Shout, O daughter of Jerusalem! Behold, your King is coming to you; He is just and having salvation, lowly and riding on a donkey, a colt, the foal of a donkey” (Zech 9:9). Our Savior wanted to enter Jerusalem publicly at a time when pilgrims flooded the city to celebrate Passover. Josephus mentions that the crowd often totaled well over two million pilgrims.[3]      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         ولما قرُبَ الوقت المعين لإتمام الفداء دخل أورشليم باحتفال عظيم كما تنبأ عنه زكريا قائلاً "إبْتَهِجِي جِدّاً يَا ابْنَةَ صِهْيَوْنَ اهْتِفِي يَا بِنْتَ أُورُشَلِيمَ. هُوَذَا مَلِكُكِ يَأْتِي إِلَيْكِ. هُوَ عَادِلٌ وَمَنْصُورٌ وَدِيعٌ وَرَاكِبٌ عَلَى حِمَارٍ وَعَلَى جَحْشٍ ابْنِ أَتَانٍ" (زك 9 : 9) إن مخلصنا له المجد أراد أن يدخل أورشليم علانية في الوقت الذي كانت فيه مزدحمة بالزائرين الذين كانوا يقصدونها ليحتفلوا بالفصح فيها، وقد ذكر يوسيفوس[3] أن عدد الجموع كان كثيراً فكان يفوق المليونين.      </Language>   </Text>      <Comment>      <Language id="English">         [3] Josephus, F., &amp; Whiston, W. (1996). The Works of Josephus : Complete and Unabridged. Peabody: Hendrickson, 1751.      </Language>   </Comment>      <Text>      <Language id="English">         As Christ drew near to the city, they chanted with joy, such that their chanting reached up to the heavens. They chanted words specific to the awaited Messiah: “Hosanna to the Son of David! Blessed is He who comes in the name of the Lord! Hosanna in the highest! ... Blessed is the kingdom of our father David that comes in the name of the Lord! Hosanna in the highest… Blessed is the King who comes in the name of the Lord! Peace in heaven and glory in the highest” (Mt 21:9; Mk 11:10; Lk 19:38). Such words did not come from the people themselves, but rather, the people were moved to speak by an unusual force. They might not have understood the truth of what they exclaimed, but unlike previous occasions, Christ did not prevent the people in their praise because in this is the fulfillment of the prophecies. The Pharisees were livid and envious, and their hearts were full of hatred. Unsuccessful in their attempts to silence the people, the Pharisees asked the Master to rebuke the crowd, but He answered, “I tell you that if these should keep silent, the stones would immediately cry out” (Lk 19:40).      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         ولما قرب المسيح من المدينة هتفت أولئك الجماهير بأصوات التهليل حتي بلغ هتافهم عنان السماء، وهم يشيرون بهتافهم الي الرب يسوع بعبارات تخص السيد المسيح المنتظر "أوصنا لإبن داود، مبارك الآتي بإسم الرب (مت21: 9)، "مباركة هى مملكة أبينا داود الآتية بإسم الرب، أوصنا فى الأعالى" (مر11 :10) مبارك الملك الآتي باسم الرب، سلام في السماء ومجد في الأعالي" (لو 19 : 38)، ولم يكن هتاف تلك الجموع من تلقاء أنفسهم، بل كانوا مدفوعين بقوة غريبة غير عادية. لأن ما فاهوا به وإن لم يفهموه كان حقاً، وقد قبِلهُ السيد المسيح ولم يحرِّم عليهم النطق به كما كان يفعل قبلاً في مناسبات كثيرة، لأن في هذا كان كمال النبوات. وقد حاول الفريسيون الذين أكلت نار الحسد صدورهم وغلت مراجل الحقد في قلوبهم، أن يسكتوهم فلم يفلحوا، فقالوا للسيد إنتهرهم، فقال لهم إن سكت هؤلاء صرخت الحجارة (لو 19 : 40).      </Language>   </Text>      <Text>      <Language id="English">         Concerning our Savior’s choice to ride a donkey that no one had ever ridden—as plainly written by the Evangelists that He rode the foal of a colt not trained to bear burdens—this is symbolic of Him as a new ruler of a new covenant who rode a new animal, and upon His death, He was placed in a new tomb. Since no one had previously ridden the colt, its mother accompanied it, symbolizing the Old Testament being fulfilled in the New Testament. This also corresponds with the milk cows from the Old Testament, which had never been yoked, that pulled the new cart on which was placed the ark of the Lord (1 Sam 6:10). Furthermore, riding a donkey was considered a sign of peace (our Lord Jesus Christ is the Prince of Peace), while riding a horse was a sign of war.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         أما إختيار مخلصنا لأن يمتطي أتاناً لم يعلُه أحد، فقد نص عنه البشيرون صريحاً، ركب جحشاً إبن أتان غير متمرن علي الحمل، ولا ريب في أنه كان لهذا معني رمزي، فإنه كان رئيساً جديداً لعهد جديد، وإمتطي حيواناً جديداً، كما أنه عند موته قد وٌضِعَ في قبر جديد. وذلك يطابق ما جاء في العهد القديم: أن البقرتين اللتين لم يعلهما نير جرَّتا العجلة الجديدة الموضوع عليها تابوت الرب (1صم 6 : 10). فإن ركوب الحمير يُعد سلمياً (لأنه رئيس السلام)، بينما كان ركوب الخيل حربياً وذلك عند الملوك. وبما أن الجحش لم يركبه أحد قط، فيقتضى ذلك أن تصحبه أمه ليستأنس بها فيتمم هذه الخدمة، ليكمل العهد القديم بالجديد.      </Language>   </Text></Document>