<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Title>      <Language id="English">         Holy Covenant Thursday      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         بيان عن يوم الخميس الكبير من البصخة المقدسة      </Language>   </Title>      <Text>      <Language id="English">         When it was the first day of Unleavened Bread, “when the Passover must be killed” (Lk 22:7), Jesus commanded two of his disciples to prepare the Passover for them to eat together. This is stated in the Gospel according to Saints Matthew, Mark, and Luke (Mt 26:17; Mk 14:12; Lk 22:8). In the afternoon, they went to the place where the disciples had prepared the Passover—the house of our teacher, St. Mark the Evangelist, as both tradition and the disciple himself reveal (Mk 14:13). On this said day, the fourteenth of the month of Nisan, the Jews refrained from work in the afternoon and removed all leaven from their homes (Ex 12:15). Preparations for the Passover are made on the fourteenth day, and hence, this day is called the first day of Unleavened Bread. At twilight (Lev 23:5), between afternoon and sunset, as the eve of the fifteenth day drew near, is when the slaughter of the Passover lamb takes place. On Thursday afternoon, our Savior returned once more to Jerusalem (but not to the temple) with His disciples to eat the Passover—the Jewish great feast commanded in chapter twelve of the Book of Exodus (Ex 12:1-14).      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         ولما جاء اليوم الاول من الفطير الذي كان ينبغي أن يُذبح فيه الفصح (لو 22: 7)، أمر يسوع إثنين من تلاميذه أن يذهبا ويُعِدا الفصح ليأكله معهم جميعاً، كما هو واضح فى البشائر متى ومرقس ولوقا (مت26: 17) ، (مر14 :12)، (لو22: 8 )، وبعد الظهر توجه الي المكان الذى أعد التلاميذ فيه الفصح، فى بيت معلمنا مرقس الإنجيلي كما يُخبر التقليد، وكما يظهر لنا من نفس إنجيله (مر14: 13)، ثم أن اليوم المشار اليه هنا هو اليوم الرابع عشر من نيسان، الذى كان اليهود يكفون فيه عن الشغل عند الظهر، ويخرجون كل مختمر من البيوت (خر 12: 15) ثم بين العشائين (لا 23: 5)، أى بين العصر والغروب يذبحون فيه خروف الفصح، ومتى إبتدأ مساء اليوم الخامس عشر كانت الإستعدادات لذلك تُصنع فى اليوم الرابع عشر، ولهذا السبب كان يُدعى هذا اليوم " اليوم الاول من الفطير" وبعد ظهر يوم الخميس رجع مخلصنا له المجد مرة أخرى إلى أورشليم لا إلى الهيكل، ومعه تلاميذه ليأكل الفصح، وهو العيد العظيم عند اليهود الذى أُمِروا بعمله فى الإصحاح الثانى عشر من سفر الخروج (خر12: 1-14).      </Language>   </Text>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Passover Ritual         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            طقوس الفصح:         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Pesah is a Hebrew word meaning “to pass over,” which is in reference to the time when the angel of death passed over the children of Israel and killed the firstborn of the Egyptians. The duration of the feast was seven days (Ex 12:15), beginning on the fifteenth day of the month of Nisan and ending on the twenty-first day of Nisan (Ex 12:18; Lev 23:6; Num 28:17). By law, it was necessary for Jews, during this period, to eat only unleavened bread (Ex 12:15,18), and hence, the name The Feast of Unleavened Bread. There were five conditions for the feast:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "الفصح" لفظة عبرانية معناها "العبور" يعنى بها عبور الملاك المُهلِك عن بنى إسرائيل حين قتل أبكار المصريين. وكانت مدة العيد سبعة أيام (خر12: 15) تبتدئ من اليوم الخامس عشر من شهر نيسان وتنتهي في الحادى والعشرين منه (خر12: 18)، (لا 23: 6)، (عدد 28: 17)، وكان محتماً على اليهود بمقتضى الناموس الا يأكلوا فى هذه المدة سوى الفطير (خر12: 15، 18)، ولذلك سمى بعيد الفطير. وتستلزم ممارسة الفصح خمسة أمور:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            1) Slaughter of the lamb         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            1. ذبح الخروف         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            2) Sprinkling the blood on the doorposts and lintel of the homes celebrating         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            2. رش الدم على قائمتى الباب وعتبته من بيت المعبد.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            3) Roasting the whole lamb without breaking any bones (Ex 12:46), (symbolic of the Passion of the Lord Christ for our sake) (Jn 19:36)         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            3. شي الخروف صحيحاً من دون أن يٌكسر منه عظم (خر12: 46)، وفى ذلك رمز إلى الآم السيد المسيح من أجلنا (يو19: 36).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            4) Eating the lamb with unleavened bread and bitter herbs         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            4. أكله مع الفطير والآعشاب المرة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            5) Not keeping any of it till morning (Ex 12:4–14)         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            5. عدم إبقاء شىء منه الي الصبح (خر12: 4-14).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Passover Eating Place         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            مكان أكله:         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            According to Jewish custom, groups of no less than ten persons and no more than twenty are formed when eating the Passover lamb. If the residents of one house were less than ten, the members of two houses shared one lamb. According to the law, each group delegated one person to bring the lamb to the temple and help the Levites to slaughter it, then, to bring it back to the house where they intended to eat it (Lev 12:4-14). For this Passover, the disciples, Peter and John, achieved this on behalf of our Savior and His disciples (Lk 22:8). They prepared the bread, wine, bitter herbs, and all the necessities for the Passover. The disciples inquired of the Lord where they could eat the Passover. Therefore, when they had asked Jesus, He sent two of them with a sign to identify the owner of the house—a man “carrying a pitcher of water” (Mk 14:13). Our Savior wisely hid the location from His disciples until the hour came in which it was time to feast. He did this to prevent Judas from informing the Jewish leaders, who intended to arrest and detain Him, until after the feast. He only informed Peter and John. And only after they had completed all necessary preparations, Jesus arrived with the rest of the disciples (who did not know the whereabouts of the feast) and ate the Passover.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كان من عوائد اليهود أن يقسموا أنفسهم في أكل خروف الفصح إلى جماعات كل منها لا تقل عن عشرة أشخاص ولا تتجاوز العشرين شخصاً. فإن لم يبلغ سكان البيت الواحد العشرة أشخاص إشترك بيتان فى خروف واحد، وكان كل جماعة تنيب عنها واحداً ليُحضر الخروف إلى دار الهيكل، ويساعد أيضاً اللاويين على ذبحه، ثم ينقل ما يُذبح إلى البيت الذى يقصدون أن يأكلوه فيه حسب الشريعة (خر12: 4-14)، وقد قام بذلك في الهيكل هذه المرة بالنيابة عن مخلصنا تلاميذه بطرس ويوحنا (لو22: 8)، وأعدا الخبز والخمر والاعشاب المرة وكل ما هو ضرورياً لإعداد الفصح. ولم يفهم التلاميذ المكان الذى سيأكلون فيه الفصح، ولذا سألوه عنه، فأرسل إثنين منهم وأعطاهما علامة يميزان بها صاحب ذلك البيت. وهو انسان حامل جرة ماء (مر 14: 13)، وكان لمخلصنا حكمة في إخفاء معرفة المكان عن تلاميذه إلى تلك الساعة حتى لا يتمكن يهوذا من أن يُعلم جماعة اليهود به فيقبضوا عليه ويحفظوه عندهم إلى ما بعد العيد. فأطلع بطرس ويوحنا فقط على ذلك. ولما أعدا كل شئ وجاءا به، ذهب هو وتلاميذه الذين لم يكونوا يعرفون المكان حتى دخلوه فاكلوا الفصح هناك.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            The Four Passover Cups         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كؤوسه الأربع         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            In the Jewish custom, four cups of red wine mixed with a little water were consumed at dinner. The host would bless saying, “Blessed be You, O Lord our God, eternal King, who creates the fruit of the vine,” and drank the inaugural glass.[35] This was called the cup of bitterness, as mentioned in the Gospel according to St. Luke (Lk 22:17). Afterward, they would wash, symbolic of their ancestors’ crossing of the Red Sea, and then, they would approach to eat what was set before them on the table—the bitter herbs, unleavened bread, roasted lamb, date soup, almonds, figs, raisins, vinegar, cinnamon, and other spices. Next, the host would take some of the herbs to dip in the soup and eat. As he does this, he thanks God, who created the bounties of the earth, and the guests in return would answer him saying, “Amen.” Following this, a boy would come forward and ask his father about the reason for keeping these laws, and his father in turn would respond by saying that the slaughter of the sheep was a reminder of the angel of death, who passing over the houses of the Hebrews did not harm them. The unleavened bread symbolizes the bread of affliction, which they ate unleavened as they fled from Pharaoh (Deut 16:3), the bitter herbs symbolize the slavery, which they suffered in Egypt, and the soup (with its color and thickness) symbolizes the cities of Pithom and Raamses, which their ancestors built for Pharaoh as forced laborers (Ex 1:11; Deut 6:20).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كان لليهود عادة أن يشربوا على العشاء أربعة كؤوس خمرٍ حمراء ممزوجة بقليل من الماء: الكأس الأول تُدعى "كأس المرارة" وتعتبر افتتاحية، فيأخذه رئيس الجماعة ويباركه قائلاً: "فليكن الرب مباركاً الذى أبدع ثمر الكرمة"[35]. ، وهو الكأس المذكورة فى إنجيل لوقا (لو22: 17) وعلى أثر ذلك كانوا يغتسلون وهذا الإغتسال كانوا يشيرون بها الى عبور أسلافهم البحر الاحمر. ثم يتقدمون الى المائدة لأكل ما قد أعد عليها من الأعشاب المرة و الفطير والخروف المشوى والمرق المصنوع من البلح، واللوز والتين والزبيب والخل والقرفة وغيرها من البهارات و أيضاً خجيجة اليوم الرابع عشر. وحينئذ يأخذ رئيس الجماعة شيئاً من الأعشاب ويغمسه فى المرق، ويأكله شاكراً الله الذى أبدع خيرات الأرض، فيجاوبه باقى المتكئين قائلين آمين. وعقب ذلك يتقدم ولد ويسأل والده عن سبب حفظ هذه الفريضة، فيجيبه على ذلك أن ذبح الخروف هو تذكار لمرور الملاك المبيد أمام بيوت العبرانيين بدون أن يؤذِهم. والفطير يشير الى خبز الشدة الذى أكلوه فطيراً وقت هروبهم من أمام فرعون (تث 16: 3)، والأعشاب المرة رمز إلي العبودية التى كابدوها بمصر، والمرق المختثر يمثل بلونه وخثورته طين مدينتى فيثوم ورعمسيس اللتين بناها أسلافهم لفرعون بالتسخير (خر1: 11)، (تث6: 20).         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [35] Dix, G. (1945). The shape of the Liturgy. London: Dacre Press, 52.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Thereafter, they would say the first part of the praise, Psalms 113 and 114, and drink the second cup, which they call the cup of joy, begging for a blessing upon each type of food. The host would then take the unleavened bread, break it, and distribute it to the guests, who would dip it into the soup until they have fully consumed it. Sometimes, the host would dip the piece of bread in the dish (as our Savior did) and give to each one of the guests. Once this is done, they conclude their meal by eating the Passover lamb, of which they leave no remainders.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            2.      ثم يقولون الجزء الاول من التسبيح وهو المزمور رقم 113 و رقم 114.بعد ذلك يشربون الكأس الثانية التى يدعونها "كأس الفرح" و يطلبون البركة على كل نوع من الطعام، فيأخذ الرئيس الفطير ويكسره و يوزعه على المتكئين، فيأكلونه بعد أن يغمسوه هو و بالمرق حتى ينتهي. وأحياناً يَغمس الرئيس الكسر فى الصحفة كما فعل مخلصلنا له المجد وناولهم. ومتى فرغوا من ذلك يأكلون خروف الفصح ولا يبقوا منه شيئاً ولا يأكلون بعده طعاماً آخر         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Then, they offer thanksgiving and drink the third cup, which is called the cup of blessing (1 Cor 10:16), and they sing the remainder of the hymn of praise, which is “Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but to Your name give glory” (Ps 115:1).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            3.      وهم يقدمون تشكرات ثم يشربون الكأس الثالثة التى تدعى "كأس البركة" (1كو 10: 16) ثم يرتلون ما بقى من ترنيمة التسبيح وهي “ليس لنا يارب ليس لنا لكن لاسمك أعطى مجداً (مز115: 1).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Drinking the fourth cup usually concludes the celebration. Sometimes, they drank a fifth cup after singing the great hymn that contains seventeen psalms, from Psalm 120 to Psalm 136.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            4.      ثم يشربون الكاس الرابعة التى كانوا غالباً يختمون بها الاحتفال. وأحياناً كانوا يشربون كأساً خامسة بعد ترنيمة التسبحة العظيمة المحتوية علي سبعة عشر مزموراً وهى من مزمور 120 إلى مزمور 136.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Washing of the Feet         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            غسل الأرجل         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            At this time, a dispute occurred between the disciples as to which of them is the first and greatest, and each one tried to elevate himself, but Jesus addressed these vain thoughts: “And He said to them, ‘The kings of the Gentiles exercise lordship over them, and those who exercise authority over them are called “benefactors.” But not so among you; on the contrary, he who is greatest among you, let him be as the younger, and he who governs as he who serves’” (Lk 22:24–26). Instantly He arose and washed each disciple’s feet. Peter was overwhelmed by the grandeur of this situation, and felt that he did not deserve this amazing act, so he told his Master, “‘You shall never wash my feet!’ Jesus answered him, ‘If I do not wash you, you have no part with Me.’ Simon Peter said to Him, ‘Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and my head!’” (Jn 13:8–9).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            حدثت فى هذا الوقت مشاجرة بين التلاميذ فيمن يظن أن يكون الاول والاعظم، وحاول كل واحد منهم أن يجعل نفسه الاول، فأنبهم يسوع علي تلك الافكار الباطلة "فقال لهم ملوك الامم يسودونهم والمتسلطون عليهم يدعون محسنين وأما أنتم فليس هكذا بل الكبير فيكم ليكن كالصغير والمتقدم كالخادم" (لو22: 24-26) وفى الحال قد قام بعملية غسل أرجل التلاميذ واحداً واحداً. أما بطرس فاستعظم هذ الامر الكبير ورأى نفسه انه لا يستحق هذا الفعل المدهش، فقال لسيده لن تغسل رجلىَّ أبداً، فأجابه يسوع أن كنت لا أغسلك فليس لك معى نصيب. فخاف بطرس وقال ياسيد ليس رجلىّ فقط بل يدى ورأسى (يو13: 8- 9).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Judas’ Betrayal         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            خيانة يهوذا         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            After this, He alerted them to His betrayal by saying, “One of you will betray me” (Jn 13:21), meaning Judas, into whom Satan entered after he had received the morsel. Then, Jesus addressed Judas directly: “What you do, do quickly” (Jn 13:27). Judas arose immediately and went to the Jews to deliver to them his Master. He guided them and was an accomplice to them in the Lord Jesus’ arrest, in return for thirty shekels of silver. Each shekel equals thirteen and a half Egyptian pounds; therefore, thirty shekels equal four hundred and five cents—the price of a slave (Ex 21:32) at that time. The Lord Christ was sold to die as a slave in order to free us from the yoke of bitter bondage. Zechariah prophesied concerning this, saying, “‘If it is agreeable to you, give me my wages; and if not, refrain.’ So they weighed out for my wages thirty pieces of silver” (Zech 11:12).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بعد ذلك أنبأهم بخيانة يهوذا بقوله –له المجد- إن واحداً منكم يسلمنى (يو13: 21)، يقصد به يهوذا الذى إذ بعد أن أخذ اللقمة دخله الشيطان. فقال له يسوع ما أنت تعمله فأعمله بأكثر سرعة (يو13 : 27)، فقام فى الحال ومضى إلى اليهود ليسلم لهم سيده بالارشاد عليه والاشتراك معهم فى القبض عليه أيضاً مقابل إعطائه ثلاثين من الفضة أى ثلاين شاقلاً من الفضة، والشاقل يساوى ثلاثة عشر قرشاً ونصف قرش من النقود المصرية، فيكون المبلغ الذى أخذه أربعمائة وخمس قروش، وهذه القيمة كانت ثمن العبد (خر21: 32) فى ذلك الوقت، فبيع السيد المسيح للموت كعبد لكى يحررنا من نير العبودية الدائمة للخطية والموت. وتنبأ زكريا عن ذلك بقوله "إن حسن في أعينكم فاعطوني أجرتي وإلا فامتنعوا، فوزنوا أجرتي ثلاثين من الفضة"(زك11: 12).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            What a vast difference between Mary’s valuation of the Lord Christ and Judas’ valuation of Him! At the dinner, she washed His feet with perfume that was valued at three hundred dinars to honor Him (Jn 12:5). On the contrary, Judas betrayed Jesus for a mere four hundred and five cents.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فما أعظم الفرق بين قيمة السيد المسيح عند مريم وقيمته عند يهوذا، فإنها أنفقت على إكرامه عند العشاء ثلثمائة دينار (يو12: 5)، وباعه يهوذا للموت بأقل من ثلث هذه القيمة أى باربعمائة وخمس قروش.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Lessons from His Betrayal         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            دروس من خيانته         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            From Judas’ story, we can learn several lessons:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فنتعلم من قصة يهوذا جملة الفوائد الآتية:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            1)  Gaining the greatest means does not guarantee salvation. Judas was a chosen disciple, one of the twelve, accompanying Christ, witnessing His miracles, hearing His teachings, a partner to Peter, James, and John, and having received from the means of grace what Abraham, Moses, Isaiah, and Daniel did not receive. He perished because he did not remove greed from his heart.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أولاً: إن الحصول على أفضل الوسائط لا يتكفل وحده بالخلاص، فإن يهوذا كان رسولا مختاراً من ضمن الاثنى عشر و كان رفيقاً للمسيح، وشاهد معجزاته وسمع تعاليمه، وكان شريكاً لبطرس ويعقوب ويوحنا، ونال من وسائط النعمة مالم ينله ابراهيم وموسي وأشعياء ودانيال، ومع كل ذلك فانه هلك، لانه لم ينزع الطمع من نفسه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            2)  A person might gain a good reputation among people, but have no godliness before God. The Lord Christ sent Judas, just as He commissioned the rest of the disciples, to teach and perform miracles, so he appeared to have left everything for the sake of Christ, like his companions. None suspected him because he was appointed treasurer to the moneybox. When the Master told the apostles, “One of you will betray Me” (Mt 26:21; Jn 13:21), none thought of Judas, but each one suspected himself, as each one asked, “Lord, is it I?” (Mt 26:22).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثا نياً: يمكن أن ينال الإنسان صيتاً حسناً بين الناس وهو بلا تقوى أمام الله، فالسيد المسيح أرسل يهوذا كسائر الرسل ليعلم ويصنع الآيات، فظهر أنه ترك كل شئ لأجل المسيح كغيره من الرسل، ولم يظن أحد منهم سوءاً لأنهم عينوه أميناً للصندوق، وحينما قال السيد للرسل "واحد منكم يسلمنى" (مت 26: 21)، (يو13: 21) لم يفكر أحد فى يهوذا بل نظر كل واحد الى نفسه أولا، بدليل قول كل واحد منهم "هل أنا يارب" (مت 26: 22).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            3)  The love of money is a great danger and a dark wickedness; Judas was conspicuous in his love of money. This is evident in his words to the chief priests, “What are you willing to give me if I deliver Him to you?” (Mt 26:15). Yes, Judas left much when he followed Jesus, yet he did not leave behind his greed, so he perished and drowned in despair, as a ship drowns for having a small hole within it. We see that Judas is not the only example. The love of money caused Delilah to deliver her husband Samson to the Philistines. It caused Gehazi to deceive Naaman and lie to Elisha, and so he was struck with leprosy. It caused Ananias and Sapphira to lie to the Holy Spirit, and so, they perished. It caused Judas to carry out the most heinous sin—betraying the Son of God to His murderers, so he hanged himself: “For the love of money is a root of all kinds of evil, for which some have strayed from the faith in their greediness, and pierced themselves through with many sorrows” (1 Tim 6:10). This fulfills the Lord Christ’s words: “From him who does not have, even what he has will be taken away” (Mt 25:29).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثالثاً: إن محبة المال خطر عظيم وشر جسيم، ويهوذا كان من أول محبى المال، ويدل على ذلك قوله لرؤساء الكهنة "ماذا تريدون أن تعطونى وأنا أسلمه إليكم"(مت26: 15). نعم إن يهوذا ترك كثيراً عندما تبع يسوع، ولكنه لم يترك طمعه فأهلكه وأغرقه فى لجة اليأس كما تغرق السفينة بواسطة ثقب صغير فيها. ولم يكن مثال يهوذا هو المثل الوحيد فحب المال حمل دليلة على تسليم زوجها شمشون الى الفلسطينيين، وحمل جيحزى على خداع نعمان والكذب على إليشع، وحمل حنانيا وسفيرة على أن يكذبا على الروح القدس، وهكذا حمل يهوذا على أن يرتكب أفظع الآثام وهو تسليم إبن الله الى قاتليه. فعلينا أن نصغى الى قول الرسول "محبة المال أصل لكل الشرور الذى إذا إبتغاه قوم ضلوا عن الإيمان وطعنوا أنفسهم بأوجاع كثيرة" (1تى6: 10) وهذا يحقق قول السيد المسيح "ومن ليس له فالذى عنده يؤخذ منه"(مت 25: 29).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            4)  Being disappointed by friends is no wonder, as the Lord Christ personally tasted the bitterness of this cup–the cup of betrayal by friends, and so, is able to sympathize with us (Heb 4:15). In fact, it is rare to find a friend upon whom one can rely in times of distress.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            رابعاً: إنه لا عجب من خيبة الأمل فى الأصحاب. لان السيد المسيح نفسه ذاق مرارة هذه الكأس، كأس خيانة الاصدقاء، وصار بذلك قادراً على أن يشعر بنا ويرثي لنا فى تلك الأحوال (عب 4: 15). وفى الحقيقة أنه قلَّ أن يوجد صديق حقيقى يركن اليه الانسان فى أوقات الضيق.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            5)  The most wicked enmity Christ suffered came from those closest to Him, as mentioned in the Book of Psalms (Ps 41:9; 55:12–14). This harmed the Church (the body of Christ) in every age, more so than external enemies. Likewise, a person is not usually harmed, except from those closest to him—his friends. This is seen and encountered on a daily basis, as the Holy Bible explicitly says, “A man’s enemies are the men of his own household” (Mic 7:6; Mt 10:36).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            خامساً: إن شر أعداء المسيح كان من أقرب أصحابه كما جاء فى سفر المزامير (مز41: 9) ، (55: 12-14) وهذه أضرت بالكنيسة التى هى "جسد المسيح" فى كل عصر أكثر من كل الأعداء الخارجين عليها. وكذلك ضرر الانسان لا يلحقه غالباً إلا من أقاربه وأصحابه كما هو مشاهد ومحسوس يومياً. وكما يقول الكتاب بصريح العبارة أن أعداء الانسان أهل بيته (مي 7: 6)، (مت 10: 36) والمقربون اليه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            6)  Sometimes, good results from evil; Judas’ outcome was the greatest evidence confounding the false accusations against Christ. After he betrayed Him, he could have silenced his conscience and the accusations of others by remembering some faults in Christ (who was flawless), yet, instead we find that he cast down in the treasury the silver which he had taken as payment for his monstrous act, saying, “I have sinned by betraying innocent blood” (Mt 27:4). This silences those who claim that we have no witness to Christ’s innocence, except the testimony of His friends.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            سادساً: أنه فى بعض الأحيان قد ينتج من الشر خير، فإن عاقبة خيانة يهوذا كانت أفضل برهان على صحة دعوى المسيح، لأنه بعدما سلمه كان عليه أن يُسكت ضميره ويٌسكت توبيخ الآخرين له بذكر شئ من عيوب المسيح الذى لم يكن فيه عيب. ولكنا رأيناه يطرح فى الخزانة الفضة التى كان قد أخذها أجرة على إثمه قائلاً "أخطأت إذ سلمت دماً بريئاً" (مت 27: 4) وهذا يفحم من يقول ليس لنا شهادة بر المسيح سوى شهادة أصحابه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            7)  Relenting over evil, after the fact, is unbeneficial and does not restore the damage, unless it is by true repentance. Although Judas repented, returned the coins, and confessed his sins, yet, he was unable to save Christ, because they did not acknowledge him with an answer, except, “What is that to us? You see to it!” (Mt 27:4). Neither was he able to silence his conscience as revealed by the fact that he “went and hanged himself” (Mt 27:5). This is because he did not resort to his Master with true relenting and repentance accompanied by tears, as Peter did, who “went out and wept bitterly” (Mt 26:75; Lk 22:62), and so, the Lord forgave Peter’s sins.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            سابعاً: إن الندامة على الشر بعد إتيانه لا تفيد شيئاً ولا تصلح ماقد فسد إلا إذا كانت من خلال توبة حقيقية، فإن يهوذا ندم ورد الدراهم وإعترف بإثمه ولكنه لم يقدر أن ينقذ المسيح، لأنهم لم يجيبوه إلا بقولهم "ماذا علينا أنت أبصر" (مت 27: 4)، ولم يستطع أن يسكت ضميره بدليل أنه "مضى وخنق نفسه" (مت 27: 5) وذلك لأنه لم يلجأ الى سيده بالندامة والتوبة الحقيقية المشفوعة بالدموع كما فعل بطرس" فإنه بكى بكاءً مراً" (مت 26: 75)، (لو22: 62) فغفر له الرب خطاياه.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Instituting the Thanksgiving Mystery         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            رسم سر الشكر:         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord Christ instituted the Mystery of the Holy Eucharist [the Lord’s Supper]: “The bread of God is He who comes down from heaven and gives life to the world” (Jn 6:33)—His holy Body and precious Blood—replacing the symbol with the essence it resembles. He entrusted to His disciples a New Covenant, instead of the Old Covenant, as the Evangelists described in their accounts of the Holy Gospel: “And as they were eating (the Passover), Jesus took bread, blessed and broke it, and gave it to them and said… ‘Take, eat; this is My body which is broken for you; do this in remembrance of Me.’ … Likewise He also took the cup after supper, saying, ‘This cup is the new covenant in My blood, which is shed for you’” (Mk 14:22–25, 1 Cor 11:24-25, Lk 22:20). This is besides the first cup mentioned by St. Luke: “Then He took the cup, and gave thanks, and said, ‘Take this and divide it among yourselves; for I say to you, I will not drink of the fruit of the vine until the kingdom of God comes’” (Lk 22:17-18). The first meal and drink were the Passover supper, but the second bread and cup are the New Covenant that is given for the remission of sins.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثم رسم لهم العشاء الربانى وهو الخبز النازل من السماء الواهب حياة للعالم (يو6: 33). أى جسده المقدس ودمه الكريم، حيث أبطل أمامم الرمز، وأشار لهم إلى المرموز اليه. بل قد سلمه لهم عوضاً عنه عهداً جديداً غير العهد الاول. كما يوضح الانجيليون ذلك فى أناجيلهم قائلين، وفيما هم يأكلون -أى يأكلون الفصح- أخذ يسوع خبزاً وبارك وكسر وأعطاهم قائلاً: "خذوا كلوا هذا هو جسدي الذى يبذل عنكم إصنعوا هذا لذكرى. وكذلك الكأس أيضاً بعد العشاء قائلاً هذه الكأس هى العهد الجديد بدمى الذى يسفك عنكم، وهذه غير الكأس الأولى التى قال عنها لوقا (مر14: 22-25)، (لو22: 20)، (1كو11: 24-25). ثم تناول كأساً وشكر وقال "خذوا هذه واقتسموها بينكم لانى أقول لكم إننى لا أشرب من نتاج الكرمة حتى يأتى ملكوت الله (لو22: 17-18). فالأكل الاول والكأس الاولى هما "عشاء الفصح". أما الخبز الثانى والكأس الثانية فهما "العهد الجديد" الذي يُعطى لمغفرة الخطايا.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            After the Passover supper, the Lord’s Supper [Holy Eucharist], and transmitting to the disciples this great Mystery, He foretold and emphasized Peter’s trice denial of Him. Then, He arose with His disciples and crossed over and entered the Kidron Valley where He prayed strenuously to the point that His sweat fell to the ground like great drops of blood, and an angel appeared to Him from heaven strengthening Him (Lk 22:43–44), saying, “Thine is the power, the glory, the blessing, and the majesty, O Immanuel our God and King.” This is the only Church hymn chanted during Holy Week.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثم بعد العشاء الفصحى وتناول العشاء الرباني و تسليم التلاميذ هذا السر العظيم، أنبأ له المجد بإنكار بطرس إياه الثلاث المرات، وأكد ذلك، ثم قام وذهب الى عبر وادى قدرون حيث دخل هو وتلاميذه، وهناك صلي بجهاد عظيم، حتى كان عرقه يتصبب كقطرات دم على الارض. وقد ظهر للسيد المسيح ملاك من السماء يقويه (لو22: 43-44) قائلاً له "لك القوة، لك المجد، لك البركة، لك العزة يا عمانوئيل الهنا وملكنا". وهى ترنيمة الكنيسة الوحيدة أيام أسبوع الآلام.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Evidence of the Changing of the Bread and Wine         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أدلة إستحالة الخبز والخمر:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord’s body and blood, which He handed to His disciples on that night, are His holy body and blood appearing as bread and wine. This is clearly evident to us from the following:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أما جسد الرب ودمه اللذان سلمهما لتلاميذه فى تلك الليلة، فهما جسده ودمه الأقدسين تحت أعراض الخبز والخمر، وهذا يتبرهن لنا جلياً فى الآتى:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            1)      From the Lord Christ’s own words, when He told the Jews, “‘Moses gave your fathers bread in the wilderness, so they ate and are dead, yet My Father gives you the true Bread from heaven. The bread of God comes down from heaven and gives life of the world.’ They said to Him, “Master, give us this bread continually.’ Jesus said to them, ‘I Am the bread of life. Whoever comes to Me will not hunger, and whoever believes in Me will never thirst. I Am the living bread coming down from heaven. If anyone eats of this bread, he will live forever. The bread that I give is My Body, which I shed for the life of the world. Whoever eats My flesh and drinks My blood has eternal life, and I will raise him up at the last day. For My flesh is food indeed, and My blood is drink indeed. He who eats My flesh and drinks My blood abides in Me, and I in him… he who feeds on Me will live because of Me’” (Cf. Jn 6:32-57).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أولاً: من أقوال الرب يسوع نفسه، حيث قال لليهود "إن موسى أعطى أبائكم الخبز فى البرية فأكلوه وماتوا، ولكن أبى يعطيكم الخبز الحقيقى من السماء، لأن خبز الله هو النازل من السماء الواهب الحياة الى للعالم، فقالوا له يا سيد أعطنا فى كل حين هذا الخبز، فقال لهم يسوع أنا هو خبز الحياة، من يقبل الىَّ فلا يجوع ومن يؤمن بى فلا يعطش إبداً، أنا هو الخبز الحى الذى نزل من السماء، إن أكل أحد من هذا الخبز يحيا الى الأبد، والخبز الذى أنا أعطى هو جسدى الذى أبذله من أجل حياة العالم، من يأكل جسدى ويشرب دمى فله حياة أبدية وأنا أقيمه فى اليوم الأخير، لأن جسدى مأكل حق ودمى مشرب حق، من يأكل جسدى ويشرب دمى يثبت فىَّ وأنا فيه، من يأكلنى يحيا بى" (يو 6: 32-57).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            2)      His words to them as He handed them the New Covenant saying, “This is My body which is given for you… This cup is… My blood, which is shed for you” (Lk 22:19,20).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثانياً: من قوله لهم عند تسليمه إياهم للعهد الجديد حيث صرخ لهم قائلاً "هذا هو جسدى الذى يبذل عنكم وهذا هو دمى الذى يسفك من أجلكم (لو22: 19-20).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            3)      The words of the Holy Spirit on the mouth of our teacher Paul the Apostle: “For he who eats and drinks in an unworthy manner eats and drinks judgment to himself, not discerning the Lord’s body... [being] guilty of the body and blood of the Lord” (1 Cor 11:29, 27).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثالثاً: ما قاله الروح القدس على لسان معلمنا بولس الرسول، من حيث من يأكل ويشرب بدون إستحقاق يأكل ويشرب دينونة لنفسه غير مميز جسد الرب، ثم قال أيضاً يكون مجرماً فى جسد الرب ودمه (1كو11: 27، 29).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Leavened Bread         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الخبز المختمر:         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Just as the Lord Christ used, and as the Evangelists mention that He took leavened bread (Artos in Greek), the Body must also be of leavened bread made of pure wheat. The apostles also used leavened bread, as is witnessed in the Book of Acts (Act 2:42,46; 20:7,11, 27:35; 1 Cor 10:16–17, 11:23-27), where bread is mentioned, but not once is unleavened bread mentioned. The Holy Orthodox Church followed through in upholding this standard of using leavened bread in this Holy Mystery.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويشترط أن يكون الجسد من خبز مختمر، مصنوع من القمح النقى. كما إستعمله الرب يسوع نفسه حيث يقول الانجيليون أخذ خبزاً، (أرطوس باليونانية أى خبز مختمر)، وقد إستعمله الرسل أيضاً بدليل ما جاء فى سفر الاعمال (أع2: 42، 46)، (أع20: 7، 11)، (أع27: 35)، (1كو10: 16-17)، (1كو11: 23-27)، حيث يذكر خبزاً ولم يذكر ولا مرة واحدة كلمة فطير. وعلى هذا المثال صارت الكنيسة الارثوذكسية المقدسة تمارس هذا السر بالخبز المختمر.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The blood also must be from pure grape juice, in order to resemble the shed Blood of the Lord Christ. This was prophesied by Jacob the Patriarch (being inspired by the Holy Spirit) concerning his son, Judah (from whose tribe the Lord descended): “He washed his garments in wine, and his clothes in the blood of grapes” (Gen 49:11).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أما الدم فيجب أن يكون من عصير العنب الخالص لكى يكون مماثلا لدم السيد المسيح المسفوك. كما تنبأ يعقوب أبو الآباء بالروح القدس عن يهوذا إبنه الذي طلع الرب من سبطه "غسل بالخمر لباسه وبدم العنب ثوبه"(تك 49: 11).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            During the Divine Liturgy, the wine is mixed with water, as the Lord also mixed the wine during the Passover, as well as to commemorate the blood and water that flowed from the Redeemer’s side on the cross (Jn 19:34). The Holy Spirit uttered of old, on the tongue of Solomon in his Proverbs concerning the Church: “She has slaughtered her meat, she has mixed her wine, she has also furnished her table” (Prov 9:2).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثم يمزج الخمر عند الخدمة بالماء كما فعل السيد له المجد، وذلك كتذكار للدم والماء اللذين قد خرجا من جنب الفادى وهو علي الصليب (يو19: 34) ، وقد نطق الروح القدس قديماً على لسان سليمان فى أمثاله عن الكنيسة قائلاً: "ذبحت ذبحها ومزجت خمرها، أيضاً رتبت مائدتها"(أم 9: 2).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Labeling the Mystery a Sacrifice         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تسمية السر ذبيحة:         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            This Mystery is called a “Holy Sacrifice,” because it is the sacrificed body of the Lord Christ and His shed blood, since the Lord Christ became a sacrifice for us. He clearly stated that His body, which is sacrificed for the life of the world, is this bread (Jn 6:51), and His blood, which is shed for us, is this wine (Mt 26:28; Mk 14:24; Lk 22:20). As He became the Lamb of God who was sacrificed, and purchased us with His blood to God His Father, taught us to commemorate Him, teaching us this great Mystery. Therefore, when we observe it, we call it a Sacrifice. What is better than the words of St. Paul in his epistle to the Corinthians, when he said, “Observe Israel after the flesh: Are not those who eat of the sacrifices partakers of the altar? What am I saying then? That an idol is anything, or what is offered to idols is anything? Rather, that the things which the Gentiles sacrifice they sacrifice to demons and not to God, and I do not want you to have fellowship with demons. You cannot drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of demons; you cannot partake of the Lord’s table and of the table of demons” (1 Cor 10:18-21). In these verses, the apostle compares the table of the Lord, the Christian altar, with the table of the Gentiles and the altar of demons. Thus, he confirms that what is offered on the Christian altar in the Divine Eucharistic Mystery is a true Sacrifice before God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يسمى هذا السر "ذبيحة مقدسة" لأنه جسد السيد المسيح المبذول ودمه المسفوك حيث أن السيد المسيح صار ذبيحة عنا. وقد وضح لنا بصريح العبارة أن جسده الذى سيبذله عن حياة العالم هو هذا الخبز (يو6: 51)، وأن دمه الذى سيسفكه عنا هو هذا الخمر (مت 26: 28)، (مر 14: 24)، (لو22: 20)، وكما صار هو حمل الله الذي ذبح وإشترانا بدمه لله أبيه ، وعلمنا أن نصنع ذكره يعلمنا هذا السر المقدس، فاذاً عندما نباشر تتميمه ندعوه ذبيحة، وما أحسن ما نطق به بولس الرسول فى رسالته لأهل كورنثوس حيث قال "إنظروا إسرائيل حسب الجسد أليس الذين يأكلون الذبائح هم شركاء المذبح فماذا أقول أأن الوثن شئ أو ان ماذُبح للوثن شئ، بل أن ما يذبحه الأمم إنما يذبحونه للشياطين لا لله، فلست أريد أن تكونوا أنتم شركاء الشياطين، لا تقدرون أن تشربوا كأس الرب وكأس شياطين، ولا تقدرون أن تشتركوا فى مائدة الرب ومائدة شياطين" (1كو 10: 18-21)، ففى هذه الآية يقابل الرسول مائدة الرب أي مذبح المسيحيين بمائدة الأمم ومذبح الشياطين، وبذلك يؤكد إن ما يقدم على مذبح المسيحيين فى سر الشكر الإلهى هو ذبيحة حقيقية أمام الله.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Benefits of Communicating         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فوائد تناوله         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As for the benefits reaped by the believers who communicate this Mystery worthily, they are very many:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أما الفوائد التى ينالها المؤمنون بتناولهم من هذا السر باستحقاق فهي كثيرة جداً منها:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            1)      It binds those who communicate to the Lord intimately, making them one flesh and one spirit with Christ, in accordance with our Savior’s words, “He who eats My flesh and drinks My blood abides in Me, and I in him” (Jn 6:56). Through it, the words of the apostle are fulfilled, “for we are members of His body, of His flesh and of His bones” (Eph 5:30), and, “partakers of the divine nature” (2 Pet 1:4).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أولاً: أنها تربط المشتركين فيه مع الرب إرتباطاً وطيداً، وتُصيرهم جسداً وروحاً واحداً فى المسيح طبقاً لقول مخلصنا له المجد "من يأكل جسدى ويشرب دمى يثبت فى وأنا فيه"(يو6: 56). فاذاً به يتم قول الرسول "نصير أعضاء جسمه من لحمه ومن عظامه" (أف 5: 30) ونصير شركاء الطبيعة الالهية (2بط 1: 4).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            2)      Divine fellowship nourishes our bodies and souls, strengthens our faith in the Lord, and advances us in Christian perfection and growth in the spiritual life, as the Lord Christ said, “For My flesh is food indeed, and My blood is drink indeed… As the living Father sent me, and I live because of my Father, so he who feeds on Me will live because of Me” (Jn 6:55,57). The Fathers of the Church teach that the Eucharistic Mystery nourishes the body and soul together; it strengthens them, gives them life, heals them of every weakness, raises them from sin, sanctifies them, purifies from all filthiness, and makes them immoveable and undefeatable in their spiritual struggle for piety, righteousness, and goodness.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثانياً: إن الشركة الالهية تُغذى أجسادنا ونفوسنا، وتوطد إيماننا فى الرب، وتقدمنا فى الكمال المسيحى والنمو فى الحياة الروحية، كما قال السيد المسيح "لأن جسدي مأكل حق ودمى مشرب حق.. كما أرسلنى الآب الحى وأنا حىّ بالآب فمن يأكلنى يحيا بى" (يو6: 55، 57).يُعلَّم آباء الكنيسة بأن سر الشكر هو يُغذى الروح والجسد معاً، ويقويهما ويحييهما ويشفيهما من كل ضعف، ويقيمهما من الخطايا، و يقدسهما ويُطهرهما من كل دنس، ويجعلهما غير متزعزعين ولا مغلوبين فى جهادهما الروحى فى سبيل التقوى والبر والصلاح.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            3)      Divine fellowship serves as a token to our forthcoming resurrection and eternal bliss, as our Savior said, “Whoever eats My flesh and drinks My blood has eternal life, and I will raise him up at the last day” (Jn 6:54), and “If anyone eats of this bread, he will live forever” (Jn 6:51). Ultimately, it is remedy against death, and steadfastness in eternal life through Jesus Christ. Our bodies, after partaking of the Divine Mystery are no longer corruptible, but have the hope of resurrection to eternal life.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثالثاً: تكون الشركة الالهية بمثابة عربون لقيامتنا المستقبلة وللغبطة الأبدية، كما قال مخلصنا "من يأكل جسدى ويشرب دمي فله حياة أبدية وأنا أقيمه فى اليوم الاخير" (يو6: 54). وأيضاً "إن أكل أحد من هذا الخبز يحيا إلى الأبد" (يو6: 51). وقد قال الآباء القديسون أيضاً عن سر الشكر إنه دواء لعدم الموت، وتثبيت للحيوة الأبدية بيسوع المسيح، وأن أجسادنا بعد إشتراكها بالسر الإلهى لا تبقى فاسدة، بل تكون لها رجاء القيامة للحياة الأبدية.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            True body and blood         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            جسد ودم حقيقيان:         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Protestant reformer, Martin Luther, thought that the bread remains bread, but within it, through faith, is the body of Christ; and the wine remains wine, but within it, through faith, is the blood of Christ. So, we eat bread and drink wine, but by faith, we eat and drink the body and blood of Christ.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إعتقد لوثيرس (وهو مارتن لوثر مؤسس البروتستانتية) أن الخبز يبقى خبزاً، ولكن داخله بالإيمان جسد السيد المسيح. والخمر يبقى خمراً، ولكن داخله بالايمان دم المسيح، فنأكل ونشرب خبزاً وخمراً ولكن بالإيمان نأكل ونشرب جسد ودم السيد المسيح.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Some others thought that the bread is only bread and the wine is only wine, without change or transformation; they are simply an indication of the body and blood of Christ.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قد اعتقد البعض أن الخبز هو خبز فقط والخمر هو خمر فقط بدون تغير ولا استحالة بل أن ذلك يشير فقط إلى جسد المسيح ودمه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Holy Orthodox Church and all the ancient churches, however, believed that they are Christ’s true body and blood, saying that this is the body that He took from the Virgin Mary, was crucified on the cross, and is in heaven. The Church supports and affirms this faith with strong evidence from the Holy Bible, even from the Lord Christ’s own words, “the bread that I shall give is My flesh, which I shall give for the life of the world” (Jn 6:51). This is the same bread that He promised and called His body.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أما الكنيسة الارثوذكسية المقدسة وجميع الكنائس القديمة تؤمن أنهما جسد المسيح ودمه الحقيقيان. وتقول انه هو الجسد الذي أخذه من مريم العذراء، وهو الذى صلب على الصليب، وهو الذي فى السماء. وتعزز معتقدها هذا وتثبته ببراهن قوية من الكتاب المقدس. ومن قول السيد المسيح نفسه "الخبز الذى أُعطى هو جسدى الذى أبذله لأجل خلاص العالم" (يو6: 51) وهو عين الخبز الذى وعد به هكذا وسماه جسده.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Figurative, Illustrative, and Symbolic Errors         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            خطأ المجاز والمثال والرمز:         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            If the Master’s words, “This is My body… this is My blood,” were figurative or symbolic, He would not have said the operative word, “This is My body… this is My blood.” This is supported by the words of inspiration by the mouth of St. Paul: “The Lord Jesus on the same night in which He was betrayed took bread; and when He had given thanks, He broke it and said, ‘Take, eat; this is My body which is broken for you’” (1 Cor 11: 23–24). This evinces that this Mystery is truly the Lord Christ’s body and blood, not simply a commemorative symbol, but authentic, according to His own words, “For My flesh is food indeed, and My blood is drink indeed. He who eats My flesh and drinks My blood abides in Me, and I in him” (Jn 6:55–56).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فلو كان قول السيد "هذا هو جسدي وهذا هو دمي" هو قول مَثَلى أو رمزي لما كان يقول تلك الكلمة الفعالة "هذا هو جسدى، وهذا هو دمى" ويؤيد ذلك ما نطق به الوحى على لسان بولس الرسول "إن الرب يسوع في الليلة التى أُسلِمَ فيها، أخذ خبزاً وشكر فكسر وقال خذوا كلوا هذا هو جسدى المكسور لأجلكم" (1كو11: 23، 24). ولذلك تحقق بأجلي بيان أن هذا السر هو جسد السيد المسيح ودمه وليس هما مجرد تذكار بل هما حقيقيان كقوله –له المجد- "لان جسدى مأكل حق ودمى مشرب حق" (يو6 : 55)، فهو ليس مجازى "من يأكل جسدى ويشرب دمى يثبت فى وأنا فيه" (يو 6: 56).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Apostle Paul demonstrated the importance of this Mystery, and warns those who approach it unworthily: “Therefore whoever eats this bread or drinks this cup of the Lord in an unworthy manner will be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord” (1 Cor 11:27). He continued, “For he who eats and drinks in an unworthy manner eats and drinks judgment to himself, not discerning the Lord’s body” (1 Cor 11:29). Is it reasonable for a person to convey such detrimental threats and warnings over eating bread and drinking wine? Would God’s justice cast His creation into condemnation, denunciation, and retribution for eating bread and drinking wine? Would God make us equivalent to the deceived, and equate the condemnation of the bread and wine with the condemnation of those who crucified Him? Would God give us a pebble and demand of us a pearl, and equate the value of His precious body and blood with the value of the bread and wine which God made for the sustenance of humans? There are two issues here: either the bread is Christ’s pure body, and the wine His precious blood, in this case, the terrible threats and severe warnings are in place; or, the bread remains simply bread and the wine remains simply wine. Does God’s justice decree for the faithful to be denounced and suffer the judgment of retribution for simple bread and wine? All the evidence provided shows that it was never mentioned in the Holy Bible that the bread and wine would be a representation, a sign, or a symbol of the holy body and blood of Christ, to whom is due all glory and honor from now and forever. Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد برهن الرسول على أهمية هذا السر ويحذر الذين يتقدمون اليه بغير استحقاق قائلاً " أى من أكل هذا الخبز أو شرب كأس الرب بدون استحقاق يكون مجرماً فى جسد الرب ودمه" (1كو 11: 27). وأردف الكلام قائلا "من يأكل ويشرب بدون استحقاق يأكل ويشرب دينونة لنفسه غير مميز جسد الرب ودمه" (1كو11: 27-29). وهل من عاقل يقول أن مثل هذه التهديدات والتحذيرات الشديدة هى لاجل أكل خبز وشرب خمر؟ أفعدل الله يقتضى هكذا أن يرمى خليقتة في الدينونة والشجب والقصاص لأجل أكل الخبز وشرب خمر. أفيجعلنا الله مساوين للصالبين ويعادل دينونة الخبز والخمر بدينونة من صلبوه؟ وهل يعطينا الله حصاة ويطالبنا بلؤلؤة، ويعادل قيمة جسده ودمه الكريمين بقيمة الخبز والخمر اللذين جعلهما الله قوتاً للإنسان. فالمسألة صارت تحت أمرين أما أن يكون الخبز جسد المسيح الطاهر والخمر دمه الكريم. وحينذاك يكون موقع التهديدات الرهيبة والتحذيرات الشديدة فى محلها. وأما أن يكون الخبز لم يزل خبزاً والخمر خمراً على بساطتهما. فعدل الله لا يقتضى أن يشجب مؤمنيه ويوقعهم فى دينونة القصاص لأجل خبز وخمر بسيطين، فمما تقدم عن البراهين التى أوردناها تبين لنا أنه لم يَرد مطلقاً فى الكتاب المقدس أن الخبز والخمر يكونان إشارة أو علامة أو رمز على جسد ودم المسيح الاقدسين الذى له المجد والكرامة من الآن والى الأبد أمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>   </Document>