<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Title>      <Language id="English">         Holy Passion Week: Tuesday      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         بيان يوم الثلاثاء من البصخة المقدسة      </Language>   </Title>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            The Master Teaches in the Temple         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تعليم المخلص فى الهيكل         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            On Tuesday morning, the Lord Jesus Christ, to whom is due all glory, returned from Bethany to the city of Jerusalem. When His disciples were amazed (Mt 21:20; Mk 11:20-23), seeing that the fig tree which He had cursed had withered, He spoke to them about faith (Mk 11:24). Upon entering the temple that day, the Pharisees cunningly asked Jesus by what authority He does these things and who gave Him this authority. In His reply, He spoke of the baptism of John (Mt 21:23–27; Mk 11:27–33; Lk 20:1–8), the parable of the two sons (Mt 21:28–32), the parable of the evil vinedressers (Mt 21:33–46), and the parable of the king’s son’s wedding (Mt 22:1–14). The Pharisees then proceeded to challenge Him, and so, asked if it was right to pay taxes to Caesar (Mt 22:15–22), the Sadducees asked about resurrection, and the lawyer inquired about the first commandment (Mt 22:23–40). In return, Jesus asked the Pharisees about their conviction of Him, and in so doing exposed their hypocrisy (Mt 22:41–46). He warned the people and the disciples of the hypocrisy of the lawyers and Pharisees (Mk 12:38–40), pronounced the woes on the scribes and Pharisees, and cried over Jerusalem (Mt 23:13–39). He then praised the poor widow who cast into the treasury the two mites, which were her whole livelihood (Mk 12:41–44).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فلما رجع السيد المسيح -له المجد- من بيت عنيا في صباح يوم الثلاثاء إلى المدينة ورأى التلاميذ أن التينة التى لعنها قد يبست فتعجبوا (مت21 :20)، (مر11: 20-23)، فكلمهم عن الإيمان (مر11: 24)، وحينما دخل ربنا يسوع الهيكل سأله الفريسيون بمكر، بأى سلطان تفعل هذا ومن أعطاك هذا السلطان؟ فأجابهم على سؤالهم قائلا لهم عن معمودية يوحنا (مت 21: 23–27)، (مر11 : 27 –33)، (لو20 :1 –8)، ثم ضرب لهم مثل الإبنين (مت21: 28–32)، ومثل الكرامين الأشرار ( مت21 : 33-46)، ومثل عرس إبن الملك (مت22 :1-14)، وبعدئذ سأله الفريسيون عن جواز إعطاء الجزية لقيصر (مت 22 :15-22)، كما سأله الصدوقيون عن القيامة، كما سأله ناموسي عن الوصية العظمي (مت22 : 23-40)، ثم سأل السيد المسيح الفريسيون عن إعتقادهم فيه وأظهر لهم رياءهم (مت22: 41-46). ثم حذر الجموع وتلاميذه من خبث الكتبة والفريسيين(مر12 : 38-40). ثم أعطى الويل للكتبة والفريسيين ورثى أورشليم (مت23 : 13-39). ثم مدح الأرملة المسكينة التى ألقت فى الخزانة الفلسين وكانا كل ما تمتلك (مر12: 41-44).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When the Greeks asked to see Him, He spoke briefly to the multitudes, and then left the temple. While He was leaving, His disciples pointed out the magnificence and grandeur of the temple buildings, which led Him to reveal to them the prophecy concerning the destruction of the temple and their persecution by the Jews, and then, He cried over Jerusalem and her pending destruction (Jn 12:20–26; Mt 24:1–14).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثم طلب أُناس يونانيون أن يروه، وبعدها تكلم قليلا مع الجمع ثم ترك الهيكل، وفيما هو خارج منه أشار تلاميذه إلى فخامة وعظمة أبنية الهيكل، فأنبأهم بخرابه وإضطهاد اليهود لهم، إذ رثى أورشليم لأجل خرابها (يو12 :20- 26)، (مت24: 1-14).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When He went up to the Mount of Olives, He sat down and began to explain to Peter, James, John, and Andrew the chronological order of events and to take heed of the signs of His coming: the destruction of Jerusalem, the toppling of the Jewish nation and organization (Mt 24:15–44; Mk 13:1–23), and His Second Coming on Judgment Day. He also cautioned them to keep watch (Mt 24:45–51), teaching them from the parables of the ten virgins and of the ten talents—all this was on Mount Olivet (Mt 25:1–30).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما صعد إلى جبل الزيتون جلس هناك وإبتدأ يشرح لبطرس ويعقوب ويوحنا واندراوس ترتيب الأحداث وعلامات مجيئه، وخراب أورشليم، ونهاية الامة اليهودية، وزوال نظامها (مت24: 15-44)، (مر13: 1-23)، ومجيئه الأخير فى يوم الدينونة، والحث علي السهر (مت24: 45-51)، ومثل العشر عذارى، ومثل الوزنات، وكان ذلك على جبل الزيتون (مت25: 1-30).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When He had finished saying these things, He told His disciples that after two days would be the feast, and the Son of Man would be delivered up to be crucified (Mt 25:31–46). At the day’s end, He went to Bethany to rest, and on this evening, the Jewish leaders plotted to kill Him (Mt 26:1–16).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما أكملَ يسوع هذه الأقوال كلها قال لتلاميذه إنه بعد يومين يكون الفصح وابن الانسان يُسَلَّم ليُصلب (مت25: 31-46)، ثم مضى إلى بيت عنيا ليستريح فيه، وفى هذا المساء تشاور رؤساء اليهود علي قتله (مت26: 1-16).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            The Temple         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بناء الهيكل:         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            It might be a good idea to insert here a brief historic summary on the construction and subsequent destruction of the temple. Solomon built the first temple in 1005 BC “on the second day of the second month in the fourth year of his reign… at Jerusalem’s Mount Moriah, where the Lord had appeared to his father David, at the place that David had prepared on the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite” (2 Chr 3:2,1). There, he built a high wall, from the heart of the Valley of Jehoshaphat to the peak of the mountain, and filled the expanse between the dome and the wall with earth and stones.[4] Josephus the historian says that some of those stones were 45 feet high, six feet wide, and five feet deep,[5] and that the biggest stones were on the eastern side.[6] Solomon decorated all the rooms, floors, corridors, pillars, and gates that he built in the temple, overlaying them with gold and silver; one being of Corinthian brass.[7] Overall, “he decorated the house with precious stones for beauty (2 Chr 3:6). It took seven and half years to build (1 Kg 6:38), using in its construction 183,300 workers: 30,000 Jews (serving in rotations of 10,000 per month), and 153,300 Canaanites (70,000 carried stones, timber, and other materials, while 80,000 were sculptors and carpenters, plus the 3,300 overseers) (1 Kg 5:13–17).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويحسُن بنا أن نُشير هنا في عجالة تاريخية الى بناء الهيكل وهدمه، وها هى: بنى "سليمان" الهيكل الأول سنة 1005 قبل الميلاد فى اليوم الثاني من الشهر الثانى من السنة الرابعة لملكه فى أورشليم، فى "جبل المريا" حيث تراءى الرب لداود أبيه. حيث هيأ مكاناً فى "بيدر ارنان اليبوسى" (2أخ3 :1-2)، فأقام جدراناً عالية من بطن "وادى يهوشافاط" إلى قمة الجبل وملأ الفراغ الكائن بين القبة والجدران بالتراب والحجارة[4]. وقال يوسيفوس المؤرخ انه كان طول بعض تلك الحجارة خمساً وأربعين قدماً، وعرضها ستةً أقدام، وسُمكها خمسة أقدام[5]، وان أكبر حجارة فىه موضوعة في الجانب الشرقى[6]. وزين "سليمان" كل ما بناه بالهيكل من غرف ودور وأروقة وأعمدة و أبواب، وكانت هذه جميلة مغشاة بالفضة والذهب وأحدها من النحاس الكرنتى[7]. وبالإجمال فأنه كان قد رصع البيت بحجارة كريمة بهية الجمال (2أخ3 : 6)، وإستمر بنائه مدة سبع سنوات ونصف (1مل6 : 38)، وقد إستخدم في عملية بنائه 183300 شخصاً: منهم 30000 من اليهود وكانوا يخدمون بالدور 10000 كل شهر، ومنهم 153300 من الكنعانيين، فتعين منهم 70000 لحمل الحجارة والاخشاب وغيرها، و 80000 من النحاتين والنجارين، و 3300 ناظراً (1مل5 : 13-17).         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [4] Josephus, F., &amp; Whiston, W. (1996). The Works of Josephus : Complete and Unabridged. Peabody: Hendrickson. The War of the Jews or The History of the Destruction of Jerusalem, 1651.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [5] Ibid, 1655.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [6] Ibid, 1653.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [7] Ibid.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The work was done at a remote construction site, “so that no hammer or chisel or any iron tool was heard in the temple while it was being built” (1 Kg 6:7). The front of the temple was eastward. Behind this was a slightly lower structure flanked by little houses that were entered from the outside.[8] Above them were houses overlaid with gold, which were exclusively reserved for the priests (1 Kg 6:8). Solomon’s Temple stood for 424 years until it was destroyed by Nebuchadnezzar in 584 BC (2 Chr 36:6–7). Zerubbabel built the second temple (Ezra 3:2) on the same site of the first temple, 70 years after its destruction. It was inferior to the first temple in decoration and beauty: It did not have the Ark of the Covenant, which had been lost in the captivity, the cloud of glory did not appear in it, there were no Cherubim of glory, Urim or Thumim, or spirit of prophecy, and yet, it did exceed the first temple in glory and honor, because the Lord Christ had entered it (Hag 2:3,9).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان العمل يتم علي بعد من مكان البناء "فلم يُسمَع فى البيت عند بنائه منحت ولا معول ولا أداة حديد" (1مل 7:6)، وقد كانت مقدمة الهيكل نحو الشرق، ومن خلفه بناء يقل عنه ارتفاعاً. وكان على جانبى هذا البناء غرف صغيرة يُدخَل إليها من الخارج[8] ، وفوقها غرف مغشاة بالذهب لا يُسمح لإحد إلا للكهنة فقط أن يصعدوا إليها (1مل 6: 8). وكان قد بقى هيكل سليمان 424 سنة الي أن هدمه نبوخذ ناصر سنة 584 قبل الميلاد (2أخ36 : 6- 7). أما الهيكل الثانى (عز3: 2) فكان قد بناه زربابل مكان الهيكل الأول بعد سبعين سنة من هدمه، ولكنه لم يكن مثل الهيكل الأول فى الزينة والبهاء، ولم يكن فيه تابوت العهد اذ كان قد فُقدَ فى السبي، ولم تظهر فيه سحابة المجد، ولم يكن فيه كاروبا المجد، ولا الأوريم ولا التميم ولا روح النبوة، مع ذلك فأنه قد فاق الأول مجداً وكرامة لدخول السيد المسيح فيه(حج 2: 3،9).         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [8] Ibid, 1654.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Often, the kings of the nations who reigned over Jerusalem defiled this temple and vandalized parts of it. Herod the Great, however, renovated and repaired it to win the hearts of the Jews. He began this in the 18th year of his reign, in 20 BC. He employed in its renovation about 10,000 skilled builders. His successors continued repairing and remodeling it until the Jews’ words to Christ were true: “It has taken forty-six years to build this temple” (Jn 2:20). The court of the temple was square, with each of its walls being 400 cubits.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان كثيراً ما قد دنس هذا الهيكل ملوك الامم الذين إستولوا علي أورشليم وخربوا منه جانباً. وأخذ هيرودس الكبير يرممه ويصلحه ليستميل اليه قلوب اليهود. وإبتدأ بعمل ذلك فى السنة الثامنة عشر لملكه، وذلك كان قبل الميلاد بعشرين سنة، وشغل فى ترميمه نحو عشرة آلاف من مهرة البنائين، وظل خلفاؤه يصلحونه، حتى صح قول اليهود للسيد المسيح أنه "بُنى فى ست وأربعين سنة " (يو2: 20)، وكانت فسحة الهيكل مربعة عرض كل من جدرانها أربعمائة ذراع.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Four Courts in that Temple         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان فى ذلك الهيكل أربع ديارات         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The first court was for the Gentiles and on its eastern side is the gate of the temple, which is called Beautiful (Acts 3:2,10). It is surrounded by porches and on the sides are houses, dwellings of the Levites. In one of those side houses was a synagogue or school for Jewish scholars. In that school sat Jesus when He was twelve years old, amid the scholars, listening to them and asking them questions (Lk 2:46). On those porches, Jesus spoke to the people. On them, the disciples gathered every day after His ascension (Acts 2:46). One of these porches gained more fame than others—Solomon’s Porch (Acts 3:11). The height of this porch was 700 feet, and this is where the devil tempted Christ to throw Himself down from its peak (Mt 4:6). In that very court were tables for money changers and those who sold doves. It was called the court of the Gentiles because non-Jews were not allowed to venture beyond this point.[9] In Solomon’s Temple, there was no court of the Gentiles; it only had the court of the priests and the great court (2 Chr 4:9).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الدار الاولى: "دار الأمم" وفي الجانب الشرقى من هذه الدار باب الهيكل الجميل (أع3: 2، 10)، ويحيط بها أروقه على جوانبها غرف لسكن اللاويين. فى أحد تلك الجوانب مجمع أو مدرسة لعلماء الهيكل، وفى تلك المدرسة جلس ربنا يسوع وهو إبن اثنتى عشرة سنة فى وسط المعلمين يسمعهم ويسألهم (لو2: 46)، وفى تلك الأروقة خاطب ربنا يسوع الشعب، وفيها كان يجتمع التلاميذ كل يوم بعد صعود الرب (أع2: 46)، وإشتهر أحد هذه الاروقة أكثر من غيره بنسبته الي رواق سليمان (أع3: 11)، وكان علو هذا الرواق سبعمائة قدم وهناك جرب الشيطان السيد المسيح بأن يطرح نفسه من سطحه الى أسفل (مت4: 6)، وكان فى تلك الدار موائد للصيارفة وباعة الحمام وأمثالهم. وسميت بدار الأمم لأنه لم يكن لغير اليهود أن يجاوزها الى الداخل[9]. ولم يكن فى هيكل سليمان دار للامم فما كان فيه سوى دار للكهنة والدار العظيمة (2أخ 4: 9).         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            [9] Ibid, 1652.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Second was the court of the women; it was attributed to women not because it is especially for them, but because they are not permitted to venture beyond it inside the temple. They came here to offer their sacrifices.[10] Higher than the first court, it is ascended by nine steps.[11] The two courts were separated by a stone partition one cubit high, and a marble pillar near the steps on which was written a warning in both Greek and Latin to the Gentiles stating that anyone venturing inside would die (Eph 2:13–14).[12] St. Paul was accused of “bringing Greeks into the temple and defiling that holy place” (Cf. Acts 21:28). Jews engaged in regular worship in this court (Lk 18:10-14; Acts 21:26–30), and in its corners were 13 collection boxes for the worshipers to deposit their offerings (Mk 12:41).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الدار الثانية: "دار النساء" ونُسبت الى النساء لا لأنها مختصة بهن بل لأنه لم يسمح لهن أن يتعدينها الى داخل، فكن يأتين اليها فقط ليقدمن القرابين[10]. وهى أعلى من الدار الاولى فكانوا يصعدون اليها بتسع درجات[11]، وفصلوا بين الدارين بجدار من حجر علٌوه ذراع، وأقاموا قرب الدرجات عُمُداً من الرخام كتبوا عليها باليونانية واللاتينية إنذارات للأمم، خلاصتها أن من تجاوزها منهم الى الداخل يُقتل (أف2: 13-14) [12]. وقد إتُهِمَ بولس الرسول إنه أدخل يونانيين الى الهيكل ودنس ذلك الموضع المقدس (إرجع الى أع21: 28). وكان اليهود يمارسون العبادة العادية فى تلك الدار (لو18: 10-14)، (اع21: 26-30)، وكان فى جوانبها ثلاثة عشر صندوقاً يضع العابدون قرابينهم فيها (مر12: 41).         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [10] Ibid, 1542.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [11] Fifteen steps according to Josephus. Ibid, 1652.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [12] Ibid.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Third is the court of Israel, that is, the court for the men of Israel. The great court in Solomon’s Temple included these three courts (2 Chr 4:9). This third court, higher than the court of the women, was ascended by 15 steps.[13] It was separated from it by a cubit high partition which had three gates.[14]         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الدار الثالثة: "دار إسرائيل" أى دار ذكور الإسرائيليين، وكانت الدار العظيمة فى هيكل سليمان تشتمل على هذه الاقسام الثلاثة (2أخ4: 9). بينما كانت دار إسرائيل أرفع من دار النساء، وكانوا يصعدون اليها بخمس عشرة درجة[13]، وفصلوا بينهما بجدار الى لوه ذراع، فيه ثلاثة أبواب.[14]         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [13] Ibid, 1653.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [14] Ibid, 1652.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Fourth is the court of the priests, east of the court of Israel, where the altar of burnt offering and the laver lie. West of this court is the inner sanctuary, which is higher, ascended by 12 steps,[15] and before it was a court facing east which peaks at 190 feet. At its entrance are two pillars; one is called Jachin and the second Boaz (2 Chr 3:17), which divided the court into two sectors.[16] The first section is the Holy, which is 60 feet in length by 20 feet in width, containing the golden candlestick, the table of showbread, and the altar of incense (2 Chr 3:3; 4:19).[17] The second section is the Holy of Holies, a square, each side of which is 20 cubits (2 Chr 3:8). The partition between it and the Holy was a luxurious veil (Mt 27:51).[18] This temple was demolished during Titus’ siege of Jerusalem after the Advent by 70 years, as predicted by the Lord of glory (Mt 24:2). Emperor Julian tried to rebuild it in 363 AD, but his efforts were in vain. He and the Jews were eager for its reconstruction. When they dug into the foundation, severe explosions occurred and fireballs appeared which destroyed the equipment, producing dust and smoke clouds to the point that the place became dark. In their second attempt, they were severely catapulted from the site, such that they abandoned all their equipment and their task despondently.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الدار الرابعة: "دار الكهنة" وهى شرقى "دار إسرائيل"، وفيها مذبح المحرقة والمرحضة، ويوجد غربى هذه الدار الهيكل الحقيقى، وهو أعلى منها، وكانوا يصعدون إليه باثنتى عشرة درجة[15]، وكان قدامه رواق متجه إلى الشرق علو قمته مائة وتسعون قدماً، وفى مدخله عمودان إسم أحدهما ياكين والثانى بوعز (2أخ 3: 17)، وكان قد قُسم إلى قسمين[16]، الاول "القدس" وطوله ستون قدماً وعرضه ثلاثون قدماً وفيه المنارة الذهبية ومائدة خبز الوجوه ومذبح البخور (2أخ 3: 3، 4: 19)[17]، والثانى "قدس الأقداس" وهو مربع طول كل من جوانبه الاربعة ثلاثون قدماً (2أخ 3: 8). وكان الفاصل بينه وبين القدس حجاباً نفيساً (مت27: 51) [18]، وقد هُدِمَ هذا الهيكل في حصار تيطس لأورشليم، بعد الميلاد بسبعين سنة، كما تنبأ عنه السيد له المجد (مت24: 2). إجتهد الإمبراطور يوليانوس أن يعيد بناؤه سنة 363 بعد الميلاد، فذهب إجتهاده هو واليهود باطلاً، الذين كانوا يطوقون لإعادة بنائه، غير أنه لما حفروا الاساس حدثت إنفجارات شديدة وظهرت كرات نارية كسرت أدوات الشغل وثار الغبار والدخان حتى أظلم المكان ولما عاود اليهود العمل فيه ثانياً إندفعوا بقوة غير عادية والقوا جميع أدواتهم تاركين الشغل يائسين.         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [15] Ibid, 1653.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [16] Ibid, 1653.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [17] Ibid, 1654.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [18] Ibid, 1654.         </Language>      </Comment>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Romans Enter and Burn the Holy of Holies with Fire         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            دخول الروم إلي قدس الاقداس ذى العظمة والفخار وإحراقهم إياها بالنار         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            During the war between the Romans and the Jews, Titus ordered his companions and commanders from other nations to surround Jerusalem, besiege it,[20] and constrain the natives who remained, such that they would submit without having to enter into battle. When this was done, and the siege dragged on, the number of Jews who died was greater than those who survived.[21] Some deserted to Titus, who pardoned them.[22] Then the Romans entered the city and into the House of God Almighty, reigned, and possessed it. There was no one to stop them; all the Jews feared the Romans.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لما كانت الحرب قائمة بين الروم واليهود، أمر تيطس أصحابه ومن جاء اليه من الجموع من سائر الامم أن يحيطوا بمدينه أورشليم[20] ويحاصروها ويُضَيقوا على من بقي من أهلها، فيخضعوهم بدون أن يتعرضوا لمحاربتهم، ففعلوا كذلك. فلما طال الحصار على اليهود مات أكثر من تبقى منهم[21]، ثم جاء من هربوا إلى تيطس فقبلهم[22]. ثم دخل الروم إلى المدينة وإلى بيت الله له المجد، فملكوه ولم يبقى من يمنعهم عنه، وأمَّنوا جميع من كانوا يخافونه من اليهود.         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            + Cf. Ibid, Bk 5, Ch 6; Bk 6, Ch 4.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [20] Ibid, 1659.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [21] Ibid, 1670.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [22] Ibid, 1681.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Titus commanded his friends not to burn the temple.[23] Conversely, Roman leaders advised him that if he did not burn the temple, he would not be able to reign over the Jews or subjugate them, for as long as it remained, the fighting would not cease. However, if the temple was burned, the pride of the Jewish nation would also be destroyed and they would not have a reason to fight, for they would be brokenhearted and humiliated. Titus realized this, but still insisted not to burn it until he commanded.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان تيطس قد أوصى أصحابه وأكد عليهم ألا يحرقوا القدس[23]، فقال له رؤساء الروم انك إذا لم تحرقه لا تستطيع أن تملك اليهود ولا أن تقهرهم لانهم لا يفترون ولا يكفون عن القتال لاجله ما دام باقياً، فاذا حرقته ذهب عزمهم و لم يبق لهم مايقاتلون عنه فتنكسر قلوبهم ويذلون. فقال لهم تيطس قد علمت ذلك ولكن على كل حال لاتحرقوه حتى آمركم بحرقه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [23] Ibid, 1729.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The entrance into the temple had a great gate armored with silver plates. It was sealed because the Jews had locked it, yet some Romans came to this gate and smelt it to take its silver. While burning it, they found a way into the temple,[24] seized it, erected their idols, and offered sacrifices to Titus their Caesar. In lifting up their idols to praise him and accept him, they began to curse the temple and boast of Roman greatness. When the remaining Jews learned of this, they could not tolerate it, and a crowd of them went out by night to the Romans who had seized the temple and killed them.[25] When the news reached Titus, he went out with his soldiers to the temple and killed those Jews. The rest fled to Mount Zion and dwelt there.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان الطريق إلى القدس عليه باب عظيم مصفح بصفائح فضية، وكان مغلقاً لان اليهود كانوا قد أغلقوه بإحكام. فجاء بعض الروم الي هذا الباب وأحرقوه ليأخذوا الفضة التى عليه. فلما أحرقوه وجدوا سبيلهم إلى القدس[24]، فدخلوا اليه وتوسطوه، ثم نصبوا أصناهم فيه، وقربوا ذبائحهم لتيطس سيدهم، ورفعوا أصنامهم بمدحه والثناء عليه، ثم أقبلوا يفترون على البيت ويتكلمون بالعظائم. فلما علم من بقى من اليهود ذلك لم يصبروا، فخرج قوم منهم فى الليل إلى الروم الذين فى القدس فقتلوهم[25]، ولما بلغ الخبر إلى "تيطس" جاء بجنوده إلى القدس فقتل أولئك، بينما هرب من بقى منهم إلى جبل صهيون فأقاموا فيه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [24] Ibid, 1730.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [25] Ibid.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The next day, the Romans gathered together and burned the gate to the Holy of Holies, which was fully overlaid with gold plates. When the gates fell, they gave out a great cry, which reached Titus, who came quickly to the Holy of Holies to stop them from burning it. He could not[26] deter them because, in addition to the Romans, many people including other nations were hostile toward the Jews and sought revenge on them. They ignored and overrode Titus, who was shouting at them loudly to stop. It was said that a group of his friends were killed on that day for entering the temple in great wrath, severe anger, and excessive rage. Titus had no control over the situation and could not stop them.[27] It was also said that in his attempt to command obedience, he lost his voice from all the shouting falling on deaf ears.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إجتمع الروم فى اليوم التالى وأحرقوا باب قدس الاقداس وكانت كلها مغشاة بصفائح الذهب، فلما سقطت الأبواب صرخوا صراخاَ عظيماً، فعلم "تيطس" بذلك فجاء مسرعاً إلى قدس الاقداس ليمنعهم من إحراقه فلم يتم له ذلك[26] لأن الناس كثروا وإجتمع فيه خلق كثير من الروم وغيرهم من الامم التى كانت تُعادى اليهود وتطلب التشفى منهم، فغلبوا "تيطس" على رأيه وهو يصرخ بأعلى صوته ليمنعهم. وقيل أنه كان قد قَتَلَ فى ذلك اليوم جماعة من أصحابه، وذلك إنهم دخلوا إلى القدس بحنق عظيم وحدة شديدة وغيظ مفرط، فخرج الامر من يد تيطس ولم يقدر على منعهم[27]. ويُقال أيضاً أنه صاح فى ذلك اليوم إلى أن بحَ صوته، ولم يُسمع كلامه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [26] Ibid.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [27] Ibid, 1731.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When he saw the splendor of the Holy of Holies and took in its magnificence, its serene beauty, and its abundant decoration, he was perplexed and amazed[28] saying that truly this majestic house should be a House of God, the God of heaven and earth, the dwelling of His Majesty, the abode for His light, and the Jews were justified in defending it and dying to preserve it. Nations were depleted, offering their best for this House, honoring it, offering it gifts and money. It is greater than the Roman temple and all the temples we have seen or heard of. God witnesses that this burning was not intended, but people did this out of their excessive evil and adamant nagging.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما رأى قدس الاقداس وشاهد حُسنه وتَفَرس فى عظم بهجته ورائق جماله وكثرة زينته[28]، تحير وتعجب وقال حقاً أن هذا البيت الجليل ينبغى أن يكون بيتاً لله إله السماء والارض ومسكن جلاله ومحل نوره، وأنه يحق لليهود أن يحاربوا عنه ويستقتلوا لاجله. وقد أصابت الامم وأحسنت إعظامها لهذا البيت واجلالها له، وحملها له الهدايا والأموال، وشهد قائلاً أنه أعظم من هياكل رومية ومن جميع الهياكل التى شاهدناها أوبلغنا خبرها، والشاهد علىَّ هو الله إنى لم أشأ إحراقه، ولكن القوم قد فعلوا ذلك من فرط شرهم وعظم الحاحهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [28] Ibid.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The temple caught fire and burned it up, and when the remaining priests received word of the entry of the Romans into the Holy of Holies, they desperately came to fight the Romans until they were drained. When they were overwhelmed from seeing the temple burnt, they said to themselves, “After the Holy of God has been burned, what reason is there to live and what life can we enjoy?” So, they threw themselves into the fire and were all burned.[29] The burning of the temple was on the tenth day of the fifth month, the same day in which the Chaldeans burned the first temple.[30]         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثم اشتعلت النار فى القدس وأحرقته جميعه، وإذ علم من بقى من الكهنه بدخول الروم إلى قدس الاقداس ليحرقوه، جاءوا مستقتلين، فحاربوا الروم إلى أن لم تبق لهم حيلة ولا قدرة على محاربتهم، فلما غُلِبوا علي أمرهم ورأوا أن البيت قد احترق، قالوا إن بعد احتراق قدس الله مالنا وللحياة، وأى عيش يطيب لنا بعد، فزجوا بأنفسهم فى النار فإحترقوا بأجمعهم[29]، وكان حريق القدس في اليوم العاشر من الشهر الخامس. مثل اليوم الذى أحرق فيه الكلدانيون البيت الاول[30].         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [29] Ibid, 1734.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [30] Ibid, 1730.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When the Jews who remained in the city learned that the Holy of Holies had been burned, they went to all of the city’s venerable mansions, palaces, and royal gates and burned them with all their many funds and treasures.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما علم اليهود الذين تبقوا فى المدينة بأن قدس الاقداس قد إحترق مضوا إلى جميع ما فى المدينة من القصور الجليلة والمنازل الحسنة والابواب الملوكية فأحرقوها، مع جميع ما كان فيها من الذخائر الكثيرة العدد والاموال.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The day after the temple was burned, a man among the Jews prophesied saying that this House will be rebuilt without anyone rebuilding it, but by the power of God Almighty, so remain steadfast in your battle against the Romans and your resistance to obey them. When the Jews who remained heard his words, they gathered together and fought against the Romans, but the Romans defeated them and killed all of them,[31] including a large crowd of the Jews whom they had previously pardoned and treated well.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما كان غد اليوم الذى أُحرق فيه القدس، ظهر رجل بين اليهود يدَّعى النبوة قائلاً: إن هذا البيت يُبنى كما كان، من غير أن يبنيه إنسان لكنه يبنى بقدرة الله، فثابروا على ما أنتم عليه من مقاومة الروم والإمتناع عن إطاعتهم. ولما سمع كلامه من بقي من اليهود، إجتمعوا وقاتلوا الروم، فظفر الروم عليهم وقتلوهم عن آخرهم[31]، وقتلوا أيضاً جمعاً كبيراً من أمة اليهود ممن كانوا قبل ذلك قد رحموهم وأحسنوا اليهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [31] Ibid, 1734–1735.         </Language>      </Comment>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Preceding Signs Indicating the Pending Destruction of Jerusalem         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أشياء دلت على خراب القدس         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Before the coming of Titus Vespasian, a great star with a very bright light sufficient to light up Jerusalem—luminous as daylight—appeared over Jerusalem. This lasted throughout the seven-day Passover holiday and then disappeared. To the general public and the simple folk, this star brought great joy, but to the scientists and the scholarly, it brought distress.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كان قبل مجئ "وسباسيانس" قد ظهر على القدس كوكب عظيم له نور قوى شديد، وكان القدس يضئ بذلك الكوكب كضوء النهار تقريباً. وإستمر ذلك مدة سبعة أيام عيد الفصح ثم غاب، ففرح به عامة الناس وجهلائهم، وإغتم العلماء وأهل الفضل والمعرفة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            + Cf. Ibid, 1735–1737.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            On the day of the feast, they had brought to Jerusalem a heifer to offer. When they came to sacrifice it, it gave birth to a sheep—leaving the people appalled and in denial of the event. The eastern gate to Jerusalem—a great heavy gate that required the effort of several men in order to open it, was found open daily on its own, so the simple folks rejoiced while the educated were disturbed. Next, the image of a very handsome, extremely gallant, and exceedingly luminous man appeared in the sky over Jerusalem. In the air in those days, there also appeared images of fiery riders on flaming horses flying close to the ground; this was seen in Jerusalem and in all the lands of the Jews.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكانوا قد احضروا الى القدس فى ذلك العيد بقرة ليقربوا بها، فلما طرحوها ليذبحوها ولدت خروفاً، فأستشنعه الناس وإستنكروه. ومن ذلك أن باب القدس الشرقى كان باباً عظيماً ثقيلاً ولم يكن يقدر أن يفتحه إلا جماعة من الرجال، فلما كان فى تلك الايام كانوا يجدونه كل يوم مفتوحاً، فكان الجهال يفرحون بذلك وأهل العلم والمعرفة يغتمون له. ظهر بعد ذلك على بيت القدس فى الهواء صورة وجه إنسان شديد الحسن عظيم الجمال والبهاء ساطع النور والضياء. وظهر فى الجو أيضاً في تلك الأيام صور فرسان من نار على خيل من نار يطيرون فى الهواء قريباً من الأرض، وكان ذلك يُري على أورشليم وعلى جميع أرض اليهود.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Following all these events, on the eve of the feast of Pentecost, the priests heard the sound of many footsteps pacing back and forth in the temple, but saw no one. Then they heard a loud voice saying, “Come let us leave this place [the temple].”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبعد ذلك سمع الكهنة فى القدس ليلة عيد العنصرة صوت جماعة كثيرة يذهبون ويجيئون ويمشون فى الهيكل من غير أن يروا أشخاصاً، وكانوا يسمعون صوتهم، ثم كانوا يسمعون صوتاً عظيماً يقول إمض بنا حتى نرحل من هذا البيت.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Four years prior to the destruction of Jerusalem, an ordinary man appeared in the city, who walked among the people as a madman crying out loud saying, “A voice from the east, a voice from the west, a voice from the four winds, a voice against Jerusalem and the holy house, a voice against the bridegrooms and the brides, and a voice against this whole people!”[33] The people hated, rebuked, and were weary of him, imagining him a crazy fellow; this continued until the Romans surrounded the city. He was eventually stoned to death as he repeated his words in the midst of the raging battle.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقبل خراب القدس بأربع سنين، ظهر فى المدينة إنسان من العامة كان يمشى بين الناس كالمجنون، ويصيح بأعلى صوته قائلاً: "صوت فى المشرق، صوت في المغرب، صوت فى أربع جهات العالم، صوت على أورشليم، صوت على الهيكل، صوت على الحصن، صوت علي العروس، صوت على جميع الناس الذين بأورشليم"[33]. وكان الناس يمقتونه وينتهرونه ويتصورونه مخبولا، ولم يكن هو يفتر من هذا، فلم يزل على ذلك حتى أحاط الروم بالمدينة. فلما كان فى بعض الأيام والحرب على المدينة إبتدأ أن يتكلم بما كان يتكلم به على عادته فرُمِىَ بحجر على هامته فمات.         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [33] Ibid, 1736.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            In those days also, an old stone was found on which was written, “That then should their city be taken, as well as their holy house, when once their temple should become four-square.”[34] Thereafter, when Titus demolished the tower beside the temple, Antonia in Hebrew, the Jews rebuilt it and added it to the temple, such that it became square.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ووُجِدَ حجر قديم فى ذلك الزمان مكتوباً عليه إذا كمل بنيان القدس وصار مربعاً عند ذلك يَخرُبْ[34]. فلما هدم تيطس البُنيان الذى كان بجانب القدس المسمى بالعبرانيه "أنطونيا"، أعاد اليهود بناؤه، وأضافوه إلى جملة القدس فصارَ مربعاً.         </Language>      </Text>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            [34] Ibid, 1737.         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Although they had forgotten the writing on the stone, when they saw that the temple had become a square, they remembered. Thus, when they found on the side wall of the temple, a stone on which was written, “If the temple becomes a square structure, then a king will rule over Israel and will take over all the land,” some said it would be the king of Israel, while the wise men and the scribes said it would be the king of Rome.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكانوا قد نسوا ذلك المكتوب الذى وجدوه على الحجر. فلما رأوا القدس وقد تربع تذكروا ذلك. ووجدوا أيضاً في جانب حائط قدس الأقداس حجراً مكتوب عليه إذا صار الهيكل مربعاً يملك حينئذ علي إسرائيل ملك ويستولى علي سائر الارض،  فقال بعض الناس هو ملك اسرائيل بينما قال الحكماء والكتبه بل هو ملك الروم.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>