<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Title>      <Language id="English">         Holy Passion Week: Wednesday      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         بيان يوم الإربعاء البصخة المقدسة      </Language>   </Title>      <Text>      <Language id="English">         Our Lord of glory spent this day in Bethany teaching the disciples and assuring them that He would not abandon them. There is no mention in the Holy Bible that Jesus did anything on this day; He sought solitude and isolation from people on this day. He avoided the multitudes, just as the Passover lamb also rested before the day of its slaughter.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         صرف مخلصنا له المجد هذا اليوم فى بيت عنيا. فى تعليم تلاميذه طمأنهم أنه لن يتخلى عنهم ولم يذكر الكتاب إنه عمل شيئاً فى هذا اليوم، ليشير على إنه –رب المجد- قصد الوحدة والإنفراد عن الناس وتجنب الاجتماعيات مثلما كان يستريح خروف الفصح قبل ذبحه فى اليوم المعد له.      </Language>   </Text>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Jesus Leaves the Temple         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يسوع يترك الهيكل         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord Christ left the temple on Tuesday evening and returned to Bethany with the intention of not returning to the temple ever again. This is why He told the Jews, “See! Your house is left to you desolate; for I say to you, you shall see Me no more till you say, ‘Blessed is He who comes in the name of the Lord!’” (Mt 23:38–39). He is the true Lord of the temple, and had revealed this authority by telling those who sold doves, “‘Take these things away! Do not make My Father’s house a house of merchandise!’ Then His disciples remembered that it was written, ‘Zeal for Your house has eaten Me up’” (Jn 2:16–17). He again established this when He entered Jerusalem publicly in a great celebration [Hosanna Sunday] (Mt 21:1–17). Since He was outright rejected and shunned by the Jews and their leaders, He left them and the place. This was to showcase that, “this house, the temple, which was built to honor the Lord and His name is only a place of worship in image and authority, and is not My house. I leave it to you desolate”; this accords with what God had told Solomon: But if you or your sons at all turn from following Me, and do not keep My commandments and My statutes which I have set before you, but go and serve other gods and worship them, then I will cut off Israel from the land which I have given them; and this house which I have consecrated for My name I will cast out of My sight. Israel will be a proverb and a byword among all peoples. And as for this house, which is exalted, everyone who passes by it will be astonished and will hiss, and say, ‘Why has the Lord done thus to this land and to this house?’ Then they will answer, ‘Because they forsook the Lord their God, who brought their fathers out of the land of Egypt, and have embraced other gods, and worshiped them and served them; therefore the Lord has brought all this calamity on them’ (1 Kg 9:6–9).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ترك السيد المسيح له المجد الهيكل عند مساء يوم الثلاثاء ورجع إلى بيت عنيا وفي نيته عدم العودة اليه البتة وذلك بعد أن قال لليهود "هوذا بيتكم يترك لكم خراباً. لاني أقول لكم إنكم لا تروننى من الآن حتى تقولوا مبارك الآتى باسم الرب" (مت 23: 38-39)، مع انه هو الرب الحقيقى للهيكل. وقد بين ذلك بسلطانه عليه قبل هذا بقوله لباعة الحمام "ارفعوا هذه من ههنا لا تجعلوا بيت أبي بيت تجارة فتذكر تلاميذه انه مكتوب غيرة بيتك أكلتنى" (يو2: 16-17)، و قد أثبت ذلك ايضاً عند دخوله أورشليم علانية بالاحتفال العظيم (مت21: 1-17)، ولكن حيث أنه قد رُفِضَ من اليهود رفضاً باتاً وقاطعه الرؤساء فتركهم السيد المسيح له المجد وترك المكان الذى كان قد اختاره الرب ليضع اسمه عليه الى الابد، وكأنه يقول إن البيت هذا الذى كان لى، وأنتم جعلتم العبادة فيه صورية ريائية ليس هو بيتى الآن، فسأتركه لكم خراباً، وذلك وفقاً لما قاله الله له المجد قديماً لسليمان "إن كنتم تنقلبون انتم او ابناؤكم من ورائي ولا تحفظون وصاياى فرائضى التى جعلتها أمامكم بل تذهبون وتعبدون آلهة أخرى وتسجدون لها، فاني أقطع اسرائيل عن وجه الارض التى اعطيتهم إياها والبيت الذى قدسته لاسمى انفيه من أمامى. ويكون اسرائيل مثلا وهزأة في  جميع الشعوب، وهذا البيت يكون عبرة، كل من يمر عليه يتعجب ويصفر ويقولون لماذا عمل الرب هكذا لهذه الارض ولهذا البيت. فيقولون من أجل أنهم تركوا الرب الهم الذى أخرج أباءهم من أرض مصر وتمسكوا بآلهة أخرى وسجدوا لها وعبدوها لذلك جلب الرب عليهم كل هذا الشر" (1مل9: 6-9).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Judas’ Treachery         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            خيانة يهوذا         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            On this Wednesday, Judas Iscariot, one of the disciples, went to the chief priests and asked them, “What are you willing to give me if I deliver Him to you?” (Mt 26:15). So they promised to give him 30 pieces of silver [the price of a slave], equivalent to 33 pennies. Judas sold his Master for this disgraceful value; He, who loved him, chose him as His disciple, and made him His treasurer. This happened to fulfill that which was spoken by the prophet: “‘If it is agreeable to you, give me my wages; and if not, refrain.’ So they weighed out for my wages thirty pieces of silver. And the Lord said to me, ‘Throw it to the potter’—that princely price they set on me. So I took the thirty pieces of silver and threw them into the house of the Lord for the potter” (Zech 11:12–13).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ففى هذا اليوم (الاربعاء) ذهب يهوذا الاسخريوطى أحد التلاميذ إلى رؤساء الكهنة وقال لهم ماذا تعطونى وأنا اسلمه لكم؟ (مت 26: 15)، فوعدوه أن يعطوه ثلاثين من الفضة تعادل ثلاثمائة وثلاثين قرشاً فباع سيده الذى أحبه وانتخبه يكون له تلميذاً وصيره أميناً للصندوق بهذه القيمة الدنية. وكان هذا لكي يتم ما قيل بالنبي القائل "ان حسن في أعينكم فاعطوني أجرتي والا فامتنعوا، فوزنوا أجرتى ثلاثين من الفضة. فقال لي الرب القها الى الفخارى الثمن الكريم الذى ثمنونى به. فاخذت الثلاثين من الفضة والقيتها الى الفخارى فى بيت الرب" (زك11: 12-13).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Judas’ Suicide         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إنتحاره         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            After Judas had betrayed Jesus to them, seeing that He was condemned, Judas tried to return the silver, the price he had received for his precious Master, saying: “I have sinned by betraying innocent blood.” And they said, “What is that to us? You see to it!” Then he threw down the pieces of silver in the temple and departed, and went and hanged himself. But the chief priests took the silver pieces and said, “It is not lawful to put them into the treasury, because they are the price of blood.” And they consulted together and bought with them the potter’s field, to bury strangers in. Therefore that field has been called the Field of Blood to this day (Mt 27:4–8). What was spoken by David the Prophet was fulfilled in Judas: For the mouth of the wicked and the mouth of the deceitful have opened against me; they have spoken against me with a lying tongue. They have also surrounded me with words of hatred, and fought against me without a cause. In return for my love they are my accusers… Set a wicked man over him, and let an accuser stand at his right hand. When he is judged, let him be found guilty, and let his prayer become sin. Let his days be few, and let another take his office. Let his children be fatherless, and his wife a widow. Let his children continually be vagabonds, and beg; let them seek their bread also from their desolate places… Let his posterity be cut off, and in the generation following let their name be blotted out. Let the iniquity of his fathers be remembered before the Lord, and let not the sin of his mother be blotted out… As he loved cursing, so let it come to him; as he did not delight in blessing, so let it be far from him. As he clothed himself with cursing as with his garment, so let it enter his body like water, and like oil into his bones… Let this be the Lord’s reward to my accusers, and to those who speak evil against my person (Ps 109:2–20).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبعد ما اسلمه لهم رأى نفسه أنه قد دين فمضي لوقته ورد لهم الفضة التى أخذها منهم ثمن سيده الكريم قائلا "قد أخطأت اذ سلمت دماً بريئاً". فقالوا ماذا علينا أنت أبصر. فطرح الفضة في الهيكل وانصرف. ثم مضي وخنق نفسه. فأخذ روساء الكهنة الفضة وقالوا لايحل ان نلقيها فى الخزانة لانها ثمن دم.  فتشاوروا واشتروا بها حقل الفخاري مقبرة للغرباء. لهذا سمى هذا الحقل حقل دم الى هذا اليوم (مت 27: 4-8)، فتم على يهوذا ما قيل على لسان داود النبى "لانه قد انفتح على فم الشرير وفم الغش. تكلموا معى بلسان كذب. بكلام بغض احاطوا بى وقاتلونى بلا سبب، بدل محبتى يخاصموننى، فاقم انت عليه سريراً وليقف شيطاناً عن يمينه. اذا حوكم فليخرج مذنباً و صلاته فتكن خطية. تكن أيامه قليلة وأسقفيته يأخذها آخر. ليكن بنوه أيتاماً وامرأته أرملة. ليتيه بنوه تيهانا ويستعطوا. ويلتمسوا خبزاً من خربهم . . . لتنقرض ذريته فى الجيل القادم. ليُمح اسمهم ليٌذكر اسم ابائه لدى الرب ولا تمح خطية أمه . . . فأحب اللعنة فاتته ولم يسر البركة فتباعدت عنه، ولبس اللعنة مثل الثوب ودخلت مثل الماء فى إمعائه وكزيت فى عظامه . . . هذه أجرة مبغضي من عند الرب وأجرة المتكلمين شراً على نفسى" (مز109 : 2-20)،         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Book of Acts also mentions: Men and brethren, this Scripture had to be fulfilled, which the Holy Spirit spoke before by the mouth of David concerning Judas, who became a guide to those who arrested Jesus; for he was numbered with us and obtained a part in this ministry. (Now this man purchased a field with the wages of iniquity; and falling headlong, he burst open in the middle and all his entrails gushed out. And it became known to all those dwelling in Jerusalem; so that field is called in their own language, Akel Dama, that is, Field of Blood.) For it is written in the book of Psalms: “Let his dwelling place be desolate, and let no one live in it”; and, “Let another take his office” (Acts 1:16–20).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وذٌكِر أيضاً فى أعمال الرسل "ايها الرجال الاخوة كان ينبغى ان يتم هذا المكتوب الذى سبق الروح القدس فقاله بفم داود عن يهوذا الذى صار دليلا للذين قبضوا على يسوع. اذ كان معدودأ بيننا وصارله نصيب فى هذه الخدمة. فأن هذا اقتنى حقلا من أجرة الظلم واذ سقط على وجهه انشق من الوسط فانسكبت أحشاؤه كلها. وصار ذلك معلوماً عند جميع سكان أورشليم حتى دُعى ذلك الحقل في لغتهم حقل دماً أى حقل دم. لانه مكتوب فى سفر المزامير لتصر داره خراباً ولا يكن فيها ساكن وليأخذ خدمته آخر" (أع1: 16-20).         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Judas Deserves Punishment         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إستحقاقه العقاب         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            One may ponder that, if it was necessary for the Lord Christ to be delivered to the Jews to be crucified (if not through Judas, it would have been through someone else), and if the Holy Scripture describe in great detail Judas’ actions, then what was his fault, how did he sin, and why did he perish? The response is that our omniscient omnipresent God preceded and revealed to His servants the prophets the life events of the Savior on earth—beginning from the Annunciation of the Angel to the Virgin until His Ascension to heaven and the descent of the Holy Spirit upon the disciples. All who treated the Lord Christ, whether with good or evil deeds, did so freely, not by force or compulsion. God’s foreknowledge was not the cause of people’s actions. All the prophecies concerning Judas, Judas fulfilled freely, and willfully accomplished—he was the author of his life choices, which he made without coercion. He had no intention of fulfilling the prophecies. Even if this had been his intention, he still would have perished, because people have a choice to do that which is good and to avoid evil. God does not wish to take vengeance on a killer because he committed murder, as he said to Cain, “Whoever kills Cain, vengeance shall be taken on him sevenfold” (Gen 4:15). If so, then how much more shall the one who delivers honorable innocent blood, a Lamb without blemish, due to greed for thirty pieces of silver—a worldly profit? His punishment comes from Divine Justice for delivering his righteous Master.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يتبادر للذهن انه إذا كان لابد أن يسلم السيد المسيح لليهود ليصلب، وإن لم يكن بيهوذا كان سيكون بغيره، والنصوص الالهية تشير الى كل ما يعمله يهوذا فما هو ذنبه وما هى خطيته ولماذا يهلك، الجواب : ان الله له المجد العالم بكل شئ قبل كونه سبق فأوحى عن أفواه عبيده الانبياء كل حياة الفادى على الارض، وذلك من بدء بشارة الملاك للسيدة العذراء الى اليوم الذى إرتفع فيه الي السماء، وأرسل الروح القدس على التلاميذ. فكل الذين عاملوا السيد المسيح بالخير أو بالشر، عملوا ذلك مخيرين لا مسيرين. ولم يُرغموا على فعل ما أتوه. فعلم الله له المجد لم يكن سبباً في تصرفات هؤلاء الناس، لذلك الانباء بيهوذا وبجميع ما يتعلق به فى كتب الانبياء كان قد فعله مخيراً ومريداً ولم يرغم علي شئ منه، ولا فعل ذلك إتماماً لنبوات الانبياء. حتى لو فعل ذلك لكان أيضاً قد هلك، لأنه ينبغى للانسان أن يفعل الصلاح ويتجنب الشر، لأن الله لا يريد أن ينتقم من القاتل كون أنه قاتل بل قال لقايين "الذي يقتلك ينتقم منه سبعة أضعاف" (تك4: 15). فكم يكون من سلم دماً بريئاً ومكرماً كما من حمل بلا عيب  حباً في ثلاثين من الفضة ابتغاه للربح الدنيوى، فالعقاب الذى حل بيهوذا يستحقه، فهو صادر عن العدل الالهي لتسليمه لسيده البار.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Likewise, many, like Judas, sell their Master for even less than thirty pieces of silver. They pursue high profits by any means, defrauding by various ways until they fulfill their self-interest. They cheat, they lie, they flatter, they live without conscience, they become imposters, and they deceive innocent souls. They break the day of the Lord for the sake of a little money, the “root of all kinds of evil, for which some have strayed from the faith in their greediness, and pierced themselves through with many sorrows” (1 Tim 6:10). May God guard and protect us from this evil and keep us faithful until death. Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهكذا كثيرون كيهوذا يبيعون سيدهم المسيح بأقل مما باعه به يهوذا، فانهم يسعون وراء الكسب العالمى بأى طريق كان، ويتحايلون بشتى الطرق حتى يصلوا إلى أغراضهم، فتراهم يغشون ويكذبون ويتملقون ويعيشون بلا ضمير خداعين مغرورين بالنفوس البريئة، ويكسرون يوم الرب إبتغاءً لربح قليل من المال الذى هو أصل لكل الشرور، الذى إذا إبتغاه قوم ضلوا عن الإيمان وطعنوا أنفسهم بأوجاع كثيرة )1تى6: 10(، وقانا الله وحمانا من ذلك وجعلنا أمناء إلى الموت آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Just Judgment of the Crucifiers         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            دينونة الصالبين العادلة         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Some might question, if it were necessary for these events to happen to the Lord Christ when He came into the world, and if it had to be done through these specific people, then why does God judge them? The response is that their actions were provoked by the devil (the enemy of humanity), and were done through personal desire—meanwhile, their consciences bore witness to the Lord Christ. God will judge them for submitting to their desires; the judgment is just, whether passed on them or on others. It was not the Lord who asked them to crucify Him, or to fulfill the inevitable, but rather it was done of their own free will.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وإن قال البعض إنه كان حتماً أن يتم بالسيد المسيح عند مجيئه الى العالم ما يتم، وإنه لابد أن يكون بغيرهم، فلماذا يدين الله هؤلاء؟ لأن ما فعله هؤلاء كان بإيعاز من إبليس عدو الإنسانية، وقد فعلوا ذلك إبتغاء لنوال شهوات بينما كانت ضمائرهم تشهد للسيد المسيح، فسيدينهم الله على إستسلامهم لشهوات نفوسهم، لأنهم عملوا أفعالهم إستسلاماً لشهواتهم وليس إتماماً للنبوات، فدينونتهم عادلة سواء كان هؤلاء أم غيرهم فإن الرب لم يطلب منهم أن يصلبوه أو أن يتمموا ما لابد أن يتم به.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>