<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">      <season id="CovenantThursday | FeastOfTheCross">      <group>         <season id="FeastOfTheCross">            <insertdocument path="include/fractions/Syrian"/>         </season>      </group>            <section>         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Fraction to the Father on the Slaughter of Isaac: And it came to pass...</language><language id="Indonesian">Fraksi bagi Sang Bapa tentang penyembelihan: Datanglah saat ketika Allah..</language>            <language id="Arabic">قسمة للآب على ذبح إسحق تقال: وحَدَثَ في الأيام...</language>             </Title>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Acswpi de qen nie~hoou e~ta Vnou] ouws e~[wnt n~Abraam: ouoh n~tefe~mi e~pefh/t nem pefmei e~qoun e~rof.            </language>            <language id="English">               And it came to pass in the days when God wanted to test Abraham and know his heart and his love for Him,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Datanglah saat ketika Allah ingin menguji Abraham untuk mengetahui hatinya dan kasihnya bagi Dia,            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وحَدَثَ في الأيامِ التي أرادَ اللهُ أَنْ يجرِّبَ إبراهيمَ ويَعلَمَ قلبَهُ ومحبتَهُ فيهِ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh pejaf naf je Abraam Abraam: [i m~pekmenrit n~s/ri Icaak ouoh a~nitf n/i n~ou[~lil: hijen pitwou e~]natamok e~rof.            </language>            <language id="English">               that He said to him, “Abraham, Abraham, take your beloved son Isaac and offer him to Me as a burnt offering, upon the mountain of which I will tell you.”            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dia berkata kepadanya, "Abraham, Abraham, bawa anakmu yang tercinta, Ishak, dan persembahkan dia kepada-Ku sebagai korban bakaran, di atas gunung yang Kukatakan kepadamu."            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أَنه قالَ لهُ: ”إبراهيمُ إبراهيمُ، خُذْ ابنَكَ الحبيبَ إسحَقَ وقدِّمْهُ لِي مُحْرَقَةً على الجبلِ الذي أُعلِمُكَ بهِ.“            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Aftwnf de n~je Abraam n~tooui~ ouoh afqwk n~tefe~w:~ af[i de n~a~lou 2 (c~nau) nem Icaak pefs/ri: af[i n~oujor] nem ou,~rwm: afmosi e~bol hijen pikahi: ouoh afnau e~pima hi v~ouei e~ta P[oic tamof e~rof.            </language>            <language id="English">               And Abraham rose up in the morning and saddled his donkey, and took two servants and Isaac his son. He took a knife and fire, walked on the earth, and saw from afar the place of which the Lord had told him.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan Abraham bangun di pagi hari dan membebani keledainya, mengambil dua pelayan dan Ishak putranya. Dan dia mengambil pisau dan api, berjalan serta melihat dari jauh tempat yang telah Tuhan katakan kepadanya.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               فقامَ إبراهيمُ باكراً وأَسْرَجَ دابتَهُ، وأخذَ غلامَينِ وإسحقَ إبنَهُ. وأخذَ سِكيناً وناراً. ومَشَى عَلى الأرضِ، فرأى الموضعَ مِنْ بعيدٍ الذي أعلَمَهُ بهِ الربُّ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh pejaf n~nefa~lwoui~ je hemci n~ywten m~paima nem ]e~w~: a~nok de nem Icaak pas/ri tennasenan n~tenouwst ouoh n~tentacyo harwten.            </language>            <language id="English">               And he said to his servants, “You sit in this place with the donkey. And I and Isaac my son shall go to worship, and return to you.”            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan dia berkata kepada hamba-hambanya, "Kamu tetap di tempat ini dengan keledai. Aku dan Ishak, putraku, akan pergi untuk beribadah, dan kembali kepadamu."            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               فقالَ لغلاميه: ”اجلِسا أنتُما هَهُنا مع الدابةِ. وأما أنا وإسحقُ ابني فنذهَبُ ونسجُد ثم نرجِعُ إليكُما.“            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Af[i de n~je Abraam n~nirwkh n~te pi[~lil: ouoh aftalwou e~jen Icaak pefs/ri: af[i de m~pi,~rwm qen tefjij nem ]jor].            </language>            <language id="English">               And Abraham took the firewood for the burnt offering and laid it upon Isaac his son, and took the fire in his hand, and the knife.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan Abraham mengambil kayu bakar untuk korban bakaran, dan meletakkannya di atas Ishak, putranya, dan mengambil api di tangannya, dan pisau.</language>            <language id="Arabic">               وأخَذَ إبراهيمُ حَطَبَ المحرَقَةِ ووضَعَهُ على إسحقَ ابنِهِ، وأخَذَ بيدِهِ النارَ والسكينَ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Peje Icaak de m~pefiwt: je paiwt h/ppe ic pi,~rwm nem pirwkh: afywn pie~cwou e~tennaenf e~pi[~lil.            </language>            <language id="English">               And Isaac spoke to his father, saying, “My father, behold the fire and the wood, but where is the sheep which we shall offer as a burnt offering?”            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan Ishak berkata kepada ayahnya, katanya, "Ayahku, lihatlah api dan kayu, tetapi di manakah domba yang akan kita persembahkan sebagai korban bakaran?"            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               فقال إسحقُ لأبيهِ: ”يا أَبَتَاهُ، هُوَذا النارُ والحطبُ، وأيْنَ الخرُوفُ الذي نُقَدِّمُهُ للمُحْرَقَةِ؟“            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Peje Abraam de naf je Vnou] v/e~tafouahcahni nan e~talo naf n~ouyucia: n~yof eynanau e~oue~cwou naf e~p~[~lil pas/ri.            </language>            <language id="English">               And Abraham said to him, “God, who commanded us to offer to Him a sacrifice, will provide Himself the sheep for a burnt offering, my son.”            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan Abraham berkata kepadanya, "Allah, yang memerintahkan kita untuk mempersembahkan korban kepada-Nya, akan menyediakan bagi diri-Nya sendiri domba untuk korban bakaran, anakku."            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               فقالَ لهُ إبراهيمُ: ”إنَّ اللهَ الذي أَمَرَنا أن نرفعَ لهُ ذبيحةً هو يَرَى حملاً لهُ للمُحْرَقَةِ يا ابْنِي.“            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Af[i de n~hanw~ni n~je Abraam afkwt n~ouman~erswousi: af[i n~nirwkh aftalwou hijen piman~erswousi: ouoh af[i n~Icaak pefs/ri afconhf aftalof e~h~r/i e~jen piman~erswousi: af[i n~]jor] e~qelqwlf.            </language>            <language id="English">               And Abraham took stones and built an altar, and took the firewood and laid it upon the altar, and took Isaac his son and bound him and laid him upon the altar, and took the knife to slay him.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan Abraham mengambil batu dan membangun sebuah mezbah, dan mengambil kayu bakar dan meletakkannya di atas mezbah, dan mengambil Ishak, putranya, mengikatnya dan meletakkannya di atas mezbah, dan mengambil pisau untuk membunuhnya.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وأخَذَ إبراهيمُ حِجارةً وبنى مذبحاً. وأخَذَ الحَطَبَ ورَفَعَهُ على المذبحِ، وأخَذَ إسحقَ ابنَهُ وربَطَهُ ووَضَعَهُ على المذبحِ، وأخَذَ السكينَ ليذبَحَهُ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh a piaggeloc n~te P[oic mou] oube Abraam efjw m~moc naf: je Abraam Abraam a~nau m~per[oh e~peka~lou oude m~peri~ri naf n~oupethwou.            </language>            <language id="English">               And the Angel of the Lord called to Abraham, saying to him, “Abraham, Abraham, behold, do not touch your lad, or do him any harm.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan Malaikat Tuhan memanggil Abraham, berkata kepadanya, "Abraham, Abraham, Lihat, janganlah menyentuh tanganmu pada anakmu, atau menyakitinya. </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وإن مَلاكَ الربِّ نادى إبراهيمَ قائلاً لَهُ: ”إبراهيمُ إبراهيمُ، انظُرْ لا تَلْمَسْ فتاكَ ولاتَصنَعْ بِهِ شراً.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Etafnau n~je P[oic e~pekmei e~qoun e~rof: ouoh pejaf je a~nok pe P[oic Peknou]: aiwrk m~moi je qen ouc~mou eie~c~mou e~rok: ouoh qen oua~sai eie~y~re pekj~roj a~sai.            </language>            <language id="English">               When the Lord saw your love for Him, He said, ‘I am the Lord your God. By Myself I have sworn that in blessing I will bless you, and in multiplying I will multiply your seed.’”            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ketika Tuhan melihat cintamu bagi Dia, Dia berkata, 'Aku Akulah TUHAN, Allahmu. Dengan diri-Ku sendiri Aku telah bersumpah bahwa dalam berkat Aku akan memberkatimu, dalam pelipatgandaan Aku akan melipatgandakan keterunanmu."            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               لما نَظَرَ الربُّ محبَّتَكَ فيهِ قالَ: إني أنا هو الربُّ إلهُكَ، أقسَمتُ بذاتي إنـي بالبَرَكةِ أبارِكُكَ، وبالكَثْرَةِ أُكثِرُ نسلَكَ.“            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh affai n~nefbal n~je Abraam: afnau e~oue~cwou ef,/ hijen pis~s/n efm/r qen peftap c~nau: ouoh af,w n~Icaak pefs/ri af[i m~pie~cwou: ouoh afenf e~h~r/i n~ou[~lil n~tefsebiw.            </language>            <language id="English">               And Abraham lifted up his eyes and saw a sheep laid upon the tree, caught by its two horns. So he left Isaac his son and took the sheep, and offered it up as a burnt offering instead of him.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan Abraham mengangkat matanya dan melihat seekor domba jantan ada di atas pohon, terjerat oleh tanduknya. Lalu ia meninggalkan Ishak, putranya, dan mengambil domba jantan itu, dan mempersembahkannya sebagai korban bakaran - ganti dari dia.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               فرَفَعَ إبراهِيمُ عينَيهِ فنَظَرَ خروفاً عندَ الشجرَةِ مُوثَقاً بقَرنيهِ، فتَرَكَ إسحقَ ابنَهُ وأخَذَ الخروفَ وأصْعَدَهُ مُحْرَقةً عِوَضاً عَنهُ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pqolqel de n~Icaak ne ou[wrem pe e~pivwn e~bol m~p~c~nof n~te Pi,~rictoc Ps/ri m~Vnou] hijen pic~tauroc eybe p~oujai m~pikocmoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Thus the slaying of Isaac was a type of the shedding of the Blood of Christ, the Son of God, on the Cross for the salvation of the world.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Jadi, pembunuhan Ishak seperti penumpahan Darah Kristus, Anak Allah, di kayu Salib untuk keselamatan dunia. </language>            <language id="Arabic">               فَذَبْحُ إسحقَ كانَ إشارةً إلى هرقِ دمِ المسيحِ ابنِ اللهِ على الصليبِ عن خلاصِ العَالَمِ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh kata v~r/] e~ta Icaak w~li n~nirwkh n~te pi[~lil: pair/] afw~li n~je Pi,~rictoc m~pise n~te pic~tauroc.            </language>            <language id="English">               And as Isaac carried the firewood for the burnt offering, likewise Christ carried the wood of the Cross.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan ketika Ishak membawa kayu bakar untuk korban bakaran, demikian juga Kristus membawa kayu Salib. </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وكما حَمَلَ إسحقُ حَطَبَ المحرَقَةِ، كذلك حَمَلَ المسيحُ خشبةَ الصليبِ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh kata v~r/] e~ta Icaak tacyo efonq: pair/] hwf Pi,~rictoc aftwnf efonq e~bolqen n/eymwout ouoh afouonhf n~nefa~gioc m~may/t/c.            </language>            <language id="English">               And as Isaac returned alive, likewise Christ rose alive from the dead and appeared to His holy disciples.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan ketika Ishak kembali hidup, demikian juga Kristus bangkit hidup, dari kematian dan menampakkan diri kepada murid-murid-Nya yang kudus.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وكما رَجَعَ إسحقُ حياً، هَكَذا أيضاً قامَ المسيحُ حياً من الأمواتِ، وظَهَرَ لتلاميذِهِ القديسينَ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Vnou] v/e~taf[i n~]yucia~ n~te peniwt Abraam: [i n~taiyucia n~toten qen taiounou yai: c~mou e~naidwron nai: c~mou e~n/e~tauenou e~jwou: mam~ton n~ni'u,/ n~n/e~taumou: marefc~mou n~je Pi,~rictoc e~jen nenh/t t/rou nem nenp~neuma.            </language>            <language id="English">               O God, who received the sacrifice of our father Abraham, receive this sacrifice from our hands in this hour. Bless these gifts. Bless those on whose behalf they have been offered, and repose the souls of those who have died. May Christ bless the hearts and spirits of us all,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ya Allah, yang menerima korban bapa kami Abraham, terimalah korban ini dari tangan kami pada jam ini. Berkatilah pemberian ini. Berkatilah mereka yang mewakili mereka yang berkorban, dan istirihatkanlah jiwa mereka yang telah mati. Kiranya Kristus memberkati hati dan roh kita semua, </language>            <language id="Arabic">               اللهُمَّ الذي قَبِلَ ذبيحةَ أبينا إبراهيمَ، اقْبَلْ هذه الذبيحةَ مِنَّا في هذه الساعةِ. بارِكْ هذه القرابينَ، بارِكْ الذينَ قُدِّمَتْ عنهُمْ. نيِّحْ نفوسَ الذين ماتوا. فليُبَارِكْ المسيحُ على جميعِ قلوبِنا وأرواحِنا.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je hina qen ouh/t efouab: nem ou'u,/ e~ac[iouwini: nem ouho n~at[isipi: nem ounah] n~atmetsobi: nem oua~gap/ ecj/k e~bol: nem ouhelpic ectajr/out.            </language>            <language id="English">               so that with a pure heart, an enlightened soul, an unashamed face, a faith unfeigned, a perfect love, and a firm hope,            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>sehingga dengan hati yang murni, jiwa yang tercerahkan, wajah yang tanpa malu, iman yang tidak munafik, kasih yang sempurna, dan harapan yang teguh, </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لكي بقلبٍ طاهرٍ، ونفسٍ مستنيرةٍ، ووجهٍ غيرِ مخزيٍّ، وإيمانٍ بِلا رياءٍ، ومحبةٍ كاملةٍ، ورجاءٍ ثابتٍ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ntenertolman qen ouparr/cia n~aterho] e~twbh m~mok: Vnou] Viwt eyouab etqen niv/oui: ouoh e~joc:            </language>            <language id="English">               we may dare with boldness, without fear, to pray to You, O God, the holy Father, who is in the heavens, and say,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               sehingga kita dengan keberanian, tanpa rasa takut, dapat  berdoa kepada-Mu, ya Allah, Bapa Suci yang ada di surga, dan berkata,            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               نجسُرَ بدالةٍ بغيرِ خوفٍ، أن ندعُوَكَ يا اللهُ الآبُ القدوسُ الذي في السمواتِ، ونقولَ:             </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je Peniwt...            </language>            <language id="English">               Our Father...            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Bapa kami...            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أبانا...            </language>                  </text>      </section>   </season></document>