<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <season id="HosannaSunday">      <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Fraction to the Father for Hosanna Sunday: O Lord, our Lord...</language><language id="Indonesian">Fraksi bagi Sang Bapa untuk Minggu Palma: Ya TUHAN, Tuhan kami,...</language>            <language id="Arabic">قسمة للآب تقال في أحد الشعانين: أيها الربُّ ربُّنا...</language>         </Title>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               P[oic Pen[oic m~v~r/] n~ous~v/ri afswpi n~je pekran hijen pikahi t/rf.            </language>            <language id="English">               O Lord, our Lord, how wondrous has become Your name in all the earth,            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya TUHAN, Tuhan kami, betapa mulianya nama-Mu di seluruh bumi! </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيها الربُّ ربُّنا، مثلَ عجبٍ صارَ إسمُكَ على الأرضِ كلِّها.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je ac[ici n~je y~metnis] n~te tekmetcaie~ cap~swi n~niv/oui.            </language>            <language id="English">               for the greatness of Your beauty is exalted above the heavens.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Keagungan-Mu yang mengatasi langit dinyanyikan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأنه قد ارتَفَعَ عِظَمُ بهائِكَ فوقَ السمواتِ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ebolqen rwou n~hankouji n~a~lwoui~ nem n/eyouem[i akcebte pic~mou.            </language>            <language id="English">               Out of the mouth of babes and nursing infants, You have prepared praise.            </language><language id="Indonesian">Dari mulut bayi-bayi dan anak-anak yang menyusu telah Kauletakkan dasar kekuatan.</language>            <language id="Arabic">               مِنْ أفواهِ الأطفالِ والرُضْعَانِ هيَّأْتَ سُبحاً.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Cob] de on P[oic n~n/e~te noun m~'u,/: e~p~jinhwc e~rok e~erhumnoc e~rok: e~c~mou e~rok: e~semsi m~mok: e~ouwst m~mok: e~]w~ou nak: e~seph~mot n~totk: kata e~hoou niben nem kata ounou niben.            </language>            <language id="English">               Prepare also, O Lord, our souls for praising You, hymning You, blessing You, serving You, worshiping You, glorifying You, giving thanks to You, every day and every hour,            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Jadi Ya Tuhan kami, mempersiapkan  juga, jiwa Kami untuk memuji-Mu, nyanyian bagi-Mu, memberkati-Mu, melayani-Mu, menyembah-Mu, memuliakan-Mu, bersyukur kepada-Mu, setiap hari Dan setiap saat</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فَهَـيِّئْ أيضاً ياربُّ نفوسَنا لنسبِّحَكَ، ونرتلَ لكَ، ونباركَكَ، ونخدُمَكَ، ونسجُدَ لكَ، ونمجدَكَ، ونشكرَكَ كلَّ يومٍ وكلَّ ساعةٍ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Hwcte n~tenouwnh nak e~bol: ouoh n~tenws e~p~swi harok: Viwt eyouab etqen niv/oui: ouoh n~tenjoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               that we may confess to You and cry out to You, O holy Father, who is in the heavens, and say,            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sehingga, dengan hati yang suci dan Bibir yang  murni, kami mengakuan kepada-Mu dan berseru kepada Bapa kami yang Kudus, yang berada di sorga, mengatakan: </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لكي نعترفَ لكَ، ونصرُخَ نحوَكَ أيها الآبُ القدوسُ الذي في السمواتِ، ونقولَ:            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je Peniwt...            </language>            <language id="English">               Our Father...            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Bapa kami ..            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أبانا...            </language>                  </text>      </section>   </season></document>