<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Title>      <language id="English">Fraction to the Father for the Resurrection and the Pentecost Period: O Master, Lord God...</language><language id="Indonesian">Fraksi bagi Sang Bapa, untuk Kebangkitan dan Masa Pentakosta: "Tuan kami dan Tuhan.."</language>      <language id="Arabic">قسمة للآب تقال في عيد القيامة والخمسين: أيها السيدُ الربُّ...</language>   </Title>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Vn/b P[oic Vnou] pipantokratwr: Viwt m~Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc.      </language>      <language id="English">         O Master, Lord God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ,      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Tuan kami dan Tuhan, Allah Pantokrator, Bapa Tuhan kami, Allah dan Juruselamat, Yesus Kristus,       </language>      <language id="Arabic">         أيها السيدُ الربُّ الإلهُ ضابطُ الكلِّ، أبو ربِّنا وإلهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         V/e~te e~bolhiten pefc~tauroc afi~ e~pec/t e~a~men]: aftacyo m~peniwt Adam nem nefs/ri e~qoun e~piparadicoc.      </language>      <language id="English">         who through His Cross descended to Hades and restored our father Adam and his children to Paradise.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         yang turun ke Hades, lewat Salib, mengembalikan Bapa Adam dan anak-anaknya ke Taman Firdaus.       </language>      <language id="Arabic">         الذي من قِبَلِ صليبِه نَزَلَ إلى الجحيمِ، وردَّ أبانا آدَمَ وبنيهِ إلى الفردوسِ.      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Afyomcen nemaf: qen pefmou afkwrf m~pia~mahi m~v~mou: ouoh qen pimahsomt n~e~hoou aftwnf e~bolqen n/eymwout.      </language>      <language id="English">         He buried us with Himself, and through His death He abolished the power of death, and on the third day He rose from the dead.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dia telah menguburkan kami bersama dengan Dia, dan oleh kematiannya, Dia telah menghapuskan akar maut dari kami. Dan pada hari ketiga, Dia telah bangkit dari antara orang mati.</language>      <language id="Arabic">         ودفَنَنا مَعَهُ، بموتِهِ أبطلَ عِزَّ الموتِ، وفي ثالثِ يومٍ قامَ من الأمواتِ.      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Afouonhf e~Maria ]magdalin/: afcaji nemac m~pair/] efjw m~moc: je matame nac~n/ou hina n~tousenwou e~}galilea: cenanau e~roi m~mau.      </language>      <language id="English">         He appeared to Mary Magdalene and spoke with her in this manner, saying, “Tell My brethren to go to Galilee, and there they will see Me.”      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dan memperlihatkan diri kepada Maria Magdalena. Engkau bicara kepada dia dan mengatakan: “Ceritakan kepada saudaraKu bahwa mereka harus pergi ke Galilea; mereka akan melihat Aku di sana.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         وظَهَرَ لمريمَ المجدليةِ وكلَّمَها هكذا قائلاً: ”أَعْلِمِي إخوتي أن يذهبُوا إلى الجليلِ، هناكَ يَرَوْنَنِي.“      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Piar,/aggeloc afi~ e~pec/t e~bolqen t~ve: afc~kerker m~piw~ni e~bol hi rwf m~pim~hau afhisennoufi n~nihio~mi m~faicojen efjw m~moc:      </language>      <language id="English">         The archangel descended from heaven and rolled the stone from the door of the tomb, and proclaimed the glad tidings to the women carrying the spices, saying,      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Malaikat Penghulu Mikhael turun dari sorga, dan menggulingkan batu dari pintu kubur, dan memberitakan Kabar Baik kepada wanita yang membawa rempah-rempah, mengatakan:       </language>      <language id="Arabic">         رئيسُ الملائكةِ نَزَلَ من السماءِ، ودحرَجَ الحجرَ عن فمِ القبرِ، وبَشَّرَ النسوةَ حاملاتِ الطيبِ قائلاً:      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Je &lt;rictoc a~nect/ ek nekrwn: yanatw yanaton pat/cac: ke tic en tic m~n/maci zw/n ,aricamenoc.      </language>      <language id="English">         “Christ is risen from the dead, trampling down death by death, and upon those in the tombs bestowing life.”      </language><language id="Indonesian">         “Kristus telah Bangkit dari antara orang mati.” Dia telah meremukkan maut dengan kematian-Ya, dan memberikan hidup kekal kepada mereka yang terbaring di kuburan.</language>      <language id="Arabic">         ”المسيحُ قامَ من الأمواتِ، بالموتِ داسَ الموتَ، والذينَ في القبورِ أنعمَ عليهِمْ بالحياةِ الأبديةِ.“      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Afnifi e~qoun qen p~ho n~nefa~gioc m~may/t/c ouoh n~a~poctoloc eyouab efjw m~moc:      </language>      <language id="English">         He breathed into the face of His saintly disciples and holy apostles, saying,      </language><language id="Indonesian">Dia telah menghembuskan pada Murid-Nya yang kudus dan Rasul yang tulus dan mengatakan: </language>      <language id="Arabic">         ونَفَخَ في وجهِ تلاميذِهِ القديسينَ، ورُسُلِهِ الأطهارِ قائلاً:      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Je [i nwten n~Oup~neuma efouab: n/e~tetenna,a nounobi nwou e~bol ce,/ nwou e~bol: ouoh n/e~tetennaa~moni m~mwou cenaa~moni m~mwou.      </language>      <language id="English">         “Receive the Holy Spirit. If you forgive the sins of any, they are forgiven; if you retain the sins of any, they are retained.”      </language><language id="Indonesian">         “Terimalah Roh Kudus. Jikalau engkau mengampuni dosa orang, dosanya diampuni, dan jikalau engkau menyatakan dosa orang tetap ada, dosanya tetap ada.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         ”اقبلوا الروحَ القدسَ، مَنْ غفرتُم لهم خطاياهم غُفِرَتْ لَهُم، ومَنْ أمسكتموها عليهِمْ أُمسِكَت.“      </language>            </text></document>