<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section>      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Fraction to the Son for the Resurrection: O Christ our God...</language><language id="Indonesian">Fraction to the Son for the Resurrection: O Christ our God...</language>         <language id="Arabic">قسمة للابن تقال للقيامة: أيها المسيحُ...</language>       </Title>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Pi,~rictoc Pennou]: piar,ie~reuc n~te nia~gayon eynaswpi: p~ouro n~te nie~wn: piaymou pisae~neh: pilogoc n~te Vnou] et hijen pie~p~t/rf.         </language>         <language id="English">            O Christ our God, the High Priest of the good things to come, King of the ages, the Immortal, the Everlasting, the Logos of God who is above all,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Kristus Allah kami, Imam Besar dari hal-hal baik yang akan datang, Raja segala zaman, Yang Tak Mati, Yang Kekal, Logos Allah yang di atas segala sesuatu,         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أيها المسيحُ إلـهُنا رئيسُ كهنةِ الخيراتِ العَتيدَةِ، ملكُ الدهورِ، غيرُ المائِتِ، الأبديُّ، كلمةُ اللهِ الذي على الكلِّ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            V/e~taferh~mot nan m~painis] m~muct/rion: e~te pefcwma eyouab nem pefc~nof ettai/out: e~p~,w e~bol n~te nennobi.         </language>         <language id="English">            who granted us this great Mystery which is His holy Body and His precious Blood for the forgiveness of our sins.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            yang telah mengaruniakan kepada kami Misteri yang besar ini yaitu Tubuh Kudus-Nya dan Darah-Nya yang berharga bagi pengampunan dosa-dosa kami.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            الذي أنعَمَ لنا بهذا السرِّ العظيمِ، الذي هو جَسَدُه المقدسُ ودمُهُ الكريمُ لغفرانِ خطايانا.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Vai pe picwma e~taf[itf e~bolqen ten[oic n~n/b t/ren ]a~gia Maria: ouoh afaif n~ouai nem tefmeynou].         </language>         <language id="English">            This is the Body which He took from our Lady, the Lady of us all, Saint Mary, and made It one with His divinity.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Inilah Tubuh yang Ia ambil dari Bunda kami, Bunda kita semua, Santa Maria, dan Ia jadikan satu dengan keilahian-Nya.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            هذا هو الجسدُ الذي أخَذَهُ مِنْ سيدتِنا، سيدتِنا كلِّنا، القديسةِ مريمَ، وجَعَلَه واحداً مع لاهوتِهِ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Vai pe v/e~tafsenaf e~pec/t e~a~men]: afkwrf m~p~a~mahi m~v~mou: afere,malwteuin n~oue,malwcia~ af] n~hantaio~ n~nirwmi.         </language>         <language id="English">            This is He who descended into Hades, abolished the power of death, led captivity captive, and gave gifts to men.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Inilah Dia yang turun ke Hades, membatalkan kuasa maut, membawa tawanan sebagai tawanan, dan memberikan karunia kepada manusia.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            هذا هو الذي نَزَلَ إلى الجحيمِ، وأبْطَلَ عزَّ الموتِ، وسبى سبياً، وأَعطى الناسَ كراماتٍ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            N/eyouab n~taf afo~lou e~p~[ici nemaf: aft/itou n~handwron e~Pefiwt: hiten pefjem]pi m~v~mou qaron afnohem n~n/etonq ouoh af]m~ton n~n/e~taumou.         </language>         <language id="English">            He lifted His saints up on high with Him and gave them as gifts to His Father. Through His tasting of death for us, He saved those who are alive and reposed those who have died.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ia mengangkat para kudus-Nya ke tempat yang tinggi bersama-Nya dan mempersembahkan mereka sebagai hadiah kepada Bapa-Nya. Melalui pencicipan-Nya akan maut bagi kami, Ia menyelamatkan mereka yang hidup dan memberi perhentian bagi mereka yang telah wafat.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            رفَعَ قديسيهِ إلى العُلَى مَعَهُ، أعطاهُم قرباناً لأبيهِ، بذوقِهِ الموتَ عنا خلَّصَ الأحياءَ، وأَعطى النياحَ للذين ماتوا.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Anon de hwn qa n/ethemci qen p~,aki n~ouc/ou: aferh~mot nan m~v~ouwini n~tefa~nactacic: e~bolhiten pefjin[icarx eyouab.         </language>         <language id="English">            And we, too, who were sitting in darkness for a season, He granted us the light of His Resurrection through His holy Incarnation.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dan kami juga, yang duduk dalam kegelapan untuk suatu waktu, Ia anugerahkan terang Kebangkitan-Nya melalui Penjelmaan Kudus-Nya.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ونحنُ أيضاً الجلوسَ في الظلمةِ زماناً، أنعَمَ لنا بنورِ قيامتِهِ من قِبَلِ تجسدِهِ الطاهرِ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Mareferouwini e~ron n~je v~ouwini n~te peke~mi m~m/i: eyren]moue~ qen pekc~mot n~wnq.         </language>         <language id="English">            May the illumination of Your true knowledge shine upon us, that we may shine with Your living image         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Semoga penerangan dari pengetahuan-Mu yang sejati bersinar atas kami, agar kami dapat bersinar dengan citra-Mu yang hidup         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            فَلْيُضِىءْ علينا نورُ معرفتِكَ الحقيقيةِ لنُضِيءَ بشكلِكَ المحيِي.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh n~tenertolman qen ouparr/cia n~aterho]: e~ws oube Pekiwt etqen niv/oui: ouoh e~joc:         </language>         <language id="English">            and may dare with boldness, without fear, to cry out to Your Father, who is in the heavens, and say,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            dan dapat berani dengan keberanian, tanpa rasa takut, berseru kepada Bapa-Mu yang ada di surga, dan berkata:         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ونجسرَ بدالةٍ بغيرِ خوفٍ أن نصرُخَ نحو أبيكَ الذي في السمواتِ، ونقولَ:         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Je Peniwt...         </language>         <language id="English">            Our Father...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Bapa Kami...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أبانا …         </language>               </text>   </section></document>