<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section>      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Syrian Fraction for the Feasts of the Cross and Standard Days: Thus truly the Logos...</language><language id="Indonesian">Syrian Fraction for the Feasts of the Cross and Standard Days: Thus truly the Logos...</language>         <language id="Arabic">القسمة السريانية تقال في عيدي الصليب والأيام العادية: هكذا بالحقيقةِ تألم...</language>      </Title>            <comment>                        <language id="English">            This fraction is from the Liturgy of the church of Antioch.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            This fraction is from the Liturgy of the church of Antioch.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            مأخوذة من قداس الكنيسة السريانية         </language>               </comment>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Pair/] a~l/ywc afsepm~kah n~je Pcaji m~Vnou] qen t~carx ouoh auqelqwlf: afrek jwf hijen pic~tauroc: ouoh acvwrj e~bol n~je tef'u,/ e~pefcwma:         </language>         <language id="English">            Thus truly the Logos of God suffered in the flesh, was slain, bowed on the Cross, and His soul parted from His body,          </language><language id="Indonesian">            Demikianlah Logos Allah benar-benar menderita dalam daging, dikorbankan serta hancur di atas kayu Salib. Jiwa-Nya terpisah dari tubuh-Nya,</language>         <language id="Arabic">            هكذا بالحقيقةِ تألم كلمةُ اللهِ بالجسدِ وذُبِحَ وانحنَى بالصليبِ وانفَصَلَتْ نفسُهُ مِن جسدِهِ،         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ere tefmeynou] vwrj e~bol an e~neh e~tef'u,/ oude pefcwma.         </language>         <language id="English">            even though His divinity never parted, either from His soul or from His body.         </language><language id="Indonesian">namun keilahian-Nya sama sekali tidak terpisahkan baik dari jiwa-Nya maupun dari tubuh-Nya.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            إذ لاهوتُهُ لم يَنفَصلْ قَطُّ لا من نفسِهِ ولا من جَسَدِهِ.         </language>               </text>                  <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Auyokcf qen pefc~vir qen ]log,/: ouoh auqa] e~bol n~q/tf n~je ouc~nof nem oumwou: e~ou,w e~bol m~pikocmoc t/rf: ouoh aucep pefcwma n~q/tou: ouoh aci~ n~je tef'u,/ acerouai nem pefcwma.         </language>         <language id="English">            He was pierced with the spear in His side, out of which flowed blood and water for the forgiveness of the whole world; His body was smeared in them, and His soul came and was reunited with His body.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dia ditikam di sisi-Nya dengan tombak; darahDemi dosa seluruh dunia, Sang Putra mati di kayu Salib.dan air mengalir dari-Nya untuk pengampunan seluruh dunia. Tubuh-Nya dibalur di dalamnya, dan jiwa-Nya datang dan dipersatukan kembali dengan tubuh-Nya.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وطُعِنَ في جَنبِهِ بالحربَةِ، وجَرَى مِنهُ دمٌ وماءٌ غفراناً لكلِّ العالمِ. وتخَضَّبَ بهِما جسدُهُ، وأتَتْ نفسُهُ واتَّحَدَتْ بجسدِهِ.         </language>               </text>                  <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Nt~sebiw de m~v~nobi etkw] m~pikocmoc afmou n~je Ps/ri hiten pic~tauroc: ouoh aftacyon e~bol ha ]oikonomia ya ja[/ e~ya oui~nam.         </language>         <language id="English">            In place of sins which engulf the world, the Son died on the Cross and turned us from the way-of-life on the left to that on the right.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Demi dosa seluruh dunia, Sang Putra mati di kayu Salib. Dia membalikkan jalan kita dari kiri menuju ke kanan.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            وعِوَضَ الخطيةِ المحيطةِ بالعالمِ، ماتَ الابنُ بالصليبِ. ورَدَّنا مِن التدبيرِ الشماليِّ إلى اليمينيِّ.         </language>               </text>                  <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh aferhir/n/ e~bolhiten pic~nof n~te pefc~tauroc: ouoh afer na niv/oui n~ouai nem na p~kahi: ouoh afhotpou pilaoc de on nem nilaoc: ]'u,/ de nem picwma.         </language>         <language id="English">            He made peace through the blood of His Cross, uniting and reconciling the heavenly with the earthly, the  people with the peoples, and the soul with the body.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dia menetapkan rekonsiliasi antara yang surgawi dengan duniawi, dan menyatukan orang-orang yang satu dengan yang lain dan juga jiwa dengan tubuh.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وأمَّنَ بدمِ صليبِهِ ووَحَّدَ وألَّفَ السمائيينَ معَ الأرضيينَ، والشعبَ مع الشعوبِ، والنفسَ مع الجسدِ.          </language>               </text>                        <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh qen pimahsomt n~e~hoou aftwnf e~bolqen pim~hau.         </language>         <language id="English">            And on the third day He rose from the tomb.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dan pada hari ketiga Ia bangkit dari kubur.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وفي اليومِ الثالثِ قامَ من القبرِ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouai pe Emmanou/l: ouoh f~oi n~atvwrj menenca ]metouai: ouoh f~oi n~atvws e~vucic c~nou]: pair/] tennah] pair/] tenero~mologin: ke palin tennah] je paicwma va paic~nof pe: ouoh paic~nof va paicwma pe.         </language>         <language id="English">            One is Immanuel, who is indivisible after the union, and undivided into two natures. Thus we believe, thus we confess, and thus we affirm that this Body belongs to this Blood, and this Blood belongs to this Body.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Satulah  Imanuel, yang tidak dapat dipisahkan sesudah penyatuan; tidak ada pembagian menjadi dua kodrat. Demikianlah kami percaya, demikianlah kami mengaku, dan demikianlah kami menegaskan bahwa Tubuh ini adalah milik Darah ini, dan Darah ini adalah milik Tubuh ini.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            واحدٌ هو عمانوئيلُ، وغيرُ مفترِقٍ مِن بعدِ الاتحادِ، وغيرُ منقسِمٍ إلى طبيعتينِ، هكذا نؤمِنُ، وهكذا نعترِفُ، وهكذا نصدِّقُ، أن هذا الجسدَ لهذا الدمِ وهذا الدمَ لهذا الجسدِ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Nyok pe Pi,~rictoc Pennou] e~tauyokcf qen pefc~vir cap~swi n~}golgoya qen Ieroucal/m eyb/ten.         </language>         <language id="English">            You are Christ our God, who was pierced in His side on Golgotha at Jerusalem for our sake.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Engkau adalah Kristus, Allah kami, yang demi kami, sisi-Mu telah ditikam dengan tombak di ketinggian Golgota di Yerusalem.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أنتَ هو المسيحُ إلـهُنا الذي طُعِنَ في جنبِهِ فوق الجلجلَةِ بأورشليمَ لأجلِنا.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Nyok pe pihi/b n~te Vnou] v/etw~li m~v~nobi n~te pikocmoc: a~ricun,wrin n~nenparaptwma ,w e~bol n~nennobi: ouoh matahon e~raten caouinam m~mok.         </language>         <language id="English">            You are the Lamb of God who takes away the sin of the world. Forgive our trespasses, and remit our sins, and make us stand at Your right-hand side.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Engkaulah Anak Domba Allah yang menghapus dosa dunia. Bebaskan kami dari pelanggaran kami dan buatlah kami berdiri di sebelah kanan-Mu.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            أنتَ هو حملُ اللهِ الحاملُ خطيةِ العالمِ. اغفِرْ ذنوبَنا واترُكْ خطايانا، وأَقِمْنا عن جانِبِكَ اليمينِ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Vnou] Viwt m~Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc: v/e~te e~bol hiten ni,eroubim cec~mou e~rof: ouoh e~bol hiten niceravim ceera~giazin m~mof: ouoh e~bol hiten nia~nanso n~so nem nianany~ba n~y~ba n~te nirefsemsi n~logikon ce[acf.         </language>         <language id="English">            O God, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who is blessed by the cherubim, hallowed by the seraphim, and exalted by thousands of thousands and ten thousand times ten thousand of rational servants;         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Allah, Bapa dari Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus, yang diberkati oleh Kerubim, dikuduskan oleh Serafim, dan ditinggikan oleh ribu ribuan dan puluhan ribu demi puluhan ribu para hamba yang rasional;         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            يا اللهُ أبا ربِّنا يسوعَ المسيحِ الذي من الكاروبيمِ يتبارَكُ، ومن السارافيمِ يتقدَّسُ، ومن ألوفِ ألوفِ وربواتِ ربواتِ الخدامِ الناطقين يتعظمُ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            V/e~tera~giazin ouoh etjwk e~bol n~nidwron nem nikarpoc etaue~nou nak: e~ouc~yoi n~c~yoinoufi: a~ria~giazin on n~nencwma nem nen'u,/ nem nenp~neuma t/ren.         </language>         <language id="English">            who sanctifies and completes the gifts and the fruits that have been brought to You as a sweet savor; sanctify also all of our bodies, souls, and spirits,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            yang menguduskan dan melengkapi karunia dan kepenuhan buah yang telah dibawa kepada-Mu sebagai rasa yang manis; sucikanlah juga seluruh tubuh kami, jiwa kami, dan roh kami,         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            الذي يقدسُ ويكملُ القرابينَ والأثمارِ التي قُدِّمَتْ لكَ رائحةً لذيذةً، قدِّس أيضاً أجسَادَنا وأنفسَنا وأرواحَنا كُلَّنا.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Hina qen ouh/t efouab: nem ouho n~at[isipi: n~tenmou] e~rok Vnou] Viwt etqen niv/oui: ouoh n~tenerp~roceu,ecye enjw m~moc:         </language>         <language id="English">            so that with a pure heart and an unashamed face, we may call upon You, O God, the Father who is in the heavens, and pray, saying,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            sehingga dengan hati yang murni dan wajah yang tanpa malu, kami dapat memanggil-Mu, ya Allah Bapa yang ada di surga, berdoa, dan berkata,         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            لكي بقلبٍ طاهرٍ ووجهٍ غيرِ مخزيٍّ ندعوكَ يا اللهُ الآبُ السماويُّ، ونُصَلِّي قائلين:         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Je Peniwt...         </language>         <language id="English">            Our Father...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Bapa Kami...</language>         <language id="Arabic">            أبانا...         </language>               </text>   </section></document>