<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="TheophanyPeriod | TheophanyParamoun">      <section>         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Fraction to the Father for the Theophany: As You have bestowed...</language><language id="Indonesian">Fraksi bagi Sang Bapa, untuk Perayaan Teofani: "Sebagaimana Engkau telah..</language>            <language id="Arabic">قسمة للآب تقال في عيد الغطاس: إذ أعطيتَنا...</language>         </Title>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Eak] nan m~pih~mot n~te ]mets/ri: hiten pijwkem n~te pioua~hemmici: nem ]metberi n~te Pip~neuma eyouab.            </language>            <language id="English">               As You have bestowed upon us the grace of sonship through the washing of rebirth and renewing of the Holy Spirit,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Sebagaimana Engkau telah memberikan anugerah yang menjadikan kami anak-Mu, melalui pembasuhan kelahiran kembali dan pembaharuan oleh Roh Kudus,            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               إذ أعطيتَنا نعمةَ البنوةِ بحميمِ الميلادِ الجديدِ، وتجديدِ الروحِ القدسِ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh ]nou on a~riten n~emp~sa qen oumetatsobi: nem ouh/t efouab nem oucunid/cic ecmeh m~parr/cia: nem hanc~votou n~athei eyrentwbh m~mok abba Viwt.            </language>            <language id="English">               so make us worthy now also, that, without hypocrisy, with a pure heart, a conscience full of boldness, and unerring lips, we may entreat You, O Abba Father,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Maka, sekarang, jadikanlah kami layak, tanpa kemunafikan, dengan hati yang murni, hati nurani yang penuh kejujuran, dan bibir yang berdosa, supaya kami memohon kepada-Mu, ya Abba, Bapa.</language>            <language id="Arabic">               الآن أيضاً اجعَلْنا مستحقينَ، بغيرِ رياءٍ، وبقَلْبٍ طاهرٍ، ونيةٍ مملوءَةٍ دالةٍ، وشفتينِ غيرِ ساقطتينِ، أن نطلبَ إليكَ يا أَبَّا الآب.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Hina e~an,w e~q~r/i n~]mete~v~l/ou n~te ]metrefkem/s n~caji n~te nieynoc: nem ]metrefhip~ho n~te Niioudai.            </language>            <language id="English">               so that having abandoned the vanity of the excessive words of the heathen and the haughtiness of the Jews,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Sehingga, sebagaimana kami telah meninggalkan perkataan yang sia-sia dari mereka yang tidak mengenal Engkau dan juga keangkuhan dari orang Yahudi,            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               لكي إذ تركناباطلَ كثرةِ كلامِالأممِ واستكبارِاليهودِ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ntens~jemjom n~i~ni nak e~qoun m~pi]ho n~te ]p~roceu,/: kata ]nomoyecia eymeh n~oujai n~te pekmonogen/c n~S/ri.            </language>            <language id="English">               we may be able to offer unto You the supplication of prayer according to the decree of Your only-begotten Son, which is full of salvation.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kami boleh dapat mempersembahkan kepada-Mu permohonan doa, sesuai dengan aturan dari PutraTunggal-Mu yang penuh keselamatan.</language>            <language id="Arabic">               نستطيعَ أن نقدمَ لكَ سؤالَ الصلاةِ، كشريعةِ ابنِكَ الوحيدِ المملوءَةِ خلاصاً.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Qen ouc~m/ men ecyebi/out ecerp~repi n~ni,~rictianoc: qen outoubo de n~te ]'u,/ nem picwma nem pip~neuma.            </language>            <language id="English">               So with a humble voice befitting Christians, and with purity of soul, body, and spirit,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Jadi, dengan suara yang rendah hati yang selayaknya sebagai orang Kristen, dan dengan kemurnian jiwa, tubuh dan roh,            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               فبصوتٍ متواضِعٍ يليقُ بالمسيحيينَ، وبطهارةِ النفسِ والجسدِ والروحِ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ntenertolman qen oumetatho] e~ws oub/k: n~yok piatcontf ouoh n~atar,/ ouoh n~atj~vof: v~n/b n~ouon niben: Vnou] Viwt eyouab etqen niv/oui ouoh e~joc.            </language>            <language id="English">               we dare without fear to cry out to You who are uncreated, without beginning, and unbegotten, the Master of everyone, God the holy Father, who is in the heavens, and say,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kami berani tanpa rasa takut untuk berseru kepada-Mu, Yang tidak diciptakan, Yang tanpa awal dan Yang tidak dilahirkan, Penguasa semua orang, Allah, Bapa yang kudus, yang ada di surga dan berkata:</language>            <language id="Arabic">               نجسُرُ بغيرِ خوفٍ أن نصرُخَ إليكَ أنتَ غيرُ المخلوقِ ولا مُبتدِئ ولا مولودٍ، سيدُ كلِّ أحدٍ، اللهُ الآبُ القدوسُ الذي في السمواتِ، ونقولَ:            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je Peniwt...            </language>            <language id="English">               Our Father...            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Bapa kami..            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أبانا...            </language>                  </text>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/fractions/StJohnTheBaptist"/>   </season></document>