<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, To the saints who are in Ephesus, and faithful in Christ Jesus: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">بولس رسول يسوع المسيح بمشيئة الله الى القديسين الذين في افسس والمؤمنون في المسيح يسوع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Dari Paulus, rasul Kristus Yesus oleh kehendak Allah, kepada orang-orang kudus di Efesus, orang-orang percaya dalam Kristus Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">نعمة لكم وسلام من الله ابينا والرب يسوع المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Kasih karunia dan damai sejahtera dari Allah, Bapa kita dan dari Tuhan Yesus Kristus menyertai kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Blessed [be] the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has blessed us with every spiritual blessing in the heavenly [places] in Christ, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">مبارك الله ابو ربنا يسوع المسيح الذي باركنا بكل بركة روحية في السماويات في المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Terpujilah Allah dan Bapa Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus yang dalam Kristus telah mengaruniakan kepada kita segala berkat rohani di dalam sorga.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> just as He chose us in Him before the foundation of the world, that we should be holy and without blame before Him in love, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">كما اختارنا فيه قبل تأسيس العالم لنكون قديسين وبلا لوم قدامه في المحبة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Sebab di dalam Dia Allah telah memilih kita sebelum dunia dijadikan, supaya kita kudus dan tak bercacat di hadapan-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> having predestined us to adoption as sons by Jesus Christ to Himself, according to the good pleasure of His will, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">اذ سبق فعيّننا للتبني بيسوع المسيح لنفسه حسب مسرة مشيئته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Dalam kasih Ia telah menentukan kita dari semula oleh Yesus Kristus untuk menjadi anak-anak-Nya, sesuai dengan kerelaan kehendak-Nya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> to the praise of the glory of His grace, by which He has made us accepted in the Beloved. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لمدح مجد نعمته التي انعم بها علينا في المحبوب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">supaya terpujilah kasih karunia-Nya yang mulia, yang dikaruniakan-Nya kepada kita di dalam Dia, yang dikasihi-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> In Him we have redemption through His blood, the forgiveness of sins, according to the riches of His grace </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">الذي فيه لنا الفداء بدمه غفران الخطايا حسب غنى نعمته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Sebab di dalam Dia dan oleh darah-Nya kita beroleh penebusan, yaitu pengampunan dosa, menurut kekayaan kasih karunia-Nya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> which He made to abound toward us in all wisdom and prudence, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">التي اجزلها لنا بكل حكمة وفطنة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">yang dilimpahkan-Nya kepada kita dalam segala hikmat dan pengertian.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> having made known to us the mystery of His will, according to His good pleasure which He purposed in Himself, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">اذ عرّفنا بسر مشيئته حسب مسرته التي قصدها في نفسه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Sebab Ia telah menyatakan rahasia kehendak-Nya kepada kita, sesuai dengan rencana kerelaan-Nya, yaitu rencana kerelaan yang dari semula telah ditetapkan-Nya di dalam Kristus</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> that in the dispensation of the fullness of the times He might gather together in one all things in Christ, both which are in heaven and which are on earth -- in Him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لتدبير ملء الازمنة ليجمع كل شيء في المسيح ما في السموات وما على الارض في ذاك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">sebagai persiapan kegenapan waktu untuk mempersatukan di dalam Kristus sebagai Kepala segala sesuatu, baik yang di sorga maupun yang di bumi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> In Him also we have obtained an inheritance, being predestined according to the purpose of Him who works all things according to the counsel of His will, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">الذي فيه ايضا نلنا نصيبا معيّنين سابقا حسب قصد الذي يعمل كل شيء حسب رأي مشيئته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Aku katakan "di dalam Kristus", karena di dalam Dialah kami mendapat bagian yang dijanjikan--kami yang dari semula ditentukan untuk menerima bagian itu sesuai dengan maksud Allah, yang di dalam segala sesuatu bekerja menurut keputusan kehendak-Nya--</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> that we who first trusted in Christ should be to the praise of His glory. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">لنكون لمدح مجده نحن الذين قد سبق رجاؤنا في المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">supaya kami, yang sebelumnya telah menaruh harapan pada Kristus, boleh menjadi puji-pujian bagi kemuliaan-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> In Him you also [trusted,] after you heard the word of truth, the gospel of your salvation; in whom also, having believed, you were sealed with the Holy Spirit of promise, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">الذي فيه ايضا انتم اذ سمعتم كلمة الحق انجيل خلاصكم الذي فيه ايضا اذ آمنتم ختمتم بروح الموعد القدوس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Di dalam Dia kamu juga--karena kamu telah mendengar firman kebenaran, yaitu Injil keselamatanmu--di dalam Dia kamu juga, ketika kamu percaya, dimeteraikan dengan Roh Kudus, yang dijanjikan-Nya itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> who is the guarantee of our inheritance until the redemption of the purchased possession, to the praise of His glory. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">الذي هو عربون ميراثنا لفداء المقتنى لمدح مجده</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Dan Roh Kudus itu adalah jaminan bagian kita sampai kita memperoleh seluruhnya, yaitu penebusan yang menjadikan kita milik Allah, untuk memuji kemuliaan-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Therefore I also, after I heard of your faith in the Lord Jesus and your love for all the saints, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">لذلك انا ايضا اذ قد سمعت بايمانكم بالرب يسوع ومحبتكم نحو جميع القديسين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Karena itu, setelah aku mendengar tentang imanmu dalam Tuhan Yesus dan tentang kasihmu terhadap semua orang kudus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> do not cease to give thanks for you, making mention of you in my prayers: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لا ازال شاكرا لاجلكم ذاكرا اياكم في صلواتي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">akupun tidak berhenti mengucap syukur karena kamu. Dan aku selalu mengingat kamu dalam doaku,</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> that the God of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Father of glory, may give to you the spirit of wisdom and revelation in the knowledge of Him, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">كي يعطيكم اله ربنا يسوع المسيح ابو المجد روح الحكمة والاعلان في معرفته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">dan meminta kepada Allah Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus, yaitu Bapa yang mulia itu, supaya Ia memberikan kepadamu Roh hikmat dan wahyu untuk mengenal Dia dengan benar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> the eyes of your understanding being enlightened; that you may know what is the hope of His calling, what are the riches of the glory of His inheritance in the saints, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">مستنيرة عيون اذهانكم لتعلموا ما هو رجاء دعوته وما هو غنى مجد ميراثه في القديسين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Dan supaya Ia menjadikan mata hatimu terang, agar kamu mengerti pengharapan apakah yang terkandung dalam panggilan-Nya: betapa kayanya kemuliaan bagian yang ditentukan-Nya bagi orang-orang kudus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> and what [is] the exceeding greatness of His power toward us who believe, according to the working of His mighty power </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">وما هي عظمة قدرته الفائقة نحونا نحن المؤمنين حسب عمل شدة قوته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">dan betapa hebat kuasa-Nya bagi kita yang percaya, sesuai dengan kekuatan kuasa-Nya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> which He worked in Christ when He raised Him from the dead and seated [Him] at His right hand in the heavenly [places,] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">الذي عمله في المسيح اذ اقامه من الاموات واجلسه عن يمينه في السماويات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">yang dikerjakan-Nya di dalam Kristus dengan membangkitkan Dia dari antara orang mati dan mendudukkan Dia di sebelah kanan-Nya di sorga,</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> far above all principality and power and might and dominion, and every name that is named, not only in this age but also in that which is to come. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">فوق كل رياسة وسلطان وقوة وسيادة وكل اسم يسمى ليس في هذا الدهر فقط بل في المستقبل ايضا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">jauh lebih tinggi dari segala pemerintah dan penguasa dan kekuasaan dan kerajaan dan tiap-tiap nama yang dapat disebut, bukan hanya di dunia ini saja, melainkan juga di dunia yang akan datang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> And He put all [things] under His feet, and gave Him [to be] head over all [things] to the church, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">واخضع كل شيء تحت قدميه واياه جعل راسا فوق كل شيء للكنيسة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Dan segala sesuatu telah diletakkan-Nya di bawah kaki Kristus dan Dia telah diberikan-Nya kepada jemaat sebagai Kepala dari segala yang ada.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> which is His body, the fullness of Him who fills all in all. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">التي هي جسده ملء الذي يملأ الكل في الكل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Jemaat yang adalah tubuh-Nya, yaitu kepenuhan Dia, yang memenuhi semua dan segala sesuatu.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="2">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> And you [He made alive,] who were dead in trespasses and sins, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وانتم اذ كنتم امواتا بالذنوب والخطايا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Kamu dahulu sudah mati karena pelanggaran-pelanggaran dan dosa-dosamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> in which you once walked according to the course of this world, according to the prince of the power of the air, the spirit who now works in the sons of disobedience, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">التي سلكتم فيها قبلا حسب دهر هذا العالم حسب رئيس سلطان الهواء الروح الذي يعمل الآن في ابناء المعصية</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Kamu hidup di dalamnya, karena kamu mengikuti jalan dunia ini, karena kamu mentaati penguasa kerajaan angkasa, yaitu roh yang sekarang sedang bekerja di antara orang-orang durhaka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> among whom also we all once conducted ourselves in the lusts of our flesh, fulfilling the desires of the flesh and of the mind, and were by nature children of wrath, just as the others. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">الذين نحن ايضا جميعا تصرفنا قبلا بينهم في شهوات جسدنا عاملين مشيئات الجسد والافكار وكنا بالطبيعة ابناء الغضب كالباقين ايضا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Sebenarnya dahulu kami semua juga terhitung di antara mereka, ketika kami hidup di dalam hawa nafsu daging dan menuruti kehendak daging dan pikiran kami yang jahat. Pada dasarnya kami adalah orang-orang yang harus dimurkai, sama seperti mereka yang lain.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> But God, who is rich in mercy, because of His great love with which He loved us, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">الله الذي هو غني في الرحمة من اجل محبته الكثيرة التي احبنا بها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Tetapi Allah yang kaya dengan rahmat, oleh karena kasih-Nya yang besar, yang dilimpahkan-Nya kepada kita,</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> even when we were dead in trespasses, made us alive together with Christ (by grace you have been saved), </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">ونحن اموات بالخطايا احيانا مع المسيح. بالنعمة انتم مخلّصون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">telah menghidupkan kita bersama-sama dengan Kristus, sekalipun kita telah mati oleh kesalahan-kesalahan kita--oleh kasih karunia kamu diselamatkan--</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> and raised [us] up together, and made [us] sit together in the heavenly [places] in Christ Jesus, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">واقامنا معه واجلسنا معه في السماويات في المسيح يسوع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">dan di dalam Kristus Yesus Ia telah membangkitkan kita juga dan memberikan tempat bersama-sama dengan Dia di sorga,</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> that in the ages to come He might show the exceeding riches of His grace in [His] kindness toward us in Christ Jesus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">ليظهر في الدهور الآتية غنى نعمته الفائق باللطف علينا في المسيح يسوع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">supaya pada masa yang akan datang Ia menunjukkan kepada kita kekayaan kasih karunia-Nya yang melimpah-limpah sesuai dengan kebaikan-Nya terhadap kita dalam Kristus Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> For by grace you have been saved through faith, and that not of yourselves; [it is] the gift of God, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لانكم بالنعمة مخلّصون بالايمان وذلك ليس منكم. هو عطية الله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Sebab karena kasih karunia kamu diselamatkan oleh iman; itu bukan hasil usahamu, tetapi pemberian Allah,</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> not of works, lest anyone should boast. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ليس من اعمال كي لا يفتخر احد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">itu bukan hasil pekerjaanmu: jangan ada orang yang memegahkan diri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> For we are His workmanship, created in Christ Jesus for good works, which God prepared beforehand that we should walk in them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لاننا نحن عمله مخلوقين في المسيح يسوع لاعمال صالحة قد سبق الله فاعدها لكي نسلك فيها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Karena kita ini buatan Allah, diciptakan dalam Kristus Yesus untuk melakukan pekerjaan baik, yang dipersiapkan Allah sebelumnya. Ia mau, supaya kita hidup di dalamnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Therefore remember that you, once Gentiles in the flesh -- who are called Uncircumcision by what is called the Circumcision made in the flesh by hands -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لذلك اذكروا انكم انتم الامم قبلا في الجسد المدعوين غرلة من المدعو ختانا مصنوعا باليد في الجسد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Karena itu ingatlah, bahwa dahulu kamu--sebagai orang-orang bukan Yahudi menurut daging, yang disebut orang-orang tak bersunat oleh mereka yang menamakan dirinya "sunat", yaitu sunat lahiriah yang dikerjakan oleh tangan manusia, --</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> that at that time you were without Christ, being aliens from the commonwealth of Israel and strangers from the covenants of promise, having no hope and without God in the world. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">انكم كنتم في ذلك الوقت بدون مسيح اجنبيين عن رعوية اسرائيل وغرباء عن عهود الموعد لا رجاء لكم وبلا اله في العالم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">bahwa waktu itu kamu tanpa Kristus, tidak termasuk kewargaan Israel dan tidak mendapat bagian dalam ketentuan-ketentuan yang dijanjikan, tanpa pengharapan dan tanpa Allah di dalam dunia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> But now in Christ Jesus you who once were far off have been brought near by the blood of Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ولكن الآن في المسيح يسوع انتم الذين كنتم قبلا بعيدين صرتم قريبين بدم المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Tetapi sekarang di dalam Kristus Yesus kamu, yang dahulu "jauh", sudah menjadi "dekat" oleh darah Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> For He Himself is our peace, who has made both one, and has broken down the middle wall of separation, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">لانه هو سلامنا الذي جعل الاثنين واحدا ونقض حائط السياج المتوسط</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Karena Dialah damai sejahtera kita, yang telah mempersatukan kedua pihak dan yang telah merubuhkan tembok pemisah, yaitu perseteruan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> having abolished in His flesh the enmity, [that is,] the law of commandments [contained] in ordinances, so as to create in Himself one new man [from] the two, [thus] making peace, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">اي العداوة. مبطلا بجسده ناموس الوصايا في فرائض لكي يخلق الاثنين في نفسه انسانا واحدا جديدا صانعا سلاما</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">sebab dengan mati-Nya sebagai manusia Ia telah membatalkan hukum Taurat dengan segala perintah dan ketentuannya, untuk menciptakan keduanya menjadi satu manusia baru di dalam diri-Nya, dan dengan itu mengadakan damai sejahtera,</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> and that He might reconcile them both to God in one body through the cross, thereby putting to death the enmity. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">ويصالح الاثنين في جسد واحد مع الله بالصليب قاتلا العداوة به.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">dan untuk memperdamaikan keduanya, di dalam satu tubuh, dengan Allah oleh salib, dengan melenyapkan perseteruan pada salib itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> And He came and preached peace to you who were afar off and to those who were near. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فجاء وبشركم بسلام انتم البعيدين والقريبين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Ia datang dan memberitakan damai sejahtera kepada kamu yang "jauh" dan damai sejahtera kepada mereka yang "dekat",</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> For through Him we both have access by one Spirit to the Father. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">لان به لنا كلينا قدوما في روح واحد الى الآب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">karena oleh Dia kita kedua pihak dalam satu Roh beroleh jalan masuk kepada Bapa.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> Now, therefore, you are no longer strangers and foreigners, but fellow citizens with the saints and members of the household of God, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">فلستم اذا بعد غرباء ونزلا بل رعية مع القديسين واهل بيت الله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Demikianlah kamu bukan lagi orang asing dan pendatang, melainkan kawan sewarga dari orang-orang kudus dan anggota-anggota keluarga Allah,</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> having been built on the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Jesus Christ Himself being the chief corner[stone,] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">مبنيين على اساس الرسل والانبياء ويسوع المسيح نفسه حجر الزاوية</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">yang dibangun di atas dasar para rasul dan para nabi, dengan Kristus Yesus sebagai batu penjuru.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> in whom the whole building, being joined together, grows into a holy temple in the Lord, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">الذي فيه كل البناء مركبا معا ينمو هيكلا مقدسا في الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Di dalam Dia tumbuh seluruh bangunan, rapih tersusun, menjadi bait Allah yang kudus, di dalam Tuhan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> in whom you also are being built together for a dwelling place of God in the Spirit. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">الذي فيه انتم ايضا مبنيون معا مسكنا للّه في الروح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Di dalam Dia kamu juga turut dibangunkan menjadi tempat kediaman Allah, di dalam Roh.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="3">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> For this reason I, Paul, the prisoner of Christ Jesus for you Gentiles -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">بسبب هذا انا بولس اسير المسيح يسوع لاجلكم ايها الامم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Itulah sebabnya aku ini, Paulus, orang yang dipenjarakan karena Kristus Yesus untuk kamu orang-orang yang tidak mengenal Allah</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> if indeed you have heard of the dispensation of the grace of God which was given to me for you, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">ان كنتم قد سمعتم بتدبير نعمة الله المعطاة لي لاجلكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">--memang kamu telah mendengar tentang tugas penyelenggaraan kasih karunia Allah, yang dipercayakan kepadaku karena kamu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> how that by revelation He made known to me the mystery (as I have briefly written already, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">انه باعلان عرّفني بالسر. كما سبقت فكتبت بالايجاز.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">yaitu bagaimana rahasianya dinyatakan kepadaku dengan wahyu, seperti yang telah kutulis di atas dengan singkat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> by which, when you read, you may understand my knowledge in the mystery of Christ), </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">الذي بحسبه حينما تقرأونه تقدرون ان تفهموا درايتي بسر المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Apabila kamu membacanya, kamu dapat mengetahui dari padanya pengertianku akan rahasia Kristus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> which in other ages was not made known to the sons of men, as it has now been revealed by the Spirit to His holy apostles and prophets: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">الذي في اجيال أخر لم يعرف به بنو البشر كما قد أعلن الآن لرسله القديسين وانبيائه بالروح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">yang pada zaman angkatan-angkatan dahulu tidak diberitakan kepada anak-anak manusia, tetapi yang sekarang dinyatakan di dalam Roh kepada rasul-rasul dan nabi-nabi-Nya yang kudus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> that the Gentiles should be fellow heirs, of the same body, and partakers of His promise in Christ through the gospel, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ان الامم شركاء في الميراث والجسد ونوال موعده في المسيح بالانجيل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">yaitu bahwa orang-orang bukan Yahudi, karena Berita Injil, turut menjadi ahli-ahli waris dan anggota-anggota tubuh dan peserta dalam janji yang diberikan dalam Kristus Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> of which I became a minister according to the gift of the grace of God given to me by the effective working of His power. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">الذي صرت انا خادما له حسب موهبة نعمة الله المعطاة لي حسب فعل قوته.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Dari Injil itu aku telah menjadi pelayannya menurut pemberian kasih karunia Allah, yang dianugerahkan kepadaku sesuai dengan pengerjaan kuasa-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> To me, who am less than the least of all the saints, this grace was given, that I should preach among the Gentiles the unsearchable riches of Christ, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لي انا اصغر جميع القديسين أعطيت هذه النعمة ان ابشر بين الامم بغنى المسيح الذي لا يستقصى</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Kepadaku, yang paling hina di antara segala orang kudus, telah dianugerahkan kasih karunia ini, untuk memberitakan kepada orang-orang bukan Yahudi kekayaan Kristus, yang tidak terduga itu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> and to make all see what [is] the fellowship of the mystery, which from the beginning of the ages has been hidden in God who created all things through Jesus Christ; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">وانير الجميع في ما هو شركة السر المكتوم منذ الدهور في الله خالق الجميع بيسوع المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">dan untuk menyatakan apa isinya tugas penyelenggaraan rahasia yang telah berabad-abad tersembunyi dalam Allah, yang menciptakan segala sesuatu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> to the intent that now the manifold wisdom of God might be made known by the church to the principalities and powers in the heavenly [places,] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لكي يعرّف الآن عند الرؤساء والسلاطين في السماويات بواسطة الكنيسة بحكمة الله المتنوعة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">supaya sekarang oleh jemaat diberitahukan pelbagai ragam hikmat Allah kepada pemerintah-pemerintah dan penguasa-penguasa di sorga,</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> according to the eternal purpose which He accomplished in Christ Jesus our Lord, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">حسب قصد الدهور الذي صنعه في المسيح يسوع ربنا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">sesuai dengan maksud abadi, yang telah dilaksanakan-Nya dalam Kristus Yesus, Tuhan kita.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> in whom we have boldness and access with confidence through faith in Him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">الذي به لنا جراءة وقدوم بايمانه عن ثقة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Di dalam Dia kita beroleh keberanian dan jalan masuk kepada Allah dengan penuh kepercayaan oleh iman kita kepada-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Therefore I ask that you do not lose heart at my tribulations for you, which is your glory. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">لذلك اطلب ان لا تكلّوا في شدائدي لاجلكم التي هي مجدكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Sebab itu aku minta kepadamu, supaya kamu jangan tawar hati melihat kesesakanku karena kamu, karena kesesakanku itu adalah kemuliaanmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> For this reason I bow my knees to the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">بسبب هذا احني ركبتيّ لدى ابي ربنا يسوع المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Itulah sebabnya aku sujud kepada Bapa,</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> from whom the whole family in heaven and earth is named, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">الذي منه تسمى كل عشيرة في السموات وعلى الارض.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">yang dari pada-Nya semua turunan yang di dalam sorga dan di atas bumi menerima namanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> that He would grant you, according to the riches of His glory, to be strengthened with might through His Spirit in the inner man, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لكي يعطيكم بحسب غنى مجده ان تتأيدوا بالقوة بروحه في الانسان الباطن</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Aku berdoa supaya Ia, menurut kekayaan kemuliaan-Nya, menguatkan dan meneguhkan kamu oleh Roh-Nya di dalam batinmu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> that Christ may dwell in your hearts through faith; that you, being rooted and grounded in love, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ليحل المسيح بالايمان في قلوبكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">sehingga oleh imanmu Kristus diam di dalam hatimu dan kamu berakar serta berdasar di dalam kasih.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> may be able to comprehend with all the saints what [is] the width and length and depth and height -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">وانتم متأصلون ومتأسسون في المحبة حتى تستطيعوا ان تدركوا مع جميع القديسين ما هو العرض والطول والعمق والعلو</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Aku berdoa, supaya kamu bersama-sama dengan segala orang kudus dapat memahami, betapa lebarnya dan panjangnya dan tingginya dan dalamnya kasih Kristus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> to know the love of Christ which passes knowledge; that you may be filled with all the fullness of God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">وتعرفوا محبة المسيح الفائقة المعرفة لكي تمتلئوا الى كل ملء الله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">dan dapat mengenal kasih itu, sekalipun ia melampaui segala pengetahuan. Aku berdoa, supaya kamu dipenuhi di dalam seluruh kepenuhan Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> Now to Him who is able to do exceedingly abundantly above all that we ask or think, according to the power that works in us, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">والقادر ان يفعل فوق كل شيء اكثر جدا مما نطلب او نفتكر بحسب القوة التي تعمل فينا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Bagi Dialah, yang dapat melakukan jauh lebih banyak dari pada yang kita doakan atau pikirkan, seperti yang ternyata dari kuasa yang bekerja di dalam kita,</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> to Him [be] glory in the church by Christ Jesus to all generations, forever and ever. Amen. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">له المجد في الكنيسة في المسيح يسوع الى جميع اجيال دهر الدهور. آمين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">bagi Dialah kemuliaan di dalam jemaat dan di dalam Kristus Yesus turun-temurun sampai selama-lamanya. Amin.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="4">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> I, therefore, the prisoner of the Lord, beseech you to walk worthy of the calling with which you were called, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">فاطلب اليكم انا الاسير في الرب ان تسلكوا كما يحق للدعوة التي دعيتم بها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Sebab itu aku menasihatkan kamu, aku, orang yang dipenjarakan karena Tuhan, supaya hidupmu sebagai orang-orang yang telah dipanggil berpadanan dengan panggilan itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> with all lowliness and gentleness, with longsuffering, bearing with one another in love, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">بكل تواضع ووداعة وبطول اناة محتملين بعضكم بعضا في المحبة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Hendaklah kamu selalu rendah hati, lemah lembut, dan sabar. Tunjukkanlah kasihmu dalam hal saling membantu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> endeavoring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">مجتهدين ان تحفظوا وحدانية الروح برباط السلام.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Dan berusahalah memelihara kesatuan Roh oleh ikatan damai sejahtera:</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> [There is] one body and one Spirit, just as you were called in one hope of your calling; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">جسد واحد وروح واحد كما دعيتم ايضا في رجاء دعوتكم الواحد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">satu tubuh, dan satu Roh, sebagaimana kamu telah dipanggil kepada satu pengharapan yang terkandung dalam panggilanmu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> one Lord, one faith, one baptism; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">رب واحد ايمان واحد معمودية واحدة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">satu Tuhan, satu iman, satu baptisan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> one God and Father of all, who [is] above all, and through all, and in you all. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">اله وآب واحد للكل الذي على الكل وبالكل وفي كلكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">satu Allah dan Bapa dari semua, Allah yang di atas semua dan oleh semua dan di dalam semua.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> But to each one of us grace was given according to the measure of Christ's gift. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">ولكن لكل واحد منا اعطيت النعمة حسب قياس هبة المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Tetapi kepada kita masing-masing telah dianugerahkan kasih karunia menurut ukuran pemberian Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Therefore He says: "When He ascended on high, He led captivity captive, And gave gifts to men." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لذلك يقول. اذ صعد الى العلاء سبى سبيا واعطى الناس عطايا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Itulah sebabnya kata nas: "Tatkala Ia naik ke tempat tinggi, Ia membawa tawanan-tawanan; Ia memberikan pemberian-pemberian kepada manusia."</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> (Now this, "He ascended" -- what does it mean but that He also first descended into the lower parts of the earth? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">واما انه صعد فما هو الا انه نزل ايضا اولا الى اقسام الارض السفلى.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Bukankah "Ia telah naik" berarti, bahwa Ia juga telah turun ke bagian bumi yang paling bawah?</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> He who descended is also the One who ascended far above all the heavens, that He might fill all things.) </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">الذي نزل هو الذي صعد ايضا فوق جميع السموات لكي يملأ الكل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Ia yang telah turun, Ia juga yang telah naik jauh lebih tinggi dari pada semua langit, untuk memenuhkan segala sesuatu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> And He Himself gave some [to be] apostles, some prophets, some evangelists, and some pastors and teachers, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">وهو اعطى البعض ان يكونوا رسلا والبعض انبياء والبعض مبشرين والبعض رعاة ومعلّمين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Dan Ialah yang memberikan baik rasul-rasul maupun nabi-nabi, baik pemberita-pemberita Injil maupun gembala-gembala dan pengajar-pengajar,</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> for the equipping of the saints for the work of ministry, for the edifying of the body of Christ, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">لاجل تكميل القديسين لعمل الخدمة لبنيان جسد المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">untuk memperlengkapi orang-orang kudus bagi pekerjaan pelayanan, bagi pembangunan tubuh Kristus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> till we all come to the unity of the faith and of the knowledge of the Son of God, to a perfect man, to the measure of the stature of the fullness of Christ; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">الى ان ننتهي جميعنا الى وحدانية الايمان ومعرفة ابن الله. الى انسان كامل. الى قياس قامة ملء المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">sampai kita semua telah mencapai kesatuan iman dan pengetahuan yang benar tentang Anak Allah, kedewasaan penuh, dan tingkat pertumbuhan yang sesuai dengan kepenuhan Kristus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> that we should no longer be children, tossed to and fro and carried about with every wind of doctrine, by the trickery of men, in the cunning craftiness of deceitful plotting, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">كي لا نكون فيما بعد اطفالا مضطربين ومحمولين بكل ريح تعليم بحيلة الناس بمكر الى مكيدة الضلال.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">sehingga kita bukan lagi anak-anak, yang diombang-ambingkan oleh rupa-rupa angin pengajaran, oleh permainan palsu manusia dalam kelicikan mereka yang menyesatkan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> but, speaking the truth in love, may grow up in all things into Him who is the head -- Christ -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">بل صادقين في المحبة ننمو في كل شيء الى ذاك الذي هو الراس المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">tetapi dengan teguh berpegang kepada kebenaran di dalam kasih kita bertumbuh di dalam segala hal ke arah Dia, Kristus, yang adalah Kepala.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> from whom the whole body, joined and knit together by what every joint supplies, according to the effective working by which every part does its share, causes growth of the body for the edifying of itself in love. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">الذي منه كل الجسد مركبا معا ومقترنا بموازرة كل مفصل حسب عمل على قياس كل جزء يحصّل نمو الجسد لبنيانه في المحبة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Dari pada-Nyalah seluruh tubuh, --yang rapih tersusun dan diikat menjadi satu oleh pelayanan semua bagiannya, sesuai dengan kadar pekerjaan tiap-tiap anggota--menerima pertumbuhannya dan membangun dirinya dalam kasih.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> This I say, therefore, and testify in the Lord, that you should no longer walk as the rest of the Gentiles walk, in the futility of their mind, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فاقول هذا واشهد في الرب ان لا تسلكوا في ما بعد كما يسلك سائر الامم ايضا ببطل ذهنهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Sebab itu kukatakan dan kutegaskan ini kepadamu di dalam Tuhan: Jangan hidup lagi sama seperti orang-orang yang tidak mengenal Allah dengan pikirannya yang sia-sia</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> having their understanding darkened, being alienated from the life of God, because of the ignorance that is in them, because of the blindness of their heart; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">اذ هم مظلمو الفكر ومتجنبون عن حياة الله لسبب الجهل الذي فيهم بسبب غلاظة قلوبهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">dan pengertiannya yang gelap, jauh dari hidup persekutuan dengan Allah, karena kebodohan yang ada di dalam mereka dan karena kedegilan hati mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> who, being past feeling, have given themselves over to lewdness, to work all uncleanness with greediness. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">الذين اذ هم قد فقدوا الحس اسلموا نفوسهم للدعارة ليعملوا كل نجاسة في الطمع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Perasaan mereka telah tumpul, sehingga mereka menyerahkan diri kepada hawa nafsu dan mengerjakan dengan serakah segala macam kecemaran.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> But you have not so learned Christ, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">واما انتم فلم تتعلّموا المسيح هكذا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Tetapi kamu bukan demikian. Kamu telah belajar mengenal Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> if indeed you have heard Him and have been taught by Him, as the truth is in Jesus: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">ان كنتم قد سمعتموه وعلمتم فيه كما هو حق في يسوع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Karena kamu telah mendengar tentang Dia dan menerima pengajaran di dalam Dia menurut kebenaran yang nyata dalam Yesus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> that you put off, concerning your former conduct, the old man which grows corrupt according to the deceitful lusts, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">ان تخلعوا من جهة التصرف السابق الانسان العتيق الفاسد بحسب شهوات الغرور</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">yaitu bahwa kamu, berhubung dengan kehidupan kamu yang dahulu, harus menanggalkan manusia lama, yang menemui kebinasaannya oleh nafsunya yang menyesatkan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> and be renewed in the spirit of your mind, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">وتتجددوا بروح ذهنكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">supaya kamu dibaharui di dalam roh dan pikiranmu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> and that you put on the new man which was created according to God, in true righteousness and holiness. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">وتلبسوا الانسان الجديد المخلوق بحسب الله في البر وقداسة الحق</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">dan mengenakan manusia baru, yang telah diciptakan menurut kehendak Allah di dalam kebenaran dan kekudusan yang sesungguhnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> Therefore, putting away lying, ["Let] each one [of you] speak truth with his neighbor," for we are members of one another. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">لذلك اطرحوا عنكم الكذب وتكلموا بالصدق كل واحد مع قريبه. لاننا بعضنا اعضاء البعض.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Karena itu buanglah dusta dan berkatalah benar seorang kepada yang lain, karena kita adalah sesama anggota.</language></verse>
			<verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26"> "Be angry, and do not sin": do not let the sun go down on your wrath, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">اغضبوا ولا تخطئوا. لا تغرب الشمس على غيظكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">Apabila kamu menjadi marah, janganlah kamu berbuat dosa: janganlah matahari terbenam, sebelum padam amarahmu</language></verse>
			<verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27"> nor give place to the devil. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">ولا تعطوا ابليس مكانا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">dan janganlah beri kesempatan kepada Iblis.</language></verse>
			<verse num="28"><language id="English" verse="28"> Let him who stole steal no longer, but rather let him labor, working with [his] hands what is good, that he may have something to give him who has need. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="28">لا يسرق السارق في ما بعد بل بالحري يتعب عاملا الصالح بيديه ليكون له ان يعطي من له احتياج.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="28">Orang yang mencuri, janganlah ia mencuri lagi, tetapi baiklah ia bekerja keras dan melakukan pekerjaan yang baik dengan tangannya sendiri, supaya ia dapat membagikan sesuatu kepada orang yang berkekurangan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="29"><language id="English" verse="29"> Let no corrupt word proceed out of your mouth, but what is good for necessary edification, that it may impart grace to the hearers. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="29">لا تخرج كلمة رديّة من افواهكم بل كل ما كان صالحا للبنيان حسب الحاجة كي يعطي نعمة للسامعين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="29">Janganlah ada perkataan kotor keluar dari mulutmu, tetapi pakailah perkataan yang baik untuk membangun, di mana perlu, supaya mereka yang mendengarnya, beroleh kasih karunia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="30"><language id="English" verse="30"> And do not grieve the Holy Spirit of God, by whom you were sealed for the day of redemption. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="30">ولا تحزنوا روح الله القدوس الذي به ختمتم ليوم الفداء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="30">Dan janganlah kamu mendukakan Roh Kudus Allah, yang telah memeteraikan kamu menjelang hari penyelamatan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="31"><language id="English" verse="31"> Let all bitterness, wrath, anger, clamor, and evil speaking be put away from you, with all malice. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="31">ليرفع من بينكم كل مرارة وسخط وغضب وصياح وتجديف مع كل خبث.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="31">Segala kepahitan, kegeraman, kemarahan, pertikaian dan fitnah hendaklah dibuang dari antara kamu, demikian pula segala kejahatan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="32"><language id="English" verse="32"> And be kind to one another, tenderhearted, forgiving one another, just as God in Christ forgave you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="32">وكونوا لطفاء بعضكم نحو بعض شفوقين متسامحين كما سامحكم الله ايضا في المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="32">Tetapi hendaklah kamu ramah seorang terhadap yang lain, penuh kasih mesra dan saling mengampuni, sebagaimana Allah di dalam Kristus telah mengampuni kamu.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="5">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Therefore be imitators of God as dear children. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">فكونوا متمثلين بالله كاولاد احباء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Sebab itu jadilah penurut-penurut Allah, seperti anak-anak yang kekasih</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> And walk in love, as Christ also has loved us and given Himself for us, an offering and a sacrifice to God for a sweet-smelling aroma. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">واسلكوا في المحبة كما احبنا المسيح ايضا واسلم نفسه لاجلنا قربانا وذبيحة للّه رائحة طيبة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">dan hiduplah di dalam kasih, sebagaimana Kristus Yesus juga telah mengasihi kamu dan telah menyerahkan diri-Nya untuk kita sebagai persembahan dan korban yang harum bagi Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> But fornication and all uncleanness or covetousness, let it not even be named among you, as is fitting for saints; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">واما الزنى وكل نجاسة او طمع فلا يسمّ بينكم كما يليق بقديسين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Tetapi percabulan dan rupa-rupa kecemaran atau keserakahan disebut sajapun jangan di antara kamu, sebagaimana sepatutnya bagi orang-orang kudus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> neither filthiness, nor foolish talking, nor coarse jesting, which are not fitting, but rather giving of thanks. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ولا القباحة ولا كلام السفاهة والهزل التي لا تليق بل بالحري الشكر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Demikian juga perkataan yang kotor, yang kosong atau yang sembrono--karena hal-hal ini tidak pantas--tetapi sebaliknya ucapkanlah syukur.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> For this you know, that no fornicator, unclean person, nor covetous man, who is an idolater, has any inheritance in the kingdom of Christ and God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فانكم تعلمون هذا ان كل زان او نجس او طماع الذي هو عابد للاوثان ليس له ميراث في ملكوت المسيح والله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Karena ingatlah ini baik-baik: tidak ada orang sundal, orang cemar atau orang serakah, artinya penyembah berhala, yang mendapat bagian di dalam Kerajaan Kristus dan Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Let no one deceive you with empty words, for because of these things the wrath of God comes upon the sons of disobedience. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لا يغركم احد بكلام باطل لانه بسبب هذه الامور يأتي غضب الله على ابناء المعصية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Janganlah kamu disesatkan orang dengan kata-kata yang hampa, karena hal-hal yang demikian mendatangkan murka Allah atas orang-orang durhaka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Therefore do not be partakers with them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فلا تكونوا شركاءهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Sebab itu janganlah kamu berkawan dengan mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> For you were once darkness, but now [you are] light in the Lord. Walk as children of light </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لانكم كنتم قبلا ظلمة واما الآن فنور في الرب. اسلكوا كاولاد نور.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Memang dahulu kamu adalah kegelapan, tetapi sekarang kamu adalah terang di dalam Tuhan. Sebab itu hiduplah sebagai anak-anak terang,</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> (for the fruit of the Spirit [is] in all goodness, righteousness, and truth), </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لان ثمر الروح هو في كل صلاح وبر وحق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">karena terang hanya berbuahkan kebaikan dan keadilan dan kebenaran,</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> finding out what is acceptable to the Lord. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">مختبرين ما هو مرضي عند الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">dan ujilah apa yang berkenan kepada Tuhan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> And have no fellowship with the unfruitful works of darkness, but rather expose [them.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ولا تشتركوا في اعمال الظلمة غير المثمرة بل بالحري وبخوها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Janganlah turut mengambil bagian dalam perbuatan-perbuatan kegelapan yang tidak berbuahkan apa-apa, tetapi sebaliknya telanjangilah perbuatan-perbuatan itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> For it is shameful even to speak of those things which are done by them in secret. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">لان الامور الحادثة منهم سرّا ذكرها ايضا قبيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Sebab menyebutkan sajapun apa yang dibuat oleh mereka di tempat-tempat yang tersembunyi telah memalukan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> But all things that are exposed are made manifest by the light, for whatever makes manifest is light. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ولكن الكل اذا توبخ يظهر بالنور. لان كل ما اظهر فهو نور.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Tetapi segala sesuatu yang sudah ditelanjangi oleh terang itu menjadi nampak, sebab semua yang nampak adalah terang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Therefore He says: "Awake, you who sleep, Arise from the dead, And Christ will give you light." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">لذلك يقول استيقظ ايها النائم وقم من الاموات فيضيء لك المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Itulah sebabnya dikatakan: "Bangunlah, hai kamu yang tidur dan bangkitlah dari antara orang mati dan Kristus akan bercahaya atas kamu."</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> See then that you walk circumspectly, not as fools but as wise, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فانظروا كيف تسلكون بالتدقيق لا كجهلاء بل كحكماء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Karena itu, perhatikanlah dengan saksama, bagaimana kamu hidup, janganlah seperti orang bebal, tetapi seperti orang arif,</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> redeeming the time, because the days are evil. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">مفتدين الوقت لان الايام شريرة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">dan pergunakanlah waktu yang ada, karena hari-hari ini adalah jahat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Therefore do not be unwise, but understand what the will of the Lord [is.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">من اجل ذلك لا تكونوا اغبياء بل فاهمين ما هي مشيئة الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Sebab itu janganlah kamu bodoh, tetapi usahakanlah supaya kamu mengerti kehendak Tuhan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> And do not be drunk with wine, in which is dissipation; but be filled with the Spirit, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">ولا تسكروا بالخمر الذي فيه الخلاعة بل امتلئوا بالروح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Dan janganlah kamu mabuk oleh anggur, karena anggur menimbulkan hawa nafsu, tetapi hendaklah kamu penuh dengan Roh,</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> speaking to one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs, singing and making melody in your heart to the Lord, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">مكلمين بعضكم بعضا بمزامير وتسابيح واغاني روحية مترنمين ومرتلين في قلوبكم للرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">dan berkata-katalah seorang kepada yang lain dalam mazmur, kidung puji-pujian dan nyanyian rohani. Bernyanyi dan bersoraklah bagi Tuhan dengan segenap hati.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> giving thanks always for all things to God the Father in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">شاكرين كل حين على كل شيء في اسم ربنا يسوع المسيح للّه والآب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Ucaplah syukur senantiasa atas segala sesuatu dalam nama Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus kepada Allah dan Bapa kita</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> submitting to one another in the fear of God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">خاضعين بعضكم لبعض في خوف الله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">dan rendahkanlah dirimu seorang kepada yang lain di dalam takut akan Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> Wives, submit to your own husbands, as to the Lord. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">ايها النساء اخضعن لرجالكنّ كما للرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Hai isteri, tunduklah kepada suamimu seperti kepada Tuhan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> For the husband is head of the wife, as also Christ is head of the church; and He is the Savior of the body. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">لان الرجل هو راس المرأة كما ان المسيح ايضا راس الكنيسة. وهو مخلّص الجسد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">karena suami adalah kepala isteri sama seperti Kristus adalah kepala jemaat. Dialah yang menyelamatkan tubuh.</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> Therefore, just as the church is subject to Christ, so [let] the wives [be] to their own husbands in everything. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">ولكن كما تخضع الكنيسة للمسيح كذلك النساء لرجالهنّ في كل شيء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">Karena itu sebagaimana jemaat tunduk kepada Kristus, demikian jugalah isteri kepada suami dalam segala sesuatu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> Husbands, love your wives, just as Christ also loved the church and gave Himself for her, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">ايها الرجال احبوا نساءكم كما احب المسيح ايضا الكنيسة واسلم نفسه لاجلها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Hai suami, kasihilah isterimu sebagaimana Kristus telah mengasihi jemaat dan telah menyerahkan diri-Nya baginya</language></verse>
			<verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26"> that He might sanctify and cleanse her with the washing of water by the word, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">لكي يقدسها مطهرا اياها بغسل الماء بالكلمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">untuk menguduskannya, sesudah Ia menyucikannya dengan memandikannya dengan air dan firman,</language></verse>
			<verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27"> that He might present her to Himself a glorious church, not having spot or wrinkle or any such thing, but that she should be holy and without blemish. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">لكي يحضرها لنفسه كنيسة مجيدة لا دنس فيها ولا غضن او شيء من مثل ذلك بل تكون مقدسة وبلا عيب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">supaya dengan demikian Ia menempatkan jemaat di hadapan diri-Nya dengan cemerlang tanpa cacat atau kerut atau yang serupa itu, tetapi supaya jemaat kudus dan tidak bercela.</language></verse>
			<verse num="28"><language id="English" verse="28"> So husbands ought to love their own wives as their own bodies; he who loves his wife loves himself. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="28">كذلك يجب على الرجال ان يحبوا نساءهم كاجسادهم. من يحب امرأته يحب نفسه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="28">Demikian juga suami harus mengasihi isterinya sama seperti tubuhnya sendiri: Siapa yang mengasihi isterinya mengasihi dirinya sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="29"><language id="English" verse="29"> For no one ever hated his own flesh, but nourishes and cherishes it, just as the Lord [does] the church. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="29">فانه لم يبغض احد جسده قط بل يقوته ويربيه كما الرب ايضا للكنيسة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="29">Sebab tidak pernah orang membenci tubuhnya sendiri, tetapi mengasuhnya dan merawatinya, sama seperti Kristus terhadap jemaat,</language></verse>
			<verse num="30"><language id="English" verse="30"> For we are members of His body, of His flesh and of His bones. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="30">لاننا اعضاء جسمه من لحمه ومن عظامه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="30">karena kita adalah anggota tubuh-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="31"><language id="English" verse="31"> "For this reason a man shall leave his father and mother and be joined to his wife, and the two shall become one flesh." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="31">من اجل هذا يترك الرجل اباه وامه ويلتصق بامرأته ويكون الاثنان جسدا واحدا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="31">Sebab itu laki-laki akan meninggalkan ayahnya dan ibunya dan bersatu dengan isterinya, sehingga keduanya itu menjadi satu daging.</language></verse>
			<verse num="32"><language id="English" verse="32"> This is a great mystery, but I speak concerning Christ and the church. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="32">هذا السر عظيم ولكنني انا اقول من نحو المسيح والكنيسة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="32">Rahasia ini besar, tetapi yang aku maksudkan ialah hubungan Kristus dan jemaat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="33"><language id="English" verse="33"> Nevertheless let each one of you in particular so love his own wife as himself, and let the wife [see] that she respects [her] husband. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="33">واما انتم الافراد فليحب كل واحد امرأته هكذا كنفسه واما المرأة فلتهب رجلها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="33">Bagaimanapun juga, bagi kamu masing-masing berlaku: kasihilah isterimu seperti dirimu sendiri dan isteri hendaklah menghormati suaminya.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="6">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Children, obey your parents in the Lord, for this is right. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ايها الاولاد اطيعوا والديكم في الرب لان هذا حق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Hai anak-anak, taatilah orang tuamu di dalam Tuhan, karena haruslah demikian.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> "Honor your father and mother," which is the first commandment with promise: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اكرم اباك وامك. التي هي اول وصية بوعد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Hormatilah ayahmu dan ibumu--ini adalah suatu perintah yang penting, seperti yang nyata dari janji ini:</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> "that it may be well with you and you may live long on the earth." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">لكي يكون لكم خير وتكونوا طوال الاعمار على الارض.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">supaya kamu berbahagia dan panjang umurmu di bumi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> And you, fathers, do not provoke your children to wrath, but bring them up in the training and admonition of the Lord. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">وانتم ايها الآباء لا تغيظوا اولادكم بل ربوهم بتأديب الرب وانذاره.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Dan kamu, bapa-bapa, janganlah bangkitkan amarah di dalam hati anak-anakmu, tetapi didiklah mereka di dalam ajaran dan nasihat Tuhan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Bondservants, be obedient to those who are your masters according to the flesh, with fear and trembling, in sincerity of heart, as to Christ; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">ايها العبيد اطيعوا سادتكم حسب الجسد بخوف ورعدة في بساطة قلوبكم كما للمسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Hai hamba-hamba, taatilah tuanmu yang di dunia dengan takut dan gentar, dan dengan tulus hati, sama seperti kamu taat kepada Kristus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> not with eyeservice, as men-pleasers, but as bondservants of Christ, doing the will of God from the heart, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لا بخدمة العين كمن يرضي الناس بل كعبيد المسيح عاملين مشيئة الله من القلب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">jangan hanya di hadapan mereka saja untuk menyenangkan hati orang, tetapi sebagai hamba-hamba Kristus yang dengan segenap hati melakukan kehendak Allah,</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> with goodwill doing service, as to the Lord, and not to men, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">خادمين بنيّة صالحة كما للرب ليس للناس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">dan yang dengan rela menjalankan pelayanannya seperti orang-orang yang melayani Tuhan dan bukan manusia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> knowing that whatever good anyone does, he will receive the same from the Lord, whether [he is] a slave or free. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">عالمين ان مهما عمل كل واحد من الخير فذلك يناله من الرب عبدا كان ام حرا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Kamu tahu, bahwa setiap orang, baik hamba, maupun orang merdeka, kalau ia telah berbuat sesuatu yang baik, ia akan menerima balasannya dari Tuhan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> And you, masters, do the same things to them, giving up threatening, knowing that your own Master also is in heaven, and there is no partiality with Him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">وانتم ايها السادة افعلوا لهم هذه الامور تاركين التهديد عالمين ان سيدكم انتم ايضا في السموات وليس عنده محاباة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Dan kamu tuan-tuan, perbuatlah demikian juga terhadap mereka dan jauhkanlah ancaman. Ingatlah, bahwa Tuhan mereka dan Tuhan kamu ada di sorga dan Ia tidak memandang muka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Finally, my brethren, be strong in the Lord and in the power of His might. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">اخيرا يا اخوتي تقووا في الرب وفي شدة قوته.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Akhirnya, hendaklah kamu kuat di dalam Tuhan, di dalam kekuatan kuasa-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Put on the whole armor of God, that you may be able to stand against the wiles of the devil. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">البسوا سلاح الله الكامل لكي تقدروا ان تثبتوا ضد مكايد ابليس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Kenakanlah seluruh perlengkapan senjata Allah, supaya kamu dapat bertahan melawan tipu muslihat Iblis;</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> For we do not wrestle against flesh and blood, but against principalities, against powers, against the rulers of the darkness of this age, against spiritual [hosts] of wickedness in the heavenly [places.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فان مصارعتنا ليست مع دم ولحم بل مع الرؤساء مع السلاطين مع ولاة العالم على ظلمة هذا الدهر مع اجناد الشر الروحية في السماويات.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">karena perjuangan kita bukanlah melawan darah dan daging, tetapi melawan pemerintah-pemerintah, melawan penguasa-penguasa, melawan penghulu-penghulu dunia yang gelap ini, melawan roh-roh jahat di udara.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Therefore take up the whole armor of God, that you may be able to withstand in the evil day, and having done all, to stand. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">من اجل ذلك احملوا سلاح الله الكامل لكي تقدروا ان تقاوموا في اليوم الشرير وبعد ان تتمموا كل شيء ان تثبتوا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Sebab itu ambillah seluruh perlengkapan senjata Allah, supaya kamu dapat mengadakan perlawanan pada hari yang jahat itu dan tetap berdiri, sesudah kamu menyelesaikan segala sesuatu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Stand therefore, having girded your waist with truth, having put on the breastplate of righteousness, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فاثبتوا ممنطقين احقاءكم بالحق ولابسين درع البر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Jadi berdirilah tegap, berikatpinggangkan kebenaran dan berbajuzirahkan keadilan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> and having shod your feet with the preparation of the gospel of peace; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">وحاذين ارجلكم باستعداد انجيل السلام.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">kakimu berkasutkan kerelaan untuk memberitakan Injil damai sejahtera;</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> above all, taking the shield of faith with which you will be able to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked one. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">حاملين فوق الكل ترس الايمان الذي به تقدرون ان تطفئوا جميع سهام الشرير الملتهبة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">dalam segala keadaan pergunakanlah perisai iman, sebab dengan perisai itu kamu akan dapat memadamkan semua panah api dari si jahat,</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> And take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">وخذوا خوذة الخلاص وسيف الروح الذي هو كلمة الله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">dan terimalah ketopong keselamatan dan pedang Roh, yaitu firman Allah,</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> praying always with all prayer and supplication in the Spirit, being watchful to this end with all perseverance and supplication for all the saints -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">مصلّين بكل صلاة وطلبة كل وقت في الروح وساهرين لهذا بعينه بكل مواظبة وطلبة لاجل جميع القديسين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">dalam segala doa dan permohonan. Berdoalah setiap waktu di dalam Roh dan berjaga-jagalah di dalam doamu itu dengan permohonan yang tak putus-putusnya untuk segala orang Kudus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> and for me, that utterance may be given to me, that I may open my mouth boldly to make known the mystery of the gospel, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">ولاجلي لكي يعطى لي كلام عند افتتاح فمي لاعلم جهارا بسر الانجيل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">juga untuk aku, supaya kepadaku, jika aku membuka mulutku, dikaruniakan perkataan yang benar, agar dengan keberanian aku memberitakan rahasia Injil,</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> for which I am an ambassador in chains; that in it I may speak boldly, as I ought to speak. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">الذي لاجله انا سفير في سلاسل. لكي اجاهر فيه كما يجب ان اتكلم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">yang kulayani sebagai utusan yang dipenjarakan. Berdoalah supaya dengan keberanian aku menyatakannya, sebagaimana seharusnya aku berbicara.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> But that you also may know my affairs [and] how I am doing, Tychicus, a beloved brother and faithful minister in the Lord, will make all things known to you; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">ولكن لكي تعلموا انتم ايضا احوالي ماذا افعل يعرّفكم بكل شيء تيخيكس الاخ الحبيب والخادم الامين في الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Supaya kamu juga mengetahui keadaan dan hal ihwalku, maka Tikhikus, saudara kita yang kekasih dan pelayan yang setia di dalam Tuhan, akan memberitahukan semuanya kepada kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> whom I have sent to you for this very purpose, that you may know our affairs, and [that] he may comfort your hearts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">الذي ارسلته اليكم لهذا بعينه لكي تعلموا احوالنا ولكي يعزي قلوبكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Dengan maksud inilah ia kusuruh kepadamu, yaitu supaya kamu tahu hal ihwal kami dan supaya ia menghibur hatimu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> Peace to the brethren, and love with faith, from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">سلام على الاخوة ومحبة بايمان من الله الآب والرب يسوع المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Damai sejahtera dan kasih dengan iman dari Allah, Bapa dan dari Tuhan Yesus Kristus menyertai sekalian saudara.</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> Grace [be] with all those who love our Lord Jesus Christ in sincerity. Amen. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">النعمة مع جميع الذين يحبون ربنا يسوع المسيح في عدم فساد. آمين. كتبت الى اهل افسس من رومية على يد تيخيكس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">Kasih karunia menyertai semua orang, yang mengasihi Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus dengan kasih yang tidak binasa.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>