<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Now it came to pass in the days of Ahasuerus (this [was] the Ahasuerus who reigned over one hundred and twenty-seven provinces, from India to Ethiopia), </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وحدث في ايام احشويروش. هو احشويروش الذي ملك من الهند الى كوش على مئة وسبع وعشرين كورة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Pada zaman Ahasyweros--dialah Ahasyweros yang merajai seratus dua puluh tujuh daerah mulai dari India sampai ke Etiopia--,</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> in those days when King Ahasuerus sat on the throne of his kingdom, which [was] in Shushan the citadel, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">انه في تلك الايام حين جلس الملك احشويروش على كرسي ملكه الذي في شوشن القصر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">pada zaman itu, ketika raja Ahasyweros bersemayam di atas takhta kerajaannya di dalam benteng Susan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> [that] in the third year of his reign he made a feast for all his officials and servants -- the powers of Persia and Media, the nobles, and the princes of the provinces [being] before him -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">في السنة الثالثة من ملكه عمل وليمة لجميع رؤسائه وعبيده جيش فارس ومادي وامامه شرفاء البلدان ورؤساؤها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">pada tahun yang ketiga dalam pemerintahannya, diadakanlah oleh baginda perjamuan bagi semua pembesar dan pegawainya; tentara Persia dan Media, kaum bangsawan dan pembesar daerah hadir di hadapan baginda.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> when he showed the riches of his glorious kingdom and the splendor of his excellent majesty for many days, one hundred and eighty days [in all.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">حين اظهر غنى مجد ملكه ووقار جلال عظمته اياما كثيرة مئة وثمانين يوما.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Di samping itu baginda memamerkan kekayaan kemuliaan kerajaannya dan keindahan kebesarannya yang bersemarak, berhari-hari lamanya, sampai seratus delapan puluh hari.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> And when these days were completed, the king made a feast lasting seven days for all the people who were present in Shushan the citadel, from great to small, in the court of the garden of the king's palace. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">وعند انقضاء هذه الايام عمل الملك لجميع الشعب الموجودين في شوشن القصر من الكبير الى الصغير وليمة سبعة ايام في دار جنة قصر الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Setelah genap hari-hari itu, maka raja mengadakan perjamuan lagi tujuh hari lamanya bagi seluruh rakyatnya yang terdapat di dalam benteng Susan, dari pada orang besar sampai kepada orang kecil, bertempat di pelataran yang ada di taman istana kerajaan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> [There were] white and blue linen [curtains] fastened with cords of fine linen and purple on silver rods and marble pillars; [and the] couches [were] of gold and silver on a [mosaic] pavement of alabaster, turquoise, and white and black marble. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">بانسجة بيضاء وخضراء واسمانجونية معلّقة بحبال من بزّ وارجوان في حلقات من فضة واعمدة من رخام واسرّة من ذهب وفضة على مجزّع من بهت ومرمر ودر ورخام اسود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Di situ tirai-mirai dari pada kain lenan, mori halus dan kain ungu tua, yang terikat dengan tali lenan halus dan ungu muda bergantung pada tombol-tombol perak di tiang-tiang marmar putih, sedang katil emas dan perak ditempatkan di atas lantai pualam, marmar putih, gewang dan pelinggam.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> And they served drinks in golden vessels, each vessel being different from the other, with royal wine in abundance, according to the generosity of the king. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">وكان السقاء من ذهب والآنية مختلفة الاشكال والخمر الملكي بكثرة حسب كرم الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Minuman dihidangkan dalam piala emas yang beraneka warna, dan anggurnya ialah anggur minuman raja yang berlimpah-limpah, sebagaimana layak bagi raja.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> In accordance with the law, the drinking was not compulsory; for so the king had ordered all the officers of his household, that they should do according to each man's pleasure. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">وكان الشرب حسب الأمر. لم يكن غاصب لانه هكذا رسم الملك على كل عظيم في بيته ان يعملوا حسب رضا كل واحد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Adapun aturan minum ialah: tiada dengan paksa; karena beginilah disyaratkan raja kepada semua bentara dalam, supaya mereka berbuat menurut keinginan tiap-tiap orang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Queen Vashti also made a feast for the women [in] the royal palace which [belonged] to King Ahasuerus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ووشتي الملكة عملت ايضا وليمة للنساء في بيت الملك الذي للملك احشويروش</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Juga Wasti, sang ratu, mengadakan perjamuan bagi semua perempuan di dalam istana raja Ahasyweros.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> On the seventh day, when the heart of the king was merry with wine, he commanded Mehuman, Biztha, Harbona, Bigtha, Abagtha, Zethar, and Carcas, seven eunuchs who served in the presence of King Ahasuerus, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">في اليوم السابع لما طاب قلب الملك بالخمر قال لمهومان وبزثا وحربونا وبغثا وابغثا وزيثار وكركس الخصيان السبعة الذين كانوا يخدمون بين يدي الملك احشويروش</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Pada hari yang ketujuh, ketika raja riang gembira hatinya karena minum anggur, bertitahlah baginda kepada Mehuman, Bizta, Harbona, Bigta, Abagta, Zetar dan Karkas, yakni ketujuh sida-sida yang bertugas di hadapan raja Ahasyweros,</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> to bring Queen Vashti before the king, [wearing] her royal crown, in order to show her beauty to the people and the officials, for she [was] beautiful to behold. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ان يأتوا بوشتي الملكة الى امام الملك بتاج الملك ليري الشعوب والرؤساء جمالها لانها كانت حسنة المنظر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">supaya mereka membawa Wasti, sang ratu, dengan memakai mahkota kerajaan, menghadap raja untuk memperlihatkan kecantikannya kepada sekalian rakyat dan pembesar-pembesar, karena sang ratu sangat elok rupanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> But Queen Vashti refused to come at the king's command [brought] by [his] eunuchs; therefore the king was furious, and his anger burned within him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فأبت الملكة وشتي ان تأتي حسب أمر الملك عن يد الخصيان فاغتاظ الملك جدا واشتعل غضبه فيه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Tetapi ratu Wasti menolak untuk menghadap menurut titah raja yang disampaikan oleh sida-sida itu, sehingga sangat geramlah raja dan berapi-apilah murkanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Then the king said to the wise men who understood the times (for this [was] the king's manner toward all who knew law and justice, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">وقال الملك للحكماء والعارفين بالازمنة. لانه هكذا كان أمر الملك نحو جميع العارفين بالسنّة والقضاء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Maka bertanyalah raja kepada orang-orang arif bijaksana, orang-orang yang mengetahui kebiasaan zaman--karena demikianlah biasanya masalah-masalah raja dikemukakan kepada para ahli undang-undang dan hukum;</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> those closest to him [being] Carshena, Shethar, Admatha, Tarshish, Meres, Marsena, and Memucan, the seven princes of Persia and Media, who had access to the king's presence, [and] who ranked highest in the kingdom): </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">وكان المقربون اليه كرشنا وشيثار وادماثا وترشيش ومرس ومرسنا ومموكان سبعة رؤساء فارس ومادي الذين يرون وجه الملك ويجلسون اولا في الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">adapun yang terdekat kepada baginda ialah Karsena, Setar, Admata, Tarsis, Meres, Marsena dan Memukan, ketujuh pembesar Persia dan Media, yang boleh memandang wajah raja dan yang mempunyai kedudukan yang tinggi di dalam kerajaan--,tanya raja:</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> "What [shall we] do to Queen Vashti, according to law, because she did not obey the command of King Ahasuerus [brought to her] by the eunuchs?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">حسب السنّة ماذا يعمل بالملكة وشتي لانها لم تعمل كقول الملك احشويروش عن يد الخصيان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">"Apakah yang harus diperbuat atas ratu Wasti menurut undang-undang, karena tidak dilakukannya titah raja Ahasyweros yang disampaikan oleh sida-sida?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> And Memucan answered before the king and the princes: "Queen Vashti has not only wronged the king, but also all the princes, and all the people who [are] in all the provinces of King Ahasuerus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فقال مموكان امام الملك والرؤساء ليس الى الملك وحده اذنبت وشتي الملكة بل الى جميع الرؤساء وجميع الشعوب الذين في كل بلدان الملك احشويروش.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Maka sembah Memukan di hadapan raja dan para pembesar itu: "Wasti, sang ratu, bukan bersalah kepada raja saja, melainkan juga kepada semua pembesar dan segala bangsa yang di dalam segala daerah raja Ahasyweros.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> "For the queen's behavior will become known to all women, so that they will despise their husbands in their eyes, when they report, 'King Ahasuerus commanded Queen Vashti to be brought in before him, but she did not come.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">لانه سوف يبلغ خبر الملكة الى جميع النساء حتى يحتقر ازواجهنّ في اعينهنّ عندما يقال ان الملك احشويروش امر ان يؤتى بوشتي الملكة الى امامه فلم تأت.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Karena kelakuan sang ratu itu akan merata kepada semua perempuan, sehingga mereka tidak menghiraukan suaminya, apabila diceritakan orang: Raja Ahasyweros menitahkan, supaya Wasti, sang ratu, dibawa menghadap kepadanya, tetapi ia tidak mau datang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> "This very day the [noble] ladies of Persia and Media will say to all the king's officials that they have heard of the behavior of the queen. Thus [there will be] excessive contempt and wrath. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">وفي هذا اليوم تقول رئيسات فارس ومادي اللواتي سمعن خبر الملكة لجميع رؤساء الملك. ومثل ذلك احتقار وغضب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Pada hari ini juga isteri para pembesar raja di Persia dan Media yang mendengar tentang kelakuan sang ratu akan berbicara tentang hal itu kepada suaminya, sehingga berlarut-larutlah penghinaan dan kegusaran.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> "If it pleases the king, let a royal decree go out from him, and let it be recorded in the laws of the Persians and the Medes, so that it will not be altered, that Vashti shall come no more before King Ahasuerus; and let the king give her royal position to another who is better than she. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">فاذا حسن عند الملك فليخرج امر ملكي من عنده وليكتب في سنن فارس ومادي فلا يتغيّر ان لا تات وشتي الى امام الملك احشويروش وليعط الملك ملكها لمن هي احسن منها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Jikalau baik pada pemandangan raja, hendaklah dikeluarkan suatu titah kerajaan dari hadapan baginda dan dituliskan di dalam undang-undang Persia dan Media, sehingga tidak dapat dicabut kembali, bahwa Wasti dilarang menghadap raja Ahasyweros, dan bahwa raja akan mengaruniakan kedudukannya sebagai ratu kepada orang lain yang lebih baik dari padanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> "When the king's decree which he will make is proclaimed throughout all his empire (for it is great), all wives will honor their husbands, both great and small." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">فيسمع أمر الملك الذي يخرجه في كل مملكته لانها عظيمة فتعطي جميع النساء الوقار لازواجهنّ من الكبير الى الصغير.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Bila keputusan yang diambil raja kedengaran di seluruh kerajaannya--alangkah besarnya kerajaan itu! --,maka semua perempuan akan memberi hormat kepada suami mereka, dari pada orang besar sampai kepada orang kecil."</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> And the reply pleased the king and the princes, and the king did according to the word of Memucan. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">فحسن الكلام في اعين الملك والرؤساء وعمل الملك حسب قول مموكان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Usul itu dipandang baik oleh raja serta para pembesar, jadi bertindaklah raja sesuai dengan usul Memukan itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> Then he sent letters to all the king's provinces, to each province in its own script, and to every people in their own language, that each man should be master in his own house, and speak in the language of his own people. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">وارسل كتبا الى كل بلدان الملك والى كل بلاد حسب كتابتها والى كل شعب حسب لسانه ليكون كل رجل متسلط في بيته ويتكلم بذلك بلسان شعبه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Dikirimkanlah oleh baginda surat-surat ke segenap daerah kerajaan, tiap-tiap daerah menurut tulisannya dan tiap-tiap bangsa menurut bahasanya, bunyinya: "Setiap laki-laki harus menjadi kepala dalam rumah tangganya dan berbicara menurut bahasa bangsanya."</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="2">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> After these things, when the wrath of King Ahasuerus subsided, he remembered Vashti, what she had done, and what had been decreed against her. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">بعد هذه الأمور لما خمد غضب الملك احشويروش ذكر وشتي وما عملته وما حتم به عليها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Sesudah peristiwa-peristiwa ini, setelah kepanasan murka raja Ahasyweros surut, terkenanglah baginda kepada Wasti dan yang dilakukannya, dan kepada apa yang diputuskan atasnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Then the king's servants who attended him said: "Let beautiful young virgins be sought for the king; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فقال غلمان الملك الذين يخدمونه ليطلب للملك فتيات عذارى حسنات المنظر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Maka sembah para biduanda raja yang bertugas pada baginda: "Hendaklah orang mencari bagi raja gadis-gadis, yaitu anak-anak dara yang elok rupanya;</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> "and let the king appoint officers in all the provinces of his kingdom, that they may gather all the beautiful young virgins to Shushan the citadel, into the women's quarters, under the custody of Hegai the king's eunuch, custodian of the women. And let beauty preparations be given [them.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">وليوكل الملك وكلاء في كل بلاد مملكته ليجمعوا كل الفتيات العذارى الحسنات المنظر الى شوشن القصر الى بيت النساء الى يد هيجاي خصي الملك حارس النساء وليعطين ادهان عطرهنّ‎.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">hendaklah raja menempatkan kuasa-kuasa di segenap daerah kerajaannya, supaya mereka mengumpulkan semua gadis, anak-anak dara yang elok rupanya, di dalam benteng Susan, di balai perempuan, di bawah pengawasan Hegai, sida-sida raja, penjaga para perempuan; hendaklah diberikan wangi-wangian kepada mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> "Then let the young woman who pleases the king be queen instead of Vashti." This thing pleased the king, and he did so. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">والفتاة التي تحسن في عيني الملك فلتملك مكان وشتي. فحسن الكلام في عيني الملك فعمل هكذا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Dan gadis yang terbaik pada pemandangan raja, baiklah dia menjadi ratu ganti Wasti." Hal itu dipandang baik oleh raja, dan dilakukanlah demikian.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> In Shushan the citadel there was a certain Jew whose name [was] Mordecai the son of Jair, the son of Shimei, the son of Kish, a Benjamite. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">كان في شوشن القصر رجل يهودي اسمه مردخاي ابن يائير بن شمعي بن قيس رجل يميني</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Pada waktu itu ada di dalam benteng Susan seorang Yahudi, yang bernama Mordekhai bin Yair bin Simei bin Kish, seorang Benyamin</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> [Kish] had been carried away from Jerusalem with the captives who had been captured with Jeconiah king of Judah, whom Nebuchadnezzar the king of Babylon had carried away. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">قد سبي من اورشليم مع السبي الذي سبي مع يكنيا ملك يهوذا الذي سباه نبوخذنصّر ملك بابل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">yang diangkut dari Yerusalem sebagai salah seorang buangan yang turut dengan Yekhonya, raja Yehuda, ketika ia diangkut ke dalam pembuangan oleh raja Nebukadnezar, raja Babel.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> And [Mordecai] had brought up Hadassah, that [is,] Esther, his uncle's daughter, for she had neither father nor mother. The young woman [was] lovely and beautiful. When her father and mother died, Mordecai took her as his own daughter. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">وكان مربّيا لهدسّة اي استير بنت عمه لانه لم يكن لها اب ولا ام. وكانت الفتاة جميلة الصورة وحسنة المنظر وعند موت ابيها وامها اتخذها مردخاي لنفسه ابنة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Mordekhai itu pengasuh Hadasa, yakni Ester, anak saudara ayahnya, sebab anak itu tidak beribu bapa lagi; gadis itu elok perawakannya dan cantik parasnya. Ketika ibu bapanya mati, ia diangkat sebagai anak oleh Mordekhai.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> So it was, when the king's command and decree were heard, and when many young women were gathered at Shushan the citadel, [under] the custody of Hegai, that Esther also was taken to the king's palace, into the care of Hegai the custodian of the women. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فلما سمع كلام الملك وامره وجمعت فتايات كثيرات الى شوشن القصر الى يد هيجاي أخذت استير الى بيت الملك الى يد هيجاي حارس النساء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Setelah titah dan undang-undang raja tersiar dan banyak gadis dikumpulkan di dalam benteng Susan, di bawah pengawasan Hegai, maka Esterpun dibawa masuk ke dalam istana raja, di bawah pengawasan Hegai, penjaga para perempuan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Now the young woman pleased him, and she obtained his favor; so he readily gave beauty preparations to her, besides her allowance. Then seven choice maidservants were provided for her from the king's palace, and he moved her and her maidservants to the best [place] in the house of the women. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">وحسنت الفتاة في عينيه ونالت نعمة بين يديه فبادر بادهان عطرها وانصبتها ليعطيها اياها مع السبع الفتيات المختارات لتعطى لها من بيت الملك ونقلها مع فتاياتها الى احسن مكان في بيت النساء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Maka gadis itu sangat baik pada pemandangannya dan menimbulkan kasih sayangnya, sehingga Hegai segera memberikan wangi-wangian dan pelabur kepadanya, dan juga tujuh orang dayang-dayang yang terpilih dari isi istana raja, kemudian memindahkan dia dengan dayang-dayangnya ke bagian yang terbaik di dalam balai perempuan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Esther had not revealed her people or family, for Mordecai had charged her not to reveal [it.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">ولم تخبر استير عن شعبها وجنسها لان مردخاي اوصاها ان لا تخبر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Ester tidak memberitahukan kebangsaan dan asal usulnya, karena dilarang oleh Mordekhai.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> And every day Mordecai paced in front of the court of the women's quarters, to learn of Esther's welfare and what was happening to her. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">وكان مردخاي يتمشى يوما فيوما امام دار بيت النساء ليستعلم عن سلامة استير وعما يصنع بها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Tiap-tiap hari berjalan-jalanlah Mordekhai di depan pelataran balai perempuan itu untuk mengetahui bagaimana keadaan Ester dan apa yang akan berlaku atasnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Each young woman's turn came to go in to King Ahasuerus after she had completed twelve months' preparation, according to the regulations for the women, for thus were the days of their preparation apportioned: six months with oil of myrrh, and six months with perfumes and preparations for beautifying women. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ولما بلغت نوبة فتاة ففتاة للدخول الى الملك احشويروش بعد ان يكون لها حسب سنة النساء اثنا عشر شهرا لانه هكذا كانت تكمل ايام تعطرهنّ ستة اشهر بزيت المرّ وستة اشهر بالاطياب وادهان تعطر النساء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Tiap-tiap kali seorang gadis mendapat giliran untuk masuk menghadap raja Ahasyweros, dan sebelumnya ia dirawat menurut peraturan bagi para perempuan selama dua belas bulan, sebab seluruh waktu itu digunakan untuk pemakaian wangi-wangian: enam bulan untuk memakai minyak mur dan enam bulan lagi untuk memakai minyak kasai serta lain-lain wangi-wangian perempuan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Thus [prepared, each] young woman went to the king, and she was given whatever she desired to take with her from the women's quarters to the king's palace. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">وهكذا كانت كل فتاة تدخل الى الملك. وكل ما قالت عنه أعطي لها للدخول معها من بيت النساء الى بيت الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Lalu gadis itu masuk menghadap raja, dan segala apa yang dimintanya harus diberikan kepadanya untuk dibawa masuk dari balai perempuan ke dalam istana raja.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> In the evening she went, and in the morning she returned to the second house of the women, to the custody of Shaashgaz, the king's eunuch who kept the concubines. She would not go in to the king again unless the king delighted in her and called for her by name. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">في المساء دخلت وفي الصباح رجعت الى بيت النساء الثاني الى يد شعشغاز خصي الملك حارس السراري. لم تعد تدخل الى الملك الا اذا سرّ بها الملك ودعيت باسمها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Pada waktu petang ia masuk dan pada waktu pagi ia kembali, tetapi sekali ini ke dalam balai perempuan yang kedua, di bawah pengawasan Saasgas, sida-sida raja, penjaga para gundik. Ia tidak diperkenankan masuk lagi menghadap raja, kecuali jikalau raja berkenan kepadanya dan ia dipanggil dengan disebutkan namanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Now when the turn came for Esther the daughter of Abihail the uncle of Mordecai, who had taken her as his daughter, to go in to the king, she requested nothing but what Hegai the king's eunuch, the custodian of the women, advised. And Esther obtained favor in the sight of all who saw her. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ولما بلغت نوبة استير ابنة ابيحائل عم مردخاي الذي اتخذها لنفسه ابنة للدخول الى الملك لم تطلب شيئا الا ما قال عنه هيجاي خصي الملك حارس النساء. وكانت استير تنال نعمة في عيني كل من رآها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Ketika Ester--anak Abihail, yakni saudara ayah Mordekhai yang mengangkat Ester sebagai anak--mendapat giliran untuk masuk menghadap raja, maka ia tidak menghendaki sesuatu apapun selain dari pada yang dianjurkan oleh Hegai, sida-sida raja, penjaga para perempuan. Maka Ester dapat menimbulkan kasih sayang pada semua orang yang melihat dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> So Esther was taken to King Ahasuerus, into his royal palace, in the tenth month, which [is] the month of Tebeth, in the seventh year of his reign. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">وأخذت استير الى الملك احشويروش الى بيت ملكه في الشهر العاشر هو شهر طيبيت في السنة السابعة لملكه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Demikianlah Ester dibawa masuk menghadap raja Ahasyweros ke dalam istananya pada bulan yang kesepuluh--yakni bulan Tebet--pada tahun yang ketujuh dalam pemerintahan baginda.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> The king loved Esther more than all the [other] women, and she obtained grace and favor in his sight more than all the virgins; so he set the royal crown upon her head and made her queen instead of Vashti. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فاحب الملك استير اكثر من جميع النساء ووجدت نعمة واحسانا قدامه اكثر من جميع العذارى فوضع تاج الملك على راسها وملّكها مكان وشتي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Maka Ester dikasihi oleh baginda lebih dari pada semua perempuan lain, dan ia beroleh sayang dan kasih baginda lebih dari pada semua anak dara lain, sehingga baginda mengenakan mahkota kerajaan ke atas kepalanya dan mengangkat dia menjadi ratu ganti Wasti.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> Then the king made a great feast, the Feast of Esther, for all his officials and servants; and he proclaimed a holiday in the provinces and gave gifts according to the generosity of a king. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">وعمل الملك وليمة عظيمة لجميع رؤسائه وعبيده وليمة استير. وعمل راحة للبلاد واعطى عطايا حسب كرم الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Kemudian diadakanlah oleh baginda suatu perjamuan bagi semua pembesar dan pegawainya, yakni perjamuan karena Ester, dan baginda menitahkan kebebasan pajak bagi daerah-daerah serta mengaruniakan anugerah, sebagaimana layak bagi raja.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> When virgins were gathered together a second time, Mordecai sat within the king's gate. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">ولما جمعت العذارى ثانية كان مردخاي جالسا بباب الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Selama anak-anak dara dikumpulkan untuk kedua kalinya, Mordekhai duduk di pintu gerbang istana raja.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> [Now] Esther had not revealed her family and her people, just as Mordecai had charged her, for Esther obeyed the command of Mordecai as when she was brought up by him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">ولم تكن استير اخبرت عن جنسها وشعبها كما اوصاها مردخاي. وكانت استير تعمل حسب قول مردخاي كما كانت في تربيتها عنده</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Adapun Ester tidak memberitahukan asal usul dan kebangsaannya seperti diperintahkan kepadanya oleh Mordekhai, sebab Ester tetap berbuat menurut perkataan Mordekhai seperti pada waktu ia masih dalam asuhannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> In those days, while Mordecai sat within the king's gate, two of the king's eunuchs, Bigthan and Teresh, doorkeepers, became furious and sought to lay hands on King Ahasuerus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">في تلك الايام بينما كان مردخاي جالسا في باب الملك غضب بغثان وترش خصيا الملك حارسا الباب وطلبا ان يمدا ايديهما الى الملك احشويروش.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Pada waktu itu, ketika Mordekhai duduk di pintu gerbang istana raja, sakit hatilah Bigtan dan Teresh, dua orang sida-sida raja yang termasuk golongan penjaga pintu, lalu berikhtiarlah mereka untuk membunuh raja Ahasyweros.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> So the matter became known to Mordecai, who told Queen Esther, and Esther informed the king in Mordecai's name. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">فعلم الأمر عند مردخاي فاخبر استير الملكة فاخبرت استير الملك باسم مردخاي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Tetapi perkara itu dapat diketahui oleh Mordekhai, lalu diberitahukannyala kepada Ester, sang ratu, dan Ester mempersembahkannya kepada raja atas nama Mordekhai.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> And when an inquiry was made into the matter, it was confirmed, and both were hanged on a gallows; and it was written in the book of the chronicles in the presence of the king. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">ففحص عن الامر ووجد فصلبا كلاهما على خشبة وكتب ذلك في سفر اخبار الايام امام الملك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Perkara itu diperiksa dan ternyata benar, maka kedua orang itu disulakan pada tiang. Dan peristiwa itu dituliskan di dalam kitab sejarah, di hadapan raja.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="3">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> After these things King Ahasuerus promoted Haman, the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, and advanced him and set his seat above all the princes who [were] with him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">بعد هذه الأمور عظّم الملك احشويروش هامان بن همداثا الاجاجي ورقّاه وجعل كرسيه فوق جميع الرؤساء الذين معه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Sesudah peristiwa-peristiwa ini maka Haman bin Hamedata, orang Agag, dikaruniailah kebesaran oleh raja Ahasyweros, dan pangkatnya dinaikkan serta kedudukannya ditetapkan di atas semua pembesar yang ada di hadapan baginda.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> And all the king's servants who [were] within the king's gate bowed and paid homage to Haman, for so the king had commanded concerning him. But Mordecai would not bow or pay homage. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فكان كل عبيد الملك الذين بباب الملك يجثون ويسجدون لهامان لانه هكذا اوصى به الملك. واما مردخاي فلم يجث ولم يسجد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Dan semua pegawai raja yang di pintu gerbang istana raja berlutut dan sujud kepada Haman, sebab demikianlah diperintahkan raja tentang dia, tetapi Mordekhai tidak berlutut dan tidak sujud.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Then the king's servants who [were] within the king's gate said to Mordecai, "Why do you transgress the king's command?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فقال عبيد الملك الذين بباب الملك لمردخاي لماذا تتعدّى امر الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Maka para pegawai raja yang di pintu gerbang istana raja berkata kepada Mordekhai: "Mengapa engkau melanggar perintah raja?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Now it happened, when they spoke to him daily and he would not listen to them, that they told [it] to Haman, to see whether Mordecai's words would stand; for [Mordecai] had told them that he [was] a Jew. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">واذ كانوا يكلمونه يوما فيوما ولم يكن يسمع لهم اخبروا هامان ليروا هل يقوم كلام مردخاي لانه اخبرهم بانه يهودي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Setelah mereka menegor dia berhari-hari dengan tidak didengarkannya juga, maka hal itu diberitahukan merekalah kepada Haman untuk melihat, apakah sikap Mordekhai itu dapat tetap, sebab ia telah menceritakan kepada mereka, bahwa ia orang Yahudi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> When Haman saw that Mordecai did not bow or pay him homage, Haman was filled with wrath. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">ولما رأى هامان ان مردخاي لا يجثو ولا يسجد له امتلأ هامان غضبا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Ketika Haman melihat, bahwa Mordekhai tidak berlutut dan sujud kepadanya, maka sangat panaslah hati Haman,</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> But he disdained to lay hands on Mordecai alone, for they had told him of the people of Mordecai. Instead, Haman sought to destroy all the Jews who [were] throughout the whole kingdom of Ahasuerus -- the people of Mordecai. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">وازدري في عينيه ان يمد يده الى مردخاي وحده لانهم اخبروه عن شعب مردخاي فطلب هامان ان يهلك جميع اليهود الذين في كل مملكة احشويروش شعب مردخاي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">tetapi ia menganggap dirinya terlalu hina untuk membunuh hanya Mordekhai saja, karena orang telah memberitahukan kepadanya kebangsaan Mordekhai itu. Jadi Haman mencari ikhtiar memunahkan semua orang Yahudi, yakni bangsa Mordekhai itu, di seluruh kerajaan Ahasyweros.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> In the first month, which is the month of Nisan, in the twelfth year of King Ahasuerus, they cast Pur (that [is,] the lot), before Haman to determine the day and the month, until [it fell on the] twelfth [month,] which [is] the month of Adar. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">في الشهر الاول اي شهر نيسان في السنة الثانية عشرة للملك احشويروش كانوا يلقون فورا اي قرعة امام هامان من يوم الى يوم ومن شهر الى شهر الى الثاني عشر اي شهر اذار.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Dalam bulan pertama, yakni bulan Nisan, dalam tahun yang kedua belas zaman raja Ahasyweros, orang membuang pur--yakni undi--di depan Haman, hari demi hari dan bulan demi bulan sampai jatuh pada bulan yang kedua belas, yakni bulan Adar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Then Haman said to King Ahasuerus, "There is a certain people scattered and dispersed among the people in all the provinces of your kingdom; their laws [are] different from all [other] people's, and they do not keep the king's laws. Therefore it [is] not fitting for the king to let them remain. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فقال هامان للملك احشويروش انه موجود شعب ما متشتت ومتفرق بين الشعوب في كل بلاد مملكتك وسننهم مغايرة لجميع الشعوب وهم لا يعملون سنن الملك فلا يليق بالملك تركهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Maka sembah Haman kepada raja Ahasyweros: "Ada suatu bangsa yang hidup tercerai-berai dan terasing di antara bangsa-bangsa di dalam seluruh daerah kerajaan tuanku, dan hukum mereka berlainan dengan hukum segala bangsa, dan hukum raja tidak dilakukan mereka, sehingga tidak patut bagi raja membiarkan mereka leluasa.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> "If it pleases the king, let [a decree] be written that they be destroyed, and I will pay ten thousand talents of silver into the hands of those who do the work, to bring [it] into the king's treasuries." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فاذا حسن عند الملك فليكتب ان يبادوا وانا ازن عشرة آلاف وزنة من الفضة في ايدي الذين يعملون العمل ليؤتى بها الى خزائن الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Jikalau baik pada pemandangan raja, hendaklah dikeluarkan surat titah untuk membinasakan mereka; maka hamba akan menimbang perak sepuluh ribu talenta dan menyerahkannya kepada tangan para pejabat yang bersangkutan, supaya mereka memasukkannya ke dalam perbendaharaan raja."</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> So the king took his signet ring from his hand and gave it to Haman, the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, the enemy of the Jews. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فنزع الملك خاتمه من يده واعطاه لهامان بن همداثا الاجاجي عدو اليهود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Maka raja mencabut cincin meterainya dari jarinya, lalu diserahkannya kepada Haman bin Hamedata, orang Agag, seteru orang Yahudi itu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> And the king said to Haman, "The money and the people [are] given to you, to do with them as seems good to you." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">وقال الملك لهامان الفضة قد أعطيت لك والشعب ايضا لتفعل به ما يحسن في عينيك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">kemudian titah raja kepada Haman: "Perak itu terserah kepadamu, juga bangsa itu untuk kauperlakukan seperti yang kaupandang baik."</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Then the king's scribes were called on the thirteenth day of the first month, and [a decree] was written according to all that Haman commanded -- to the king's satraps, to the governors who [were] over each province, to the officials of all people, to every province according to its script, and to every people in their language. In the name of King Ahasuerus it was written, and sealed with the king's signet ring. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فدعي كتّاب الملك في الشهر الاول في اليوم الثالث عشر منه وكتب حسب كل ما أمر به هامان الى مرازبة الملك والى ولاة بلاد فبلاد والى رؤساء شعب فشعب كل بلاد ككتابتها وكل شعب كلسانه كتب باسم الملك احشويروش وختم بخاتم الملك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Maka dalam bulan yang pertama pada hari yang ketiga belas dipanggillah para panitera raja, lalu, sesuai dengan segala yang diperintahkan Haman, ditulislah surat kepada wakil-wakil raja, kepada setiap bupati yang menguasai daerah dan kepada setiap pembesar bangsa, yakni kepada tiap-tiap daerah menurut tulisannya dan kepada tiap-tiap bangsa menurut bahasanya; surat itu ditulis atas nama raja Ahasyweros dan dimeterai dengan cincin meterai raja.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> And the letters were sent by couriers into all the king's provinces, to destroy, to kill, and to annihilate all the Jews, both young and old, little children and women, in one day, on the thirteenth [day] of the twelfth [month,] which [is] the month of Adar, and to plunder their possessions. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">وأرسلت الكتابات بيد السعاة الى كل بلدان الملك لاهلاك وقتل وابادة جميع اليهود من الغلام الى الشيخ والاطفال والنساء في يوم واحد في الثالث عشر من الشهر الثاني عشر اي شهر اذار وان يسلبوا غنيمتهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Surat-surat itu dikirimkan dengan perantaraan pesuruh-pesuruh cepat ke segala daerah kerajaan, supaya dipunahkan, dibunuh dan dibinasakan semua orang Yahudi dari pada yang muda sampai kepada yang tua, bahkan anak-anak dan perempuan-perempuan, pada satu hari juga, pada tanggal tiga belas bulan yang kedua belas--yakni bulan Adar--,dan supaya dirampas harta milik mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> A copy of the document was to be issued as law in every province, being published for all people, that they should be ready for that day. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">صورة الكتابة المعطاة سنّة في كل البلدان أشهرت بين جميع الشعوب ليكونوا مستعدين لهذا اليوم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Salinan surat itu harus diundangkan di dalam tiap-tiap daerah, lalu diumumkan kepada segala bangsa, supaya mereka bersiap-siap untuk hari itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> The couriers went out, hastened by the king's command; and the decree was proclaimed in Shushan the citadel. So the king and Haman sat down to drink, but the city of Shushan was perplexed. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فخرج السعاة وأمر الملك يحثّهم وأعطي الامر في شوشن القصر. وجلس الملك وهامان للشرب واما المدينة شوشن فارتبكت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Maka dengan tergesa-gesa berangkatlah pesuruh-pesuruh cepat itu, atas titah raja, dan undang-undang itu dikeluarkan di dalam benteng Susan. Sementara itu raja serta Haman duduk minum-minum, tetapi kota Susan menjadi gempar.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="4">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> When Mordecai learned all that had happened, he tore his clothes and put on sackcloth and ashes, and went out into the midst of the city. He cried out with a loud and bitter cry. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ولما علم مردخاي كل ما عمل شق مردخاي ثيابه ولبس مسحا برماد وخرج الى وسط المدينة وصرخ صرخة عظيمة مرّة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Setelah Mordekhai mengetahui segala yang terjadi itu, ia mengoyakkan pakaiannya, lalu memakai kain kabung dan abu, kemudian keluar berjalan di tengah-tengah kota, sambil melolong-lolong dengan nyaring dan pedih.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> He went as far as the front of the king's gate, for no one [might] enter the king's gate clothed with sackcloth. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">وجاء الى قدام باب الملك لانه لا يدخل احد باب الملك وهو لابس مسحا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Dengan demikian datanglah ia sampai ke depan pintu gerbang istana raja, karena seorangpun tidak boleh masuk pintu gerbang istana raja dengan berpakaian kain kabung.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> And in every province where the king's command and decree arrived, [there was] great mourning among the Jews, with fasting, weeping, and wailing; and many lay in sackcloth and ashes. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">وفي كل كورة حيثما وصل اليها امر الملك وسنته كانت مناحة عظيمة عند اليهود وصوم وبكاء ونحيب. وانفرش مسح ورماد لكثيرين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Di tiap-tiap daerah, ke mana titah dan undang-undang raja telah sampai, ada perkabungan yang besar di antara orang Yahudi disertai puasa dan ratap tangis; oleh banyak orang dibentangkan kain kabung dengan abu sebagai lapik tidurnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> So Esther's maids and eunuchs came and told her, and the queen was deeply distressed. Then she sent garments to clothe Mordecai and take his sackcloth away from him, but he would not accept [them.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فدخلت جواري استير وخصيانها واخبروها فاغتمّت الملكة جدا وارسلت ثيابا لإلباس مردخاي ولاجل نزع مسحه عنه فلم يقبل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Ketika dayang-dayang dan sida-sida Ester memberitahukan hal itu kepadanya, maka sangatlah risau hati sang ratu, lalu dikirimkannyalah pakaian, supaya dipakaikan kepada Mordekhai dan supaya ditanggalkan kain kabungnya dari padanya, tetapi tidak diterimanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Then Esther called Hathach, [one] of the king's eunuchs whom he had appointed to attend her, and she gave him a command concerning Mordecai, to learn what and why this [was.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فدعت استير هتاخ واحد من خصيان الملك الذي اوقفه بين يديها واعطته وصية الى مردخاي لتعلم ماذا ولماذا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Maka Ester memanggil Hatah, salah seorang sida-sida raja yang ditetapkan baginda melayani dia, lalu memberi perintah kepadanya menanyakan Mordekhai untuk mengetahui apa artinya dan apa sebabnya hal itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> So Hathach went out to Mordecai in the city square that [was] in front of the king's gate. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فخرج هتاخ الى مردخاي الى ساحة المدينة التي امام باب الملك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Lalu keluarlah Hatah mendapatkan Mordekhai di lapangan kota yang di depan pintu gerbang istana raja,</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> And Mordecai told him all that had happened to him, and the sum of money that Haman had promised to pay into the king's treasuries to destroy the Jews. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فاخبره مردخاي بكل ما اصابه وعن مبلغ الفضة الذي وعد هامان بوزنه لخزائن الملك عن اليهود لابادتهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">dan Mordekhai menceritakan kepadanya segala yang dialaminya, serta berapa banyaknya perak yang dijanjikan oleh Haman akan ditimbang untuk perbendaharaan raja sebagai harga pembinasaan orang Yahudi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> He also gave him a copy of the written decree for their destruction, which was given at Shushan, that he might show it to Esther and explain it to her, and that he might command her to go in to the king to make supplication to him and plead before him for her people. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">واعطاه صورة كتابة الأمر الذي أعطي في شوشن لاهلاكهم لكي يريها لاستير ويخبرها ويوصيها ان تدخل الى الملك وتتضرع اليه وتطلب منه لاجل شعبها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Juga salinan surat undang-undang, yang dikeluarkan di Susan untuk memunahkan mereka itu, diserahkannya kepada Hatah, supaya diperlihatkan dan diberitahukan kepada Ester. Lagipula Hatah disuruh menyampaikan pesan kepada Ester, supaya pergi menghadap raja untuk memohon karunianya dan untuk membela bangsanya di hadapan baginda.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> So Hathach returned and told Esther the words of Mordecai. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فأتى هتاخ واخبر استير بكلام مردخاي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Lalu masuklah Hatah dan menyampaikan perkataan Mordekhai kepada Ester.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Then Esther spoke to Hathach, and gave him a command for Mordecai: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فكلمت استير هتاخ واعطته وصية الى مردخاي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Akan tetapi Ester menyuruh Hatah memberitahukan kepada Mordekhai:</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> "All the king's servants and the people of the king's provinces know that any man or woman who goes into the inner court to the king, who has not been called, [he has] but one law: put [all] to death, except the one to whom the king holds out the golden scepter, that he may live. Yet I myself have not been called to go in to the king these thirty days." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ان كل عبيد الملك وشعوب بلاد الملك يعلمون ان كل رجل دخل او امرأة الى الملك الى الدار الداخلية ولم يدع فشريعته واحدة ان يقتل الا الذي يمدّ له الملك قضيب الذهب فانه يحيا. وانا لم أدع لادخل الى الملك هذه الثلاثين يوما.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">"Semua pegawai raja serta penduduk daerah-daerah kerajaan mengetahui bahwa bagi setiap laki-laki atau perempuan, yang menghadap raja di pelataran dalam dengan tiada dipanggil, hanya berlaku satu undang-undang, yakni hukuman mati. Hanya orang yang kepadanya raja mengulurkan tongkat emas, yang akan tetap hidup. Dan aku selama tiga puluh hari ini tidak dipanggil menghadap raja."</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> So they told Mordecai Esther's words. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فاخبروا مردخاي بكلام استير.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Ketika disampaikan orang perkataan Ester itu kepada Mordekhai,</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> And Mordecai told [them] to answer Esther: "Do not think in your heart that you will escape in the king's palace any more than all the other Jews. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فقال مردخاي ان تجاوب استير. لا تفتكري في نفسك انك تنجين في بيت الملك دون جميع اليهود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">maka Mordekhai menyuruh menyampaikan jawab ini kepada Ester: "Jangan kira, karena engkau di dalam istana raja, hanya engkau yang akan terluput dari antara semua orang Yahudi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> "For if you remain completely silent at this time, relief and deliverance will arise for the Jews from another place, but you and your father's house will perish. Yet who knows whether you have come to the kingdom for [such] a time as this?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">لانك ان سكتّ سكوتا في هذا الوقت يكون الفرج والنجاة لليهود من مكان آخر واما انت وبيت ابيك فتبيدون. ومن يعلم ان كنت لوقت مثل هذا وصلت الى الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Sebab sekalipun engkau pada saat ini berdiam diri saja, bagi orang Yahudi akan timbul juga pertolongan dan kelepasan dari pihak lain, dan engkau dengan kaum keluargamu akan binasa. Siapa tahu, mungkin justru untuk saat yang seperti ini engkau beroleh kedudukan sebagai ratu."</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Then Esther told [them] to reply to Mordecai: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فقالت استير ان يجاوب مردخاي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Maka Ester menyuruh menyampaikan jawab ini kepada Mordekhai:</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> "Go, gather all the Jews who are present in Shushan, and fast for me; neither eat nor drink for three days, night or day. My maids and I will fast likewise. And so I will go to the king, which [is] against the law; and if I perish, I perish!" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">اذهب اجمع جميع اليهود الموجودين في شوشن وصوموا من جهتي ولا تأكلوا ولا تشربوا ثلاثة ايام ليلا ونهارا. وانا ايضا وجواريّ نصوم كذلك وهكذا ادخل الى الملك خلاف السنّة. فاذا هلكت هلكت.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">"Pergilah, kumpulkanlah semua orang Yahudi yang terdapat di Susan dan berpuasalah untuk aku; janganlah makan dan janganlah minum tiga hari lamanya, baik waktu malam, baik waktu siang. Aku serta dayang-dayangkupun akan berpuasa demikian, dan kemudian aku akan masuk menghadap raja, sungguhpun berlawanan dengan undang-undang; kalau terpaksa aku mati, biarlah aku mati."</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> So Mordecai went his way and did according to all that Esther commanded him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فانصرف مردخاي وعمل حسب كل ما اوصته به استير</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Maka pergilah Mordekhai dan diperbuatnyalah tepat seperti yang dipesankan Ester kepadanya.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="5">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Now it happened on the third day that Esther put on [her] royal [robes] and stood in the inner court of the king's palace, across from the king's house, while the king sat on his royal throne in the royal house, facing the entrance of the house. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وفي اليوم الثالث لبست استير ثيابا ملكية ووقفت في دار بيت الملك الداخلية مقابل بيت الملك والملك جالس على كرسي ملكه في بيت الملك مقابل مدخل البيت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Pada hari yang ketiga Ester mengenakan pakaian ratu, lalu berdirilah ia di pelataran dalam istana raja, tepat di depan istana raja. Raja bersemayam di atas takhta kerajaan di dalam istana, berhadapan dengan pintu istana itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> So it was, when the king saw Queen Esther standing in the court, [that] she found favor in his sight, and the king held out to Esther the golden scepter that [was] in his hand. Then Esther went near and touched the top of the scepter. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فلما رأى الملك استير الملكة واقفة في الدار نالت نعمة في عينيه فمدّ الملك لاستير قضيب الذهب الذي بيده فدنت استير ولمست راس القضيب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Ketika raja melihat Ester, sang ratu, berdiri di pelataran, berkenanlah raja kepadanya, sehingga raja mengulurkan tongkat emas yang di tangannya ke arah Ester, lalu mendekatlah Ester dan menyentuh ujung tongkat itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> And the king said to her, "What do you wish, Queen Esther? What [is] your request? It shall be given to you -- up to half the kingdom!" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فقال لها الملك ما لك يا استير الملكة وما هي طلبتك. الى نصف المملكة تعطى لك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Tanya raja kepadanya: "Apa maksudmu, hai ratu Ester, dan apa keinginanmu? Sampai setengah kerajaan sekalipun akan diberikan kepadamu."</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> So Esther answered, "If it pleases the king, let the king and Haman come today to the banquet that I have prepared for him." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فقالت استير ان حسن عند الملك فليأت الملك وهامان اليوم الى الوليمة التي عملتها له.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Jawab Ester: "Jikalau baik pada pemandangan raja, datanglah kiranya raja dengan Haman pada hari ini ke perjamuan yang diadakan oleh hamba bagi raja."</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Then the king said, "Bring Haman quickly, that he may do as Esther has said." So the king and Haman went to the banquet that Esther had prepared. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فقال الملك اسرعوا بهامان ليفعل كلام استير. فأتى الملك وهامان الى الوليمة التي عملتها استير.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Maka titah raja: "Suruhlah Haman datang dengan segera, supaya kami memenuhi permintaan Ester." Lalu raja datang dengan Haman ke perjamuan yang diadakan oleh Ester.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> At the banquet of wine the king said to Esther, "What [is] your petition? It shall be granted you. What [is] your request, up to half the kingdom? It shall be done!" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فقال الملك لاستير عند شرب الخمر ما هو سؤلك فيعطى لك وما هي طلبتك. الى نصف المملكة تقضى.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Sementara minum anggur bertanyalah raja kepada Ester: "Apakah permintaanmu? Niscaya akan dikabulkan. Dan apakah keinginanmu? Sampai setengah kerajaan sekalipun akan dipenuhi."</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Then Esther answered and said, "My petition and request [is this:] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فاجابت استير وقالت ان سؤلي وطلبتي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Maka jawab Ester: "Permintaan dan keinginan hamba ialah:</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> "If I have found favor in the sight of the king, and if it pleases the king to grant my petition and fulfill my request, then let the king and Haman come to the banquet which I will prepare for them, and tomorrow I will do as the king has said." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ان وجدت نعمة في عيني الملك واذا حسن عند الملك ان يعطى سؤلي وتقضى طلبتي ان يأتي الملك وهامان الى الوليمة التي اعملها لهما وغدا افعل حسب امر الملك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Jikalau hamba mendapat kasih raja, dan jikalau baik pada pemandangan raja mengabulkan permintaan serta memenuhi keinginan hamba, datang pulalah kiranya raja dengan Haman ke perjamuan yang akan hamba adakan bagi raja dan Haman; maka besok akan hamba lakukan yang dikehendaki raja."</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> So Haman went out that day joyful and with a glad heart; but when Haman saw Mordecai in the king's gate, and that he did not stand or tremble before him, he was filled with indignation against Mordecai. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فخرج هامان في ذلك اليوم فرحا وطيب القلب. ولكن لما رأى هامان مردخاي في باب الملك ولم يقم ولا تحرك له امتلأ هامان غيظا على مردخاي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Pada hari itu keluarlah Haman dengan hati riang dan gembira; tetapi ketika Haman melihat Mordekhai ada di pintu gerbang istana raja, tidak bangkit dan tidak bergerak menghormati dia, maka sangat panaslah hati Haman kepada Mordekhai.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Nevertheless Haman restrained himself and went home, and he sent and called for his friends and his wife Zeresh. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">وتجلد هامان ودخل بيته وارسل فاستحضر احباءه وزرش زوجته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Tetapi Haman menahan hatinya, lalu pulanglah ia ke rumahnya dan menyuruh datang sahabat-sahabatnya dan Zeresh, isterinya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Then Haman told them of his great riches, the multitude of his children, everything in which the king had promoted him, and how he had advanced him above the officials and servants of the king. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">وعدد لهم هامان عظمة غناه وكثرة بنيه وكل ما عظّمه الملك به ورقّاه على الرؤساء وعبيد الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Maka Haman menceriterakan kepada mereka itu besarnya kekayaannya, banyaknya anaknya laki-laki, dan segala kebesaran yang diberikan raja kepadanya serta kenaikan pangkatnya di atas para pembesar dan pegawai raja.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Moreover Haman said, "Besides, Queen Esther invited no one but me to come in with the king to the banquet that she prepared; and tomorrow I am again invited by her, along with the king. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">وقال هامان حتى ان استير الملكة لم تدخل مع الملك الى الوليمة التي عملتها الا اياي وانا غدا ايضا مدعو اليها مع الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Lagi kata Haman: "Tambahan pula tiada seorangpun diminta oleh Ester, sang ratu, untuk datang bersama-sama dengan raja ke perjamuan yang diadakannya, kecuali aku; dan untuk besokpun aku diundangnya bersama-sama dengan raja.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> "Yet all this avails me nothing, so long as I see Mordecai the Jew sitting at the king's gate." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">وكل هذا لا يساوي عندي شيئا كلما ارى مردخاي اليهودي جالسا في باب الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Akan tetapi semuanya itu tidak berguna bagiku, selama aku masih melihat si Mordekhai, si Yahudi itu, duduk di pintu gerbang istana raja."</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Then his wife Zeresh and all his friends said to him, "Let a gallows be made, fifty cubits high, and in the morning suggest to the king that Mordecai be hanged on it; then go merrily with the king to the banquet." And the thing pleased Haman; so he had the gallows made. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فقالت له زرش زوجته وكل احبائه فليعملوا خشبة ارتفاعها خمسون ذراعا وفي الصباح قل للملك ان يصلبوا مردخاي عليها ثم ادخل مع الملك الى الوليمة فرحا. فحسن الكلام عند هامان وعمل الخشبة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Lalu kata Zeresh, isterinya, dan semua sahabatnya kepadanya: "Suruhlah orang membuat tiang yang tingginya lima puluh hasta, dan persembahkanlah besok pagi kepada raja, supaya Mordekhai disulakan orang pada tiang itu; kemudian dapatlah engkau dengan bersukacita pergi bersama-sama dengan raja ke perjamuan itu." Hal itu dipandang baik oleh Haman, lalu ia menyuruh membuat tiang itu.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="6">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> That night the king could not sleep. So one was commanded to bring the book of the records of the chronicles; and they were read before the king. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">في تلك الليلة طار نوم الملك فامر بان يؤتى بسفر تذكار اخبار الايام فقرئت امام الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Pada malam itu juga raja tidak dapat tidur. Maka bertitahlah baginda membawa kitab pencatatan sejarah, lalu dibacakan di hadapan raja.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> And it was found written that Mordecai had told of Bigthana and Teresh, two of the king's eunuchs, the doorkeepers who had sought to lay hands on King Ahasuerus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فوجد مكتوبا ما اخبر به مردخاي عن بغثانا وترش خصيّي الملك حارسي الباب اللذين طلبا ان يمدا ايديهما الى الملك احشويروش.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Dan di situ didapati suatu catatan tentang Mordekhai, yang pernah memberitahukan bahwa Bigtan dan Teresh, dua orang sida-sida raja yang termasuk golongan penjaga pintu, telah berikhtiar membunuh raja Ahasyweros.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Then the king said, "What honor or dignity has been bestowed on Mordecai for this?" And the king's servants who attended him said, "Nothing has been done for him." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فقال الملك ايّة كرامة وعظمة عملت لمردخاي لاجل هذا. فقال غلمان الملك الذين يخدمونه لم يعمل معه شيء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Maka bertanyalah raja: "Kehormatan dan kebesaran apakah yang dianugerahkan kepada Mordekhai oleh sebab perkara itu?" Jawab para biduanda raja yang bertugas pada baginda: "Kepadanya tidak dianugerahkan suatu apapun."</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> So the king said, "Who [is] in the court?" Now Haman had [just] entered the outer court of the king's palace to suggest that the king hang Mordecai on the gallows that he had prepared for him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فقال الملك من في الدار. وكان هامان قد دخل دار بيت الملك الخارجية لكي يقول للملك ان يصلب مردخاي على الخشبة التي اعدها له.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Maka bertanyalah raja: "Siapakah itu yang ada di pelataran?" Pada waktu itu Haman baru datang di pelataran luar istana raja untuk memberitahukan kepada baginda, bahwa ia hendak menyulakan Mordekhai pada tiang yang sudah didirikannya untuk dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> The king's servants said to him, "Haman is there, standing in the court." And the king said, "Let him come in." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فقال غلمان الملك له هوذا هامان واقف في الدار. فقال الملك ليدخل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Lalu jawab para biduanda raja kepada baginda: "Itulah Haman, ia berdiri di pelataran." Maka titah raja: "Suruhlah dia masuk."</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> So Haman came in, and the king asked him, "What shall be done for the man whom the king delights to honor?" Now Haman thought in his heart, "Whom would the king delight to honor more than me?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ولما دخل هامان قال له الملك ماذا يعمل لرجل يسرّ الملك بان يكرمه. فقال هامان في قلبه من يسرّ الملك بان يكرمه اكثر مني.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Setelah Haman masuk, bertanyalah raja kepadanya: "Apakah yang harus dilakukan kepada orang yang raja berkenan menghormatinya?" Kata Haman dalam hatinya: "Kepada siapa lagi raja berkenan menganugerahkan kehormatan lebih dari kepadaku?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> And Haman answered the king, "[For] the man whom the king delights to honor, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فقال هامان للملك ان الرجل الذي يسرّ الملك بان يكرمه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Oleh karena itu jawab Haman kepada raja: "Mengenai orang yang raja berkenan menghormatinya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> "let a royal robe be brought which the king has worn, and a horse on which the king has ridden, which has a royal crest placed on its head. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">يأتون باللباس السلطاني الذي يلبسه الملك وبالفرس الذي يركبه الملك وبتاج الملك الذي يوضع على راسه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">hendaklah diambil pakaian kerajaan yang biasa dipakai oleh raja sendiri, dan lagi kuda yang biasa dikendarai oleh raja sendiri dan yang diberi mahkota kerajaan di kepalanya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> "Then let this robe and horse be delivered to the hand of one of the king's most noble princes, that he may array the man whom the king delights to honor. Then parade him on horseback through the city square, and proclaim before him: 'Thus shall it be done to the man whom the king delights to honor!' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ويدفع اللباس والفرس لرجل من رؤساء الملك الاشراف ويلبسون الرجل الذي سرّ الملك بان يكرمه ويركبونه على الفرس في ساحة المدينة وينادون قدامه هكذا يصنع للرجل الذي يسرّ الملك بان يكرمه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">dan hendaklah diserahkan pakaian dan kuda itu ke tangan seorang dari antara para pembesar raja, orang-orang bangsawan, lalu hendaklah pakaian itu dikenakan kepada orang yang raja berkenan menghormatinya, kemudian hendaklah ia diarak dengan mengendarai kuda itu melalui lapangan kota sedang orang berseru-seru di depannya: Beginilah dilakukan kepada orang yang raja berkenan menghormatinya!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Then the king said to Haman, "Hurry, take the robe and the horse, as you have suggested, and do so for Mordecai the Jew who sits within the king's gate! Leave nothing undone of all that you have spoken." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فقال الملك لهامان اسرع وخذ اللباس والفرس كما تكلمت وافعل هكذا لمردخاي اليهودي الجالس في باب الملك. لا يسقط شيء من جميع ما قلته.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Maka titah raja kepada Haman: "Segera ambillah pakaian dan kuda itu, seperti yang kaukatakan itu, dan lakukanlah demikian kepada Mordekhai, orang Yahudi, yang duduk di pintu gerbang istana. Sepatah katapun janganlah kaulalaikan dari pada segala yang kaukatakan itu."</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> So Haman took the robe and the horse, arrayed Mordecai and led him on horseback through the city square, and proclaimed before him, "Thus shall it be done to the man whom the king delights to honor!" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فاخذ هامان اللباس والفرس وألبس مردخاي واركبه في ساحة المدينة ونادى قدامه هكذا يصنع للرجل الذي يسرّ الملك بان يكرمه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Lalu Haman mengambil pakaian dan kuda itu, dan dikenakannya pakaian itu kepada Mordekhai, kemudian diaraknya Mordekhai melalui lapangan kota itu, sedang ia menyerukan di depannya: "Beginilah dilakukan kepada orang yang raja berkenan menghormatinya."</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Afterward Mordecai went back to the king's gate. But Haman hurried to his house, mourning and with his head covered. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ورجع مردخاي الى باب الملك. واما هامان فاسرع الى بيته نائحا ومغطى الراس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Kemudian kembalilah Mordekhai ke pintu gerbang istana raja, tetapi Haman bergesa-gesa pulang ke rumahnya dengan sedih hatinya dan berselubung kepalanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> When Haman told his wife Zeresh and all his friends everything that had happened to him, his wise men and his wife Zeresh said to him, "If Mordecai, before whom you have begun to fall, is of Jewish descent, you will not prevail against him but will surely fall before him." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">وقصّ هامان على زرش زوجته وجميع احبائه كل ما اصابه. فقال له حكماؤه وزرش زوجته اذا كان مردخاي الذي ابتدأت تسقط قدامه من نسل اليهود فلا تقدر عليه بل تسقط قدامه سقوطا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Dan Haman menceritakan kepada Zeresh, isterinya, dan kepada semua sahabatnya apa yang dialaminya. Maka kata para orang arif bijaksana dan Zeresh, isterinya, kepadanya: "Jikalau Mordekhai, yang di depannya engkau sudah mulai jatuh, adalah keturunan Yahudi, maka engkau tidak akan sanggup melawan dia, malahan engkau akan jatuh benar-benar di depannya."</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> While they [were] still talking with him, the king's eunuchs came, and hastened to bring Haman to the banquet which Esther had prepared. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">وفيما هم يكلمونه وصل خصيان الملك واسرعوا للأتيان بهامان الى الوليمة التي عملتها استير</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Selagi mereka itu bercakap-cakap dengan dia, datanglah sida-sida raja, lalu mengantarkan Haman dengan segera ke perjamuan yang diadakan oleh Ester.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="7">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> So the king and Haman went to dine with Queen Esther. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">فجاء الملك وهامان ليشربا عند استير الملكة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Datanglah raja dengan Haman untuk dijamu oleh Ester, sang ratu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> And on the second day, at the banquet of wine, the king again said to Esther, "What [is] your petition, Queen Esther? It shall be granted you. And what [is] your request, up to half the kingdom? It shall be done!" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فقال الملك لاستير في اليوم الثاني ايضا عند شرب الخمر ما هو سؤلك يا استير الملكة فيعطى لك وما هي طلبتك. ولو الى نصف المملكة تقضى.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Pada hari yang kedua itu, sementara minum anggur, bertanyalah pula raja kepada Ester: "Apakah permintaanmu, hai ratu Ester? Niscaya akan dikabulkan. Dan apakah keinginanmu? Sampai setengah kerajaan sekalipun akan dipenuhi."</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Then Queen Esther answered and said, "If I have found favor in your sight, O king, and if it pleases the king, let my life be given me at my petition, and my people at my request. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فاجابت استير الملكة وقالت ان كنت قد وجدت نعمة في عينيك ايها الملك واذا حسن عند الملك فلتعطى لي نفسي بسؤلي وشعبي بطلبتي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Maka jawab Ester, sang ratu: "Ya raja, jikalau hamba mendapat kasih raja dan jikalau baik pada pemandangan raja, karuniakanlah kiranya kepada hamba nyawa hamba atas permintaan hamba, dan bangsa hamba atas keinginan hamba.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> "For we have been sold, my people and I, to be destroyed, to be killed, and to be annihilated. Had we been sold as male and female slaves, I would have held my tongue, although the enemy could never compensate for the king's loss." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">لاننا قد بعنا انا وشعبي للهلاك والقتل والابادة ولو بعنا عبيدا واماء لكنت سكت مع ان العدوّ لا يعوّض عن خسارة الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Karena kami, hamba serta bangsa hamba, telah terjual untuk dipunahkan, dibunuh dan dibinasakan. Jikalau seandainya kami hanya dijual sebagai budak laki-laki dan perempuan, niscaya hamba akan berdiam diri, tetapi malapetaka ini tiada taranya di antara bencana yang menimpa raja."</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> So King Ahasuerus answered and said to Queen Esther, "Who is he, and where is he, who would dare presume in his heart to do such a thing?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فتكلم الملك احشويروش وقال لاستير الملكة من هو واين هو هذا الذي يتجاسر بقلبه على ان يعمل هكذا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Maka bertanyalah raja Ahasyweros kepada Ester, sang ratu: "Siapakah orang itu dan di manakah dia yang hatinya mengandung niat akan berbuat demikian?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> And Esther said, "The adversary and enemy [is] this wicked Haman!" So Haman was terrified before the king and queen. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فقالت استير هو رجل خصم وعدو هذا هامان الردي. فارتاع هامان امام الملك والملكة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Lalu jawab Ester: "Penganiaya dan musuh itu, ialah Haman, orang jahat ini!" Maka Hamanpun sangatlah ketakutan di hadapan raja dan ratu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Then the king arose in his wrath from the banquet of wine [and went] into the palace garden; but Haman stood before Queen Esther, pleading for his life, for he saw that evil was determined against him by the king. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فقام الملك بغيظه عن شرب الخمر الى جنة القصر ووقف هامان ليتوسل عن نفسه الى استير الملكة لانه رأى ان الشر قد أعد عليه من قبل الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Lalu bangkitlah raja dengan panas hatinya dari pada minum anggur dan keluar ke taman istana; akan tetapi Haman masih tinggal untuk memohon nyawanya kepada Ester, sang ratu, karena ia melihat, bahwa telah putus niat raja untuk mendatangkan celaka kepadanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> When the king returned from the palace garden to the place of the banquet of wine, Haman had fallen across the couch where Esther [was.] Then the king said, "Will he also assault the queen while I [am] in the house?" As the word left the king's mouth, they covered Haman's face. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ولما رجع الملك من جنة القصر الى بيت شرب الخمر وهامان متواقع على السرير الذي كانت استير عليه قال الملك هل ايضا يكبس الملكة معي في البيت. ولما خرجت الكلمة من فم الملك غطوا وجه هامان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Ketika raja kembali dari taman istana ke dalam ruangan minum anggur, maka Haman berlutut pada katil tempat Ester berbaring. Maka titah raja: "Masih jugakah ia hendak menggagahi sang ratu di dalam istanaku sendiri?" Tatkala titah raja itu keluar dari mulutnya, maka diselubungi oranglah muka Haman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Now Harbonah, one of the eunuchs, said to the king, "Look! The gallows, fifty cubits high, which Haman made for Mordecai, who spoke good on the king's behalf, is standing at the house of Haman." Then the king said, "Hang him on it!" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فقال حربونا واحد من الخصيان الذين بين يدي الملك هوذا الخشبة ايضا التي عملها هامان لمردخاي الذي تكلم بالخير نحو الملك قائمة في بيت هامان ارتفاعها خمسون ذراعا. فقال الملك اصلبوه عليها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Sembah Harbona, salah seorang sida-sida yang di hadapan raja: "Lagipula tiang yang dibuat Haman untuk Mordekhai, orang yang menyelamatkan raja dengan pemberitahuannya itu, telah berdiri di dekat rumah Haman, lima puluh hasta tingginya." Lalu titah raja: "Sulakan dia pada tiang itu."</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> So they hanged Haman on the gallows that he had prepared for Mordecai. Then the king's wrath subsided. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فصلبوا هامان على الخشبة التي اعدها لمردخاي. ثم سكن غضب الملك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Kemudian Haman disulakan pada tiang yang didirikannya untuk Mordekhai. Maka surutlah panas hati raja.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="8">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> On that day King Ahasuerus gave Queen Esther the house of Haman, the enemy of the Jews. And Mordecai came before the king, for Esther had told how he [was related] to her. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">في ذلك اليوم اعطى الملك احشويروش لاستير الملكة بيت هامان عدو اليهود. وأتى مردخاي الى امام الملك لان استير اخبرته بما هو لها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Pada hari itu juga raja Ahasyweros mengaruniakan harta milik Haman, seteru orang Yahudi, kepada Ester, sang ratu, dan Mordekhai masuk menghadap raja, karena Ester telah memberitahukan apa pertalian Mordekhai dengan dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> So the king took off his signet ring, which he had taken from Haman, and gave it to Mordecai; and Esther appointed Mordecai over the house of Haman. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">ونزع الملك خاتمه الذي اخذه من هامان واعطاه لمردخاي واقامت استير مردخاي على بيت هامان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Maka raja mencabut cincin meterai yang diambil dari pada Haman, lalu diserahkannya kepada Mordekhai; dan Mordekhai diangkat oleh Ester menjadi kuasa atas harta milik Haman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Now Esther spoke again to the king, fell down at his feet, and implored him with tears to counteract the evil of Haman the Agagite, and the scheme which he had devised against the Jews. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">ثم عادت استير وتكلمت امام الملك وسقطت عند رجليه وبكت وتضرعت اليه ان يزيل شرّ هامان الاجاجي وتدبيره الذي دبره على اليهود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Kemudian Ester berkata lagi kepada raja sambil sujud pada kakinya dan menangis memohon karunianya, supaya dibatalkannya maksud jahat Haman, orang Agag itu, serta rancangan yang sudah dibuatnya terhadap orang Yahudi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> And the king held out the golden scepter toward Esther. So Esther arose and stood before the king, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فمدّ الملك لاستير قضيب الذهب فقامت استير ووقفت امام الملك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Maka raja mengulurkan tongkat emas kepada Ester, lalu bangkitlah Ester dan berdiri di hadapan raja,</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> and said, "If it pleases the king, and if I have found favor in his sight and the thing [seems] right to the king and I am pleasing in his eyes, let it be written to revoke the letters devised by Haman, the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, which he wrote to annihilate the Jews who [are] in all the king's provinces. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">وقالت اذا حسن عند الملك وان كنت قد وجدت نعمة امامه واستقام الأمر امام الملك وحسنت انا لديه فليكتب لكي ترد كتابات تدبير هامان بن همداثا الاجاجي التي كتبها لابادة اليهود الذين في كل بلاد الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">serta sembahnya: "Jikalau baik pada pemandangan raja dan jikalau hamba mendapat kasih raja, dan hal ini kiranya dipandang benar oleh raja dan raja berkenan kepada hamba, maka hendaklah dikeluarkan surat titah untuk menarik kembali surat-surat yang berisi rancangan Haman bin Hamedata, orang Agag itu, yang ditulisnya untuk membinasakan orang Yahudi di dalam semua daerah kerajaan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> "For how can I endure to see the evil that will come to my people? Or how can I endure to see the destruction of my countrymen?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لانني كيف استطيع ان ارى الشر الذي يصيب شعبي وكيف استطيع ان ارى هلاك جنسي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Karena bagaimana hamba dapat melihat malapetaka yang menimpa bangsa hamba dan bagaimana hamba dapat melihat kebinasaan sanak saudara hamba?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Then King Ahasuerus said to Queen Esther and Mordecai the Jew, "Indeed, I have given Esther the house of Haman, and they have hanged him on the gallows because he [tried to] lay his hand on the Jews. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فقال الملك احشويروش لاستير الملكة ومردخاي اليهودي هوذا قد اعطيت بيت هامان لاستير اما هو فقد صلبوه على الخشبة من اجل انه مدّ يده الى اليهود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Maka jawab raja Ahasyweros kepada Ester, sang ratu, serta kepada Mordekhai, orang Yahudi itu: "Harta milik Haman telah kukaruniakan kepada Ester, dan Haman sendiri telah disulakan pada tiang karena ia sudah mengacungkan tangannya kepada orang Yahudi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> "You yourselves write [a decree] concerning the Jews, as you please, in the king's name, and seal [it] with the king's signet ring; for whatever is written in the king's name and sealed with the king's signet ring no one can revoke." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فاكتبا انتما الى اليهود ما يحسن في اعينكما باسم الملك واختماه بخاتم الملك لان الكتابة التي تكتب باسم الملك وتختم بخاتمه لا ترد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Tuliskanlah atas nama raja apa yang kamu pandang baik tentang orang Yahudi dan meteraikanlah surat itu dengan cincin meterai raja, karena surat yang dituliskan atas nama raja dan dimeteraikan dengan cincin meterai raja tidak dapat ditarik kembali."</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> So the king's scribes were called at that time, in the third month, which [is] the month of Sivan, on the twenty-third [day;] and it was written, according to all that Mordecai commanded, to the Jews, the satraps, the governors, and the princes of the provinces from India to Ethiopia, one hundred and twenty-seven provinces [in all,] to every province in its own script, to every people in their own language, and to the Jews in their own script and language. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فدعي كتاب الملك في ذلك الوقت في الشهر الثالث اي شهر سيوان في الثالث والعشرين منه وكتب حسب كل ما امر به مردخاي الى اليهود والى المرازبة والولاة ورؤساء البلدان التي من الهند الى كوش مئة وسبع وعشرين كورة الى كل كورة بكتابتها وكل شعب بلسانه والى اليهود بكتابتهم ولسانهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Pada waktu itu juga dipanggillah para panitera raja, dalam bulan yang ketiga--yakni bulan Siwan--pada tanggal dua puluh tiga, dan sesuai dengan segala yang diperintahkan Mordekhai ditulislah surat kepada orang Yahudi, dan kepada para wakil pemerintah, para bupati dan para pembesar daerah, dari India sampai ke Etiopia, seratus dua puluh tujuh daerah, kepada tiap-tiap daerah menurut tulisannya dan kepada tiap-tiap bangsa menurut bahasanya, dan juga kepada orang Yahudi menurut tulisan dan bahasanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> And he wrote in the name of King Ahasuerus, sealed [it] with the king's signet ring, and sent letters by couriers on horseback, riding on royal horses bred from swift steeds. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فكتب باسم الملك احشويروش وختم بخاتم الملك وارسل رسائل بايدي بريد الخيل ركاب الجياد والبغال بني الرّمك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Maka ditulislah pesan atas nama raja Ahasyweros dan dimeterai dengan cincin meterai raja, lalu dengan perantaraan pesuruh-pesuruh cepat yang berkuda, yang mengendarai kuda kerajaan yang tangkas yang diternakkan di pekudaan, dikirimkanlah surat-surat</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> By these letters the king permitted the Jews who [were] in every city to gather together and protect their lives -- to destroy, kill, and annihilate all the forces of any people or province that would assault them, [both] little children and women, and to plunder their possessions, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">التي بها اعطى الملك اليهود في مدينة فمدينة ان يجتمعوا ويقفوا لاجل انفسهم ويهلكوا ويقتلوا ويبيدوا قوة كل شعب وكورة تضادهم حتى الاطفال والنساء وان يسلبوا غنيمتهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">yang isinya: raja mengizinkan orang Yahudi di tiap-tiap kota untuk berkumpul dan mempertahankan nyawanya serta memunahkan, membunuh atau membinasakan segala tentara, bahkan anak-anak dan perempuan-perempuan, dari bangsa dan daerah yang hendak menyerang mereka, dan untuk merampas harta miliknya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> on one day in all the provinces of King Ahasuerus, on the thirteenth [day] of the twelfth month, which [is] the month of Adar. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">في يوم واحد في كل كور الملك احشويروش في الثالث عشر من الشهر الثاني عشر اي شهر اذار.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">pada hari yang sama di segala daerah raja Ahasyweros, pada tanggal tiga belas bulan yang kedua belas, yakni bulan Adar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> A copy of the document was to be issued as a decree in every province and published for all people, so that the Jews would be ready on that day to avenge themselves on their enemies. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">صورة الكتابة المعطاة سنّة في كل البلدان أشهرت على جميع الشعوب ان يكون اليهود مستعدين لهذا اليوم لينتقموا من اعدائهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Salinan pesan tertulis itu harus diundangkan di tiap-tiap daerah, lalu diumumkan kepada segala bangsa, dan orang Yahudi harus bersiap-siap untuk hari itu akan melakukan pembalasan kepada musuhnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> The couriers who rode on royal horses went out, hastened and pressed on by the king's command. And the decree was issued in Shushan the citadel. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فخرج البريد ركاب الجياد والبغال وأمر الملك يحثهم ويعجلهم واعطي الأمر في شوشن القصر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Maka dengan terburu-buru dan tergesa-gesa berangkatlah pesuruh-pesuruh cepat yang mengendarai kuda kerajaan yang tangkas itu, atas titah raja, dan undang-undang itu dikeluarkan di dalam benteng Susan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> So Mordecai went out from the presence of the king in royal apparel of blue and white, with a great crown of gold and a garment of fine linen and purple; and the city of Shushan rejoiced and was glad. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">وخرج مردخاي من امام الملك بلباس ملكي اسمانجوني وابيض وتاج عظيم من ذهب وحلة من بزّ وارجوان. وكانت مدينة شوشن متهللة وفرحة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Dan Mordekhai keluar dari hadapan raja dengan memakai pakaian kerajaan dari pada kain ungu tua dan kain lenan, dengan memakai tajuk emas yang mengagumkan serta jubah dari pada kain lenan halus dan kain ungu muda. Maka kota Susanpun bertempiksoraklah dan bersukaria:</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> The Jews had light and gladness, joy and honor. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">وكان لليهود نور وفرح وبهجة وكرامة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">orang Yahudi telah beroleh kelapangan hati dan sukacita, kegirangan dan kehormatan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> And in every province and city, wherever the king's command and decree came, the Jews had joy and gladness, a feast and a holiday. Then many of the people of the land became Jews, because fear of the Jews fell upon them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">وفي كل بلاد ومدينة كل مكان وصل اليه كلام الملك وأمره كان فرح وبهجة عند اليهود وولائم ويوم طيب. وكثيرون من شعوب الارض تهودوا لان رعب اليهود وقع عليهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Demikian juga di tiap-tiap daerah dan di tiap-tiap kota, di tempat manapun titah dan undang-undang raja telah sampai, ada sukacita dan kegirangan di antara orang Yahudi, dan perjamuan serta hari gembira; dan lagi banyak dari antara rakyat negeri itu masuk Yahudi, karena mereka ditimpa ketakutan kepada orang Yahudi.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="9">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Now in the twelfth month, that [is,] the month of Adar, on the thirteenth day, [the time] came for the king's command and his decree to be executed. On the day that the enemies of the Jews had hoped to overpower them, the opposite occurred, in that the Jews themselves overpowered those who hated them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وفي الشهر الثاني عشر اي شهر اذار في اليوم الثالث عشر منه حين قرب كلام الملك وأمره من الاجراء في اليوم الذي انتظر فيه اعداء اليهود ان يتسلطوا عليهم فتحول ذلك حتى ان اليهود تسلطوا على مبغضيهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Dalam bulan yang kedua belas--yakni bulan Adar--,pada hari yang ketiga belas, ketika titah serta undang-undang raja akan dilaksanakan, pada hari musuh-musuh orang Yahudi berharap mengalahkan orang Yahudi, terjadilah yang sebaliknya: orang Yahudi mengalahkan pembenci-pembenci mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> The Jews gathered together in their cities throughout all the provinces of King Ahasuerus to lay hands on those who sought their harm. And no one could withstand them, because fear of them fell upon all people. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اجتمع اليهود في مدنهم في كل بلاد الملك احشويروش ليمدوا ايديهم الى طالبي اذيتهم فلم يقف احد قدامهم لان رعبهم سقط على جميع الشعوب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Maka berkumpullah orang Yahudi di dalam kota-kotanya di seluruh daerah raja Ahasyweros, untuk membunuh orang-orang yang berikhtiar mencelakakan mereka, dan tiada seorangpun tahan menghadapi mereka, karena ketakutan kepada orang Yahudi telah menimpa segala bangsa itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> And all the officials of the provinces, the satraps, the governors, and all those doing the king's work, helped the Jews, because the fear of Mordecai fell upon them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">وكل رؤساء البلدان والمرازبة والولاة وعمال الملك ساعدوا اليهود لان رعب مردخاي سقط عليهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Dan semua pembesar daerah dan wakil pemerintahan dan bupati serta pejabat kerajaan menyokong orang Yahudi, karena ketakutan kepada Mordekhai telah menimpa mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> For Mordecai [was] great in the king's palace, and his fame spread throughout all the provinces; for this man Mordecai became increasingly prominent. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">لان مردخاي كان عظيما في بيت الملك وسار خبره في كل البلدان لان الرجل مردخاي كان يتزايد عظمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Sebab Mordekhai besar kekuasaannya di dalam istana raja dan tersiarlah berita tentang dia ke segenap daerah, karena Mordekhai itu bertambah-tambah besar kekuasaannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Thus the Jews defeated all their enemies with the stroke of the sword, with slaughter and destruction, and did what they pleased with those who hated them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فضرب اليهود جميع اعدائهم ضربة سيف وقتل وهلاك وعملوا بمبغضيهم ما ارادوا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Maka orang Yahudi mengalahkan semua musuhnya: mereka memukulnya dengan pedang, membunuh dan membinasakannya; mereka berbuat sekehendak hatinya terhadap pembenci-pembenci mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> And in Shushan the citadel the Jews killed and destroyed five hundred men. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">وقتل اليهود في شوشن القصر واهلكوا خمس مئة رجل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Di dalam benteng Susan saja orang Yahudi membunuh dan membinasakan lima ratus orang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Also Parshandatha, Dalphon, Aspatha, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">وفرشنداثا ودلفون واسفاثا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Juga Parsandata, Dalfon, Aspata,</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Poratha, Adalia, Aridatha, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">وفوراثا وادليا واريداثا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Porata, Adalya, Aridata,</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Parmashta, Arisai, Aridai, and Vajezatha -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">وفرمشتا واريساي واريداي ويزاثا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Parmasta, Arisai, Aridai dan Waizata,</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> the ten sons of Haman the son of Hammedatha, the enemy of the Jews -- they killed; but they did not lay a hand on the plunder. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">عشرة بني هامان بن همداثا عدو اليهود قتلوهم ولكنهم لم يمدوا ايديهم الى النهب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">kesepuluh anak laki-laki Haman bin Hamedata, seteru orang Yahudi, dibunuh oleh mereka, tetapi kepada barang rampasan tidaklah mereka mengulurkan tangan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> On that day the number of those who were killed in Shushan the citadel was brought to the king. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">في ذلك اليوم أتي بعدد القتلى في شوشن القصر الى بين يدي الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Pada hari itu juga jumlah orang-orang yang terbunuh di dalam benteng Susan disampaikan ke hadapan raja.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> And the king said to Queen Esther, "The Jews have killed and destroyed five hundred men in Shushan the citadel, and the ten sons of Haman. What have they done in the rest of the king's provinces? Now what [is] your petition? It shall be granted to you. Or what [is] your further request? It shall be done." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فقال الملك لاستير الملكة في شوشن القصر قد قتل اليهود واهلكوا خمس مئة رجل وبني هامان العشرة فماذا عملوا في باقي بلدان الملك. فما هو سؤلك فيعطى لك وما هي طلبتك بعد فتقضى.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Lalu titah raja kepada Ester, sang ratu: "Di dalam benteng Susan saja orang Yahudi telah membunuh dan membinasakan lima ratus orang beserta kesepuluh anak Haman. Di daerah-daerah kerajaan yang lain, entahlah apa yang diperbuat mereka. Dan apakah permintaanmu sekarang? Niscaya akan dikabulkan. Dan apakah keinginanmu lagi? Niscaya dipenuhi."</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Then Esther said, "If it pleases the king, let it be granted to the Jews who [are] in Shushan to do again tomorrow according to today's decree, and let Haman's ten sons be hanged on the gallows." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فقالت استير ان حسن عند الملك فليعطى غدا ايضا لليهود الذين في شوشن ان يعملوا كما في هذا اليوم ويصلبوا بني هامان العشرة على الخشبة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Lalu jawab Ester: "Jikalau baik pada pemandangan raja, diizinkanlah kiranya kepada orang Yahudi yang di Susan untuk berbuat besokpun sesuai dengan undang-undang untuk hari ini, dan kesepuluh anak Haman itu hendaklah disulakan pada tiang."</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> So the king commanded this to be done; the decree was issued in Shushan, and they hanged Haman's ten sons. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فأمر الملك ان يعملوا هكذا واعطي الامر في شوشن. فصلبوا بني هامان العشرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Rajapun menitahkan berbuat demikian; maka undang-undang itu dikeluarkan di Susan dan kesepuluh anak Haman disulakan orang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> And the Jews who [were] in Shushan gathered together again on the fourteenth day of the month of Adar and killed three hundred men at Shushan; but they did not lay a hand on the plunder. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ثم اجتمع اليهود الذين في شوشن في اليوم الرابع عشر ايضا من شهر اذار وقتلوا في شوشن ثلاث مئة رجل ولكنهم لم يمدوا ايديهم الى النهب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Jadi berkumpullah orang Yahudi yang di Susan pada hari yang keempat belas bulan Adar juga dan dibunuhnyalah di Susan tiga ratus orang, tetapi kepada barang rampasan tidaklah mereka mengulurkan tangan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> The remainder of the Jews in the king's provinces gathered together and protected their lives, had rest from their enemies, and killed seventy-five thousand of their enemies; but they did not lay a hand on the plunder. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">وباقي اليهود الذين في بلدان الملك اجتمعوا ووقفوا لاجل انفسهم واستراحوا من اعدائهم وقتلوا من مبغضيهم خمسة وسبعين الفا. ولكنهم لم يمدوا ايديهم الى النهب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Orang Yahudi yang lain, yang ada di dalam daerah kerajaan, berkumpul dan mempertahankan nyawanya serta mendapat keamanan terhadap musuhnya; mereka membunuh tujuh puluh lima ribu orang di antara pembenci-pembenci mereka, tetapi kepada barang rampasan tidaklah mereka mengulurkan tangan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> [This was] on the thirteenth day of the month of Adar. And on the fourteenth day of [the month] they rested and made it a day of feasting and gladness. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">في اليوم الثالث عشر من شهر اذار. واستراحوا في اليوم الرابع عشر منه وجعلوه يوم شرب وفرح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Hal itu terjadi pada hari yang ketiga belas dalam bulan Adar. Pada hari yang keempat belas berhentilah mereka dan hari itu dijadikan mereka hari perjamuan dan sukacita.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> But the Jews who [were] at Shushan assembled together on the thirteenth [day,] as well as on the fourteenth; and on the fifteenth of [the month] they rested, and made it a day of feasting and gladness. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">واليهود الذين في شوشن اجتمعوا في الثالث عشر والرابع عشر منه واستراحوا في الخامس عشر وجعلوه يوم شرب وفرح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Akan tetapi orang Yahudi yang di Susan berkumpul, baik pada hari yang ketiga belas, baik pada hari yang keempat belas dalam bulan itu. Lalu berhentilah mereka pada hari yang kelima belas dan hari itu dijadikan mereka hari perjamuan dan sukacita.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> Therefore the Jews of the villages who dwelt in the unwalled towns celebrated the fourteenth day of the month of Adar [with] gladness and feasting, as a holiday, and for sending presents to one another. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">لذلك يهود الاعراء الساكنون في مدن الاعراء جعلوا اليوم الرابع عشر من شهر اذار للفرح والشرب ويوما طيبا ولارسال انصبة من كل واحد الى صاحبه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Oleh sebab itu orang Yahudi yang di pedusunan, yakni yang diam di perkampungan merayakan hari yang keempat belas bulan Adar itu sebagai hari sukacita dan hari perjamuan, dan sebagai hari gembira untuk antar-mengantar makanan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> And Mordecai wrote these things and sent letters to all the Jews, near and far, who [were] in all the provinces of King Ahasuerus, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">وكتب مردخاي هذه الأمور وارسل رسائل الى جميع اليهود الذين في كل بلدان الملك احشويروش القريبين والبعيدين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Maka Mordekhai menuliskan peristiwa itu, lalu mengirimkan surat-surat kepada semua orang Yahudi di seluruh daerah raja Ahasyweros, baik yang dekat baik yang jauh,</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> to establish among them that they should celebrate yearly the fourteenth and fifteenth days of the month of Adar, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">ليوجب عليهم ان يعيّدوا في اليوم الرابع عشر من شهر اذار واليوم الخامس عشر منه في كل سنة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">untuk mewajibkan mereka, supaya tiap-tiap tahun merayakan hari yang keempat belas dan yang kelima belas bulan Adar,</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> as the days on which the Jews had rest from their enemies, as the month which was turned from sorrow to joy for them, and from mourning to a holiday; that they should make them days of feasting and joy, of sending presents to one another and gifts to the poor. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">حسب الايام التي استراح فيها اليهود من اعدائهم والشهر الذي تحول عندهم من حزن الى فرح ومن نوح الى يوم طيب ليجعلوها ايام شرب وفرح وارسال انصبة من كل واحد الى صاحبه وعطايا للفقراء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">karena pada hari-hari itulah orang Yahudi mendapat keamanan terhadap musuhnya dan dalam bulan itulah dukacita mereka berubah menjadi sukacita dan hari perkabungan menjadi hari gembira, dan supaya menjadikan hari-hari itu hari perjamuan dan sukacita dan hari untuk antar-mengantar makanan dan untuk bersedekah kepada orang-orang miskin.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> So the Jews accepted the custom which they had begun, as Mordecai had written to them, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">فقبل اليهود ما ابتدأوا يعملونه وما كتبه مردخاي اليهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Maka orang Yahudi menerima sebagai ketetapan apa yang sudah dimulai mereka melakukannya dan apa yang ditulis Mordekhai kepada mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> because Haman, the son of Hammedatha the Agagite, the enemy of all the Jews, had plotted against the Jews to annihilate them, and had cast Pur (that [is,] the lot), to consume them and destroy them; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">ولان هامان بن همداثا الاجاجي عدو اليهود جميعا تفكر على اليهود ليبيدهم والقى فورا اي قرعة لافنائهم وابادتهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">Sesungguhnya Haman bin Hamedata, orang Agag, seteru semua orang Yahudi itu, telah merancangkan hendak membinasakan orang Yahudi dan diapun telah membuang pur--yakni undi--untuk menghancurkan dan membinasakan mereka,</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> but when [Esther] came before the king, he commanded by letter that this wicked plot which [Haman] had devised against the Jews should return on his own head, and that he and his sons should be hanged on the gallows. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">وعند دخولها الى امام الملك أمر بكتابة ان يرد تدبيره الرديء الذي دبّره ضد اليهود على راسه وان يصلبوه هو وبنيه على الخشبة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">akan tetapi ketika hal itu disampaikan ke hadapan raja, maka dititahkannyalah dengan surat, supaya rancangan jahat yang dibuat Haman terhadap orang Yahudi itu dibalikkan ke atas kepalanya. Maka Haman beserta anak-anaknya disulakan pada tiang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26"> So they called these days Purim, after the name Pur. Therefore, because of all the words of this letter, what they had seen concerning this matter, and what had happened to them, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">لذلك دعوا تلك الايام فوريم على اسم الفور. لذلك من اجل جميع كلمات هذه الرسالة وما راوه من ذلك وما اصابهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">Oleh sebab itulah hari-hari itu disebut Purim, menurut kata pur. Oleh sebab itu jugalah, yakni karena seluruh isi surat itu dan karena apa yang dilihat mereka mengenai hal itu dan apa yang dialami mereka,</language></verse>
			<verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27"> the Jews established and imposed it upon themselves and their descendants and all who would join them, that without fail they should celebrate these two days every year, according to the written [instructions] and according to the [prescribed] time, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">اوجب اليهود وقبلوا على انفسهم وعلى نسلهم وعلى جميع الذين يلتصقون بهم حتى لا يزول ان يعيّدوا هذين اليومين حسب كتابتهما وحسب اوقاتهما كل سنة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">orang Yahudi menerima sebagai kewajiban dan sebagai ketetapan bagi dirinya sendiri dan keturunannya dan bagi sekalian orang yang akan bergabung dengan mereka, bahwa mereka tidak akan melampaui merayakan kedua hari itu tiap-tiap tahun, menurut yang dituliskan tentang itu dan pada waktu yang ditentukan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="28"><language id="English" verse="28"> [that] these days [should be] remembered and kept throughout every generation, every family, every province, and every city, that these days of Purim should not fail [to be observed] among the Jews, and [that] the memory of them should not perish among their descendants. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="28">وان يذكر هذان اليومان ويحفظا في دور فدور وعشيرة فعشيرة وبلاد فبلاد ومدينة فمدينة ويوما الفور هذان لا يزولان من وسط اليهود وذكرهما لا يفني من نسلهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="28">dan bahwa hari-hari itu akan diperingati dan dirayakan di dalam tiap-tiap angkatan, di dalam tiap-tiap kaum, di tiap-tiap daerah, di tiap-tiap kota, sehingga hari-hari Purim itu tidak akan lenyap dari tengah-tengah orang Yahudi dan peringatannya tidak akan berakhir dari antara keturunan mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="29"><language id="English" verse="29"> Then Queen Esther, the daughter of Abihail, with Mordecai the Jew, wrote with full authority to confirm this second letter about Purim. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="29">وكتبت استير الملكة بنت ابيجائل ومردخاي اليهودي بكل سلطان بايجاب رسالة الفوريم هذه ثانية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="29">Lalu Ester, sang ratu, anak Abihail, menulis surat, bersama-sama dengan Mordekhai, orang Yahudi itu; surat yang kedua tentang hari raya Purim ini dituliskannya dengan segala ketegasan untuk menguatkannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="30"><language id="English" verse="30"> And [Mordecai] sent letters to all the Jews, to the one hundred and twenty-seven provinces of the kingdom of Ahasuerus, [with] words of peace and truth, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="30">وارسل الكتابات الى جميع اليهود الى كور مملكة احشويروش المئة والسبع والعشرين بكلام سلام وامانة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="30">Lalu dikirimkanlah surat-surat kepada semua orang Yahudi di dalam keseratus dua puluh tujuh daerah kerajaan Ahasyweros, dengan kata-kata salam dan setia,</language></verse>
			<verse num="31"><language id="English" verse="31"> to confirm these days of Purim at their [appointed] time, as Mordecai the Jew and Queen Esther had prescribed for them, and as they had decreed for themselves and their descendants concerning matters of their fasting and lamenting. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="31">لإيجاب يومي الفوريم هذين في اوقاتهما كما اوجب عليهم مردخاي اليهودي واستير الملكة وكما اوجبوا على انفسهم وعلى نسلهم امور الاصوام وصراخهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="31">supaya hari-hari Purim itu dirayakan pada waktu yang ditentukan, seperti yang diwajibkan kepada mereka oleh Mordekhai, orang Yahudi itu, dan oleh Ester, sang ratu, dan seperti yang diwajibkan mereka kepada dirinya sendiri serta keturunan mereka, mengenai hal berpuasa dan meratap-ratap.</language></verse>
			<verse num="32"><language id="English" verse="32"> So the decree of Esther confirmed these matters of Purim, and it was written in the book. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="32">وأمر استير اوجب امور الفوريم هذه فكتبت في السفر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="32">Demikianlah perintah Ester menetapkan perihal Purim itu, kemudian dituliskan di dalam kitab.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="10">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> And King Ahasuerus imposed tribute on the land and [on] the islands of the sea. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ووضع الملك احشويروش جزية على الارض وجزائر البحر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Maka raja Ahasyweros mengenakan upeti atas negeri dan daerah-daerah pesisir juga.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Now all the acts of his power and his might, and the account of the greatness of Mordecai, to which the king advanced him, [are] they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Media and Persia? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">وكل عمل سلطانه وجبروته واذاعة عظمة مردخاي الذي عظّمه الملك أما هي مكتوبة في سفر اخبار الايام لملوك مادي وفارس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Segala perbuatannya yang hebat serta gagah dan pemberitaan yang seksama tentang kebesaran yang dikaruniakan raja kepada Mordekhai, bukankah semuanya itu tertulis di dalam kitab sejarah raja-raja Media dan Persia?</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> For Mordecai the Jew [was] second to King Ahasuerus, and was great among the Jews and well received by the multitude of his brethren, seeking the good of his people and speaking peace to all his countrymen. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">لان مردخاي اليهودي كان ثاني الملك احشويروش وعظيما بين اليهود ومقبولا عند كثرة اخوته وطالبا الخير لشعبه ومتكلما بالسلام لكل نسله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Karena Mordekhai, orang Yahudi itu, menjadi orang kedua di bawah raja Ahasyweros, dan ia dihormati oleh orang Yahudi serta disukai oleh banyak sanak saudaranya, sebab ia mengikhtiarkan yang baik bagi bangsanya dan berbicara untuk keselamatan bagi semua orang sebangsanya.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>