<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Paul, an apostle (not from men nor through man, but through Jesus Christ and God the Father who raised Him from the dead), </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">بولس رسول لا من الناس ولا بانسان بل بيسوع المسيح والله الآب الذي اقامه من الاموات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Dari Paulus, seorang rasul, bukan karena manusia, juga bukan oleh seorang manusia, melainkan oleh Yesus Kristus dan Allah, Bapa, yang telah membangkitkan Dia dari antara orang mati,</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> and all the brethren who are with me, To the churches of Galatia: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">وجميع الاخوة الذين معي الى كنائس غلاطية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">dan dari semua saudara yang ada bersama-sama dengan aku, kepada jemaat-jemaat di Galatia:</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Grace to you and peace from God the Father and our Lord Jesus Christ, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">نعمة لكم وسلام من الله الآب ومن ربنا يسوع المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">kasih karunia menyertai kamu dan damai sejahtera dari Allah, Bapa kita, dan dari Tuhan Yesus Kristus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> who gave Himself for our sins, that He might deliver us from this present evil age, according to the will of our God and Father, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">الذي بذل نفسه لاجل خطايانا لينقذنا من العالم الحاضر الشرير حسب ارادة الله وابينا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">yang telah menyerahkan diri-Nya karena dosa-dosa kita, untuk melepaskan kita dari dunia jahat yang sekarang ini, menurut kehendak Allah dan Bapa kita.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> to whom [be] glory forever and ever. Amen. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">الذي له المجد الى ابد الآبدين. آمين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Bagi-Nyalah kemuliaan selama-lamanya! Amin.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> I marvel that you are turning away so soon from Him who called you in the grace of Christ, to a different gospel, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">اني اتعجب انكم تنتقلون هكذا سريعا عن الذي دعاكم بنعمة المسيح الى انجيل آخر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Aku heran, bahwa kamu begitu lekas berbalik dari pada Dia, yang oleh kasih karunia Kristus telah memanggil kamu, dan mengikuti suatu injil lain,</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> which is not another; but there are some who trouble you and want to pervert the gospel of Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">ليس هو آخر غير انه يوجد قوم يزعجونكم ويريدون ان يحوّلوا انجيل المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">yang sebenarnya bukan Injil. Hanya ada orang yang mengacaukan kamu dan yang bermaksud untuk memutarbalikkan Injil Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> But even if we, or an angel from heaven, preach any other gospel to you than what we have preached to you, let him be accursed. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ولكن ان بشرناكم نحن او ملاك من السماء بغير ما بشرناكم فليكن اناثيما.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Tetapi sekalipun kami atau seorang malaikat dari sorga yang memberitakan kepada kamu suatu injil yang berbeda dengan Injil yang telah kami beritakan kepadamu, terkutuklah dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> As we have said before, so now I say again, if anyone preaches any other gospel to you than what you have received, let him be accursed. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">كما سبقنا فقلنا اقول الآن ايضا ان كان احد يبشركم في غير ما قبلتم فليكن اناثيما.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Seperti yang telah kami katakan dahulu, sekarang kukatakan sekali lagi: jikalau ada orang yang memberitakan kepadamu suatu injil, yang berbeda dengan apa yang telah kamu terima, terkutuklah dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> For do I now persuade men, or God? Or do I seek to please men? For if I still pleased men, I would not be a bondservant of Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">أفاستعطف الآن الناس ام الله. ام اطلب ان ارضي الناس. فلو كنت بعد ارضي الناس لم اكن عبدا للمسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Jadi bagaimana sekarang: adakah kucari kesukaan manusia atau kesukaan Allah? Adakah kucoba berkenan kepada manusia? Sekiranya aku masih mau mencoba berkenan kepada manusia, maka aku bukanlah hamba Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> But I make known to you, brethren, that the gospel which was preached by me is not according to man. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">واعرّفكم ايها الاخوة الانجيل الذي بشرت به انه ليس بحسب انسان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Sebab aku menegaskan kepadamu, saudara-saudaraku, bahwa Injil yang kuberitakan itu bukanlah injil manusia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> For I neither received it from man, nor was I taught [it,] but [it came] through the revelation of Jesus Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">لاني لم اقبله من عند انسان ولا علّمته بل باعلان يسوع المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Karena aku bukan menerimanya dari manusia, dan bukan manusia yang mengajarkannya kepadaku, tetapi aku menerimanya oleh penyataan Yesus Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> For you have heard of my former conduct in Judaism, how I persecuted the church of God beyond measure and [tried to] destroy it. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فانكم سمعتم بسيرتي قبلا في الديانة اليهودية اني كنت اضطهد كنيسة الله بافراط واتلفها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Sebab kamu telah mendengar tentang hidupku dahulu dalam agama Yahudi: tanpa batas aku menganiaya jemaat Allah dan berusaha membinasakannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> And I advanced in Judaism beyond many of my contemporaries in my own nation, being more exceedingly zealous for the traditions of my fathers. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">وكنت اتقدم في الديانة اليهودية على كثيرين من اترابي في جنسي اذ كنت اوفر غيرة في تقليدات آبائي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Dan di dalam agama Yahudi aku jauh lebih maju dari banyak teman yang sebaya dengan aku di antara bangsaku, sebagai orang yang sangat rajin memelihara adat istiadat nenek moyangku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> But when it pleased God, who separated me from my mother's womb and called [me] through His grace, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ولكن لما سرّ الله الذي افرزني من بطن امي ودعاني بنعمته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Tetapi waktu Ia, yang telah memilih aku sejak kandungan ibuku dan memanggil aku oleh kasih karunia-Nya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> to reveal His Son in me, that I might preach Him among the Gentiles, I did not immediately confer with flesh and blood, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">ان يعلن ابنه فيّ لابشر به بين الامم للوقت لم استشر لحما ودما</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">berkenan menyatakan Anak-Nya di dalam aku, supaya aku memberitakan Dia di antara bangsa-bangsa bukan Yahudi, maka sesaatpun aku tidak minta pertimbangan kepada manusia;</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> nor did I go up to Jerusalem to those [who were] apostles before me; but I went to Arabia, and returned again to Damascus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ولا صعدت الى اورشليم الى الرسل الذين قبلي بل انطلقت الى العربية ثم رجعت ايضا الى دمشق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">juga aku tidak pergi ke Yerusalem mendapatkan mereka yang telah menjadi rasul sebelum aku, tetapi aku berangkat ke tanah Arab dan dari situ kembali lagi ke Damsyik.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> Then after three years I went up to Jerusalem to see Peter, and remained with him fifteen days. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">ثم بعد ثلاث سنين صعدت الى اورشليم لأتعرّف ببطرس فمكثت عنده خمسة عشر يوما.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Lalu, tiga tahun kemudian, aku pergi ke Yerusalem untuk mengunjungi Kefas, dan aku menumpang lima belas hari di rumahnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> But I saw none of the other apostles except James, the Lord's brother. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">ولكنني لم ار غيره من الرسل الا يعقوب اخا الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Tetapi aku tidak melihat seorangpun dari rasul-rasul yang lain, kecuali Yakobus, saudara Tuhan Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> (Now [concerning] the things which I write to you, indeed, before God, I do not lie.) </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">والذي اكتب به اليكم هوذا قدّام الله اني لست اكذب فيه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Di hadapan Allah kutegaskan: apa yang kutuliskan kepadamu ini benar, aku tidak berdusta.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> Afterward I went into the regions of Syria and Cilicia. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">وبعد ذلك جئت الى اقاليم سورية وكيليكية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Kemudian aku pergi ke daerah-daerah Siria dan Kilikia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> And I was unknown by face to the churches of Judea which [were] in Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">ولكنني كنت غير معروف بالوجه عند كنائس اليهودية التي في المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Tetapi rupaku tetap tidak dikenal oleh jemaat-jemaat Kristus di Yudea.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> But they were hearing only, "He who formerly persecuted us now preaches the faith which he once [tried to] destroy." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">غير انهم كانوا يسمعون ان الذي كان يضطهدنا قبلا يبشر الآن بالايمان الذي كان قبلا يتلفه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Mereka hanya mendengar, bahwa ia yang dahulu menganiaya mereka, sekarang memberitakan iman, yang pernah hendak dibinasakannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> And they glorified God in me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">فكانوا يمجدون الله فيّ</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">Dan mereka memuliakan Allah karena aku.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="2">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Then after fourteen years I went up again to Jerusalem with Barnabas, and also took Titus with [me.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ثم بعد اربع عشرة سنة صعدت ايضا الى اورشليم مع برنابا آخذا معي تيطس ايضا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Kemudian setelah lewat empat belas tahun, aku pergi pula ke Yerusalem dengan Barnabas dan Tituspun kubawa juga.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> And I went up by revelation, and communicated to them that gospel which I preach among the Gentiles, but privately to those who were of reputation, lest by any means I might run, or had run, in vain. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">وانما صعدت بموجب اعلان وعرضت عليهم الانجيل الذي اكرز به بين الامم ولكن بالانفراد على المعتبرين لئلا اكون اسعى او قد سعيت باطلا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Aku pergi berdasarkan suatu penyataan. Dan kepada mereka kubentangkan Injil yang kuberitakan di antara bangsa-bangsa bukan Yahudi--dalam percakapan tersendiri kepada mereka yang terpandang--,supaya jangan dengan percuma aku berusaha atau telah berusaha.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Yet not even Titus who [was] with me, being a Greek, was compelled to be circumcised. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">لكن لم يضطر ولا تيطس الذي كان معي وهو يوناني ان يختتن.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Tetapi kendatipun Titus, yang bersama-sama dengan aku, adalah seorang Yunani, namun ia tidak dipaksa untuk menyunatkan dirinya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> And [this occurred] because of false brethren secretly brought in (who came in by stealth to spy out our liberty which we have in Christ Jesus, that they might bring us into bondage), </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ولكن بسبب الاخوة الكذبة المدخلين خفية الذين دخلوا اختلاسا ليتجسسوا حريتنا التي لنا في المسيح كي يستعبدونا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Memang ada desakan dari saudara-saudara palsu yang menyusup masuk, yaitu mereka yang menyelundup ke dalam untuk menghadang kebebasan kita yang kita miliki di dalam Kristus Yesus, supaya dengan jalan itu mereka dapat memperhambakan kita.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> to whom we did not yield submission even for an hour, that the truth of the gospel might continue with you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">الذين لم نذعن لهم بالخضوع ولا ساعة ليبقى عندكم حق الانجيل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Tetapi sesaatpun kami tidak mau mundur dan tunduk kepada mereka, agar kebenaran Injil dapat tinggal tetap pada kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> But from those who seemed to be something -- whatever they were, it makes no difference to me; God shows personal favoritism to no man -- for those who seemed [to be something] added nothing to me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">واما المعتبرون انهم شيء مهما كانوا لا فرق عندي. الله لا يأخذ بوجه انسان. فان هؤلاء المعتبرين لم يشيروا عليّ بشيء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Dan mengenai mereka yang dianggap terpandang itu--bagaimana kedudukan mereka dahulu, itu tidak penting bagiku, sebab Allah tidak memandang muka--bagaimanapun juga, mereka yang terpandang itu tidak memaksakan sesuatu yang lain kepadaku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> But on the contrary, when they saw that the gospel for the uncircumcised had been committed to me, as [the gospel] for the circumcised [was] to Peter </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">بل بالعكس اذ رأوا اني اؤتمنت على انجيل الغرلة كما بطرس على انجيل الختان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Tetapi sebaliknya, setelah mereka melihat bahwa kepadaku telah dipercayakan pemberitaan Injil untuk orang-orang tak bersunat, sama seperti kepada Petrus untuk orang-orang bersunat</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> (for He who worked effectively in Peter for the apostleship to the circumcised also worked effectively in me toward the Gentiles), </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فان الذي عمل في بطرس لرسالة الختان عمل فيّ ايضا للامم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">--karena Ia yang telah memberikan kekuatan kepada Petrus untuk menjadi rasul bagi orang-orang bersunat, Ia juga yang telah memberikan kekuatan kepadaku untuk orang-orang yang tidak bersunat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> and when James, Cephas, and John, who seemed to be pillars, perceived the grace that had been given to me, they gave me and Barnabas the right hand of fellowship, that we [should go] to the Gentiles and they to the circumcised. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فاذ علم بالنعمة المعطاة لي يعقوب وصفا ويوحنا المعتبرون انهم اعمدة اعطوني وبرنابا يمين الشركة لنكون نحن للامم واما هم فللختان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Dan setelah melihat kasih karunia yang dianugerahkan kepadaku, maka Yakobus, Kefas dan Yohanes, yang dipandang sebagai sokoguru jemaat, berjabat tangan dengan aku dan dengan Barnabas sebagai tanda persekutuan, supaya kami pergi kepada orang-orang yang tidak bersunat dan mereka kepada orang-orang yang bersunat;</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> [They desired] only that we should remember the poor, the very thing which I also was eager to do. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">غير ان نذكر الفقراء. وهذا عينه كنت اعتنيت ان افعله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">hanya kami harus tetap mengingat orang-orang miskin dan memang itulah yang sungguh-sungguh kuusahakan melakukannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Now when Peter had come to Antioch, I withstood him to his face, because he was to be blamed; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ولكن لما أتى بطرس الى انطاكية قاومته مواجهة لانه كان ملوما.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Tetapi waktu Kefas datang ke Antiokhia, aku berterang-terang menentangnya, sebab ia salah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> for before certain men came from James, he would eat with the Gentiles; but when they came, he withdrew and separated himself, fearing those who were of the circumcision. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">لانه قبلما أتى قوم من عند يعقوب كان يأكل مع الامم ولكن لما أتوا كان يؤخر ويفرز نفسه خائفا من الذين هم من الختان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Karena sebelum beberapa orang dari kalangan Yakobus datang, ia makan sehidangan dengan saudara-saudara yang tidak bersunat, tetapi setelah mereka datang, ia mengundurkan diri dan menjauhi mereka karena takut akan saudara-saudara yang bersunat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> And the rest of the Jews also played the hypocrite with him, so that even Barnabas was carried away with their hypocrisy. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">وراءى معه باقي اليهود ايضا حتى ان برنابا ايضا انقاد الى ريائهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Dan orang-orang Yahudi yang lainpun turut berlaku munafik dengan dia, sehingga Barnabas sendiri turut terseret oleh kemunafikan mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> But when I saw that they were not straightforward about the truth of the gospel, I said to Peter before [them] all, "If you, being a Jew, live in the manner of Gentiles and not as the Jews, why do you compel Gentiles to live as Jews? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">لكن لما رأيت انهم لا يسلكون باستقامة حسب حق الانجيل قلت لبطرس قدام الجميع ان كنت وانت يهودي تعيش امميا لا يهوديا فلماذا تلزم الامم ان يتهوّدوا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Tetapi waktu kulihat, bahwa kelakuan mereka itu tidak sesuai dengan kebenaran Injil, aku berkata kepada Kefas di hadapan mereka semua: "Jika engkau, seorang Yahudi, hidup secara kafir dan bukan secara Yahudi, bagaimanakah engkau dapat memaksa saudara-saudara yang tidak bersunat untuk hidup secara Yahudi?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> "We [who are] Jews by nature, and not sinners of the Gentiles, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">نحن بالطبيعة يهود ولسنا من الامم خطاة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Menurut kelahiran kami adalah orang Yahudi dan bukan orang berdosa dari bangsa-bangsa lain.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> "knowing that a man is not justified by the works of the law but by faith in Jesus Christ, even we have believed in Christ Jesus, that we might be justified by faith in Christ and not by the works of the law; for by the works of the law no flesh shall be justified. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">اذ نعلم ان الانسان لا يتبرر باعمال الناموس بل بايمان يسوع المسيح آمنّا نحن ايضا بيسوع المسيح لنتبرر بايمان يسوع لا باعمال الناموس. لانه باعمال الناموس لا يتبرر جسد ما.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Kamu tahu, bahwa tidak seorangpun yang dibenarkan oleh karena melakukan hukum Taurat, tetapi hanya oleh karena iman dalam Kristus Yesus. Sebab itu kamipun telah percaya kepada Kristus Yesus, supaya kami dibenarkan oleh karena iman dalam Kristus dan bukan oleh karena melakukan hukum Taurat. Sebab: "tidak ada seorangpun yang dibenarkan" oleh karena melakukan hukum Taurat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> "But if, while we seek to be justified by Christ, we ourselves also are found sinners, [is] Christ therefore a minister of sin? Certainly not! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فان كنا ونحن طالبون ان نتبرر في المسيح نوجد نحن انفسنا ايضا خطاة أفالمسيح خادم للخطية. حاشا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Tetapi jika kami sendiri, sementara kami berusaha untuk dibenarkan dalam Kristus ternyata adalah orang-orang berdosa, apakah hal itu berarti, bahwa Kristus adalah pelayan dosa? Sekali-kali tidak.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> "For if I build again those things which I destroyed, I make myself a transgressor. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فاني ان كنت ابني ايضا هذا الذي قد هدمته فاني اظهر نفسي متعديا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Karena, jikalau aku membangun kembali apa yang telah kurombak, aku menyatakan diriku sebagai pelanggar hukum Taurat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> "For I through the law died to the law that I might live to God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">لاني مت بالناموس للناموس لاحيا للّه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Sebab aku telah mati oleh hukum Taurat untuk hukum Taurat, supaya aku hidup untuk Allah. Aku telah disalibkan dengan Kristus;</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> "I have been crucified with Christ; it is no longer I who live, but Christ lives in me; and the [life] which I now live in the flesh I live by faith in the Son of God, who loved me and gave Himself for me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">مع المسيح صلبت فاحيا لا انا بل المسيح يحيا فيّ. فما احياه الآن في الجسد فانما احياه في الايمان ايمان ابن الله الذي احبني واسلم نفسه لاجلي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">namun aku hidup, tetapi bukan lagi aku sendiri yang hidup, melainkan Kristus yang hidup di dalam aku. Dan hidupku yang kuhidupi sekarang di dalam daging, adalah hidup oleh iman dalam Anak Allah yang telah mengasihi aku dan menyerahkan diri-Nya untuk aku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> "I do not set aside the grace of God; for if righteousness [comes] through the law, then Christ died in vain." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">لست ابطل نعمة الله. لانه ان كان بالناموس بر فالمسيح اذا مات بلا سبب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Aku tidak menolak kasih karunia Allah. Sebab sekiranya ada kebenaran oleh hukum Taurat, maka sia-sialah kematian Kristus.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="3">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> O foolish Galatians! Who has bewitched you that you should not obey the truth, before whose eyes Jesus Christ was clearly portrayed among you as crucified? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ايها الغلاطيون الاغبياء من رقاكم حتى لا تذعنوا للحق انتم الذين امام عيونكم قد رسم يسوع المسيح بينكم مصلوبا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Hai orang-orang Galatia yang bodoh, siapakah yang telah mempesona kamu? Bukankah Yesus Kristus yang disalibkan itu telah dilukiskan dengan terang di depanmu?</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> This only I want to learn from you: Did you receive the Spirit by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اريد ان اتعلّم منكم هذا فقط أباعمال الناموس اخذتم الروح ام بخبر الايمان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Hanya ini yang hendak kuketahui dari pada kamu: Adakah kamu telah menerima Roh karena melakukan hukum Taurat atau karena percaya kepada pemberitaan Injil?</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Are you so foolish? Having begun in the Spirit, are you now being made perfect by the flesh? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">أهكذا انتم اغبياء. أبعد ما أبتدأتم بالروح تكملون الآن بالجسد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Adakah kamu sebodoh itu? Kamu telah mulai dengan Roh, maukah kamu sekarang mengakhirinya di dalam daging?</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Have you suffered so many things in vain -- if indeed [it was] in vain? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">أهذا المقدار احتملتم عبثا ان كان عبثا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Sia-siakah semua yang telah kamu alami sebanyak itu? Masakan sia-sia!</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Therefore He who supplies the Spirit to you and works miracles among you, [does He do it] by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith? -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فالذي يمنحكم الروح ويعمل قوات فيكم أباعمال الناموس ام بخبر الايمان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Jadi bagaimana sekarang, apakah Ia yang menganugerahkan Roh kepada kamu dengan berlimpah-limpah dan yang melakukan mujizat di antara kamu, berbuat demikian karena kamu melakukan hukum Taurat atau karena kamu percaya kepada pemberitaan Injil?</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> just as Abraham "believed God, and it was accounted to him for righteousness." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">كما آمن ابراهيم بالله فحسب له برا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Secara itu jugalah Abraham percaya kepada Allah, maka Allah memperhitungkan hal itu kepadanya sebagai kebenaran.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Therefore know that [only] those who are of faith are sons of Abraham. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">اعلموا اذا ان الذين هم من الايمان اولئك هم بنو ابراهيم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Jadi kamu lihat, bahwa mereka yang hidup dari iman, mereka itulah anak-anak Abraham.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> And the Scripture, foreseeing that God would justify the Gentiles by faith, preached the gospel to Abraham beforehand, [saying,] "In you all the nations shall be blessed." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">والكتاب اذ سبق فرأى ان الله بالايمان يبرر الامم سبق فبشر ابراهيم ان فيك تتبارك جميع الامم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Dan Kitab Suci, yang sebelumnya mengetahui, bahwa Allah membenarkan orang-orang bukan Yahudi oleh karena iman, telah terlebih dahulu memberitakan Injil kepada Abraham: "Olehmu segala bangsa akan diberkati."</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> So then those who [are] of faith are blessed with believing Abraham. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">اذا الذين هم من الايمان يتباركون مع ابراهيم المؤمن.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Jadi mereka yang hidup dari iman, merekalah yang diberkati bersama-sama dengan Abraham yang beriman itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> For as many as are of the works of the law are under the curse; for it is written, "Cursed [is] everyone who does not continue in all things which are written in the book of the law, to do them." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لان جميع الذين هم من اعمال الناموس هم تحت لعنة لانه مكتوب ملعون كل من لا يثبت في جميع ما هو مكتوب في كتاب الناموس ليعمل به.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Karena semua orang, yang hidup dari pekerjaan hukum Taurat, berada di bawah kutuk. Sebab ada tertulis: "Terkutuklah orang yang tidak setia melakukan segala sesuatu yang tertulis dalam kitab hukum Taurat."</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> But that no one is justified by the law in the sight of God [is] evident, for "the just shall live by faith." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ولكن ان ليس احد يتبرر بالناموس عند الله فظاهر لان البار بالايمان يحيا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Dan bahwa tidak ada orang yang dibenarkan di hadapan Allah karena melakukan hukum Taurat adalah jelas, karena: "Orang yang benar akan hidup oleh iman."</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Yet the law is not of faith, but "the man who does them shall live by them." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ولكن الناموس ليس من الايمان بل الانسان الذي يفعلها سيحيا بها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Tetapi dasar hukum Taurat bukanlah iman, melainkan siapa yang melakukannya, akan hidup karenanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Christ has redeemed us from the curse of the law, having become a curse for us (for it is written, "Cursed [is] everyone who hangs on a tree"), </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">المسيح افتدانا من لعنة الناموس اذ صار لعنة لاجلنا لانه مكتوب ملعون كل من علّق على خشبة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Kristus telah menebus kita dari kutuk hukum Taurat dengan jalan menjadi kutuk karena kita, sebab ada tertulis: "Terkutuklah orang yang digantung pada kayu salib!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> that the blessing of Abraham might come upon the Gentiles in Christ Jesus, that we might receive the promise of the Spirit through faith. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">لتصير بركة ابراهيم للامم في المسيح يسوع لننال بالايمان موعد الروح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Yesus Kristus telah membuat ini, supaya di dalam Dia berkat Abraham sampai kepada bangsa-bangsa lain, sehingga oleh iman kita menerima Roh yang telah dijanjikan itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Brethren, I speak in the manner of men: Though [it is] only a man's covenant, yet [if it is] confirmed, no one annuls or adds to it. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ايها الاخوة بحسب الانسان اقول ليس احد يبطّل عهدا قد تمكن ولو من انسان او يزيد عليه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Saudara-saudara, baiklah kupergunakan suatu contoh dari hidup sehari-hari. Suatu wasiat yang telah disahkan, sekalipun ia dari manusia, tidak dapat dibatalkan atau ditambahi oleh seorangpun.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> Now to Abraham and his Seed were the promises made. He does not say, "And to seeds," as of many, but as of one, "And to your Seed," who is Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">واما المواعيد فقيلت في ابراهيم وفي نسله. لا يقول وفي الانسال كانه عن كثيرين بل كانه عن واحد وفي نسلك الذي هو المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Adapun kepada Abraham diucapkan segala janji itu dan kepada keturunannya. Tidak dikatakan "kepada keturunan-keturunannya" seolah-olah dimaksud banyak orang, tetapi hanya satu orang: "dan kepada keturunanmu", yaitu Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> And this I say, [that] the law, which was four hundred and thirty years later, cannot annul the covenant that was confirmed before by God in Christ, that it should make the promise of no effect. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">وانما اقول هذا ان الناموس الذي صار بعد اربع مئة وثلاثين سنة لا ينسخ عهدا قد سبق فتمكن من الله نحو المسيح حتى يبطّل الموعد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Maksudku ialah: Janji yang sebelumnya telah disahkan Allah, tidak dapat dibatalkan oleh hukum Taurat, yang baru terbit empat ratus tiga puluh tahun kemudian, sehingga janji itu hilang kekuatannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> For if the inheritance [is] of the law, [it is] no longer of promise; but God gave [it] to Abraham by promise. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">لانه ان كانت الوراثة من الناموس فلم تكن ايضا من موعد. ولكن الله وهبها لابراهيم بموعد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Sebab, jikalau apa yang ditentukan Allah berasal dari hukum Taurat, ia tidak berasal dari janji; tetapi justru oleh janjilah Allah telah menganugerahkan kasih karunia-Nya kepada Abraham.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> What purpose then [does] the law [serve?] It was added because of transgressions, till the Seed should come to whom the promise was made; [and it was] appointed through angels by the hand of a mediator. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">فلماذا الناموس. قد زيد بسبب التعديات الى ان يأتي النسل الذي قد وعد له مرتبا بملائكة في يد وسيط.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Kalau demikian, apakah maksudnya hukum Taurat? Ia ditambahkan oleh karena pelanggaran-pelanggaran--sampai datang keturunan yang dimaksud oleh janji itu--dan ia disampaikan dengan perantaraan malaikat-malaikat ke dalam tangan seorang pengantara.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> Now a mediator does not [mediate] for one [only,] but God is one. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">واما الوسيط فلا يكون لواحد. ولكن الله واحد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Seorang pengantara bukan hanya mewakili satu orang saja, sedangkan Allah adalah satu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> [Is] the law then against the promises of God? Certainly not! For if there had been a law given which could have given life, truly righteousness would have been by the law. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">فهل الناموس ضد مواعيد الله. حاشا. لانه لو أعطي ناموس قادر ان يحيي لكان بالحقيقة البر بالناموس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Kalau demikian, bertentangankah hukum Taurat dengan janji-janji Allah? Sekali-kali tidak. Sebab andaikata hukum Taurat diberikan sebagai sesuatu yang dapat menghidupkan, maka memang kebenaran berasal dari hukum Taurat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> But the Scripture has confined all under sin, that the promise by faith in Jesus Christ might be given to those who believe. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">لكن الكتاب اغلق على الكل تحت الخطية ليعطى الموعد من ايمان يسوع المسيح للذين يؤمنون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Tetapi Kitab Suci telah mengurung segala sesuatu di bawah kekuasaan dosa, supaya oleh karena iman dalam Yesus Kristus janji itu diberikan kepada mereka yang percaya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> But before faith came, we were kept under guard by the law, kept for the faith which would afterward be revealed. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">ولكن قبلما جاء الايمان كنا محروسين تحت الناموس مغلقا علينا الى الايمان العتيد ان يعلن.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Sebelum iman itu datang kita berada di bawah pengawalan hukum Taurat, dan dikurung sampai iman itu telah dinyatakan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> Therefore the law was our tutor [to bring us] to Christ, that we might be justified by faith. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">اذا قد كان الناموس مؤدبنا الى المسيح لكي نتبرر بالايمان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">Jadi hukum Taurat adalah penuntun bagi kita sampai Kristus datang, supaya kita dibenarkan karena iman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> But after faith has come, we are no longer under a tutor. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">ولكن بعد ما جاء الايمان لسنا بعد تحت مؤدب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Sekarang iman itu telah datang, karena itu kita tidak berada lagi di bawah pengawasan penuntun.</language></verse>
			<verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26"> For you are all sons of God through faith in Christ Jesus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">لانكم جميعا ابناء الله بالايمان بالمسيح يسوع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">Sebab kamu semua adalah anak-anak Allah karena iman di dalam Yesus Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27"> For as many of you as were baptized into Christ have put on Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">لان كلكم الذين اعتمدتم بالمسيح قد لبستم المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">Karena kamu semua, yang dibaptis dalam Kristus, telah mengenakan Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="28"><language id="English" verse="28"> There is neither Jew nor Greek, there is neither slave nor free, there is neither male nor female; for you are all one in Christ Jesus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="28">ليس يهودي ولا يوناني. ليس عبد ولا حر. ليس ذكر وانثى لانكم جميعا واحد في المسيح يسوع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="28">Dalam hal ini tidak ada orang Yahudi atau orang Yunani, tidak ada hamba atau orang merdeka, tidak ada laki-laki atau perempuan, karena kamu semua adalah satu di dalam Kristus Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="29"><language id="English" verse="29"> And if you [are] Christ's, then you are Abraham's seed, and heirs according to the promise. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="29">فان كنتم للمسيح فانتم اذا نسل ابراهيم وحسب الموعد ورثة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="29">Dan jikalau kamu adalah milik Kristus, maka kamu juga adalah keturunan Abraham dan berhak menerima janji Allah.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="4">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Now I say [that] the heir, as long as he is a child, does not differ at all from a slave, though he is master of all, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وانما اقول ما دام الوارث قاصرا لا يفرق شيئا عن العبد مع كونه صاحب الجميع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Yang dimaksud ialah: selama seorang ahli waris belum akil balig, sedikitpun ia tidak berbeda dengan seorang hamba, sungguhpun ia adalah tuan dari segala sesuatu;</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> but is under guardians and stewards until the time appointed by the father. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">بل هو تحت اوصياء ووكلاء الى الوقت المؤجل من ابيه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">tetapi ia berada di bawah perwalian dan pengawasan sampai pada saat yang telah ditentukan oleh bapanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Even so we, when we were children, were in bondage under the elements of the world. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">هكذا نحن ايضا لما كنا قاصرين كنا مستعبدين تحت اركان العالم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Demikian pula kita: selama kita belum akil balig, kita takluk juga kepada roh-roh dunia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> But when the fullness of the time had come, God sent forth His Son, born of a woman, born under the law, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ولكن لما جاء ملء الزمان ارسل الله ابنه مولودا من امرأة مولودا تحت الناموس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Tetapi setelah genap waktunya, maka Allah mengutus Anak-Nya, yang lahir dari seorang perempuan dan takluk kepada hukum Taurat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> to redeem those who were under the law, that we might receive the adoption as sons. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">ليفتدي الذين تحت الناموس لننال التبني.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Ia diutus untuk menebus mereka, yang takluk kepada hukum Taurat, supaya kita diterima menjadi anak.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> And because you are sons, God has sent forth the Spirit of His Son into your hearts, crying out, "Abba, Father!" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ثم بما انكم ابناء ارسل الله روح ابنه الى قلوبكم صارخا يا ابا الآب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Dan karena kamu adalah anak, maka Allah telah menyuruh Roh Anak-Nya ke dalam hati kita, yang berseru: "ya Abba, ya Bapa!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Therefore you are no longer a slave but a son, and if a son, then an heir of God through Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">اذا لست بعد عبدا بل ابنا وان كنت ابنا فوارث للّه بالمسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Jadi kamu bukan lagi hamba, melainkan anak; jikalau kamu anak, maka kamu juga adalah ahli-ahli waris, oleh Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> But then, indeed, when you did not know God, you served those which by nature are not gods. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لكن حينئذ اذ كنتم لا تعرفون الله استعبدتم للذين ليسوا بالطبيعة آلهة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Dahulu, ketika kamu tidak mengenal Allah, kamu memperhambakan diri kepada allah-allah yang pada hakekatnya bukan Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> But now after you have known God, or rather are known by God, how [is it that] you turn again to the weak and beggarly elements, to which you desire again to be in bondage? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">واما الآن اذ عرفتم الله بل بالحري عرفتم من الله فكيف ترجعون ايضا الى الاركان الضعيفة الفقيرة التي تريدون ان تستعبدوا لها من جديد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Tetapi sekarang sesudah kamu mengenal Allah, atau lebih baik, sesudah kamu dikenal Allah, bagaimanakah kamu berbalik lagi kepada roh-roh dunia yang lemah dan miskin dan mau mulai memperhambakan diri lagi kepadanya?</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> You observe days and months and seasons and years. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">أتحفظون اياما وشهورا واوقاتا وسنين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Kamu dengan teliti memelihara hari-hari tertentu, bulan-bulan, masa-masa yang tetap dan tahun-tahun.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> I am afraid for you, lest I have labored for you in vain. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">اخاف عليكم ان اكون قد تعبت فيكم عبثا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Aku kuatir kalau-kalau susah payahku untuk kamu telah sia-sia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Brethren, I urge you to become like me, for I [became] like you. You have not injured me at all. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">اتضرع اليكم ايها الاخوة كونوا كما انا لاني انا ايضا كما انتم لم تظلموني شيئا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Aku minta kepadamu, saudara-saudara, jadilah sama seperti aku, sebab akupun telah menjadi sama seperti kamu. Belum pernah kualami sesuatu yang tidak baik dari padamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> You know that because of physical infirmity I preached the gospel to you at the first. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ولكنكم تعلمون اني بضعف الجسد بشرتكم في الاول.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Kamu tahu, bahwa aku pertama kali telah memberitakan Injil kepadamu oleh karena aku sakit pada tubuhku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> And my trial which was in my flesh you did not despise or reject, but you received me as an angel of God, [even] as Christ Jesus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">وتجربتي التي في جسدي لم تزدروا بها ولا كرهتموها بل كملاك من الله قبلتموني كالمسيح يسوع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Sungguhpun demikian keadaan tubuhku itu, yang merupakan pencobaan bagi kamu, namun kamu tidak menganggapnya sebagai sesuatu yang hina dan yang menjijikkan, tetapi kamu telah menyambut aku, sama seperti menyambut seorang malaikat Allah, malahan sama seperti menyambut Kristus Yesus sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> What then was the blessing you [enjoyed?] For I bear you witness that, if possible, you would have plucked out your own eyes and given them to me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فماذا كان اذا تطويبكم. لاني اشهد لكم انه لو امكن لقلعتم عيونكم واعطيتموني.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Betapa bahagianya kamu pada waktu itu! Dan sekarang, di manakah bahagiamu itu? Karena aku dapat bersaksi tentang kamu, bahwa jika mungkin, kamu telah mencungkil matamu dan memberikannya kepadaku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> Have I therefore become your enemy because I tell you the truth? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">أفقد صرت اذا عدوا لكم لاني اصدق لكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Apakah dengan mengatakan kebenaran kepadamu aku telah menjadi musuhmu?</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> They zealously court you, [but] for no good; yes, they want to exclude you, that you may be zealous for them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">يغارون لكم ليس حسنا بل يريدون ان يصدوكم لكي تغاروا لهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Mereka dengan giat berusaha untuk menarik kamu, tetapi tidak dengan tulus hati, karena mereka mau mengucilkan kamu, supaya kamu dengan giat mengikuti mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> But it is good to be zealous in a good thing always, and not only when I am present with you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">حسنة هي الغيرة في الحسنى كل حين وليس حين حضوري عندكم فقط.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Memang baik kalau orang dengan giat berusaha menarik orang lain dalam perkara-perkara yang baik, asal pada setiap waktu dan bukan hanya bila aku ada di antaramu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> My little children, for whom I labor in birth again until Christ is formed in you, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">يا اولادي الذين اتمخض بكم ايضا الى ان يتصور المسيح فيكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Hai anak-anakku, karena kamu aku menderita sakit bersalin lagi, sampai rupa Kristus menjadi nyata di dalam kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> I would like to be present with you now and to change my tone; for I have doubts about you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">ولكني كنت اريد ان اكون حاضرا عندكم الآن واغيّر صوتي لاني متحيّر فيكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Betapa rinduku untuk berada di antara kamu pada saat ini dan dapat berbicara dengan suara yang lain, karena aku telah habis akal menghadapi kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> Tell me, you who desire to be under the law, do you not hear the law? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">قولوا لي انتم الذين تريدون ان تكونوا تحت الناموس ألستم تسمعون الناموس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Katakanlah kepadaku, hai kamu yang mau hidup di bawah hukum Taurat, tidakkah kamu mendengarkan hukum Taurat?</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> For it is written that Abraham had two sons: the one by a bondwoman, the other by a freewoman. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">فانه مكتوب انه كان لابراهيم ابنان واحد من الجارية والآخر من الحرة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Bukankah ada tertulis, bahwa Abraham mempunyai dua anak, seorang dari perempuan yang menjadi hambanya dan seorang dari perempuan yang merdeka?</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> But he [who was] of the bondwoman was born according to the flesh, and he of the freewoman through promise, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">لكن الذي من الجارية ولد حسب الجسد واما الذي من الحرة فبالموعد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Tetapi anak dari perempuan yang menjadi hambanya itu diperanakkan menurut daging dan anak dari perempuan yang merdeka itu oleh karena janji.</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> which things are symbolic. For these are the two covenants: the one from Mount Sinai which gives birth to bondage, which is Hagar -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">وكل ذلك رمز لان هاتين هما العهدان احداهما من جبل سيناء الوالد للعبودية الذي هو هاجر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">Ini adalah suatu kiasan. Sebab kedua perempuan itu adalah dua ketentuan Allah: yang satu berasal dari gunung Sinai dan melahirkan anak-anak perhambaan, itulah Hagar--</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> for this Hagar is Mount Sinai in Arabia, and corresponds to Jerusalem which now is, and is in bondage with her children -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">لان هاجر جبل سيناء في العربية. ولكنه يقابل اورشليم الحاضرة فانها مستعبدة مع بنيها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Hagar ialah gunung Sinai di tanah Arab--dan ia sama dengan Yerusalem yang sekarang, karena ia hidup dalam perhambaan dengan anak-anaknya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26"> but the Jerusalem above is free, which is the mother of us all. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">واما اورشليم العليا التي هي امنا جميعا فهي حرة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">Tetapi Yerusalem sorgawi adalah perempuan yang merdeka, dan ialah ibu kita.</language></verse>
			<verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27"> For it is written: "Rejoice, O barren, [You] who do not bear! Break forth and shout, You who are not in labor! For the desolate has many more children Than she who has a husband." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">لانه مكتوب افرحي ايتها العاقر التي لم تلد. اهتفي واصرخي ايتها التي لم تتمخض فان اولاد الموحشة اكثر من التي لها زوج.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">Karena ada tertulis: "Bersukacitalah, hai si mandul yang tidak pernah melahirkan! Bergembira dan bersorak-sorailah, hai engkau yang tidak pernah menderita sakit bersalin! Sebab yang ditinggalkan suaminya akan mempunyai lebih banyak anak dari pada yang bersuami."</language></verse>
			<verse num="28"><language id="English" verse="28"> Now we, brethren, as Isaac [was,] are children of promise. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="28">واما نحن ايها الاخوة فنظير اسحق اولاد الموعد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="28">Dan kamu, saudara-saudara, kamu sama seperti Ishak adalah anak-anak janji.</language></verse>
			<verse num="29"><language id="English" verse="29"> But, as he who was born according to the flesh then persecuted him [who was born] according to the Spirit, even so [it is] now. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="29">ولكن كما كان حينئذ الذي ولد حسب الجسد يضطهد الذي حسب الروح هكذا الآن ايضا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="29">Tetapi seperti dahulu, dia, yang diperanakkan menurut daging, menganiaya yang diperanakkan menurut Roh, demikian juga sekarang ini.</language></verse>
			<verse num="30"><language id="English" verse="30"> Nevertheless what does the Scripture say? "Cast out the bondwoman and her son, for the son of the bondwoman shall not be heir with the son of the freewoman." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="30">لكن ماذا يقول الكتاب. اطرد الجارية وابنها لانه لا يرث ابن الجارية مع ابن الحرة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="30">Tetapi apa kata nas Kitab Suci? "Usirlah hamba perempuan itu beserta anaknya, sebab anak hamba perempuan itu tidak akan menjadi ahli waris bersama-sama dengan anak perempuan merdeka itu."</language></verse>
			<verse num="31"><language id="English" verse="31"> So then, brethren, we are not children of the bondwoman but of the free. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="31">اذا ايها الاخوة لسنا اولاد جارية بل اولاد الحرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="31">Karena itu, saudara-saudara, kita bukanlah anak-anak hamba perempuan, melainkan anak-anak perempuan merdeka.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="5">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Stand fast therefore in the liberty by which Christ has made us free, and do not be entangled again with a yoke of bondage. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">فاثبتوا اذا في الحرية التي قد حررنا المسيح بها ولا ترتبكوا ايضا بنير عبودية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Supaya kita sungguh-sungguh merdeka, Kristus telah memerdekakan kita. Karena itu berdirilah teguh dan jangan mau lagi dikenakan kuk perhambaan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Indeed I, Paul, say to you that if you become circumcised, Christ will profit you nothing. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">ها انا بولس اقول لكم انه ان اختتنتم لا ينفعكم المسيح شيئا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Sesungguhnya, aku, Paulus, berkata kepadamu: jikalau kamu menyunatkan dirimu, Kristus sama sekali tidak akan berguna bagimu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> And I testify again to every man who becomes circumcised that he is a debtor to keep the whole law. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">لكن اشهد ايضا لكل انسان مختتن انه ملتزم ان يعمل بكل الناموس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Sekali lagi aku katakan kepada setiap orang yang menyunatkan dirinya, bahwa ia wajib melakukan seluruh hukum Taurat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> You have become estranged from Christ, you who [attempt to] be justified by law; you have fallen from grace. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">قد تبطلتم عن المسيح ايها الذين تتبررون بالناموس. سقطتم من النعمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Kamu lepas dari Kristus, jikalau kamu mengharapkan kebenaran oleh hukum Taurat; kamu hidup di luar kasih karunia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> For we through the Spirit eagerly wait for the hope of righteousness by faith. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فاننا بالروح من الايمان نتوقع رجاء بر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Sebab oleh Roh, dan karena iman, kita menantikan kebenaran yang kita harapkan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> For in Christ Jesus neither circumcision nor uncircumcision avails anything, but faith working through love. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لانه في المسيح يسوع لا الختان ينفع شيئا ولا الغرلة بل الايمان العامل بالمحبة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Sebab bagi orang-orang yang ada di dalam Kristus Yesus hal bersunat atau tidak bersunat tidak mempunyai sesuatu arti, hanya iman yang bekerja oleh kasih.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> You ran well. Who hindered you from obeying the truth? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">كنتم تسعون حسنا. فمن صدكم حتى لا تطاوعوا للحق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Dahulu kamu berlomba dengan baik. Siapakah yang menghalang-halangi kamu, sehingga kamu tidak menuruti kebenaran lagi?</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> This persuasion does not [come] from Him who calls you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">هذه المطاوعة ليست من الذي دعاكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Ajakan untuk tidak menurutinya lagi bukan datang dari Dia, yang memanggil kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> A little leaven leavens the whole lump. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">خميرة صغيرة تخمّر العجين كله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Sedikit ragi sudah mengkhamirkan seluruh adonan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> I have confidence in you, in the Lord, that you will have no other mind; but he who troubles you shall bear his judgment, whoever he is. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">ولكنني اثق بكم في الرب انكم لا تفتكرون شيئا آخر. ولكن الذي يزعجكم سيحمل الدينونة ايّ من كان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Dalam Tuhan aku yakin tentang kamu, bahwa kamu tidak mempunyai pendirian lain dari pada pendirian ini. Tetapi barangsiapa yang mengacaukan kamu, ia akan menanggung hukumannya, siapapun juga dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> And I, brethren, if I still preach circumcision, why do I still suffer persecution? Then the offense of the cross has ceased. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">واما انا ايها الاخوة فان كنت بعد اكرز بالختان فلماذا أضطهد بعد. اذا عثرة الصليب قد بطلت.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Dan lagi aku ini, saudara-saudara, jikalau aku masih memberitakan sunat, mengapakah aku masih dianiaya juga? Sebab kalau demikian, salib bukan batu sandungan lagi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> I could wish that those who trouble you would even cut themselves off! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">يا ليت الذين يقلقونكم يقطعون ايضا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Baiklah mereka yang menghasut kamu itu mengebirikan saja dirinya!</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> For you, brethren, have been called to liberty; only do not [use] liberty as an opportunity for the flesh, but through love serve one another. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فانكم انما دعيتم للحرية ايها الاخوة. غير انه لا تصيّروا الحرية فرصة للجسد بل بالمحبة اخدموا بعضكم بعضا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Saudara-saudara, memang kamu telah dipanggil untuk merdeka. Tetapi janganlah kamu mempergunakan kemerdekaan itu sebagai kesempatan untuk kehidupan dalam dosa, melainkan layanilah seorang akan yang lain oleh kasih.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> For all the law is fulfilled in one word, [even] in this: "You shall love your neighbor as yourself." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">لان كل الناموس في كلمة واحده يكمل. تحب قريبك كنفسك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Sebab seluruh hukum Taurat tercakup dalam satu firman ini, yaitu: "Kasihilah sesamamu manusia seperti dirimu sendiri!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> But if you bite and devour one another, beware lest you be consumed by one another! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فاذا كنتم تنهشون وتأكلون بعضكم بعضا فانظروا لئلا تفنوا بعضكم بعضا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Tetapi jikalau kamu saling menggigit dan saling menelan, awaslah, supaya jangan kamu saling membinasakan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> I say then: Walk in the Spirit, and you shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">وانما اقول اسلكوا بالروح فلا تكملوا شهوة الجسد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Maksudku ialah: hiduplah oleh Roh, maka kamu tidak akan menuruti keinginan daging.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> For the flesh lusts against the Spirit, and the Spirit against the flesh; and these are contrary to one another, so that you do not do the things that you wish. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">لان الجسد يشتهي ضد الروح والروح ضد الجسد. وهذان يقاوم احدهما الآخر حتى تفعلون ما لا تريدون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Sebab keinginan daging berlawanan dengan keinginan Roh dan keinginan Roh berlawanan dengan keinginan daging--karena keduanya bertentangan--sehingga kamu setiap kali tidak melakukan apa yang kamu kehendaki.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> But if you are led by the Spirit, you are not under the law. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">ولكن اذا انقدتم بالروح فلستم تحت الناموس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Akan tetapi jikalau kamu memberi dirimu dipimpin oleh Roh, maka kamu tidak hidup di bawah hukum Taurat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> Now the works of the flesh are evident, which are: adultery, fornication, uncleanness, lewdness, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">واعمال الجسد ظاهرة التي هي زنى عهارة نجاسة دعارة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Perbuatan daging telah nyata, yaitu: percabulan, kecemaran, hawa nafsu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> idolatry, sorcery, hatred, contentions, jealousies, outbursts of wrath, selfish ambitions, dissensions, heresies, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">عبادة الاوثان سحر عداوة خصام غيرة سخط تحزب شقاق بدعة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">penyembahan berhala, sihir, perseteruan, perselisihan, iri hati, amarah, kepentingan diri sendiri, percideraan, roh pemecah,</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> envy, murders, drunkenness, revelries, and the like; of which I tell you beforehand, just as I also told [you] in time past, that those who practice such things will not inherit the kingdom of God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">حسد قتل سكر بطر وامثال هذه التي اسبق فاقول لكم عنها كما سبقت فقلت ايضا ان الذين يفعلون مثل هذه لا يرثون ملكوت الله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">kedengkian, kemabukan, pesta pora dan sebagainya. Terhadap semuanya itu kuperingatkan kamu--seperti yang telah kubuat dahulu--bahwa barangsiapa melakukan hal-hal yang demikian, ia tidak akan mendapat bagian dalam Kerajaan Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, longsuffering, kindness, goodness, faithfulness, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">واما ثمر الروح فهو محبة فرح سلام طول اناة لطف صلاح ايمان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Tetapi buah Roh ialah: kasih, sukacita, damai sejahtera, kesabaran, kemurahan, kebaikan, kesetiaan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> gentleness, self-control. Against such there is no law. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">وداعة تعفف. ضد امثال هذه ليس ناموس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">kelemahlembutan, penguasaan diri. Tidak ada hukum yang menentang hal-hal itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> And those [who are] Christ's have crucified the flesh with its passions and desires. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">ولكن الذين هم للمسيح قد صلبوا الجسد مع الاهواء والشهوات.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">Barangsiapa menjadi milik Kristus Yesus, ia telah menyalibkan daging dengan segala hawa nafsu dan keinginannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> If we live in the Spirit, let us also walk in the Spirit. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">ان كنا نعيش بالروح فلنسلك ايضا بحسب الروح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Jikalau kita hidup oleh Roh, baiklah hidup kita juga dipimpin oleh Roh,</language></verse>
			<verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26"> Let us not become conceited, provoking one another, envying one another. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">لا نكن معجبين نغاضب بعضنا بعضا ونحسد بعضنا بعضا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">dan janganlah kita gila hormat, janganlah kita saling menantang dan saling mendengki.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="6">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Brethren, if a man is overtaken in any trespass, you who [are] spiritual restore such a one in a spirit of gentleness, considering yourself lest you also be tempted. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ايها الاخوة ان انسبق انسان فأخذ في زلة ما فاصلحوا انتم الروحانيين مثل هذا بروح الوداعة ناظرا الى نفسك لئلا تجرب انت ايضا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Saudara-saudara, kalaupun seorang kedapatan melakukan suatu pelanggaran, maka kamu yang rohani, harus memimpin orang itu ke jalan yang benar dalam roh lemah lembut, sambil menjaga dirimu sendiri, supaya kamu juga jangan kena pencobaan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Bear one another's burdens, and so fulfill the law of Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">احملوا بعضكم اثقال بعض وهكذا تمموا ناموس المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Bertolong-tolonganlah menanggung bebanmu! Demikianlah kamu memenuhi hukum Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> For if anyone thinks himself to be something, when he is nothing, he deceives himself. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">لانه ان ظن احد انه شيء وهو ليس شيئا فانه يغش نفسه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Sebab kalau seorang menyangka, bahwa ia berarti, padahal ia sama sekali tidak berarti, ia menipu dirinya sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> But let each one examine his own work, and then he will have rejoicing in himself alone, and not in another. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ولكن ليمتحن كل واحد عمله وحينئذ يكون له الفخر من جهة نفسه فقط لا من جهة غيره.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Baiklah tiap-tiap orang menguji pekerjaannya sendiri; maka ia boleh bermegah melihat keadaannya sendiri dan bukan melihat keadaan orang lain.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> For each one shall bear his own load. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">لان كل واحد سيحمل حمل نفسه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Sebab tiap-tiap orang akan memikul tanggungannya sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Let him who is taught the word share in all good things with him who teaches. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ولكن ليشارك الذي يتعلّم الكلمة المعلّم في جميع الخيرات.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Dan baiklah dia, yang menerima pengajaran dalam Firman, membagi segala sesuatu yang ada padanya dengan orang yang memberikan pengajaran itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Do not be deceived, God is not mocked; for whatever a man sows, that he will also reap. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">لا تضلوا. الله لا يشمخ عليه. فان الذي يزرعه الانسان اياه يحصد ايضا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Jangan sesat! Allah tidak membiarkan diri-Nya dipermainkan. Karena apa yang ditabur orang, itu juga yang akan dituainya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> For he who sows to his flesh will of the flesh reap corruption, but he who sows to the Spirit will of the Spirit reap everlasting life. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لان من يزرع لجسده فمن الجسد يحصد فسادا. ومن يزرع للروح فمن الروح يحصد حياة ابدية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Sebab barangsiapa menabur dalam dagingnya, ia akan menuai kebinasaan dari dagingnya, tetapi barangsiapa menabur dalam Roh, ia akan menuai hidup yang kekal dari Roh itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> And let us not grow weary while doing good, for in due season we shall reap if we do not lose heart. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فلا نفشل في عمل الخير لاننا سنحصد في وقته ان كنا لا نكل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Janganlah kita jemu-jemu berbuat baik, karena apabila sudah datang waktunya, kita akan menuai, jika kita tidak menjadi lemah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Therefore, as we have opportunity, let us do good to all, especially to those who are of the household of faith. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فاذا حسبما لنا فرصة فلنعمل الخير للجميع ولا سيما لاهل الايمان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Karena itu, selama masih ada kesempatan bagi kita, marilah kita berbuat baik kepada semua orang, tetapi terutama kepada kawan-kawan kita seiman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> See with what large letters I have written to you with my own hand! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">انظروا ما اكبر الاحرف التي كتبتها اليكم بيدي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Lihatlah, bagaimana besarnya huruf-huruf yang kutulis kepadamu dengan tanganku sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> As many as desire to make a good showing in the flesh, these [would] compel you to be circumcised, only that they may not suffer persecution for the cross of Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">جميع الذين يريدون ان يعملوا منظرا حسنا في الجسد هؤلاء يلزمونكم ان تختتنوا لئلا يضطهدوا لاجل صليب المسيح فقط.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Mereka yang secara lahiriah suka menonjolkan diri, merekalah yang berusaha memaksa kamu untuk bersunat, hanya dengan maksud, supaya mereka tidak dianiaya karena salib Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> For not even those who are circumcised keep the law, but they desire to have you circumcised that they may boast in your flesh. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">لان الذين يختتنون هم لا يحفظون الناموس بل يريدون ان تختتنوا انتم لكي يفتخروا في جسدكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Sebab mereka yang menyunatkan dirinyapun, tidak memelihara hukum Taurat. Tetapi mereka menghendaki, supaya kamu menyunatkan diri, agar mereka dapat bermegah atas keadaanmu yang lahiriah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> But God forbid that I should boast except in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom the world has been crucified to me, and I to the world. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">واما من جهتي فحاشا لي ان افتخر الا بصليب ربنا يسوع المسيح الذي به قد صلب العالم لي وانا للعالم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Tetapi aku sekali-kali tidak mau bermegah, selain dalam salib Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus, sebab olehnya dunia telah disalibkan bagiku dan aku bagi dunia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> For in Christ Jesus neither circumcision nor uncircumcision avails anything, but a new creation. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">لانه في المسيح يسوع ليس الختان ينفع شيئا ولا الغرلة بل الخليقة الجديدة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Sebab bersunat atau tidak bersunat tidak ada artinya, tetapi menjadi ciptaan baru, itulah yang ada artinya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> And as many as walk according to this rule, peace and mercy [be] upon them, and upon the Israel of God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فكل الذين يسلكون بحسب هذا القانون عليهم سلام ورحمة وعلى اسرائيل الله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Dan semua orang, yang memberi dirinya dipimpin oleh patokan ini, turunlah kiranya damai sejahtera dan rahmat atas mereka dan atas Israel milik Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> From now on let no one trouble me, for I bear in my body the marks of the Lord Jesus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">في ما بعد لا يجلب احد عليّ اتعابا لاني حامل في جسدي سمات الرب يسوع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Selanjutnya janganlah ada orang yang menyusahkan aku, karena pada tubuhku ada tanda-tanda milik Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> Brethren, the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ [be] with your spirit. Amen. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">نعمة ربنا يسوع المسيح مع روحكم ايها الاخوة. آمين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Kasih karunia Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus menyertai roh kamu, saudara-saudara! Amin.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>