<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> In the second year of King Darius, in the sixth month, on the first day of the month, the word of the LORD came by Haggai the prophet to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, saying, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">في السنة الثانية لداريوس الملك في الشهر السادس في اول يوم من الشهر كانت كلمة الرب عن يد حجي النبي الى زربابل بن شألتيئيل والي يهوذا والى يهوشع بن يهوصادق الكاهن العظيم قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Pada tahun yang kedua zaman raja Darius, dalam bulan yang keenam, pada hari pertama bulan itu, datanglah firman TUHAN dengan perantaraan nabi Hagai kepada Zerubabel bin Sealtiel, bupati Yehuda, dan kepada Yosua bin Yozadak, imam besar, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> "Thus speaks the LORD of hosts, saying: 'This people says, "The time has not come, the time that the LORD's house should be built." ' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">هكذا قال رب الجنود قائلا. هذا الشعب قال ان الوقت لم يبلغ وقت بناء بيت الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">"Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Bangsa ini berkata: Sekarang belum tiba waktunya untuk membangun kembali rumah TUHAN!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Then the word of the LORD came by Haggai the prophet, saying, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فكانت كلمة الرب عن يد حجي النبي قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Maka datanglah firman TUHAN dengan perantaraan nabi Hagai, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> "[Is it] time for you yourselves to dwell in your paneled houses, and this temple [to lie] in ruins?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">هل الوقت لكم انتم ان تسكنوا في بيوتكم المغشّاة وهذا البيت خراب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">"Apakah sudah tiba waktunya bagi kamu untuk mendiami rumah-rumahmu yang dipapani dengan baik, sedang Rumah ini tetap menjadi reruntuhan?</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Now therefore, thus says the LORD of hosts: "Consider your ways! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">والآن فهكذا قال رب الجنود. اجعلوا قلبكم على طرقكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Oleh sebab itu, beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Perhatikanlah keadaanmu!</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> "You have sown much, and bring in little; You eat, but do not have enough; You drink, but you are not filled with drink; You clothe yourselves, but no one is warm; And he who earns wages, Earns wages [to put] into a bag with holes." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">زرعتم كثيرا ودخلتم قليلا. تأكلون وليس الى الشبع. تشربون ولا تروون. تكتسون ولا تدفأون. والآخذ اجرة يأخذ اجرة لكيس منقوب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Kamu menabur banyak, tetapi membawa pulang hasil sedikit; kamu makan, tetapi tidak sampai kenyang; kamu minum, tetapi tidak sampai puas; kamu berpakaian, tetapi badanmu tidak sampai panas; dan orang yang bekerja untuk upah, ia bekerja untuk upah yang ditaruh dalam pundi-pundi yang berlobang!</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Thus says the LORD of hosts: "Consider your ways! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">هكذا قال رب الجنود. اجعلوا قلبكم على طرقكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Perhatikanlah keadaanmu!</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> "Go up to the mountains and bring wood and build the temple, that I may take pleasure in it and be glorified," says the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">اصعدوا الى الجبل واتوا بخشب وابنوا البيت فارضى عليه واتمجد قال الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Jadi naiklah ke gunung, bawalah kayu dan bangunlah Rumah itu; maka Aku akan berkenan kepadanya dan akan menyatakan kemuliaan-Ku di situ, firman TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> "[You] looked for much, but indeed [it came to] little; and when you brought it home, I blew it away. Why?" says the LORD of hosts. "Because of My house that [is in] ruins, while every one of you runs to his own house. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">انتظرتم كثيرا واذا هو قليل ولما ادخلتموه البيت نفخت عليه. لماذا يقول رب الجنود. لاجل بيتي الذي هو خراب وانتم راكضون كل انسان الى بيته.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Kamu mengharapkan banyak, tetapi hasilnya sedikit, dan ketika kamu membawanya ke rumah, Aku menghembuskannya. Oleh karena apa? demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam. Oleh karena rumah-Ku yang tetap menjadi reruntuhan, sedang kamu masing-masing sibuk dengan urusan rumahnya sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> "Therefore the heavens above you withhold the dew, and the earth withholds its fruit. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لذلك منعت السموات من فوقكم الندى ومنعت الارض غلتها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Itulah sebabnya langit menahan embunnya dan bumi menahan hasilnya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> "For I called for a drought on the land and the mountains, on the grain and the new wine and the oil, on whatever the ground brings forth, on men and livestock, and on all the labor of [your] hands." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ودعوت بالحرّ على الارض وعلى الجبال وعلى الحنطة وعلى المسطار وعلى الزيت وعلى ما تنبته الارض وعلى الناس وعلى البهائم وعلى كل اتعاب اليدين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">dan Aku memanggil kekeringan datang ke atas negeri, ke atas gunung-gunung, ke atas gandum, ke atas anggur, ke atas minyak, ke atas segala yang dihasilkan tanah, ke atas manusia dan hewan dan ke atas segala hasil usaha."</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Then Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, and Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, with all the remnant of the people, obeyed the voice of the LORD their God, and the words of Haggai the prophet, as the LORD their God had sent him; and the people feared the presence of the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">حينئذ سمع زربابل بن شألتيئيل ويهوشع بن يهوصادق الكاهن العظيم وكل بقية الشعب صوت الرب الههم وكلام حجي النبي كما ارسله الرب الههم وخاف الشعب امام وجه الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Lalu Zerubabel bin Sealtiel dan Yosua bin Yozadak, imam besar, dan selebihnya dari bangsa itu mendengarkan suara TUHAN, Allah mereka, dan juga perkataan nabi Hagai, sesuai dengan apa yang disuruhkan kepadanya oleh TUHAN, Allah mereka; lalu takutlah bangsa itu kepada TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Then Haggai, the LORD's messenger, spoke the LORD's message to the people, saying, "I [am] with you, says the LORD." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فقال حجي رسول الرب برسالة الرب لجميع الشعب قائلا انا معكم يقول الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Maka berkatalah Hagai, utusan TUHAN itu, menurut pesan TUHAN kepada bangsa itu, demikian: "Aku ini menyertai kamu, demikianlah firman TUHAN."</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> So the LORD stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people; and they came and worked on the house of the LORD of hosts, their God, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ونبّه الرب روح زربابل بن شألتيئيل والي يهوذا وروح يهوشع بن يهوصادق الكاهن العظيم وروح كل بقية الشعب فجاءوا وعملوا الشغل في بيت رب الجنود الههم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">TUHAN menggerakkan semangat Zerubabel bin Sealtiel, bupati Yehuda, dan semangat Yosua bin Yozadak, imam besar, dan semangat selebihnya dari bangsa itu, maka datanglah mereka, lalu melakukan pekerjaan pembangunan rumah TUHAN semesta alam, Allah mereka,</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> on the twenty-fourth day of the sixth month, in the second year of King Darius. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">في اليوم الرابع والعشرين من الشهر السادس في السنة الثانية لداريوس الملك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">(2-1a) pada hari yang kedua puluh empat dalam bulan yang keenam. (2-1b) Pada tahun yang kedua zaman raja Darius,</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="2">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> In the seventh [month,] on the twenty-first of the month, the word of the LORD came by Haggai the prophet, saying: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">في الشهر السابع في الحادي والعشرين من الشهر كانت كلمة الرب عن يد حجي النبي قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">(2-2) dalam bulan yang ketujuh, pada tanggal dua puluh satu bulan itu, datanglah firman TUHAN dengan perantaraan nabi Hagai, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> "Speak now to Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">كلم زربابل بن شألتيئيل والي يهوذا ويهوشع بن يهوصادق الكاهن العظيم وبقية الشعب قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">(2-3) "Katakanlah kepada Zerubabel bin Sealtiel, bupati Yehuda, dan kepada Yosua bin Yozadak, imam besar, dan kepada selebihnya dari bangsa itu, demikian:</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> 'Who is left among you who saw this temple in its former glory? And how do you see it now? In comparison with it, [is this] not in your eyes as nothing? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">من الباقي فيكم الذي رأى هذا البيت في مجده الاول. وكيف تنظرونه الآن. أما هو في اعينكم كلا شيء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">(2-4) Masih adakah di antara kamu yang telah melihat Rumah ini dalam kemegahannya semula? Dan bagaimanakah kamu lihat keadaannya sekarang? Bukankah keadaannya di matamu seperti tidak ada artinya?</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> 'Yet now be strong, Zerubbabel,' says the LORD; 'and be strong, Joshua, son of Jehozadak, the high priest; and be strong, all you people of the land,' says the LORD, 'and work; for I [am] with you,' says the LORD of hosts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فالآن تشدد يا زربابل يقول الرب وتشدد يا يهوشع بن يهوصادق الكاهن العظيم وتشددوا يا جميع شعب الارض يقول الرب واعملوا فاني معكم يقول رب الجنود</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">(2-5) Tetapi sekarang, kuatkanlah hatimu, hai Zerubabel, demikianlah firman TUHAN; kuatkanlah hatimu, hai Yosua bin Yozadak, imam besar; kuatkanlah hatimu, hai segala rakyat negeri, demikianlah firman TUHAN; bekerjalah, sebab Aku ini menyertai kamu, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam,</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> '[According to] the word that I covenanted with you when you came out of Egypt, so My Spirit remains among you; do not fear!' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">حسب الكلام الذي عاهدتكم به عند خروجكم من مصر وروحي قائم في وسطكم. لا تخافوا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">(2-6) sesuai dengan janji yang telah Kuikat dengan kamu pada waktu kamu keluar dari Mesir. Dan Roh-Ku tetap tinggal di tengah-tengahmu. Janganlah takut!</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> " For thus says the LORD of hosts: 'Once more (it [is] a little while) I will shake heaven and earth, the sea and dry land; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لانه هكذا قال رب الجنود. هي مرّة بعد قليل فازلزل السموات والارض والبحر واليابسة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">(2-7) Sebab beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Sedikit waktu lagi maka Aku akan menggoncangkan langit dan bumi, laut dan darat;</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> 'and I will shake all nations, and they shall come to the Desire of All Nations, and I will fill this temple with glory,' says the LORD of hosts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">وازلزل كل الامم وياتي مشتهى كل الامم فاملأ هذا البيت مجدا قال رب الجنود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">(2-8) Aku akan menggoncangkan segala bangsa, sehingga barang yang indah-indah kepunyaan segala bangsa datang mengalir, maka Aku akan memenuhi Rumah ini dengan kemegahan, firman TUHAN semesta alam.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> ' The silver [is] Mine, and the gold [is] Mine,' says the LORD of hosts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لي الفضة ولي الذهب يقول رب الجنود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">(2-9) Kepunyaan-Kulah perak dan kepunyaan-Kulah emas, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> 'The glory of this latter temple shall be greater than the former,' says the LORD of hosts. 'And in this place I will give peace,' says the LORD of hosts." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">مجد هذا البيت الاخير يكون اعظم من مجد الاول قال رب الجنود وفي هذا المكان اعطي السلام يقول رب الجنود</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">(2-10) Adapun Rumah ini, kemegahannya yang kemudian akan melebihi kemegahannya yang semula, firman TUHAN semesta alam, dan di tempat ini Aku akan memberi damai sejahtera, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam."</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> On the twenty-fourth [day] of the ninth [month,] in the second year of Darius, the word of the LORD came by Haggai the prophet, saying, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">في الرابع والعشرين من الشهر التاسع في السنة الثانية لداريوس كانت كلمة الرب عن يد حجي النبي قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">(2-11) Pada tanggal dua puluh empat bulan yang kesembilan, pada tahun yang kedua zaman Darius, datanglah firman TUHAN kepada nabi Hagai, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> "Thus says the LORD of hosts: 'Now, ask the priests [concerning the] law, saying, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">هكذا قال رب الجنود. اسأل الكهنة عن الشريعة قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">(2-12) "Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam itu: Tanyakanlah pengajaran kepada para imam.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> "If one carries holy meat in the fold of his garment, and with the edge he touches bread or stew, wine or oil, or any food, will it become holy?" ' " Then the priests answered and said, "No." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ان حمل انسان لحما مقدسا في طرف ثوبه ومس بطرفه خبزا او طبيخا او خمرا او زيتا او طعاما ما فهل يتقدس. فاجاب الكهنة وقالوا لا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">(2-13) Andaikata seseorang membawa daging kudus dalam punca bajunya, lalu dengan puncanya itu ia menyentuh roti atau sesuatu masakan atau anggur atau minyak atau sesuatu yang dapat dimakan, menjadi kuduskah yang disentuh itu?" Lalu para imam itu menjawab, katanya: "Tidak!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> And Haggai said, "If [one who is] unclean [because] of a dead body touches any of these, will it be unclean?" So the priests answered and said, "It shall be unclean." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فقال حجي ان كان المنجس بميت يمسّ شيئا من هذه فهل يتنجس. فاجاب الكهنة وقالوا يتنجس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">(2-14) Berkatalah pula Hagai: "Jika seseorang yang najis oleh mayat menyentuh semuanya ini, menjadi najiskah yang disentuh itu?" Lalu para imam itu menjawab, katanya: "Tentu!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Then Haggai answered and said, " 'So is this people, and so is this nation before Me,' says the LORD, 'and so is every work of their hands; and what they offer there is unclean. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فاجاب حجي وقال. هكذا هذا الشعب وهكذا هذه الامة قدامي يقول الرب وهكذا كل عمل ايديهم وما يقربونه هناك هو نجس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">(2-15) Maka berbicaralah Hagai, katanya: "Begitu juga dengan umat ini dan dengan bangsa ini di hadapan-Ku, demikianlah firman TUHAN, dan dengan segala yang dibuat tangan mereka; dan yang dipersembahkan mereka di sana adalah najis."</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> ' And now, carefully consider from this day forward: from before stone was laid upon stone in the temple of the LORD -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">والآن فاجعلوا قلبكم من هذا اليوم فراجعا قبل وضع حجر على حجر في هيكل الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">(2-16) "Maka sekarang, perhatikanlah mulai dari hari ini dan selanjutnya! Sebelum ditaruh orang batu demi batu untuk pembangunan bait TUHAN,</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> 'since those [days,] when [one] came to a heap of twenty ephahs, there were [but] ten; when [one] came to the wine vat to draw out fifty baths from the press, there were [but] twenty. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">مذ تلك الايام كان احدكم يأتي الى عرمة عشرين فكانت عشرة. أتى الى حوض المعصرة ليغرف خمسين فورة فكانت عشرين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">(2-17) bagaimana keadaanmu? Ketika orang pergi melihat suatu timbunan gandum yang seharusnya sebanyak dua puluh gantang, hanya ada sepuluh; dan ketika orang pergi ke tempat pemerasan anggur untuk mencedok lima puluh takar, hanya ada dua puluh.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> 'I struck you with blight and mildew and hail in all the labors of your hands; yet you did not [turn] to Me,' says the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">قد ضربتكم باللفح وباليرقان وبالبرد في كل عمل ايديكم وما رجعتم اليّ يقول الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">(2-18) Aku telah memukul kamu dengan hama dan penyakit gandum dan segala yang dibuat tanganmu dengan hujan batu; namun kamu tidak berbalik kepada-Ku, demikianlah firman TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> 'Consider now from this day forward, from the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month, from the day that the foundation of the LORD's temple was laid -- consider it: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فاجعلوا قلبكم من هذا اليوم فصاعدا من اليوم الرابع والعشرين من الشهر التاسع من اليوم الذي فيه تأسّس هيكل الرب اجعلوا قلبكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">(2-19) Perhatikanlah mulai dari hari ini dan selanjutnya--mulai dari hari yang kedua puluh empat bulan kesembilan. Mulai dari hari diletakkannya dasar bait TUHAN perhatikanlah</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> 'Is the seed still in the barn? As yet the vine, the fig tree, the pomegranate, and the olive tree have not yielded [fruit. But] from this day I will bless [you.'] " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">هل البذر في الاهراء بعد. والكرم والتين والرمان والزيتون لم يحمل بعد. فمن هذا اليوم ابارك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">(2-20) apakah benih masih tinggal tersimpan dalam lumbung, dan apakah pohon anggur dan pohon ara, pohon delima dan pohon zaitun belum berbuah? Mulai dari hari ini Aku akan memberi berkat!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> And again the word of the LORD came to Haggai on the twenty-fourth day of the month, saying, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">وصارت كلمة الرب ثانية الى حجي في الرابع والعشرين من الشهر قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">(2-21) Maka datanglah firman TUHAN untuk kedua kalinya kepada Hagai pada tanggal dua puluh empat bulan itu, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> "Speak to Zerubbabel, governor of Judah, saying: 'I will shake heaven and earth. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">كلم زربابل والي يهوذا قائلا. اني ازلزل السموات والارض</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">(2-22) "Katakanlah kepada Zerubabel, bupati Yehuda, begini: Aku akan menggoncangkan langit dan bumi</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms; I will destroy the strength of the Gentile kingdoms. I will overthrow the chariots And those who ride in them; The horses and their riders shall come down, Every one by the sword of his brother. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">واقلب كرسي الممالك وابيد قوّة ممالك الامم واقلب المركبات والراكبين فيها وينحطّ الخيل وراكبوها كل منها بسيف اخيه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">(2-23) dan akan menunggangbalikkan takhta raja-raja; Aku akan memunahkan kekuasaan kerajaan bangsa-bangsa dan akan menjungkirbalikkan kereta dan pengendaranya; kuda dan pengendaranya akan mati rebah, masing-masing oleh pedang temannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> 'In that day,' says the LORD of hosts, 'I will take you, Zerubbabel My servant, the son of Shealtiel,' says the LORD, 'and will make you like a signet [ring;] for I have chosen you,' says the LORD of hosts." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">في ذلك اليوم يقول رب الجنود آخذك يا زربابل عبدي ابن شألتيئيل يقول الرب واجعلك كخاتم لاني قد اخترتك يقول رب الجنود</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">(2-24) Pada waktu itu, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam, Aku akan mengambil engkau, hai Zerubabel bin Sealtiel, hamba-Ku--demikianlah firman TUHAN--dan akan menjadikan engkau seperti cincin meterai; sebab engkaulah yang Kupilih, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam."</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>