<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> James, a bondservant of God and of the Lord Jesus Christ, To the twelve tribes which are scattered abroad: Greetings. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">يعقوب عبد الله والرب يسوع المسيح يهدي السلام الى الاثني عشر سبطا الذين في الشتات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Salam dari Yakobus, hamba Allah dan Tuhan Yesus Kristus, kepada kedua belas suku di perantauan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> My brethren, count it all joy when you fall into various trials, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">احسبوه كل فرح يا اخوتي حينما تقعون في تجارب متنوعة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Saudara-saudaraku, anggaplah sebagai suatu kebahagiaan, apabila kamu jatuh ke dalam berbagai-bagai pencobaan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> knowing that the testing of your faith produces patience. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">عالمين ان امتحان ايمانكم ينشئ صبرا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">sebab kamu tahu, bahwa ujian terhadap imanmu itu menghasilkan ketekunan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> But let patience have [its] perfect work, that you may be perfect and complete, lacking nothing. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">واما الصبر فليكن له عمل تام لكي تكونوا تامّين وكاملين غير ناقصين في شيء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Dan biarkanlah ketekunan itu memperoleh buah yang matang, supaya kamu menjadi sempurna dan utuh dan tak kekurangan suatu apapun.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> If any of you lacks wisdom, let him ask of God, who gives to all liberally and without reproach, and it will be given to him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">وانما ان كان احد تعوزه حكمة فليطلب من الله الذي يعطي الجميع بسخاء ولا يعيّر فسيعطى له.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Tetapi apabila di antara kamu ada yang kekurangan hikmat, hendaklah ia memintakannya kepada Allah, --yang memberikan kepada semua orang dengan murah hati dan dengan tidak membangkit-bangkit--,maka hal itu akan diberikan kepadanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> But let him ask in faith, with no doubting, for he who doubts is like a wave of the sea driven and tossed by the wind. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ولكن ليطلب بايمان غير مرتاب البتة لان المرتاب يشبه موجا من البحر تخبطه الريح وتدفعه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Hendaklah ia memintanya dalam iman, dan sama sekali jangan bimbang, sebab orang yang bimbang sama dengan gelombang laut, yang diombang-ambingkan kian ke mari oleh angin.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> For let not that man suppose that he will receive anything from the Lord; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فلا يظن ذلك الانسان انه ينال شيئا من عند الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Orang yang demikian janganlah mengira, bahwa ia akan menerima sesuatu dari Tuhan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> [he is] a double-minded man, unstable in all his ways. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">رجل ذو رايين هو متقلقل في جميع طرقه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Sebab orang yang mendua hati tidak akan tenang dalam hidupnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Let the lowly brother glory in his exaltation, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">وليفتخر الاخ المتضع بارتفاعه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Baiklah saudara yang berada dalam keadaan yang rendah bermegah karena kedudukannya yang tinggi,</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> but the rich in his humiliation, because as a flower of the field he will pass away. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">واما الغني فباتضاعه لانه كزهر العشب يزول.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">dan orang kaya karena kedudukannya yang rendah sebab ia akan lenyap seperti bunga rumput.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> For no sooner has the sun risen with a burning heat than it withers the grass; its flower falls, and its beautiful appearance perishes. So the rich man also will fade away in his pursuits. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لان الشمس اشرقت بالحرّ فيبّست العشب فسقط زهره وفني جمال منظره. هكذا يذبل الغني ايضا في طرقه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Karena matahari terbit dengan panasnya yang terik dan melayukan rumput itu, sehingga gugurlah bunganya dan hilanglah semaraknya. Demikian jugalah halnya dengan orang kaya; di tengah-tengah segala usahanya ia akan lenyap.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Blessed [is] the man who endures temptation; for when he has been approved, he will receive the crown of life which the Lord has promised to those who love Him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">طوبى للرجل الذي يحتمل التجربة. لانه اذا تزكى ينال اكليل الحياة الذي وعد به الرب للذين يحبونه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Berbahagialah orang yang bertahan dalam pencobaan, sebab apabila ia sudah tahan uji, ia akan menerima mahkota kehidupan yang dijanjikan Allah kepada barangsiapa yang mengasihi Dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Let no one say when he is tempted, "I am tempted by God"; for God cannot be tempted by evil, nor does He Himself tempt anyone. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">لا يقل احد اذا جرّب اني أجرّب من قبل الله. لان الله غير مجرّب بالشرور وهو لا يجرّب احدا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Apabila seorang dicobai, janganlah ia berkata: "Pencobaan ini datang dari Allah!" Sebab Allah tidak dapat dicobai oleh yang jahat, dan Ia sendiri tidak mencobai siapapun.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> But each one is tempted when he is drawn away by his own desires and enticed. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ولكن كل واحد يجرّب اذا انجذب وانخدع من شهوته.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Tetapi tiap-tiap orang dicobai oleh keinginannya sendiri, karena ia diseret dan dipikat olehnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Then, when desire has conceived, it gives birth to sin; and sin, when it is full-grown, brings forth death. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ثم الشهوة اذا حبلت تلد خطية والخطية اذا كملت تنتج موتا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Dan apabila keinginan itu telah dibuahi, ia melahirkan dosa; dan apabila dosa itu sudah matang, ia melahirkan maut.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> Do not be deceived, my beloved brethren. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لا تضلّوا يا اخوتي الاحباء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Saudara-saudara yang kukasihi, janganlah sesat!</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Every good gift and every perfect gift is from above, and comes down from the Father of lights, with whom there is no variation or shadow of turning. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">كل عطية صالحة وكل موهبة تامة هي من فوق نازلة من عند ابي الانوار الذي ليس عنده تغيير ولا ظل دوران.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Setiap pemberian yang baik dan setiap anugerah yang sempurna, datangnya dari atas, diturunkan dari Bapa segala terang; pada-Nya tidak ada perubahan atau bayangan karena pertukaran.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> Of His own will He brought us forth by the word of truth, that we might be a kind of firstfruits of His creatures. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">شاء فولدنا بكلمة الحق لكي نكون باكورة من خلائقه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Atas kehendak-Nya sendiri Ia telah menjadikan kita oleh firman kebenaran, supaya kita pada tingkat yang tertentu menjadi anak sulung di antara semua ciptaan-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> So then, my beloved brethren, let every man be swift to hear, slow to speak, slow to wrath; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">اذا يا اخوتي الاحباء ليكن كل انسان مسرعا في الاستماع مبطئا في التكلم مبطئا في الغضب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Hai saudara-saudara yang kukasihi, ingatlah hal ini: setiap orang hendaklah cepat untuk mendengar, tetapi lambat untuk berkata-kata, dan juga lambat untuk marah;</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> for the wrath of man does not produce the righteousness of God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">لان غضب الانسان لا يصنع بر الله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">sebab amarah manusia tidak mengerjakan kebenaran di hadapan Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> Therefore lay aside all filthiness and overflow of wickedness, and receive with meekness the implanted word, which is able to save your souls. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">لذلك اطرحوا كل نجاسة وكثرة شر فاقبلوا بوداعة الكلمة المغروسة القادرة ان تخلّص نفوسكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Sebab itu buanglah segala sesuatu yang kotor dan kejahatan yang begitu banyak itu dan terimalah dengan lemah lembut firman yang tertanam di dalam hatimu, yang berkuasa menyelamatkan jiwamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> But be doers of the word, and not hearers only, deceiving yourselves. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">ولكن كونوا عاملين بالكلمة لا سامعين فقط خادعين نفوسكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Tetapi hendaklah kamu menjadi pelaku firman dan bukan hanya pendengar saja; sebab jika tidak demikian kamu menipu diri sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> For if anyone is a hearer of the word and not a doer, he is like a man observing his natural face in a mirror; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">لانه ان كان احد سامعا للكلمة وليس عاملا فذاك يشبه رجلا ناظرا وجه خلقته في مرآة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Sebab jika seorang hanya mendengar firman saja dan tidak melakukannya, ia adalah seumpama seorang yang sedang mengamat-amati mukanya yang sebenarnya di depan cermin.</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> for he observes himself, goes away, and immediately forgets what kind of man he was. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">فانه نظر ذاته ومضى وللوقت نسي ما هو.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">Baru saja ia memandang dirinya, ia sudah pergi atau ia segera lupa bagaimana rupanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> But he who looks into the perfect law of liberty and continues [in it,] and is not a forgetful hearer but a doer of the work, this one will be blessed in what he does. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">ولكن من اطّلع على الناموس الكامل ناموس الحرية وثبت وصار ليس سامعا ناسيا بل عاملا بالكلمة فهذا يكون مغبوطا في عمله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Tetapi barangsiapa meneliti hukum yang sempurna, yaitu hukum yang memerdekakan orang, dan ia bertekun di dalamnya, jadi bukan hanya mendengar untuk melupakannya, tetapi sungguh-sungguh melakukannya, ia akan berbahagia oleh perbuatannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26"> If anyone among you thinks he is religious, and does not bridle his tongue but deceives his own heart, this one's religion [is] useless. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">ان كان احد فيكم يظن انه ديّن وهو ليس يلجم لسانه بل يخدع قلبه فديانة هذا باطلة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">Jikalau ada seorang menganggap dirinya beribadah, tetapi tidak mengekang lidahnya, ia menipu dirinya sendiri, maka sia-sialah ibadahnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27"> Pure and undefiled religion before God and the Father is this: to visit orphans and widows in their trouble, [and] to keep oneself unspotted from the world. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">الديانة الطاهرة النقية عند الله الآب هي هذه افتقاد اليتامى والارامل في ضيقتهم وحفظ الانسان نفسه بلا دنس من العالم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">Ibadah yang murni dan yang tak bercacat di hadapan Allah, Bapa kita, ialah mengunjungi yatim piatu dan janda-janda dalam kesusahan mereka, dan menjaga supaya dirinya sendiri tidak dicemarkan oleh dunia.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="2">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> My brethren, do not hold the faith of our Lord Jesus Christ, [the Lord] of glory, with partiality. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">يا اخوتي لا يكن لكم ايمان ربنا يسوع المسيح رب المجد في المحاباة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Saudara-saudaraku, sebagai orang yang beriman kepada Yesus Kristus, Tuhan kita yang mulia, janganlah iman itu kamu amalkan dengan memandang muka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> For if there should come into your assembly a man with gold rings, in fine apparel, and there should also come in a poor man in filthy clothes, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فانه ان دخل الى مجمعكم رجل بخواتم ذهب في لباس بهي ودخل ايضا فقير بلباس وسخ</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Sebab, jika ada seorang masuk ke dalam kumpulanmu dengan memakai cincin emas dan pakaian indah dan datang juga seorang miskin ke situ dengan memakai pakaian buruk,</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> and you pay attention to the one wearing the fine clothes and say to him, "You sit here in a good place," and say to the poor man, "You stand there," or, "Sit here at my footstool," </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فنظرتم الى اللابس اللباس البهي وقلتم له اجلس انت هنا حسنا وقلتم للفقير قف انت هناك او اجلس هنا تحت موطئ قدميّ</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">dan kamu menghormati orang yang berpakaian indah itu dan berkata kepadanya: "Silakan tuan duduk di tempat yang baik ini!", sedang kepada orang yang miskin itu kamu berkata: "Berdirilah di sana!" atau: "Duduklah di lantai ini dekat tumpuan kakiku!",</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> have you not shown partiality among yourselves, and become judges with evil thoughts? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فهل لا ترتابون في انفسكم وتصيرون قضاة افكار شريرة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">bukankah kamu telah membuat pembedaan di dalam hatimu dan bertindak sebagai hakim dengan pikiran yang jahat?</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Listen, my beloved brethren: Has God not chosen the poor of this world [to be] rich in faith and heirs of the kingdom which He promised to those who love Him? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">اسمعوا يا اخوتي الاحباء أما اختار الله فقراء هذا العالم اغنياء في الايمان وورثة الملكوت الذي وعد به الذين يحبونه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Dengarkanlah, hai saudara-saudara yang kukasihi! Bukankah Allah memilih orang-orang yang dianggap miskin oleh dunia ini untuk menjadi kaya dalam iman dan menjadi ahli waris Kerajaan yang telah dijanjikan-Nya kepada barangsiapa yang mengasihi Dia?</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> But you have dishonored the poor man. Do not the rich oppress you and drag you into the courts? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">واما انتم فاهنتم الفقير. أليس الاغنياء يتسلطون عليكم وهم يجرّونكم الى المحاكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Tetapi kamu telah menghinakan orang-orang miskin. Bukankah justru orang-orang kaya yang menindas kamu dan yang menyeret kamu ke pengadilan?</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Do they not blaspheme that noble name by which you are called? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">أما هم يجدّفون على الاسم الحسن الذي دعي به عليكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Bukankah mereka yang menghujat Nama yang mulia, yang oleh-Nya kamu menjadi milik Allah?</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> If you really fulfill [the] royal law according to the Scripture, "You shall love your neighbor as yourself," you do well; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فان كنتم تكملون الناموس الملوكي حسب الكتاب. تحب قريبك كنفسك. فحسنا تفعلون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Akan tetapi, jikalau kamu menjalankan hukum utama yang tertulis dalam Kitab Suci: "Kasihilah sesamamu manusia seperti dirimu sendiri", kamu berbuat baik.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> but if you show partiality, you commit sin, and are convicted by the law as transgressors. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ولكن ان كنتم تحابون تفعلون خطية موبّخين من الناموس كمتعدّين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Tetapi, jikalau kamu memandang muka, kamu berbuat dosa, dan oleh hukum itu menjadi nyata, bahwa kamu melakukan pelanggaran.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> For whoever shall keep the whole law, and yet stumble in one [point,] he is guilty of all. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لان من حفظ كل الناموس وانما عثر في واحدة فقد صار مجرما في الكل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Sebab barangsiapa menuruti seluruh hukum itu, tetapi mengabaikan satu bagian dari padanya, ia bersalah terhadap seluruhnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> For He who said, "Do not commit adultery," also said, "Do not murder." Now if you do not commit adultery, but you do murder, you have become a transgressor of the law. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لان الذي قال لا تزن قال ايضا لا تقتل. فان لم تزن ولكن قتلت فقد صرت متعديا الناموس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Sebab Ia yang mengatakan: "Jangan berzinah", Ia mengatakan juga: "Jangan membunuh". Jadi jika kamu tidak berzinah tetapi membunuh, maka kamu menjadi pelanggar hukum juga.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> So speak and so do as those who will be judged by the law of liberty. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">هكذا تكلموا وهكذا افعلوا كعتيدين ان تحاكموا بناموس الحرية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Berkatalah dan berlakulah seperti orang-orang yang akan dihakimi oleh hukum yang memerdekakan orang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> For judgment is without mercy to the one who has shown no mercy. Mercy triumphs over judgment. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">لان الحكم هو بلا رحمة لمن لم يعمل رحمة. والرحمة تفتخر على الحكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Sebab penghakiman yang tak berbelas kasihan akan berlaku atas orang yang tidak berbelas kasihan. Tetapi belas kasihan akan menang atas penghakiman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> What [does it] profit, my brethren, if someone says he has faith but does not have works? Can faith save him? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ما المنفعة يا اخوتي ان قال احد ان له ايمانا ولكن ليس له اعمال. هل يقدر الايمان ان يخلّصه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Apakah gunanya, saudara-saudaraku, jika seorang mengatakan, bahwa ia mempunyai iman, padahal ia tidak mempunyai perbuatan? Dapatkah iman itu menyelamatkan dia?</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> If a brother or sister is naked and destitute of daily food, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ان كان اخ واخت عريانين ومعتازين للقوت اليومي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Jika seorang saudara atau saudari tidak mempunyai pakaian dan kekurangan makanan sehari-hari,</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> and one of you says to them, "Depart in peace, be warmed and filled," but you do not give them the things which are needed for the body, what [does it] profit? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فقال لهما احدكم امضيا بسلام استدفيا واشبعا ولكن لم تعطوهما حاجات الجسد فما المنفعة ‎.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">dan seorang dari antara kamu berkata: "Selamat jalan, kenakanlah kain panas dan makanlah sampai kenyang!", tetapi ia tidak memberikan kepadanya apa yang perlu bagi tubuhnya, apakah gunanya itu?</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Thus also faith by itself, if it does not have works, is dead. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">هكذا الايمان ايضا ان لم يكن له اعمال ميت في ذاته.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Demikian juga halnya dengan iman: Jika iman itu tidak disertai perbuatan, maka iman itu pada hakekatnya adalah mati.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> But someone will say, "You have faith, and I have works." Show me your faith without your works, and I will show you my faith by my works. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">لكن يقول قائل انت لك ايمان وانا لي اعمال. أرني ايمانك بدون اعمالك وانا اريك باعمالي ايماني.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Tetapi mungkin ada orang berkata: "Padamu ada iman dan padaku ada perbuatan", aku akan menjawab dia: "Tunjukkanlah kepadaku imanmu itu tanpa perbuatan, dan aku akan menunjukkan kepadamu imanku dari perbuatan-perbuatanku."</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> You believe that there is one God. You do well. Even the demons believe -- and tremble! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">انت تؤمن ان الله واحد. حسنا تفعل. والشياطين يؤمنون ويقشعرون</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Engkau percaya, bahwa hanya ada satu Allah saja? Itu baik! Tetapi setan-setanpun juga percaya akan hal itu dan mereka gemetar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> But do you want to know, O foolish man, that faith without works is dead? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">ولكن هل تريد ان تعلم ايها الانسان الباطل ان الايمان بدون اعمال ميت.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Hai manusia yang bebal, maukah engkau mengakui sekarang, bahwa iman tanpa perbuatan adalah iman yang kosong?</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> Was not Abraham our father justified by works when he offered Isaac his son on the altar? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">ألم يتبرر ابراهيم ابونا بالاعمال اذ قدم اسحق ابنه على المذبح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Bukankah Abraham, bapa kita, dibenarkan karena perbuatan-perbuatannya, ketika ia mempersembahkan Ishak, anaknya, di atas mezbah?</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> Do you see that faith was working together with his works, and by works faith was made perfect? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">فترى ان الايمان عمل مع اعماله وبالاعمال اكمل الايمان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Kamu lihat, bahwa iman bekerjasama dengan perbuatan-perbuatan dan oleh perbuatan-perbuatan itu iman menjadi sempurna.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> And the Scripture was fulfilled which says, "Abraham believed God, and it was accounted to him for righteousness." And he was called the friend of God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">وتم الكتاب القائل فآمن ابراهيم بالله فحسب له برا ودعي خليل الله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Dengan jalan demikian genaplah nas yang mengatakan: "Lalu percayalah Abraham kepada Allah, maka Allah memperhitungkan hal itu kepadanya sebagai kebenaran." Karena itu Abraham disebut: "Sahabat Allah."</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> You see then that a man is justified by works, and not by faith only. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">ترون اذا انه بالاعمال يتبرر الانسان لا بالايمان وحده.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">Jadi kamu lihat, bahwa manusia dibenarkan karena perbuatan-perbuatannya dan bukan hanya karena iman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> Likewise, was not Rahab the harlot also justified by works when she received the messengers and sent [them] out another way? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">كذلك راحاب الزانية ايضا أما تبررت بالاعمال اذ قبلت الرسل واخرجتهم في طريق آخر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Dan bukankah demikian juga Rahab, pelacur itu, dibenarkan karena perbuatan-perbuatannya, ketika ia menyembunyikan orang-orang yang disuruh itu di dalam rumahnya, lalu menolong mereka lolos melalui jalan yang lain?</language></verse>
			<verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26"> For as the body without the spirit is dead, so faith without works is dead also. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">لانه كما ان الجسد بدون روح ميت هكذا الايمان ايضا بدون اعمال ميت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">Sebab seperti tubuh tanpa roh adalah mati, demikian jugalah iman tanpa perbuatan-perbuatan adalah mati.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="3">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> My brethren, let not many of you become teachers, knowing that we shall receive a stricter judgment. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">لا تكونوا معلّمين كثيرين يا اخوتي عالمين اننا نأخذ دينونة اعظم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Saudara-saudaraku, janganlah banyak orang di antara kamu mau menjadi guru; sebab kita tahu, bahwa sebagai guru kita akan dihakimi menurut ukuran yang lebih berat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> For we all stumble in many things. If anyone does not stumble in word, he [is] a perfect man, able also to bridle the whole body. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">لاننا في اشياء كثيرة نعثر جميعنا. ان كان احد لا يعثر في الكلام فذاك رجل كامل قادر ان يلجم كل الجسد ايضا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Sebab kita semua bersalah dalam banyak hal; barangsiapa tidak bersalah dalam perkataannya, ia adalah orang sempurna, yang dapat juga mengendalikan seluruh tubuhnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Indeed, we put bits in horses' mouths that they may obey us, and we turn their whole body. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">هوذا الخيل نضع اللجم في افواهها لكي تطاوعنا فندير جسمها كله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Kita mengenakan kekang pada mulut kuda, sehingga ia menuruti kehendak kita, dengan jalan demikian kita dapat juga mengendalikan seluruh tubuhnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Look also at ships: although they are so large and are driven by fierce winds, they are turned by a very small rudder wherever the pilot desires. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">هوذا السفن ايضا وهي عظيمة بهذا المقدار وتسوقها رياح عاصفة تديرها دفة صغيرة جدا الى حيثما شاء قصد المدير.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Dan lihat saja kapal-kapal, walaupun amat besar dan digerakkan oleh angin keras, namun dapat dikendalikan oleh kemudi yang amat kecil menurut kehendak jurumudi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Even so the tongue is a little member and boasts great things. See how great a forest a little fire kindles! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">هكذا اللسان ايضا هو عضو صغير ويفتخر متعظما. هوذا نار قليلة اي وقود تحرق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Demikian juga lidah, walaupun suatu anggota kecil dari tubuh, namun dapat memegahkan perkara-perkara yang besar. Lihatlah, betapapun kecilnya api, ia dapat membakar hutan yang besar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> And the tongue [is] a fire, a world of iniquity. The tongue is so set among our members that it defiles the whole body, and sets on fire the course of nature; and it is set on fire by hell. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فاللسان نار. عالم الاثم. هكذا جعل في اعضائنا اللسان الذي يدنس الجسم كله ويضرم دائرة الكون ويضرم من جهنم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Lidahpun adalah api; ia merupakan suatu dunia kejahatan dan mengambil tempat di antara anggota-anggota tubuh kita sebagai sesuatu yang dapat menodai seluruh tubuh dan menyalakan roda kehidupan kita, sedang ia sendiri dinyalakan oleh api neraka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> For every kind of beast and bird, of reptile and creature of the sea, is tamed and has been tamed by mankind. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">لان كل طبع للوحوش والطيور والزحافات والبحريات يذلل وقد تذلل للطبع البشري.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Semua jenis binatang liar, burung-burung, serta binatang-binatang menjalar dan binatang-binatang laut dapat dijinakkan dan telah dijinakkan oleh sifat manusia,</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> But no man can tame the tongue. [It is] an unruly evil, full of deadly poison. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">واما اللسان فلا يستطيع احد من الناس ان يذلله. هو شر لا يضبط مملوء سمّا مميتا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">tetapi tidak seorangpun yang berkuasa menjinakkan lidah; ia adalah sesuatu yang buas, yang tak terkuasai, dan penuh racun yang mematikan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> With it we bless our God and Father, and with it we curse men, who have been made in the similitude of God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">به نبارك الله الآب وبه نلعن الناس الذين قد تكوّنوا على شبه الله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Dengan lidah kita memuji Tuhan, Bapa kita; dan dengan lidah kita mengutuk manusia yang diciptakan menurut rupa Allah,</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Out of the same mouth proceed blessing and cursing. My brethren, these things ought not to be so. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">من الفم الواحد تخرج بركة ولعنة. لا يصلح يا اخوتي ان تكون هذه الامور هكذا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">dari mulut yang satu keluar berkat dan kutuk. Hal ini, saudara-saudaraku, tidak boleh demikian terjadi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Does a spring send forth fresh [water] and bitter from the same opening? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ألعل ينبوعا ينبع من نفس عين واحدة العذب والمر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Adakah sumber memancarkan air tawar dan air pahit dari mata air yang sama?</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Can a fig tree, my brethren, bear olives, or a grapevine bear figs? Thus no spring yields both salt water and fresh. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">هل تقدر يا اخوتي تينة ان تصنع زيتونا او كرمة تينا. ولا كذلك ينبوع يصنع ماء مالحا وعذبا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Saudara-saudaraku, adakah pohon ara dapat menghasilkan buah zaitun dan adakah pokok anggur dapat menghasilkan buah ara? Demikian juga mata air asin tidak dapat mengeluarkan air tawar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Who [is] wise and understanding among you? Let him show by good conduct [that] his works [are done] in the meekness of wisdom. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">من هو حكيم وعالم بينكم فلير اعماله بالتصرف الحسن في وداعة الحكمة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Siapakah di antara kamu yang bijak dan berbudi? Baiklah ia dengan cara hidup yang baik menyatakan perbuatannya oleh hikmat yang lahir dari kelemahlembutan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> But if you have bitter envy and self-seeking in your hearts, do not boast and lie against the truth. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ولكن ان كان لكم غيرة مرة وتحزب في قلوبكم فلا تفتخروا وتكذبوا على الحق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Jika kamu menaruh perasaan iri hati dan kamu mementingkan diri sendiri, janganlah kamu memegahkan diri dan janganlah berdusta melawan kebenaran!</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> This wisdom does not descend from above, but [is] earthly, sensual, demonic. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ليست هذه الحكمة نازلة من فوق بل هي ارضية نفسانية شيطانية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Itu bukanlah hikmat yang datang dari atas, tetapi dari dunia, dari nafsu manusia, dari setan-setan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> For where envy and self-seeking [exist,] confusion and every evil thing [are] there. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لانه حيث الغيرة والتحزب هناك التشويش وكل امر رديء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Sebab di mana ada iri hati dan mementingkan diri sendiri di situ ada kekacauan dan segala macam perbuatan jahat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> But the wisdom that is from above is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, willing to yield, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality and without hypocrisy. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">واما الحكمة التي من فوق فهي اولا طاهرة ثم مسالمة مترفقة مذعنة مملوءة رحمة واثمارا صالحة عديمة الريب والرياء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Tetapi hikmat yang dari atas adalah pertama-tama murni, selanjutnya pendamai, peramah, penurut, penuh belas kasihan dan buah-buah yang baik, tidak memihak dan tidak munafik.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> Now the fruit of righteousness is sown in peace by those who make peace. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">وثمر البر يزرع في السلام من الذين يفعلون السلام</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Dan buah yang terdiri dari kebenaran ditaburkan dalam damai untuk mereka yang mengadakan damai.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="4">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Where do wars and fights [come] from among you? Do [they] not [come] from your [desires for] pleasure that war in your members? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">من اين الحروب والخصومات بينكم أليست من هنا من لذّاتكم المحاربة في اعضائكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Dari manakah datangnya sengketa dan pertengkaran di antara kamu? Bukankah datangnya dari hawa nafsumu yang saling berjuang di dalam tubuhmu?</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> You lust and do not have. You murder and covet and cannot obtain. You fight and war. Yet you do not have because you do not ask. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">تشتهون ولستم تمتلكون. تقتلون وتحسدون ولستم تقدرون ان تنالوا. تخاصمون وتحاربون ولستم تمتلكون لانكم لا تطلبون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Kamu mengingini sesuatu, tetapi kamu tidak memperolehnya, lalu kamu membunuh; kamu iri hati, tetapi kamu tidak mencapai tujuanmu, lalu kamu bertengkar dan kamu berkelahi. Kamu tidak memperoleh apa-apa, karena kamu tidak berdoa.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> You ask and do not receive, because you ask amiss, that you may spend [it] on your pleasures. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">تطلبون ولستم تأخذون لانكم تطلبون رديّا لكي تنفقوا في لذّاتكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Atau kamu berdoa juga, tetapi kamu tidak menerima apa-apa, karena kamu salah berdoa, sebab yang kamu minta itu hendak kamu habiskan untuk memuaskan hawa nafsumu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Adulterers and adulteresses! Do you not know that friendship with the world is enmity with God? Whoever therefore wants to be a friend of the world makes himself an enemy of God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ايها الزناة والزواني أما تعلمون ان محبة العالم عداوة للّه. فمن اراد ان يكون محبا للعالم فقد صار عدوا للّه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Hai kamu, orang-orang yang tidak setia! Tidakkah kamu tahu, bahwa persahabatan dengan dunia adalah permusuhan dengan Allah? Jadi barangsiapa hendak menjadi sahabat dunia ini, ia menjadikan dirinya musuh Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Or do you think that the Scripture says in vain, "The Spirit who dwells in us yearns jealously"? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">ام تظنون ان الكتاب يقول باطلا. الروح الذي حل فينا يشتاق الى الحسد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Janganlah kamu menyangka, bahwa Kitab Suci tanpa alasan berkata: "Roh yang ditempatkan Allah di dalam diri kita, diingini-Nya dengan cemburu!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> But He gives more grace. Therefore He says: "God resists the proud, But gives grace to the humble." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ولكنه يعطي نعمة اعظم. لذلك يقول يقاوم الله المستكبرين واما المتواضعون فيعطيهم نعمة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Tetapi kasih karunia, yang dianugerahkan-Nya kepada kita, lebih besar dari pada itu. Karena itu Ia katakan: "Allah menentang orang yang congkak, tetapi mengasihani orang yang rendah hati."</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Therefore submit to God. Resist the devil and he will flee from you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فاخضعوا للّه. قاوموا ابليس فيهرب منكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Karena itu tunduklah kepada Allah, dan lawanlah Iblis, maka ia akan lari dari padamu!</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Draw near to God and He will draw near to you. Cleanse [your] hands, [you] sinners; and purify [your] hearts, [you] double-minded. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">اقتربوا الى الله فيقترب اليكم. نقوا ايديكم ايها الخطاة وطهروا قلوبكم يا ذوي الرأيين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Mendekatlah kepada Allah, dan Ia akan mendekat kepadamu. Tahirkanlah tanganmu, hai kamu orang-orang berdosa! dan sucikanlah hatimu, hai kamu yang mendua hati!</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Lament and mourn and weep! Let your laughter be turned to mourning and [your] joy to gloom. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">اكتئبوا ونوحوا وابكوا. ليتحول ضحككم الى نوح وفرحكم الى غم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Sadarilah kemalanganmu, berdukacita dan merataplah; hendaklah tertawamu kamu ganti dengan ratap dan sukacitamu dengan dukacita.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Humble yourselves in the sight of the Lord, and He will lift you up. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">اتضعوا قدام الرب فيرفعكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Rendahkanlah dirimu di hadapan Tuhan, dan Ia akan meninggikan kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Do not speak evil of one another, brethren. He who speaks evil of a brother and judges his brother, speaks evil of the law and judges the law. But if you judge the law, you are not a doer of the law but a judge. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لا يذم بعضكم بعضا ايها الاخوة. الذي يذم اخاه ويدين اخاه يذم الناموس ويدين الناموس. وان كنت تدين الناموس فلست عاملا بالناموس بل ديانا له.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Saudara-saudaraku, janganlah kamu saling memfitnah! Barangsiapa memfitnah saudaranya atau menghakiminya, ia mencela hukum dan menghakiminya; dan jika engkau menghakimi hukum, maka engkau bukanlah penurut hukum, tetapi hakimnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> There is one Lawgiver, who is able to save and to destroy. Who are you to judge another? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">واحد هو واضع الناموس القادر ان يخلّص ويهلك. فمن انت يا من تدين غيرك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Hanya ada satu Pembuat hukum dan Hakim, yaitu Dia yang berkuasa menyelamatkan dan membinasakan. Tetapi siapakah engkau, sehingga engkau mau menghakimi sesamamu manusia?</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Come now, you who say, "Today or tomorrow we will go to such and such a city, spend a year there, buy and sell, and make a profit"; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">هلم الآن ايها القائلون نذهب اليوم او غدا الى هذه المدينة او تلك وهناك نصرف سنة واحدة ونتجر ونربح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Jadi sekarang, hai kamu yang berkata: "Hari ini atau besok kami berangkat ke kota anu, dan di sana kami akan tinggal setahun dan berdagang serta mendapat untung",</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> whereas you do not know what [will happen] tomorrow. For what [is] your life? It is even a vapor that appears for a little time and then vanishes away. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">انتم الذين لا تعرفون امر الغد. لانه ما هي حياتكم. انها بخار يظهر قليلا ثم يضمحل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">sedang kamu tidak tahu apa yang akan terjadi besok. Apakah arti hidupmu? Hidupmu itu sama seperti uap yang sebentar saja kelihatan lalu lenyap.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Instead you [ought] to say, "If the Lord wills, we shall live and do this or that." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">عوض ان تقولوا ان شاء الرب وعشنا نفعل هذا او ذاك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Sebenarnya kamu harus berkata: "Jika Tuhan menghendakinya, kami akan hidup dan berbuat ini dan itu."</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> But now you boast in your arrogance. All such boasting is evil. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">واما الآن فانكم تفتخرون في تعظمكم. كل افتخار مثل هذا رديء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Tetapi sekarang kamu memegahkan diri dalam congkakmu, dan semua kemegahan yang demikian adalah salah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Therefore, to him who knows to do good and does not do [it,] to him it is sin. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فمن يعرف ان يعمل حسنا ولا يعمل فذلك خطية له</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Jadi jika seorang tahu bagaimana ia harus berbuat baik, tetapi ia tidak melakukannya, ia berdosa.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="5">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Come now, [you] rich, weep and howl for your miseries that are coming upon [you!] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">هلم الآن ايها الاغنياء ابكوا مولولين على شقاوتكم القادمة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Jadi sekarang hai kamu orang-orang kaya, menangislah dan merataplah atas sengsara yang akan menimpa kamu!</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Your riches are corrupted, and your garments are moth-eaten. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">غناكم قد تهرأ وثيابكم قد اكلها العث.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Kekayaanmu sudah busuk, dan pakaianmu telah dimakan ngengat!</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Your gold and silver are corroded, and their corrosion will be a witness against you and will eat your flesh like fire. You have heaped up treasure in the last days. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">ذهبكم وفضتكم قد صدئا وصدأهما يكون شهادة عليكم ويأكل لحومكم كنار. قد كنزتم في الايام الاخيرة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Emas dan perakmu sudah berkarat, dan karatnya akan menjadi kesaksian terhadap kamu dan akan memakan dagingmu seperti api. Kamu telah mengumpulkan harta pada hari-hari yang sedang berakhir.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Indeed the wages of the laborers who mowed your fields, which you kept back by fraud, cry out; and the cries of the reapers have reached the ears of the Lord of Sabaoth. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">هوذا اجرة الفعلة الذين حصدوا حقولكم المبخوسة منكم تصرخ وصياح الحصادين قد دخل الى أذني رب الجنود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Sesungguhnya telah terdengar teriakan besar, karena upah yang kamu tahan dari buruh yang telah menuai hasil ladangmu, dan telah sampai ke telinga Tuhan semesta alam keluhan mereka yang menyabit panenmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> You have lived on the earth in pleasure and luxury; you have fattened your hearts as in a day of slaughter. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">قد ترفهتم على الارض وتنعمتم وربيتم قلوبكم كما في يوم الذبح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Dalam kemewahan kamu telah hidup dan berfoya-foya di bumi, kamu telah memuaskan hatimu sama seperti pada hari penyembelihan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> You have condemned, you have murdered the just; he does not resist you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">حكمتم على البار. قتلتموه. لا يقاومكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Kamu telah menghukum, bahkan membunuh orang yang benar dan ia tidak dapat melawan kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Therefore be patient, brethren, until the coming of the Lord. See [how] the farmer waits for the precious fruit of the earth, waiting patiently for it until it receives the early and latter rain. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فتأنوا ايها الاخوة الى مجيء الرب. هوذا الفلاح ينتظر ثمر الارض الثمين متأنيا عليه حتى ينال المطر المبكر والمتأخر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Karena itu, saudara-saudara, bersabarlah sampai kepada kedatangan Tuhan! Sesungguhnya petani menantikan hasil yang berharga dari tanahnya dan ia sabar sampai telah turun hujan musim gugur dan hujan musim semi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> You also be patient. Establish your hearts, for the coming of the Lord is at hand. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فتأنوا انتم وثبتوا قلوبكم لان مجيء الرب قد اقترب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Kamu juga harus bersabar dan harus meneguhkan hatimu, karena kedatangan Tuhan sudah dekat!</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Do not grumble against one another, brethren, lest you be condemned. Behold, the Judge is standing at the door! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لا يئن بعضكم على بعض ايها الاخوة لئلا تدانوا. هوذا الديان واقف قدام الباب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Saudara-saudara, janganlah kamu bersungut-sungut dan saling mempersalahkan, supaya kamu jangan dihukum. Sesungguhnya Hakim telah berdiri di ambang pintu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> My brethren, take the prophets, who spoke in the name of the Lord, as an example of suffering and patience. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">خذوا يا اخوتي مثالا لاحتمال المشقات والاناة الانبياء الذين تكلموا باسم الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Saudara-saudara, turutilah teladan penderitaan dan kesabaran para nabi yang telah berbicara demi nama Tuhan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Indeed we count them blessed who endure. You have heard of the perseverance of Job and seen the end [intended by] the Lord -- that the Lord is very compassionate and merciful. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ها نحن نطوّب الصابرين. قد سمعتم بصبر ايوب ورأيتم عاقبة الرب. لان الرب كثير الرحمة ورأوف</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Sesungguhnya kami menyebut mereka berbahagia, yaitu mereka yang telah bertekun; kamu telah mendengar tentang ketekunan Ayub dan kamu telah tahu apa yang pada akhirnya disediakan Tuhan baginya, karena Tuhan maha penyayang dan penuh belas kasihan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> But above all, my brethren, do not swear, either by heaven or by earth or with any other oath. But let your "Yes," be "Yes," and [your] "No," "No," lest you fall into judgment. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ولكن قبل كل شيء يا اخوتي لا تحلفوا لا بالسماء ولا بالارض ولا بقسم آخر. بل لتكن نعمكم نعم ولاكم لا لئلا تقعوا تحت دينونة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Tetapi yang terutama, saudara-saudara, janganlah kamu bersumpah demi sorga maupun demi bumi atau demi sesuatu yang lain. Jika ya, hendaklah kamu katakan ya, jika tidak hendaklah kamu katakan tidak, supaya kamu jangan kena hukuman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Is anyone among you suffering? Let him pray. Is anyone cheerful? Let him sing psalms. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">أعلى احد بينكم مشقات فليصلّ. أمسرور احد فليرتل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Kalau ada seorang di antara kamu yang menderita, baiklah ia berdoa! Kalau ada seorang yang bergembira baiklah ia menyanyi!</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Is anyone among you sick? Let him call for the elders of the church, and let them pray over him, anointing him with oil in the name of the Lord. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">أمريض احد بينكم فليدع شيوخ الكنيسة فيصلّوا عليه ويدهنوه بزيت باسم الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Kalau ada seorang di antara kamu yang sakit, baiklah ia memanggil para penatua jemaat, supaya mereka mendoakan dia serta mengolesnya dengan minyak dalam nama Tuhan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> And the prayer of faith will save the sick, and the Lord will raise him up. And if he has committed sins, he will be forgiven. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">وصلاة الايمان تشفي المريض والرب يقيمه وان كان قد فعل خطية تغفر له.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Dan doa yang lahir dari iman akan menyelamatkan orang sakit itu dan Tuhan akan membangunkan dia; dan jika ia telah berbuat dosa, maka dosanya itu akan diampuni.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> Confess [your] trespasses to one another, and pray for one another, that you may be healed. The effective, fervent prayer of a righteous man avails much. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">اعترفوا بعضكم لبعض بالزلات وصلّوا بعضكم لاجل بعض لكي تشفوا. طلبة البار تقتدر كثيرا في فعلها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Karena itu hendaklah kamu saling mengaku dosamu dan saling mendoakan, supaya kamu sembuh. Doa orang yang benar, bila dengan yakin didoakan, sangat besar kuasanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Elijah was a man with a nature like ours, and he prayed earnestly that it would not rain; and it did not rain on the land for three years and six months. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">كان ايليا انسانا تحت الآلام مثلنا وصلّى صلاة ان لا تمطر فلم تمطر على الارض ثلاث سنين وستة اشهر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Elia adalah manusia biasa sama seperti kita, dan ia telah bersungguh-sungguh berdoa, supaya hujan jangan turun, dan hujanpun tidak turun di bumi selama tiga tahun dan enam bulan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> And he prayed again, and the heaven gave rain, and the earth produced its fruit. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">ثم صلّى ايضا فاعطت السماء مطرا واخرجت الارض ثمرها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Lalu ia berdoa pula dan langit menurunkan hujan dan bumipun mengeluarkan buahnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> Brethren, if anyone among you wanders from the truth, and someone turns him back, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">ايها الاخوة ان ضل احد بينكم عن الحق فردّه احد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Saudara-saudaraku, jika ada di antara kamu yang menyimpang dari kebenaran dan ada seorang yang membuat dia berbalik,</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> let him know that he who turns a sinner from the error of his way will save a soul from death and cover a multitude of sins. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">فليعلم ان من رد خاطئا عن ضلال طريقه يخلّص نفسا من الموت ويستر كثرة من الخطايا ٍ</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">ketahuilah, bahwa barangsiapa membuat orang berdosa berbalik dari jalannya yang sesat, ia akan menyelamatkan jiwa orang itu dari maut dan menutupi banyak dosa.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>