<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> The word of the LORD that came to Joel the son of Pethuel. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">قول الرب الذي صار الى يوئيل بن فثوئيل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Firman TUHAN yang datang kepada Yoel bin Petuel.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Hear this, you elders, And give ear, all you inhabitants of the land! Has [anything like] this happened in your days, Or even in the days of your fathers? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اسمعوا هذا ايها الشيوخ واصغوا يا جميع سكان الارض. هل حدث هذا في ايامكم او في ايام آبائكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Dengarlah ini, hai para tua-tua, pasanglah telinga, hai seluruh penduduk negeri! Pernahkah terjadi seperti ini dalam zamanmu, atau dalam zaman nenek moyangmu?</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Tell your children about it, [Let] your children [tell] their children, And their children another generation. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">اخبروا بنيكم عنه وبنوكم بنيهم وبنوهم دورا آخر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Ceritakanlah tentang itu kepada anak-anakmu, dan biarlah anak-anakmu menceritakannya kepada anak-anak mereka, dan anak-anak mereka kepada angkatan yang kemudian.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> What the chewing locust left, the swarming locust has eaten; What the swarming locust left, the crawling locust has eaten; And what the crawling locust left, the consuming locust has eaten. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فضلة القمص اكلها الزحّاف وفضلة الزحّاف اكلها الغوغاء وفضلة الغوغاء اكلها الطيّار</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Apa yang ditinggalkan belalang pengerip telah dimakan belalang pindahan, apa yang ditinggalkan belalang pindahan telah dimakan belalang pelompat, dan apa yang ditinggalkan belalang pelompat telah dimakan belalang pelahap.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Awake, you drunkards, and weep; And wail, all you drinkers of wine, Because of the new wine, For it has been cut off from your mouth. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">اصحوا ايها السكارى وابكوا وولولوا يا جميع شاربي الخمر على العصير لانه انقطع عن افواهكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Bangunlah, hai pemabuk, dan menangislah! Merataplah, hai semua peminum anggur karena anggur baru, sebab sudah dirampas dari mulutmu anggur itu!</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> For a nation has come up against My land, Strong, and without number; His teeth [are] the teeth of a lion, And he has the fangs of a fierce lion. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">اذ قد صعدت على ارضي امة قوية بلا عدد اسنانها اسنان الاسد ولها اضراس اللبوة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Sebab maju menyerang negeriku suatu bangsa yang kuat dan tidak terbilang banyaknya; giginya bagaikan gigi singa, dan taringnya bagaikan taring singa betina.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> He has laid waste My vine, And ruined My fig tree; He has stripped it bare and thrown [it] away; Its branches are made white. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">جعلت كرمتي خربة وتينتي متهشّمة. قد قشرتها وطرحتها فابيضّت قضبانها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Telah dibuatnya pohon anggurku menjadi musnah, dan pohon araku menjadi buntung; dikelupasnya kulitnya sama sekali dan dilemparkannya, sehingga carang-carangnya menjadi putih.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Lament like a virgin girded with sackcloth For the husband of her youth. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">نوحي يا ارضي كعروس مؤتزرة بمسح من اجل بعل صباها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Merataplah seperti anak dara yang berlilitkan kain kabung karena mempelai, kekasih masa mudanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> The grain offering and the drink offering Have been cut off from the house of the LORD; The priests mourn, who minister to the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">انقطعت التقدمة والسكيب عن بيت الرب. ناحت الكهنة خدام الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Korban sajian dan korban curahan sudah lenyap dari rumah TUHAN; dan berkabunglah para imam, yakni pelayan-pelayan TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> The field is wasted, The land mourns; For the grain is ruined, The new wine is dried up, The oil fails. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">تلف الحقل ناحت الارض لانه قد تلف القمح جف المسطار ذبل الزيت.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Ladang sudah musnah, tanah berkabung, sebab gandum sudah musnah, buah anggur sudah kering, minyak sudah menipis.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Be ashamed, you farmers, Wail, you vinedressers, For the wheat and the barley; Because the harvest of the field has perished. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">خجل الفلاحون ولول الكرّامون على الحنطة وعلى الشعير لانه قد تلف حصيد الحقل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Para petani menjadi malu, tukang-tukang kebun anggur meratap karena gandum dan karena jelai, sebab sudah musnah panen ladang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> The vine has dried up, And the fig tree has withered; The pomegranate tree, The palm tree also, And the apple tree -- All the trees of the field are withered; Surely joy has withered away from the sons of men. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">الجفنة يبست والتينة ذبلت. الرمانة والنخلة والتفاحة كل اشجار الحقل يبست. انه قد يبست البهجة من بني البشر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Pohon anggur sudah kering dan pohon ara sudah merana; pohon delima, juga pohon korma dan pohon apel, segala pohon di padang sudah mengering. Sungguh, kegirangan melayu dari antara anak-anak manusia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Gird yourselves and lament, you priests; Wail, you who minister before the altar; Come, lie all night in sackcloth, You who minister to my God; For the grain offering and the drink offering Are withheld from the house of your God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">تنطّقوا ونوحوا ايها الكهنة. ولولوا يا خدام المذبح. ادخلوا بيتوا بالمسوح يا خدام الهي لانه قد امتنع عن بيت الهكم التقدمة والسكيب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Lilitkanlah kain kabung dan mengeluhlah, hai para imam; merataplah, hai para pelayan mezbah; masuklah, bermalamlah dengan memakai kain kabung, hai para pelayan Allahku, sebab sudah ditahan dari rumah Allahmu, korban sajian dan korban curahan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Consecrate a fast, Call a sacred assembly; Gather the elders [And] all the inhabitants of the land [Into] the house of the LORD your God, And cry out to the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">قدسوا صوما نادوا باعتكاف اجمعوا الشيوخ جميع سكان الارض الى بيت الرب الهكم واصرخوا الى الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Adakanlah puasa yang kudus, maklumkanlah perkumpulan raya; kumpulkanlah para tua-tua dan seluruh penduduk negeri ke rumah TUHAN, Allahmu, dan berteriaklah kepada TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Alas for the day! For the day of the LORD [is] at hand; It shall come as destruction from the Almighty. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">آه على اليوم لان يوم الرب قريب. ياتي كخراب من القادر على كل شيء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Wahai, hari itu! Sungguh, hari TUHAN sudah dekat, datangnya sebagai pemusnahan dari Yang Mahakuasa.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> Is not the food cut off before our eyes, Joy and gladness from the house of our God? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">أما انقطع الطعام تجاه عيوننا. الفرح والابتهاج عن بيت الهنا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Bukankah di depan mata kita sudah lenyap makanan, sukaria dan sorak-sorai dari rumah Allah kita?</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> The seed shrivels under the clods, Storehouses are in shambles; Barns are broken down, For the grain has withered. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">عفّنت الحبوب تحت مدرها. خلت الاهراء. انهدمت المخازن لانه قد يبس القمح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Biji-bijian menjadi kering di dalam tanah, lumbung-lumbung sudah licin tandas, rengkiang-rengkiang sudah runtuh, sebab gandum sudah habis.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> How the animals groan! The herds of cattle are restless, Because they have no pasture; Even the flocks of sheep suffer punishment. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">كم تئن البهائم هامت قطعان البقر لان ليس لها مرعى حتى قطعان الغنم تفنى.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Betapa mengeluhnya hewan dan gempar kawanan-kawanan lembu, sebab tidak ada lagi padang rumput baginya; juga kawanan kambing domba terkejut.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> O LORD, to You I cry out; For fire has devoured the open pastures, And a flame has burned all the trees of the field. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">اليك يا رب اصرخ لان نارا قد اكلت مراعي البرية ولهيبا احرق جميع اشجار الحقل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Kepada-Mu, ya TUHAN, aku berseru, sebab api telah memakan habis tanah gembalaan di padang gurun, dan nyala api telah menghanguskan segala pohon di padang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> The beasts of the field also cry out to You, For the water brooks are dried up, And fire has devoured the open pastures. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">حتى بهائم الصحراء تنظر اليك لان جداول المياه قد جفّت والنار اكلت مراعي البرية</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Juga binatang-binatang di padang menjerit karena rindu kepada-Mu, sebab wadi telah kering, dan apipun telah memakan habis tanah gembalaan di padang gurun.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="2">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Blow the trumpet in Zion, And sound an alarm in My holy mountain! Let all the inhabitants of the land tremble; For the day of the LORD is coming, For it is at hand: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">اضربوا بالبوق في صهيون صوّتوا في جبل قدسي. ليرتعد جميع سكان الارض لان يوم الرب قادم لانه قريب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Tiuplah sangkakala di Sion dan berteriaklah di gunung-Ku yang kudus! Biarlah gemetar seluruh penduduk negeri, sebab hari TUHAN datang, sebab hari itu sudah dekat;</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> A day of darkness and gloominess, A day of clouds and thick darkness, Like the morning [clouds] spread over the mountains. A people [come,] great and strong, The like of whom has never been; Nor will there ever be any [such] after them, Even for many successive generations. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">يوم ظلام وقتام يوم غيم وضباب مثل الفجر ممتدا على الجبال. شعب كثير وقوي لم يكن نظيره منذ الازل ولا يكون ايضا بعده الى سني دور فدور.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">suatu hari gelap gulita dan kelam kabut, suatu hari berawan dan kelam pekat; seperti fajar di atas gunung-gunung terbentang suatu bangsa yang banyak dan kuat, yang serupa itu tidak pernah ada sejak purbakala, dan tidak akan ada lagi sesudah itu turun-temurun, pada masa yang akan datang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> A fire devours before them, And behind them a flame burns; The land [is] like the Garden of Eden before them, And behind them a desolate wilderness; Surely nothing shall escape them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">قدامه نار تأكل وخلفه لهيب يحرق. الارض قدامه كجنة عدن وخلفه قفر خرب ولا تكون منه نجاة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Di depannya api memakan habis, di belakangnya nyala api berkobar. Tanah di depannya seperti Taman Eden, tetapi di belakangnya padang gurun tandus, dan sama sekali tidak ada yang dapat luput.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Their appearance is like the appearance of horses; And like swift steeds, so they run. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">كمنظر الخيل منظره ومثل الافراس يركضون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Rupanya seperti kuda, dan seperti kuda balapan mereka berlari.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> With a noise like chariots Over mountaintops they leap, Like the noise of a flaming fire that devours the stubble, Like a strong people set in battle array. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">كصريف المركبات على رؤوس الجبال يثبون. كزفير لهيب نار تأكل قشا. كقوم اقوياء مصطفين للقتال.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Seperti gemertaknya kereta-kereta, mereka melompat-lompat di atas puncak gunung-gunung; seperti geletiknya nyala api yang memakan habis jerami; seperti suatu bangsa yang kuat, teratur barisannya untuk berperang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Before them the people writhe in pain; All faces are drained of color. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">منه ترتعد الشعوب. كل الوجوه تجمع حمرة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Terhadapnya bangsa-bangsa gemetar, segala muka bertambah menjadi pucat pasi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> They run like mighty men, They climb the wall like men of war; Every one marches in formation, And they do not break ranks. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">يجرون كابطال. يصعدون السور كرجال الحرب ويمشون كل واحد في طريقه ولا يغيّرون سبلهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Seperti pahlawan mereka berlari, seperti prajurit mereka naik tembok; dan mereka masing-masing berjalan terus dengan tidak membelok dari jalannya;</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> They do not push one another; Every one marches in his own column. Though they lunge between the weapons, They are not cut down. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ولا يزاحم بعضهم بعضا يمشون كل واحد في سبيله وبين الاسلحة يقعون ولا ينكسرون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">mereka tidak berdesak-desakan, mereka berjalan terus masing-masing di jalannya; mereka menerobos pertahanan dengan tombak, mereka tidak membiarkan barisannya terputus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> They run to and fro in the city, They run on the wall; They climb into the houses, They enter at the windows like a thief. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">يتراكضون في المدينة يجرون على السور يصعدون الى البيوت يدخلون من الكوى كاللص.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Mereka menyerbu ke dalam kota, mereka berlari ke atas tembok, mereka memanjat ke dalam rumah-rumah, mereka masuk melalui jendela-jendela seperti pencuri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> The earth quakes before them, The heavens tremble; The sun and moon grow dark, And the stars diminish their brightness. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">قدامه ترتعد الارض وترجف السماء. الشمس والقمر يظلمان والنجوم تحجز لمعانها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Di depannya bumi gemetar, langit bergoncang; matahari dan bulan menjadi gelap, dan bintang-bintang menghilangkan cahayanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> The LORD gives voice before His army, For His camp is very great; For strong [is the One] who executes His word. For the day of the LORD [is] great and very terrible; Who can endure it? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">والرب يعطي صوته امام جيشه. ان عسكره كثير جدا. فان صانع قوله قوي لان يوم الرب عظيم ومخوف جدا فمن يطيقه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Dan TUHAN memperdengarkan suara-Nya di depan tentara-Nya. Pasukan-Nya sangat banyak dan pelaksana firman-Nya kuat. Betapa hebat dan sangat dahsyat hari TUHAN! Siapakah yang dapat menahannya?</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> " Now, therefore," says the LORD, "Turn to Me with all your heart, With fasting, with weeping, and with mourning." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ولكن الآن يقول الرب ارجعوا اليّ بكل قلوبكم وبالصوم والبكاء والنوح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">"Tetapi sekarang juga," demikianlah firman TUHAN, "berbaliklah kepada-Ku dengan segenap hatimu, dengan berpuasa, dengan menangis dan dengan mengaduh."</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> So rend your heart, and not your garments; Return to the LORD your God, For He [is] gracious and merciful, Slow to anger, and of great kindness; And He relents from doing harm. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ومزقوا قلوبكم لا ثيابكم وارجعوا الى الرب الهكم لانه رؤوف رحيم بطيء الغضب وكثير الرأفة ويندم على الشر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Koyakkanlah hatimu dan jangan pakaianmu, berbaliklah kepada TUHAN, Allahmu, sebab Ia pengasih dan penyayang, panjang sabar dan berlimpah kasih setia, dan Ia menyesal karena hukuman-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Who knows [if] He will turn and relent, And leave a blessing behind Him -- A grain offering and a drink offering For the LORD your God? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">لعله يرجع ويندم فيبقي وراءه بركة تقدمة وسكيبا للرب الهكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Siapa tahu, mungkin Ia mau berbalik dan menyesal, dan ditinggalkan-Nya berkat, menjadi korban sajian dan korban curahan bagi TUHAN, Allahmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Blow the trumpet in Zion, Consecrate a fast, Call a sacred assembly; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">اضربوا بالبوق في صهيون قدسوا صوما نادوا باعتكاف.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Tiuplah sangkakala di Sion, adakanlah puasa yang kudus, maklumkanlah perkumpulan raya;</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> Gather the people, Sanctify the congregation, Assemble the elders, Gather the children and nursing babes; Let the bridegroom go out from his chamber, And the bride from her dressing room. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">اجمعوا الشعب قدسوا الجماعة احشدوا الشيوخ اجمعوا الاطفال وراضعي الثدي ليخرج العريس من مخدعه والعروس من حجلتها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">kumpulkanlah bangsa ini, kuduskanlah jemaah, himpunkanlah orang-orang yang tua, kumpulkanlah anak-anak, bahkan anak-anak yang menyusu; baiklah penganten laki-laki keluar dari kamarnya, dan penganten perempuan dari kamar tidurnya;</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Let the priests, who minister to the LORD, Weep between the porch and the altar; Let them say, "Spare Your people, O LORD, And do not give Your heritage to reproach, That the nations should rule over them. Why should they say among the peoples, 'Where [is] their God?' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ليبك الكهنة خدام الرب بين الرواق والمذبح ويقولوا اشفق يا رب على شعبك ولا تسلم ميراثك للعار حتى تجعلهم الامم مثلا. لماذا يقولون بين الشعوب اين الههم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">baiklah para imam, pelayan-pelayan TUHAN, menangis di antara balai depan dan mezbah, dan berkata: "Sayangilah, ya TUHAN, umat-Mu, dan janganlah biarkan milik-Mu sendiri menjadi cela, sehingga bangsa-bangsa menyindir kepada mereka. Mengapa orang berkata di antara bangsa: Di mana Allah mereka?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> Then the LORD will be zealous for His land, And pity His people. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فيغار الرب لارضه ويرقّ لشعبه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">TUHAN menjadi cemburu karena tanah-Nya, dan Ia belas kasihan kepada umat-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> The LORD will answer and say to His people, "Behold, I will send you grain and new wine and oil, And you will be satisfied by them; I will no longer make you a reproach among the nations. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">ويجيب الرب ويقول لشعبه هانذا مرسل لكم قمحا ومسطارا وزيتا لتشبعوا منها ولا اجعلكم ايضا عارا بين الامم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">TUHAN menjawab, kata-Nya kepada umat-Nya: "Sesungguhnya, Aku akan mengirim kepadamu gandum, anggur dan minyak, dan kamu akan kenyang memakannya; Aku tidak akan menyerahkan kamu lagi menjadi cela di antara bangsa-bangsa.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> "But I will remove far from you the northern [army,] And will drive him away into a barren and desolate land, With his face toward the eastern sea And his back toward the western sea; His stench will come up, And his foul odor will rise, Because he has done monstrous things." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">والشمالي ابعده عنكم واطرده الى ارض ناشفة ومقفرة مقدمته الى البحر الشرقي وساقته الى البحر الغربي فيصعد نتنه وتطلع زهمته لانه قد تصلّف في عمله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Yang datang dari utara itu akan Kujauhkan dari padamu, dan akan Kuusir ke suatu negeri kering dan tandus, barisan mukanya ke laut timur, dan barisan belakangnya ke laut barat, maka bau busuknya dan bau anyirnya akan naik, sebab ia telah melakukan perkara yang besar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> Fear not, O land; Be glad and rejoice, For the LORD has done marvelous things! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">لا تخافي ايتها الارض ابتهجي وافرحي لان الرب يعظّم عمله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Jangan takut, hai tanah, bersorak-soraklah dan bersukacitalah, sebab juga TUHAN telah melakukan perkara yang besar!</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> Do not be afraid, you beasts of the field; For the open pastures are springing up, And the tree bears its fruit; The fig tree and the vine yield their strength. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">لا تخافي يا بهائم الصحراء فان مراعي البرية تنبت لان الاشجار تحمل ثمرها التينة والكرمة تعطيان قوتهما.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Jangan takut, hai binatang-binatang di padang, sebab tanah gembalaan di padang gurun menghijau, pohon menghasilkan buahnya, pohon ara dan pohon anggur memberi kekayaannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> Be glad then, you children of Zion, And rejoice in the LORD your God; For He has given you the former rain faithfully, And He will cause the rain to come down for you -- The former rain, And the latter rain in the first [month.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">ويا بني صهيون ابتهجوا وافرحوا بالرب الهكم لانه يعطيكم المطر المبكر على حقه وينزل عليكم مطرا مبكرا ومتأخرا في اول الوقت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Hai bani Sion, bersorak-soraklah dan bersukacitalah karena TUHAN, Allahmu! Sebab telah diberikan-Nya kepadamu hujan pada awal musim dengan adilnya, dan diturunkan-Nya kepadamu hujan, hujan pada awal dan hujan pada akhir musim seperti dahulu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> The threshing floors shall be full of wheat, And the vats shall overflow with new wine and oil. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">فتملأ البيادر حنطة وتفيض حياض المعاصر خمرا وزيتا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">Tempat-tempat pengirikan menjadi penuh dengan gandum, dan tempat pemerasan kelimpahan anggur dan minyak.</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> "So I will restore to you the years that the swarming locust has eaten, The crawling locust, The consuming locust, And the chewing locust, My great army which I sent among you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">واعوض لكم عن السنين التي اكلها الجراد الغوغاء والطيّار والقمص جيشي العظيم الذي ارسلته عليكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Aku akan memulihkan kepadamu tahun-tahun yang hasilnya dimakan habis oleh belalang pindahan, belalang pelompat, belalang pelahap dan belalang pengerip, tentara-Ku yang besar yang Kukirim ke antara kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26"> You shall eat in plenty and be satisfied, And praise the name of the LORD your God, Who has dealt wondrously with you; And My people shall never be put to shame. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">فتأكلون اكلا وتشبعون وتسبّحون اسم الرب الهكم الذي صنع معكم عجبا ولا يخزى شعبي الى الابد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">Maka kamu akan makan banyak-banyak dan menjadi kenyang, dan kamu akan memuji-muji nama TUHAN, Allahmu, yang telah memperlakukan kamu dengan ajaib; dan umat-Ku tidak akan menjadi malu lagi untuk selama-lamanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27"> Then you shall know that I [am] in the midst of Israel: I [am] the LORD your God And there is no other. My people shall never be put to shame. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">وتعلمون اني انا في وسط اسرائيل واني انا الرب الهكم وليس غيري ولا يخزى شعبي الى الابد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">Kamu akan mengetahui bahwa Aku ini ada di antara orang Israel, dan bahwa Aku ini, TUHAN, adalah Allahmu dan tidak ada yang lain; dan umat-Ku tidak akan menjadi malu lagi untuk selama-lamanya."</language></verse>
			<verse num="28"><language id="English" verse="28"> " And it shall come to pass afterward That I will pour out My Spirit on all flesh; Your sons and your daughters shall prophesy, Your old men shall dream dreams, Your young men shall see visions. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="28">ويكون بعد ذلك اني اسكب روحي على كل بشر فيتنبأ بنوكم وبناتكم ويحلم شيوخكم احلاما ويرى شبابكم رؤى.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="28">"Kemudian dari pada itu akan terjadi, bahwa Aku akan mencurahkan Roh-Ku ke atas semua manusia, maka anak-anakmu laki-laki dan perempuan akan bernubuat; orang-orangmu yang tua akan mendapat mimpi, teruna-terunamu akan mendapat penglihatan-penglihatan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="29"><language id="English" verse="29"> And also on [My] menservants and on [My] maidservants I will pour out My Spirit in those days. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="29">وعلى العبيد ايضا وعلى الإماء اسكب روحي في تلك الايام</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="29">Juga ke atas hamba-hambamu laki-laki dan perempuan akan Kucurahkan Roh-Ku pada hari-hari itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="30"><language id="English" verse="30"> "And I will show wonders in the heavens and in the earth: Blood and fire and pillars of smoke. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="30">واعطي عجائب في السماء والارض دما ونارا واعمدة دخان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="30">Aku akan mengadakan mujizat-mujizat di langit dan di bumi: darah dan api dan gumpalan-gumpalan asap.</language></verse>
			<verse num="31"><language id="English" verse="31"> The sun shall be turned into darkness, And the moon into blood, Before the coming of the great and awesome day of the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="31">تتحول الشمس الى ظلمة والقمر الى دم قبل ان يجيء يوم الرب العظيم المخوف.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="31">Matahari akan berubah menjadi gelap gulita dan bulan menjadi darah sebelum datangnya hari TUHAN yang hebat dan dahsyat itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="32"><language id="English" verse="32"> And it shall come to pass [That] whoever calls on the name of the LORD Shall be saved. For in Mount Zion and in Jerusalem there shall be deliverance, As the LORD has said, Among the remnant whom the LORD calls. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="32">ويكون ان كل من يدعو باسم الرب ينجو. لانه في جبل صهيون وفي اورشليم تكون نجاة. كما قال الرب. وبين الباقين من يدعوه الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="32">Dan barangsiapa yang berseru kepada nama TUHAN akan diselamatkan, sebab di gunung Sion dan di Yerusalem akan ada keselamatan, seperti yang telah difirmankan TUHAN; dan setiap orang yang dipanggil TUHAN akan termasuk orang-orang yang terlepas."</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="3">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> "For behold, in those days and at that time, When I bring back the captives of Judah and Jerusalem, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">لانه هوذا في تلك الايام وفي ذلك الوقت عندما ارد سبي يهوذا واورشليم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">"Sebab sesungguhnya pada hari-hari itu dan pada waktu itu, apabila Aku memulihkan keadaan Yehuda dan Yerusalem,</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> I will also gather all nations, And bring them down to the Valley of Jehoshaphat; And I will enter into judgment with them there On account of My people, My heritage Israel, Whom they have scattered among the nations; They have also divided up My land. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اجمع كل الامم وانزلهم الى وادي يهوشافاط واحاكمهم هناك على شعبي وميراثي اسرائيل الذين بدّدوهم بين الامم وقسموا ارضي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Aku akan mengumpulkan segala bangsa dan akan membawa mereka turun ke lembah Yosafat; Aku akan berperkara dengan mereka di sana mengenai umat-Ku dan milik-Ku sendiri, Israel, oleh karena mereka mencerai-beraikannya ke antara bangsa-bangsa dan membagi-bagi tanah-Ku,</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> They have cast lots for My people, Have given a boy [as payment] for a harlot, And sold a girl for wine, that they may drink. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">والقوا قرعة على شعبي واعطوا الصبي بزانية وباعوا البنت بخمر ليشربوا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">oleh karena mereka membuang undi mengenai umat-Ku, menyerahkan seorang anak laki-laki karena seorang sundal, dan menjual seorang anak perempuan karena anggur untuk diminum.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> " Indeed, what have you to do with Me, O Tyre and Sidon, and all the coasts of Philistia? Will you retaliate against Me? But if you retaliate against Me, Swiftly and speedily I will return your retaliation upon your own head; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">وماذا انتنّ لي يا صور وصيدون وجميع دائرة فلسطين. هل تكافئونني عن العمل أم هل تصنعون بي شيئا. سريعا بالعجل ارد عملكم على رؤوسكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Lagi apakah sangkut pautmu dengan Aku, hai Tirus dan Sidon dan seluruh wilayah Filistin? Apakah kamu ini hendak membalas perbuatan-Ku? Apabila kamu melakukan sesuatu terhadap Aku, maka dengan cepat, dengan segera Aku akan membalikkan perbuatanmu itu kepadamu sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Because you have taken My silver and My gold, And have carried into your temples My prized possessions. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">لانكم اخذتم فضتي وذهبي وادخلتم نفائسي الجيدة الى هياكلكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Oleh karena kamu telah mengambil perak-Ku dan emas-Ku dan telah membawa barang-barang-Ku yang berharga yang indah-indah ke tempat-tempat ibadahmu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Also the people of Judah and the people of Jerusalem You have sold to the Greeks, That you may remove them far from their borders. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">وبعتم بني يهوذا وبني اورشليم لبني الياوانيين لكي تبعدوهم عن تخومهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">dan telah menjual orang-orang Yehuda dan orang-orang Yerusalem kepada orang Yunani dengan maksud menjauhkan mereka dari daerah mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> "Behold, I will raise them Out of the place to which you have sold them, And will return your retaliation upon your own head. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">هانذا انهضهم من الموضع الذي بعتموهم اليه وارد عملكم على رؤوسكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Sesungguhnya Aku akan menggerakkan mereka dari tempat ke mana kamu menjual mereka, dan Aku akan membalikkan perbuatanmu itu ke atas kepalamu sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> I will sell your sons and your daughters Into the hand of the people of Judah, And they will sell them to the Sabeans, To a people far off; For the LORD has spoken." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">وابيع بنيكم وبناتكم بيد بني يهوذا ليبيعوهم للسبائيين لأمة بعيدة لان الرب قد تكلم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Aku akan menjual anak-anakmu laki-laki dan perempuan kepada orang-orang Yehuda dan mereka akan menjual anak-anakmu itu kepada orang-orang Syeba, kepada suatu bangsa yang jauh, sebab TUHAN telah mengatakannya."</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Proclaim this among the nations: "Prepare for war! Wake up the mighty men, Let all the men of war draw near, Let them come up. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">نادوا بهذا بين الامم. قدسوا حربا انهضوا الابطال ليتقدم ويصعد كل رجال الحرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Maklumkanlah hal ini di antara bangsa-bangsa: bersiaplah untuk peperangan, gerakkanlah para pahlawan; suruhlah semua prajurit tampil dan maju!</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Beat your plowshares into swords And your pruning hooks into spears; Let the weak say, 'I [am] strong.' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">اطبعوا سكّاتكم سيوفا ومناجلكم رماحا. ليقل الضعيف بطل انا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Tempalah mata bajakmu menjadi pedang dan pisau-pisau pemangkasmu menjadi tombak; baiklah orang yang tidak berdaya berkata: "Aku ini pahlawan!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Assemble and come, all you nations, And gather together all around. Cause Your mighty ones to go down there, O LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">اسرعوا وهلموا يا جميع الامم من كل ناحية واجتمعوا. الى هناك أنزل يا رب ابطالك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Bergeraklah dan datanglah, hai segala bangsa dari segenap penjuru, dan berkumpullah ke sana! Bawalah turun, ya TUHAN, pahlawan-pahlawan-M</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> "Let the nations be wakened, and come up to the Valley of Jehoshaphat; For there I will sit to judge all the surrounding nations. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">تنهض وتصعد الامم الى وادي يهوشافاط لاني هناك اجلس لاحاكم جميع الامم من كل ناحية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Baiklah bangsa-bangsa bergerak dan maju ke lembah Yosafat, sebab di sana Aku akan duduk untuk menghakimi segala bangsa dari segenap penjuru.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Put in the sickle, for the harvest is ripe. Come, go down; For the winepress is full, The vats overflow -- For their wickedness [is] great." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ارسلوا المنجل لان الحصيد قد نضج. هلموا دوسوا لانه قد امتلأت المعصرة. فاضت الحياض لان شرهم كثير</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Ayunkanlah sabit, sebab sudah masak tuaian; marilah, iriklah, sebab sudah penuh tempat anggur; tempat-tempat pemerasan kelimpahan, sebab banyak kejahatan mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Multitudes, multitudes in the valley of decision! For the day of the LORD [is] near in the valley of decision. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">جماهير جماهير في وادي القضاء لان يوم الرب قريب في وادي القضاء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Banyak orang, banyak orang di lembah penentuan! Ya, sudah dekat hari TUHAN di lembah penentuan!</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> The sun and moon will grow dark, And the stars will diminish their brightness. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">الشمس والقمر يظلمان والنجوم تحجز لمعانها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Matahari dan bulan menjadi gelap, dan bintang-bintang menghilangkan cahayanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> The LORD also will roar from Zion, And utter His voice from Jerusalem; The heavens and earth will shake; But the LORD will be a shelter for His people, And the strength of the children of Israel. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">والرب من صهيون يزمجر ومن اورشليم يعطي صوته فترجف السماء والارض. ولكن الرب ملجأ لشعبه وحصن لبني اسرائيل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">TUHAN mengaum dari Sion, dari Yerusalem Ia memperdengarkan suara-Nya, dan langit dan bumi bergoncang. Tetapi TUHAN adalah tempat perlindungan bagi umat-Nya, dan benteng bagi orang Israel.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> "So you shall know that I [am] the LORD your God, Dwelling in Zion My holy mountain. Then Jerusalem shall be holy, And no aliens shall ever pass through her again." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فتعرفون اني انا الرب الهكم ساكنا في صهيون جبل قدسي وتكون اورشليم مقدسة ولا يجتاز فيها الاعاجم في ما بعد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">"Maka kamu akan mengetahui bahwa Aku, TUHAN, adalah Allahmu, yang diam di Sion, gunung-Ku yang kudus. Dan Yerusalem akan menjadi kudus, dan orang-orang luar tidak akan melintasinya lagi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> And it will come to pass in that day [That] the mountains shall drip with new wine, The hills shall flow with milk, And all the brooks of Judah shall be flooded with water; A fountain shall flow from the house of the LORD And water the Valley of Acacias. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">ويكون في ذلك اليوم ان الجبال تقطر عصيرا والتلال تفيض لبنا وجميع ينابيع يهوذا تفيض ماء ومن بيت الرب يخرج ينبوع ويسقي وادي السنط.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Pada waktu itu akan terjadi, bahwa gunung-gunung akan meniriskan anggur baru, bukit-bukit akan mengalirkan susu, dan segala sungai Yehuda akan mengalirkan air; mata air akan terbit dari rumah TUHAN dan akan membasahi lembah Sitim.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> "Egypt shall be a desolation, And Edom a desolate wilderness, Because of violence [against] the people of Judah, For they have shed innocent blood in their land. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">مصر تصير خرابا وادوم تصير قفرا خربا من اجل ظلمهم لبني يهوذا الذين سفكوا دما بريئا في ارضهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Mesir akan menjadi sunyi sepi, dan Edom akan menjadi padang gurun tandus, oleh sebab kekerasan terhadap keturunan Yehuda, oleh karena mereka telah menumpahkan darah orang yang tak bersalah di tanahnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> But Judah shall abide forever, And Jerusalem from generation to generation. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">ولكن يهوذا تسكن الى الابد واورشليم الى دور فدور.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Tetapi Yehuda tetap didiami untuk selama-lamanya dan Yerusalem turun-temurun.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> "For I will acquit them of the guilt of bloodshed, whom I had not acquitted; For the LORD dwells in Zion." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">وابرّئ دمهم الذي لم ابرّئه والرب يسكن في صهيون</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Aku akan membalas darah mereka yang belum Kubalas; TUHAN tetap diam di Sion."</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>