<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> The burden against Nineveh. The book of the vision of Nahum the Elkoshite. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وحي على نينوى. سفر رؤيا ناحوم الالقوشي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Ucapan ilahi tentang Niniwe. Kitab penglihatan Nahum, orang Elkosh.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> God [is] jealous, and the LORD avenges; The LORD avenges and [is] furious. The LORD will take vengeance on His adversaries, And He reserves [wrath] for His enemies; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">الرب اله غيور ومنتقم. الرب منتقم وذو سخط. الرب منتقم من مبغضيه وحافظ غضبه على اعدائه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">TUHAN itu Allah yang cemburu dan pembalas, TUHAN itu pembalas dan penuh kehangatan amarah. TUHAN itu pembalas kepada para lawan-Nya dan pendendam kepada para musuh-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> The LORD [is] slow to anger and great in power, And will not at all acquit [the wicked.] The LORD has His way In the whirlwind and in the storm, And the clouds [are] the dust of His feet. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">الرب بطيء الغضب وعظيم القدرة ولكنه لا يبرئ البتة. الرب في الزوبعة وفي العاصف طريقه والسحاب غبار رجليه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">TUHAN itu panjang sabar dan besar kuasa, tetapi Ia tidak sekali-kali membebaskan dari hukuman orang yang bersalah. Ia berjalan dalam puting beliung dan badai, dan awan adalah debu kaki-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> He rebukes the sea and makes it dry, And dries up all the rivers. Bashan and Carmel wither, And the flower of Lebanon wilts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ينتهر البحر فينشفه ويجفف جميع الانهار. يذبل باشان والكرمل وزهر لبنان يذبل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Ia menghardik laut dan mengeringkannya, dan segala sungai dijadikan-Nya kering. Basan dan Karmel menjadi merana dan kembang Libanon menjadi layu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> The mountains quake before Him, The hills melt, And the earth heaves at His presence, Yes, the world and all who dwell in it. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">الجبال ترجف منه والتلال تذوب والارض ترفع من وجهه والعالم وكل الساكنين فيه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Gunung-gunung gemetar terhadap Dia, dan bukit-bukit mencair. Bumi menjadi sunyi sepi di hadapan-Nya, dunia serta seluruh penduduknya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Who can stand before His indignation? And who can endure the fierceness of His anger? His fury is poured out like fire, And the rocks are thrown down by Him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">من يقف امام سخطه ومن يقوم في حمو غضبه. غيظه ينسكب كالنار والصخور تنهدم منه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Siapakah yang tahan berdiri menghadapi geram-Nya? Dan siapakah yang tahan tegak terhadap murka-Nya yang bernyala-nyala? Kehangatan amarah-Nya tercurah seperti api, dan gunung-gunung batu menjadi roboh di hadapan-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> The LORD [is] good, A stronghold in the day of trouble; And He knows those who trust in Him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">صالح هو الرب حصن في يوم الضيق وهو يعرف المتوكلين عليه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">TUHAN itu baik; Ia adalah tempat pengungsian pada waktu kesusahan; Ia mengenal orang-orang yang berlindung kepada-Nya</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> But with an overflowing flood He will make an utter end of its place, And darkness will pursue His enemies. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ولكن بطوفان عابر يصنع هلاكا تاما لموضعها واعداؤه يتبعهم ظلام</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">dan menyeberangkan mereka pada waktu banjir. Ia menghabisi sama sekali orang-orang yang bangkit melawan Dia, dan musuh-Nya dihalau-Nya ke dalam gelap.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> What do you conspire against the LORD? He will make an utter end [of it.] Affliction will not rise up a second time. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ماذا تفتكرون على الرب. هو صانع هلاكا تاما. لا يقوم الضيق مرتين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Apakah maksudmu menentang TUHAN? Ia akan menghabisi sama sekali; kesengsaraan tidak akan timbul dua kali!</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> For while tangled [like] thorns, And while drunken [like] drunkards, They shall be devoured like stubble fully dried. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فانهم وهم مشتبكون مثل الشوك وسكرانون كمن خمرهم يؤكلون كالقش اليابس بالكمال.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Sebab merekapun akan lenyap seperti duri yang berjalin-jalin, dimakan habis seperti jerami kering.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> From you comes forth [one] Who plots evil against the LORD, A wicked counselor. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">منك خرج المفتكر على الرب شرا المشير بالهلاك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Bukankah dari padamu muncul orang yang merancang kejahatan terhadap TUHAN, orang yang memberi nasihat dursila?</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Thus says the LORD: "Though [they are] safe, and likewise many, Yet in this manner they will be cut down When he passes through. Though I have afflicted you, I will afflict you no more; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">هكذا قال الرب. ان كانوا سالمين وكثيرين هكذا فهكذا يجزّون فيعبر. اذللتك. لا اذلّك ثانية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Beginilah firman TUHAN: "Sekalipun mereka utuh dan begitu banyak jumlahnya, tetapi mereka akan hilang terbabat dan mati binasa; sekalipun Aku telah merendahkan engkau, tetapi Aku tidak akan merendahkan engkau lagi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> For now I will break off his yoke from you, And burst your bonds apart." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">والآن اكسر نيره عنك واقطع ربطك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Sekarang, Aku akan mematahkan gandarnya yang memberati engkau, dan akan memutuskan belenggu-belenggu yang mengikat engkau."</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> The LORD has given a command concerning you: "Your name shall be perpetuated no longer. Out of the house of your gods I will cut off the carved image and the molded image. I will dig your grave, For you are vile." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ولكن قد اوصى عنك الرب لا يزرع من اسمك في ما بعد. اني اقطع من بيت الهك التماثيل المنحوتة والمسبوكة. اجعله قبرك لانك صرت حقيرا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Terhadap engkau, inilah perintah TUHAN: "Tidak akan ada lagi keturunan dengan namamu. Dari rumah allahmu Aku akan melenyapkan patung pahatan dan patung tuangan; kuburmu akan Kusediakan, sebab engkau hina."</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Behold, on the mountains The feet of him who brings good tidings, Who proclaims peace! O Judah, keep your appointed feasts, Perform your vows. For the wicked one shall no more pass through you; He is utterly cut off. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">هوذا على الجبال قدما مبشّر مناد بالسلام عيّدي يا يهوذا اعيادك اوفي نذورك فانه لا يعود يعبر فيك ايضا المهلك. قد انقرض كله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Lihatlah! Di atas gunung-gunung berjalan orang yang membawa berita, yang mengabarkan berita damai sejahtera. Rayakanlah hari rayamu, hai Yehuda, bayarlah nazarmu! Sebab tidak akan datang lagi orang dursila menyerang engkau; ia telah dilenyapkan sama sekali!</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="2">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> He who scatters has come up before your face. Man the fort! Watch the road! Strengthen [your] flanks! Fortify [your] power mightily. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">قد ارتفعت المقمعة على وجهك. احرس الحصن راقب الطريق شدّد الحقوين مكّن القوة جدا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Pembongkar maju terhadap engkau; adakan penjagaan di benteng, mengintailah di jalan, ikatlah pinggangmu teguh-teguh, kumpulkanlah segala kekuatan!</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> For the LORD will restore the excellence of Jacob Like the excellence of Israel, For the emptiers have emptied them out And ruined their vine branches. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فان الرب يرد عظمة يعقوب كعظمة اسرائيل لان السالبين قد سلبوهم واتلفوا قضبان كرومهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Sungguh, TUHAN memulihkan kebanggaan Yakub, seperti kebanggaan Israel; sebab perusak telah merusakkannya dan telah membinasakan carang-carangnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> The shields of his mighty men [are] made red, The valiant men [are] in scarlet. The chariots [come] with flaming torches In the day of his preparation, And the spears are brandished. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">ترس ابطاله محمّر. رجال الجيش قرمزيّون. المركبات بنار الفولاذ في يوم اعداده. والسرو يهتزّ.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Perisai para pahlawannya berwarna merah, prajuritnya berpakaian kirmizi; kereta berkilat-kilat seperti api suluh pada hari ia melengkapinya, dan kuda-kuda penuh gelisah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> The chariots rage in the streets, They jostle one another in the broad roads; They seem like torches, They run like lightning. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">تهيج المركبات في الازقة. تتراكض في الساحات. منظرها كمصابيح. تجري كالبروق</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Kereta melaju galak di jalan, kejar-mengejar di lapangan; kelihatannya seperti suluh, berpacu seperti kilat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> He remembers his nobles; They stumble in their walk; They make haste to her walls, And the defense is prepared. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">يذكر عظماءه. يتعثرون في مشيهم. يسرعون الى سورها وقد اقيمت المترسة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Pasukan-pasukan istimewa dikerahkan, mereka tersandung jatuh di waktu berjalan maju; mereka lari terburu-buru ke arah tembok kota, sedang alat pendobrak sudah ditegakkan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> The gates of the rivers are opened, And the palace is dissolved. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ابواب الانهار انفتحت والقصر قد ذاب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Pintu-pintu di sungai-sungai telah dibuka, dan istana menjadi gempar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> It is decreed: She shall be led away captive, She shall be brought up; And her maidservants shall lead [her] as with the voice of doves, Beating their breasts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">وهصّب قد انكشفت. أطلعت. وجواريها تئنّ كصوت الحمام ضاربات على صدورهنّ.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Permaisuri dibawa ke luar dan ditelanjangi dan dayang-dayangnya mengerang, mengaduh seperti suara merpati sambil memukul-mukul dada.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Though Nineveh of old [was] like a pool of water, Now they flee away. "Halt! Halt!" [they cry;] But no one turns back. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ونينوى كبركة ماء منذ كانت ولكنهم الآن هاربون. قفوا قفوا ولا ملتفت.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Niniwe sendiri seperti kolam air yang airnya mengalir ke luar. "Berhenti! Berhenti!" teriak orang, tetapi tidak ada yang berpaling.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Take spoil of silver! Take spoil of gold! [There is] no end of treasure, Or wealth of every desirable prize. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">انهبوا فضة انهبوا ذهبا فلا نهاية للتحف للكثرة من كل متاع شهي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Jarahlah perak, jarahlah emas! Sebab tidak berkesudahan persediaan harta benda, kelimpahan segala barang yang indah-indah!</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> She is empty, desolate, and waste! The heart melts, and the knees shake; Much pain [is] in every side, And all their faces are drained of color. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فراغ وخلاء وخراب وقلب ذائب وارتخاء ركب ووجع في كل حقو. واوجه جميعهم تجمع حمرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Ketandusan, penandusan dan penindasan! Hati menjadi tawar dan lutut goyah! Segenap pinggang gemetar, dan muka sekalian orang menjadi pucat pasi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Where [is] the dwelling of the lions, And the feeding place of the young lions, Where the lion walked, the lioness [and] lion's cub, And no one made [them] afraid? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">اين مأوى الأسود ومرعى اشبال الأسود. حيث يمشي الاسد واللبوة وشبل الاسد وليس من يخوّف.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Di mana gerangan persembunyian singa dan gua singa-singa muda, tempat singa pulang pergi, tempat anak singa, di mana tidak ada yang mengganggunya?</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> The lion tore in pieces enough for his cubs, Killed for his lionesses, Filled his caves with prey, And his dens with flesh. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">الاسد المفترس لحاجة جرائه والخانق لاجل لبواته حتى ملأ مغاراته فرائس ومآويه مفترسات.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Biasanya singa itu menerkam supaya cukup makan anak-anaknya, mencekik mangsa bagi betina-betinanya, dan memenuhi liangnya dengan mangsa dan persembunyiannya dengan terkaman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> " Behold, I [am] against you," says the LORD of hosts, "I will burn your chariots in smoke, and the sword shall devour your young lions; I will cut off your prey from the earth, and the voice of your messengers shall be heard no more." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ها انا عليك يقول رب الجنود. فاحرق مركباتك دخانا واشبالك ياكلها السيف واقطع من الارض فرائسك ولا يسمع ايضا صوت رسلك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Lihat, Aku akan menjadi lawanmu, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam, Aku akan membakar keretamu menjadi asap, dan pedang akan memakan habis singa mudamu; Aku akan melenyapkan mangsamu dari atas bumi, dan suara utusan-utusanmu tidak akan terdengar lagi.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="3">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Woe to the bloody city! It [is] all full of lies [and] robbery. [Its] victim never departs. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ويل لمدينة الدماء. كلها ملآنة كذبا وخطفا. لا يزول الافتراس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Celakalah kota penumpah darah itu! Seluruhnya dusta belaka, penuh dengan perampasan, dan tidak henti-hentinya penerkaman!</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> The noise of a whip And the noise of rattling wheels, Of galloping horses, Of clattering chariots! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">صوت السوط وصوت رعشة البكر وخيل تخبّ ومركبات تقفز</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Dengar, lecut cambuk dan derak-derik roda! Dengar, kuda lari menderap, dan kereta meloncat-loncat!</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Horsemen charge with bright sword and glittering spear. [There is] a multitude of slain, A great number of bodies, Countless corpses -- They stumble over the corpses -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">وفرسان تنهض ولهيب السيف وبريق الرمح وكثرة جرحى ووفرة قتلى ولا نهاية للجثث. يعثرون بجثثهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Pasukan berkuda menyerang, pedang bernyala-nyala dan tombak berkilat-kilat! Banyak yang mati terbunuh dan bangkai bertimbun-timbun! Tidak habis-habisnya mayat-mayat, orang tersandung jatuh pada mayat-mayat!</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Because of the multitude of harlotries of the seductive harlot, The mistress of sorceries, Who sells nations through her harlotries, And families through her sorceries. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">من اجل زنى الزانية الحسنة الجمال صاحبة السحر البائعة امما بزناها وقبائل بسحرها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Semuanya karena banyaknya persundalan si perempuan sundal, yang cantik parasnya dan ahli dalam sihir, yang memperdayakan bangsa-bangsa dengan persundalannya dan kaum-kaum dengan sihirnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> " Behold, I [am] against you," says the LORD of hosts; "I will lift your skirts over your face, I will show the nations your nakedness, And the kingdoms your shame. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">هانذا عليك يقول رب الجنود فاكشف اذيالك الى فوق وجهك وأري الامم عورتك والممالك خزيك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Lihat, Aku akan menjadi lawanmu, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam; Aku akan mengangkat ujung kainmu sampai ke mukamu dan akan memperlihatkan auratmu kepada bangsa-bangsa dan kemaluanmu kepada kerajaan-kerajaan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> I will cast abominable filth upon you, Make you vile, And make you a spectacle. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">واطرح عليك اوساخا واهينك واجعلك عبرة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Aku akan melemparkan barang keji ke atasmu, akan menghina engkau dan akan membuat engkau menjadi tontonan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> It shall come to pass [that] all who look upon you Will flee from you, and say, 'Nineveh is laid waste! Who will bemoan her?' Where shall I seek comforters for you?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">ويكون كل من يراك يهرب منك ويقول خربت نينوى من يرثي لها. من اين اطلب لك معزّين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Maka semua orang yang melihat engkau akan lari meninggalkan engkau serta berkata: "Niniwe sudah rusak! Siapakah yang meratapi dia? Dari manakah aku akan mencari penghibur-penghibur untuk dia?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Are you better than No Amon [That was] situated by the River, That had the waters around her, Whose rampart [was] the sea, Whose wall [was] the sea? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">هل انت افضل من نوأمون الجالسة بين الانهار حولها المياه التي هي حصن البحر ومن البحر سورها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Adakah engkau lebih baik dari Tebe, kota dewa Amon, yang letaknya di sungai Nil, dengan air sekelilingnya, yang tembok kotanya adalah laut, dan bentengnya adalah air?</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Ethiopia and Egypt [were] her strength, And [it was] boundless; Put and Lubim were your helpers. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">كوش قوتها مع مصر وليست نهاية. فوط ولوبيم كانوا معونتك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Etiopia adalah kekuatannya, juga Mesir, dengan tidak terbatas; Put dan orang-orang Libia adalah pembantunya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Yet she [was] carried away, She went into captivity; Her young children also were dashed to pieces At the head of every street; They cast lots for her honorable men, And all her great men were bound in chains. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">هي ايضا قد مضت الى المنفى بالسبي واطفالها حطّمت في راس جميع الازقة وعلى اشرافها القوا قرعة وجميع عظمائها تقيدوا بالقيود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Tetapi dia sendiripun terpaksa pergi ke dalam pembuangan, terpaksa masuk ke dalam tawanan. Bayi-bayinyapun diremukkan di ujung segala jalan; tentang semua orangnya yang dihormati dibuang undi, dan semua pembesarnya dibelenggu dengan rantai.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> You also will be drunk; You will be hidden; You also will seek refuge from the enemy. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">انت ايضا تسكرين تكونين خافية. انت ايضا تطلبين حصنا بسبب العدو</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Engkaupun akan menjadi mabuk, akan menjadi tidak berdaya; engkaupun akan mencari tempat perlindungan terhadap musuh.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> All your strongholds [are] fig trees with ripened figs: If they are shaken, They fall into the mouth of the eater. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">جميع قلاعك اشجار تين بالبواكير اذا انهزّت تسقط في فم الآكل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Segala kubumu adalah seperti pohon ara dengan buah ara yang masak duluan; jika diayunkan, maka jatuhlah buahnya ke dalam mulut orang yang hendak memakannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Surely, your people in your midst [are] women! The gates of your land are wide open for your enemies; Fire shall devour the bars of your [gates.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">هوذا شعبك نساء في وسطك. تنفتح لاعدائك ابواب ارضك. تأكل النار مغاليقك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Sesungguhnya, laskar yang di tengah-tengahmu itu adalah perempuan-perempua pintu-pintu gerbang negerimu terbuka lebar-lebar untuk musuhmu; api telah memakan habis palang pintumu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Draw your water for the siege! Fortify your strongholds! Go into the clay and tread the mortar! Make strong the brick kiln! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">استقي لنفسك ماء للحصار. اصلحي قلاعك ادخلي في الطين ودوسي في الملاط. اصلحي الملبن.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Timbalah air menghadapi pengepungan, perkuatlah kubu-kubumu! Pijaklah lumpur, injaklah tanah liat, peganglah acuan batu bata!</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> There the fire will devour you, The sword will cut you off; It will eat you up like a locust. Make yourself many -- like the locust! Make yourself many -- like the [swarming] locusts! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">هناك تأكلك نار يقطعك سيف يأكلك كالغوغاء. تكاثري كالغوغاء تعاظمي كالجراد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Di sana api akan memakan engkau habis, pedang akan membabat engkau, akan memakan engkau seperti belalang pelompat. Sekalipun engkau berjumlah besar seperti belalang pelompat, berjumlah besar seperti belalang pindahan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> You have multiplied your merchants more than the stars of heaven. The locust plunders and flies away. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">اكثرت تجّارك اكثر من نجوم السماء. الغوغاء جنّحت وطارت.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">sekalipun kauperbanyak orang-orang dagangmu lebih dari bintang-bintang di langit, seperti belalang pelompat mereka mengembangkan sayap dan terbang menghilang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Your commanders [are] like [swarming] locusts, And your generals like great grasshoppers, Which camp in the hedges on a cold day; When the sun rises they flee away, And the place where they [are] is not known. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">رؤساؤك كالجراد وولاتك كحرجلة الجراد الحالّة على الجدران في يوم البرد. تشرق الشمس فتطير ولا يعرف مكانها اين هو.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Sekalipun para penjagamu seperti belalang pindahan dan para pegawaimu seperti kawanan belalang, yang hinggap pada tembok-tembok pada waktu dingin, namun jika matahari terbit, mereka lari menghilang, tidak ketahuan tempatnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> Your shepherds slumber, O king of Assyria; Your nobles rest [in the dust.] Your people are scattered on the mountains, And no one gathers them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">نعست رعاتك يا ملك اشور اضطجعت عظماؤك تشتّت شعبك على الجبال ولا من يجمع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Celaka! Alangkah terlelapnya para gembalamu, hai raja negeri Asyur! Para pemukamu tertidur, laskarmu berserak-serak di gunung-gunung, dan tidak ada yang mengumpulkan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> Your injury [has] no healing, Your wound is severe. All who hear news of you Will clap [their] hands over you, For upon whom has not your wickedness passed continually? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">ليس جبر لانكسارك. جرحك عديم الشفاء. كل الذين يسمعون خبرك يصفّقون بايديهم عليك لانه على من لم يمرّ شرّك على الدوام</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Tiada pengobatan untuk cederamu, lukamu tidak tersembuhkan. Semua orang yang mendengar tentang engkau bertepuk tangan karena engkau; sebab kepada siapakah tidak tertimpa perbuatan jahatmu terus-menerus?</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>