<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> The vision of Obadiah. Thus says the Lord GOD concerning Edom (We have heard a report from the LORD, And a messenger has been sent among the nations, [saying,] "Arise, and let us rise up against her for battle"): </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">رؤيا عوبديا. هكذا قال السيد الرب عن ادوم. سمعنا خبرا من قبل الرب وأرسل رسول بين الامم. قوموا ولنقم عليها للحرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Penglihatan Obaja. Beginilah firman Tuhan ALLAH tentang Edom--suatu kabar telah kami dengar dari TUHAN, seorang utusan telah disuruh ke tengah bangsa-bangsa: "Bangunlah, marilah kita bangkit memeranginya!" --</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> "Behold, I will make you small among the nations; You shall be greatly despised. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اني قد جعلتك صغيرا بين الامم. انت محتقر جدا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Sesungguhnya, Aku membuat engkau kecil di antara bangsa-bangsa, engkau dihinakan sangat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> The pride of your heart has deceived you, [You] who dwell in the clefts of the rock, Whose habitation is high; [You] who say in your heart, 'Who will bring me down to the ground?' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">تكبر قلبك قد خدعك ايها الساكن في محاجئ الصخر رفعة مقعده القائل في قلبه من يحدرني الى الارض.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Keangkuhan hatimu telah memperdayakan engkau, ya engkau yang tinggal di liang-liang batu, di tempat kediamanmu yang tinggi; engkau yang berkata dalam hatimu: "Siapakah yang sanggup menurunkan aku ke bumi?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Though you ascend [as] high as the eagle, And though you set your nest among the stars, From there I will bring you down," says the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ان كنت ترتفع كالنسر وان كان عشّك موضوعا بين النجوم فمن هناك احدرك يقول الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Sekalipun engkau terbang tinggi seperti burung rajawali, bahkan, sekalipun sarangmu ditempatkan di antara bintang-bintang, dari sanapun Aku akan menurunkan engkau, --demikianlah firman TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> " If thieves had come to you, If robbers by night -- Oh, how you will be cut off! -- Would they not have stolen till they had enough? If grape-gatherers had come to you, Would they not have left [some] gleanings? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">ان أتاك سارقون او لصوص ليل. كيف هلكت. أفلا يسرقون حاجتهم. ان أتاك قاطفون أفلا يبقون خصاصة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Jika malam-malam pencuri atau perampok datang kepadamu--betapa engkau dibinasakannya--bukankah mereka akan mencuri seberapa yang diperlukannya? Jika pemetik buah anggur datang kepadamu, bukankah mereka akan meninggalkan sisa-sisa pemetikannya?</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> "Oh, how Esau shall be searched out! [How] his hidden treasures shall be sought after! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">كيف فتّش عيسو وفحصت مخابئه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Betapa kaum Esau digeledah, betapa harta bendanya yang tersembunyi dicari-cari!</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> All the men in your confederacy Shall force you to the border; The men at peace with you Shall deceive you [and] prevail against you. [Those who eat] your bread shall lay a trap for you. No one is aware of it. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">طردك الى التخم كل معاهديك. خدعك وغلب عليك مسالموك. اهل خبزك وضعوا شركا تحتك. لا فهم فيه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Sampai ke tapal batas engkau diusir oleh semua teman sekutumu; engkau diperdayakan, dikalahkan oleh sahabat-sahabatmu. Siapa yang makan sehidangan dengan engkau memasang jerat terhadap engkau. --Tidak ada pengertian padanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> "Will I not in that day," says the LORD, "Even destroy the wise [men] from Edom, And understanding from the mountains of Esau? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ألا أبيد في ذلك اليوم يقول الرب الحكماء من ادوم والفهم من جبل عيسو.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Bukankah pada waktu itu, demikianlah firman TUHAN, Aku akan melenyapkan orang-orang bijaksana dari Edom, dan pengertian dari pegunungan Esau?</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Then your mighty men, O Teman, shall be dismayed, To the end that everyone from the mountains of Esau May be cut off by slaughter. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فيرتاع ابطالك يا تيمان لكي ينقرض كل واحد من جبل عيسو بالقتال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Juga para pahlawanmu, hai Teman, akan tertegun, supaya semua orang di pegunungan Esau lenyap terbunuh.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> " For violence against your brother Jacob, Shame shall cover you, And you shall be cut off forever. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">من اجل ظلمك لاخيك يعقوب يغشاك الخزي وتنقرض الى الابد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Karena kekerasan terhadap saudaramu Yakub, maka cela akan meliputi engkau, dan engkau akan dilenyapkan untuk selama-lamanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> In the day that you stood on the other side -- In the day that strangers carried captive his forces, When foreigners entered his gates And cast lots for Jerusalem -- Even you [were] as one of them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">يوم وقفت مقابله يوم سبت الاعاجم قدرته ودخلت الغرباء ابوابه والقوا قرعة على اورشليم كنت انت ايضا كواحد منهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Pada waktu engkau berdiri di kejauhan, sedang orang-orang luar mengangkut kekayaan Yerusalem dan orang-orang asing memasuki pintu gerbangnya dan membuang undi atasnya, engkaupun seperti salah seorang dari mereka itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> But you should not have gazed on the day of your brother In the day of his captivity; Nor should you have rejoiced over the children of Judah In the day of their destruction; Nor should you have spoken proudly In the day of distress. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ويجب ان لا تنظر الى يوم اخيك يوم مصيبته ولا تشمت ببني يهوذا يوم هلاكهم ولا تفغر فمك يوم الضيق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Janganlah memandang rendah saudaramu, pada hari kemalangannya, dan janganlah bersukacita atas keturunan Yehuda pada hari kebinasaannya; dan janganlah membual pada hari kesusahannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> You should not have entered the gate of My people In the day of their calamity. Indeed, you should not have gazed on their affliction In the day of their calamity, Nor laid [hands] on their substance In the day of their calamity. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ولا تدخل باب شعبي يوم بليتهم. ولا تنظر انت ايضا الى مصيبته يوم بليّته ولا تمد يدا الى قدرته يوم بليّته.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Janganlah masuk ke pintu gerbang umat-Ku pada hari sialnya, bahkan janganlah memandang ringan malapetaka yang menimpanya pada hari sialnya; dan janganlah merenggut kekayaannya pada hari sialnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> You should not have stood at the crossroads To cut off those among them who escaped; Nor should you have delivered up those among them who remained In the day of distress. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ولا تقف على المفرق لتقطع منفلتيه ولا تسلّم بقاياه يوم الضيق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Janganlah berdiri di persimpangan untuk melenyapkan orang-orangnya yang luput, dan janganlah serahkan orang-orangnya yang terlepas pada hari kesusahan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> " For the day of the LORD upon all the nations [is] near; As you have done, it shall be done to you; Your reprisal shall return upon your own head. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فانه قريب يوم الرب على كل الامم. كما فعلت يفعل بك. عملك يرتد على راسك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Sebab telah dekat hari TUHAN menimpa segala bangsa. Seperti yang engkau lakukan, demikianlah akan dilakukan kepadamu, perbuatanmu akan kembali menimpa kepalamu sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> For as you drank on my holy mountain, [So] shall all the nations drink continually; Yes, they shall drink, and swallow, And they shall be as though they had never been. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لانه كما شربتم على جبل قدسي يشرب جميع الامم دائما يشربون ويجرعون ويكونون كانهم لم يكونوا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Sesungguhnya, seperti kamu telah minum di atas gunung-Ku yang kudus, segala bangsapun akan minum dengan tidak henti-hentinya; bahkan, mereka akan minum dengan lahap, dan mereka akan menjadi seakan-akan mereka tidak pernah ada.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> "But on Mount Zion there shall be deliverance, And there shall be holiness; The house of Jacob shall possess their possessions. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">واما جبل صهيون فتكون عليه نجاة ويكون مقدّسا ويرث بيت يعقوب مواريثهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Tetapi di gunung Sion akan ada orang-orang yang terluput, dan gunung itu akan menjadi tempat kudus; dan kaum keturunan Yakub akan memiliki pula tanah miliknya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> The house of Jacob shall be a fire, And the house of Joseph a flame; But the house of Esau [shall be] stubble; They shall kindle them and devour them, And no survivor shall [remain] of the house of Esau," For the LORD has spoken. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">ويكون بيت يعقوب نارا وبيت يوسف لهيبا وبيت عيسو قشا فيشعلونهم وياكلونهم ولا يكون باق من بيت عيسو لان الرب تكلم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Kaum keturunan Yakub akan menjadi api dan kaum keturunan Yusuf menjadi nyala api, dan kaum keturunan Esau menjadi tunggul gandum: mereka akan membakar dan memakan habis sekaliannya, dan dari kaum keturunan Esau tidak ada seorangpun yang terlepas, sebab Tuhanlah yang berfirman demikian.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> The South shall possess the mountains of Esau, And the Lowland shall possess Philistia. They shall possess the fields of Ephraim And the fields of Samaria. Benjamin [shall possess] Gilead. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">ويرث اهل الجنوب جبل عيسو واهل السهل الفلسطينيين ويرثون بلاد افرايم وبلاد السامرة ويرث بنيامين جلعاد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Maka orang-orang Tanah Negeb akan memiliki pegunungan Esau, dan orang-orang Daerah Bukit akan memiliki tanah orang Filistin. Mereka akan memiliki daerah Efraim dan daerah Samaria, dan suku Benyamin akan memiliki daerah Gilead.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> And the captives of this host of the children of Israel [Shall possess the land] of the Canaanites As far as Zarephath. The captives of Jerusalem who are in Sepharad Shall possess the cities of the South. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">وسبي هذا الجيش من بني اسرائيل يرثون الذين هم من الكنعانيين الى صرفة. وسبي اورشليم الذين في صفارد يرثون مدن الجنوب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Orang-orang Israel yang diangkut ke dalam pembuangan akan memiliki tanah orang Kanaan sampai ke Zarfat; dan orang-orang Yerusalem yang diangkut ke dalam pembuangan, yang ada di Sefarad, akan memiliki kota-kota di Tanah Negeb.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> Then saviors shall come to Mount Zion To judge the mountains of Esau, And the kingdom shall be the LORD's. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">ويصعد مخلّصون على جبل صهيون ليدينوا جبل عيسو ويكون الملك للرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Penyelamat-penyelamat akan naik ke atas gunung Sion untuk menghukumkan pegunungan Esau; maka Tuhanlah yang akan empunya kerajaan itu.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>