<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Paul and Timothy, bondservants of Jesus Christ, To all the saints in Christ Jesus who are in Philippi, with the bishops and deacons: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">بولس وتيموثاوس عبدا يسوع المسيح الى جميع القديسين في المسيح يسوع الذين في فيلبي مع اساقفة وشمامسة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Dari Paulus dan Timotius, hamba-hamba Kristus Yesus, kepada semua orang kudus dalam Kristus Yesus di Filipi, dengan para penilik jemaat dan diaken.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">نعمة لكم وسلام من الله ابينا والرب يسوع المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Kasih karunia dan damai sejahtera dari Allah, Bapa kita, dan dari Tuhan Yesus Kristus menyertai kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> I thank my God upon every remembrance of you, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">اشكر الهي عند كل ذكري اياكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Aku mengucap syukur kepada Allahku setiap kali aku mengingat kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> always in every prayer of mine making request for you all with joy, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">دائما في كل ادعيتي مقدما الطلبة لاجل جميعكم بفرح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Dan setiap kali aku berdoa untuk kamu semua, aku selalu berdoa dengan sukacita.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> for your fellowship in the gospel from the first day until now, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">لسبب مشاركتكم في الانجيل من اول يوم الى الآن</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Aku mengucap syukur kepada Allahku karena persekutuanmu dalam Berita Injil mulai dari hari pertama sampai sekarang ini.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> being confident of this very thing, that He who has begun a good work in you will complete [it] until the day of Jesus Christ; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">واثقا بهذا عينه ان الذي ابتدأ فيكم عملا صالحا يكمل الى يوم يسوع المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Akan hal ini aku yakin sepenuhnya, yaitu Ia, yang memulai pekerjaan yang baik di antara kamu, akan meneruskannya sampai pada akhirnya pada hari Kristus Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> just as it is right for me to think this of you all, because I have you in my heart, inasmuch as both in my chains and in the defense and confirmation of the gospel, you all are partakers with me of grace. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">كما يحق لي ان افتكر هذا من جهة جميعكم لاني حافظكم في قلبي في وثقي وفي المحاماة عن الانجيل وتثبيته انتم الذين جميعكم شركائي في النعمة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Memang sudahlah sepatutnya aku berpikir demikian akan kamu semua, sebab kamu ada di dalam hatiku, oleh karena kamu semua turut mendapat bagian dalam kasih karunia yang diberikan kepadaku, baik pada waktu aku dipenjarakan, maupun pada waktu aku membela dan meneguhkan Berita Injil.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> For God is my witness, how greatly I long for you all with the affection of Jesus Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فان الله شاهد لي كيف اشتاق الى جميعكم في احشاء يسوع المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Sebab Allah adalah saksiku betapa aku dengan kasih mesra Kristus Yesus merindukan kamu sekalian.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> And this I pray, that your love may abound still more and more in knowledge and all discernment, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">وهذا اصلّيه ان تزداد محبتكم ايضا اكثر فاكثر في المعرفة وفي كل فهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Dan inilah doaku, semoga kasihmu makin melimpah dalam pengetahuan yang benar dan dalam segala macam pengertian,</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> that you may approve the things that are excellent, that you may be sincere and without offense till the day of Christ, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">حتى تميّزوا الامور المتخالفة لكي تكونوا مخلصين وبلا عثرة الى يوم المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">sehingga kamu dapat memilih apa yang baik, supaya kamu suci dan tak bercacat menjelang hari Kristus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> being filled with the fruits of righteousness which [are] by Jesus Christ, to the glory and praise of God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">مملوئين من ثمر البر الذي بيسوع المسيح لمجد الله وحمده</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">penuh dengan buah kebenaran yang dikerjakan oleh Yesus Kristus untuk memuliakan dan memuji Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> But I want you to know, brethren, that the things [which happened] to me have actually turned out for the furtherance of the gospel, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ثم اريد ان تعلموا ايها الاخوة ان اموري قد آلت اكثر الى تقدم الانجيل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Aku menghendaki, saudara-saudara, supaya kamu tahu, bahwa apa yang terjadi atasku ini justru telah menyebabkan kemajuan Injil,</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> so that it has become evident to the whole palace guard, and to all the rest, that my chains are in Christ; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">حتى ان وثقي صارت ظاهرة في المسيح في كل دار الولاية وفي باقي الاماكن اجمع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">sehingga telah jelas bagi seluruh istana dan semua orang lain, bahwa aku dipenjarakan karena Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> and most of the brethren in the Lord, having become confident by my chains, are much more bold to speak the word without fear. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">واكثر الاخوة وهم واثقون في الرب بوثقي يجترئون اكثر على التكلم بالكلمة بلا خوف.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Dan kebanyakan saudara dalam Tuhan telah beroleh kepercayaan karena pemenjaraanku untuk bertambah berani berkata-kata tentang firman Allah dengan tidak takut.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Some indeed preach Christ even from envy and strife, and some also from good will: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">اما قوم فعن حسد وخصام يكرزون بالمسيح واما قوم فعن مسرة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Ada orang yang memberitakan Kristus karena dengki dan perselisihan, tetapi ada pula yang memberitakan-Nya dengan maksud baik.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> The former preach Christ from selfish ambition, not sincerely, supposing to add affliction to my chains; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فهؤلاء عن تحزب ينادون بالمسيح لا عن اخلاص ظانين انهم يضيفون الى وثقي ضيقا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Mereka ini memberitakan Kristus karena kasih, sebab mereka tahu, bahwa aku ada di sini untuk membela Injil,</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> but the latter out of love, knowing that I am appointed for the defense of the gospel. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">واولئك عن محبة عالمين اني موضوع لحماية الانجيل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">tetapi yang lain karena kepentingan sendiri dan dengan maksud yang tidak ikhlas, sangkanya dengan demikian mereka memperberat bebanku dalam penjara.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> What then? Only [that] in every way, whether in pretense or in truth, Christ is preached; and in this I rejoice, yes, and will rejoice. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فماذا. غير انه على كل وجه سواء كان بعلّة ام بحق ينادى بالمسيح وبهذا انا افرح. بل سافرح ايضا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Tetapi tidak mengapa, sebab bagaimanapun juga, Kristus diberitakan, baik dengan maksud palsu maupun dengan jujur. Tentang hal itu aku bersukacita. Dan aku akan tetap bersukacita,</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> For I know that this will turn out for my deliverance through your prayer and the supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">لاني اعلم ان هذا يأول لي الى خلاص بطلبتكم وموازرة روح يسوع المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">karena aku tahu, bahwa kesudahan semuanya ini ialah keselamatanku oleh doamu dan pertolongan Roh Yesus Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> according to my earnest expectation and hope that in nothing I shall be ashamed, but with all boldness, as always, so now also Christ will be magnified in my body, whether by life or by death. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">حسب انتظاري ورجائي اني لا اخزى في شيء بل بكل مجاهرة كما في كل حين كذلك الآن يتعظم المسيح في جسدي سواء كان بحياة ام بموت.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Sebab yang sangat kurindukan dan kuharapkan ialah bahwa aku dalam segala hal tidak akan beroleh malu, melainkan seperti sediakala, demikianpun sekarang, Kristus dengan nyata dimuliakan di dalam tubuhku, baik oleh hidupku, maupun oleh matiku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> For to me, to live [is] Christ, and to die [is] gain. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">لان لي الحياة هي المسيح والموت هو ربح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Karena bagiku hidup adalah Kristus dan mati adalah keuntungan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> But if [I] live on in the flesh, this [will mean] fruit from [my] labor; yet what I shall choose I cannot tell. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">ولكن ان كانت الحياة في الجسد هي لي ثمر عملي فماذا اختار لست ادري.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Tetapi jika aku harus hidup di dunia ini, itu berarti bagiku bekerja memberi buah. Jadi mana yang harus kupilih, aku tidak tahu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> For I am hard pressed between the two, having a desire to depart and be with Christ, [which is] far better. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">فاني محصور من الاثنين. لي اشتهاء ان انطلق واكون مع المسيح. ذاك افضل جدا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Aku didesak dari dua pihak: aku ingin pergi dan diam bersama-sama dengan Kristus--itu memang jauh lebih baik;</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> Nevertheless to remain in the flesh [is] more needful for you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">ولكن ان ابقى في الجسد الزم من اجلكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">tetapi lebih perlu untuk tinggal di dunia ini karena kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> And being confident of this, I know that I shall remain and continue with you all for your progress and joy of faith, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">فاذ انا واثق بهذا اعلم اني امكث وابقى مع جميعكم لاجل تقدمكم وفرحكم في الايمان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Dan dalam keyakinan ini tahulah aku: aku akan tinggal dan akan bersama-sama lagi dengan kamu sekalian supaya kamu makin maju dan bersukacita dalam iman,</language></verse>
			<verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26"> that your rejoicing for me may be more abundant in Jesus Christ by my coming to you again. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">لكي يزداد افتخاركم في المسيح يسوع فيّ بواسطة حضوري ايضا عندكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">sehingga kemegahanmu dalam Kristus Yesus makin bertambah karena aku, apabila aku kembali kepada kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27"> Only let your conduct be worthy of the gospel of Christ, so that whether I come and see you or am absent, I may hear of your affairs, that you stand fast in one spirit, with one mind striving together for the faith of the gospel, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">فقط عيشوا كما يحق لانجيل المسيح حتى اذا جئت ورأيتكم او كنت غائبا اسمع اموركم انكم تثبتون في روح واحد مجاهدين معا بنفس واحدة لايمان الانجيل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">Hanya, hendaklah hidupmu berpadanan dengan Injil Kristus, supaya, apabila aku datang aku melihat, dan apabila aku tidak datang aku mendengar, bahwa kamu teguh berdiri dalam satu roh, dan sehati sejiwa berjuang untuk iman yang timbul dari Berita Injil,</language></verse>
			<verse num="28"><language id="English" verse="28"> and not in any way terrified by your adversaries, which is to them a proof of perdition, but to you of salvation, and that from God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="28">غير مخوّفين بشيء من المقاومين الامر الذي هو لهم بيّنة للهلاك واما لكم فللخلاص وذلك من الله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="28">dengan tiada digentarkan sedikitpun oleh lawanmu. Bagi mereka semuanya itu adalah tanda kebinasaan, tetapi bagi kamu tanda keselamatan, dan itu datangnya dari Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="29"><language id="English" verse="29"> For to you it has been granted on behalf of Christ, not only to believe in Him, but also to suffer for His sake, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="29">لانه قد وهب لكم لاجل المسيح لا ان تؤمنوا به فقط بل ايضا ان تتألموا لاجله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="29">Sebab kepada kamu dikaruniakan bukan saja untuk percaya kepada Kristus, melainkan juga untuk menderita untuk Dia,</language></verse>
			<verse num="30"><language id="English" verse="30"> having the same conflict which you saw in me and now hear [is] in me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="30">اذ لكم الجهاد عينه الذي رأيتموه فيّ والآن تسمعون فيّ</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="30">dalam pergumulan yang sama seperti yang dahulu kamu lihat padaku, dan yang sekarang kamu dengar tentang aku.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="2">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Therefore if [there is] any consolation in Christ, if any comfort of love, if any fellowship of the Spirit, if any affection and mercy, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">فان كان وعظ ما في المسيح ان كانت تسلية ما للمحبة ان كانت شركة ما في الروح ان كانت احشاء ورأفة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Jadi karena dalam Kristus ada nasihat, ada penghiburan kasih, ada persekutuan Roh, ada kasih mesra dan belas kasihan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> fulfill my joy by being like-minded, having the same love, [being] of one accord, of one mind. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فتمموا فرحي حتى تفتكروا فكرا واحدا ولكم محبة واحدة بنفس واحدة مفتكرين شيئا واحدا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">karena itu sempurnakanlah sukacitaku dengan ini: hendaklah kamu sehati sepikir, dalam satu kasih, satu jiwa, satu tujuan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> [Let] nothing [be done] through selfish ambition or conceit, but in lowliness of mind let each esteem others better than himself. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">لا شيئا بتحزب او بعجب بل بتواضع حاسبين بعضكم البعض افضل من انفسهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">dengan tidak mencari kepentingan sendiri atau puji-pujian yang sia-sia. Sebaliknya hendaklah dengan rendah hati yang seorang menganggap yang lain lebih utama dari pada dirinya sendiri;</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Let each of you look out not only for his own interests, but also for the interests of others. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">لا تنظروا كل واحد الى ما هو لنفسه بل كل واحد الى ما هو لآخرين ايضا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">dan janganlah tiap-tiap orang hanya memperhatikan kepentingannya sendiri, tetapi kepentingan orang lain juga.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Let this mind be in you which was also in Christ Jesus, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فليكن فيكم هذا الفكر الذي في المسيح يسوع ايضا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Hendaklah kamu dalam hidupmu bersama, menaruh pikiran dan perasaan yang terdapat juga dalam Kristus Yesus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> who, being in the form of God, did not consider it robbery to be equal with God, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">الذي اذ كان في صورة الله لم يحسب خلسة ان يكون معادلا للّه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">yang walaupun dalam rupa Allah, tidak menganggap kesetaraan dengan Allah itu sebagai milik yang harus dipertahankan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> but made Himself of no reputation, taking the form of a bondservant, [and] coming in the likeness of men. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">لكنه اخلى نفسه آخذا صورة عبد صائرا في شبه الناس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">melainkan telah mengosongkan diri-Nya sendiri, dan mengambil rupa seorang hamba, dan menjadi sama dengan manusia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> And being found in appearance as a man, He humbled Himself and became obedient to [the point of] death, even the death of the cross. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">واذ وجد في الهيئة كانسان وضع نفسه واطاع حتى الموت موت الصليب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Dan dalam keadaan sebagai manusia, Ia telah merendahkan diri-Nya dan taat sampai mati, bahkan sampai mati di kayu salib.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Therefore God also has highly exalted Him and given Him the name which is above every name, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لذلك رفعه الله ايضا واعطاه اسما فوق كل اسم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Itulah sebabnya Allah sangat meninggikan Dia dan mengaruniakan kepada-Nya nama di atas segala nama,</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> that at the name of Jesus every knee should bow, of those in heaven, and of those on earth, and of those under the earth, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لكي تجثو باسم يسوع كل ركبة ممن في السماء ومن على الارض ومن تحت الارض</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">supaya dalam nama Yesus bertekuk lutut segala yang ada di langit dan yang ada di atas bumi dan yang ada di bawah bumi,</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> and [that] every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ [is] Lord, to the glory of God the Father. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ويعترف كل لسان ان يسوع المسيح هو رب لمجد الله الآب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">dan segala lidah mengaku: "Yesus Kristus adalah Tuhan," bagi kemuliaan Allah, Bapa!</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Therefore, my beloved, as you have always obeyed, not as in my presence only, but now much more in my absence, work out your own salvation with fear and trembling; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">اذا يا احبائي كما اطعتم كل حين ليس كما في حضوري فقط بل الآن بالأولى جدا في غيابي تمموا خلاصكم بخوف ورعدة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Hai saudara-saudaraku yang kekasih, kamu senantiasa taat; karena itu tetaplah kerjakan keselamatanmu dengan takut dan gentar, bukan saja seperti waktu aku masih hadir, tetapi terlebih pula sekarang waktu aku tidak hadir,</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> for it is God who works in you both to will and to do for [His] good pleasure. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">لان الله هو العامل فيكم ان تريدوا وان تعملوا من اجل المسرّة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">karena Allahlah yang mengerjakan di dalam kamu baik kemauan maupun pekerjaan menurut kerelaan-Nya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Do all things without complaining and disputing, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">افعلوا كل شيء بلا دمدمة ولا مجادلة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Lakukanlah segala sesuatu dengan tidak bersungut-sungut dan berbantah-bantahan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> that you may become blameless and harmless, children of God without fault in the midst of a crooked and perverse generation, among whom you shine as lights in the world, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">لكي تكونوا بلا لوم وبسطاء اولادا للّه بلا عيب في وسط جيل معوج وملتو تضيئون بينهم كانوار في العالم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">supaya kamu tiada beraib dan tiada bernoda, sebagai anak-anak Allah yang tidak bercela di tengah-tengah angkatan yang bengkok hatinya dan yang sesat ini, sehingga kamu bercahaya di antara mereka seperti bintang-bintang di dunia,</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> holding fast the word of life, so that I may rejoice in the day of Christ that I have not run in vain or labored in vain. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">متمسكين بكلمة الحياة لافتخاري في يوم المسيح باني لم اسع باطلا ولا تعبت باطلا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">sambil berpegang pada firman kehidupan, agar aku dapat bermegah pada hari Kristus, bahwa aku tidak percuma berlomba dan tidak percuma bersusah-susah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Yes, and if I am being poured out [as a drink offering] on the sacrifice and service of your faith, I am glad and rejoice with you all. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">لكنني وان كنت انسكب ايضا على ذبيحة ايمانكم وخدمته اسرّ وافرح معكم اجمعين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Tetapi sekalipun darahku dicurahkan pada korban dan ibadah imanmu, aku bersukacita dan aku bersukacita dengan kamu sekalian.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> For the same reason you also be glad and rejoice with me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">وبهذا عينه كونوا انتم مسرورين ايضا وافرحوا معي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Dan kamu juga harus bersukacita demikian dan bersukacitalah dengan aku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> But I trust in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy to you shortly, that I also may be encouraged when I know your state. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">على اني ارجو في الرب يسوع ان ارسل اليكم سريعا تيموثاوس لكي تطيب نفسي اذا عرفت احوالكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Tetapi dalam Tuhan Yesus kuharap segera mengirimkan Timotius kepadamu, supaya tenang juga hatiku oleh kabar tentang hal ihwalmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> For I have no one like-minded, who will sincerely care for your state. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">لان ليس لي احد آخر نظير نفسي يهتم باحوالكم بإخلاص.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Karena tak ada seorang padaku, yang sehati dan sepikir dengan dia dan yang begitu bersungguh-sungguh memperhatikan kepentinganmu;</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> For all seek their own, not the things which are of Christ Jesus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">اذ الجميع يطلبون ما هو لانفسهم لا ما هو ليسوع المسيح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">sebab semuanya mencari kepentingannya sendiri, bukan kepentingan Kristus Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> But you know his proven character, that as a son with [his] father he served with me in the gospel. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">واما اختباره فانتم تعرفون انه كولد مع اب خدم معي لاجل الانجيل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Kamu tahu bahwa kesetiaannya telah teruji dan bahwa ia telah menolong aku dalam pelayanan Injil sama seperti seorang anak menolong bapanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> Therefore I hope to send him at once, as soon as I see how it goes with me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">هذا ارجو ان ارسله اول ما ارى احوالي حالا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Dialah yang kuharap untuk kukirimkan dengan segera, sesudah jelas bagiku bagaimana jalannya perkaraku;</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> But I trust in the Lord that I myself shall also come shortly. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">وأثق بالرب اني انا ايضا سآتي اليكم سريعا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">tetapi dalam Tuhan aku percaya, bahwa aku sendiripun akan segera datang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> Yet I considered it necessary to send to you Epaphroditus, my brother, fellow worker, and fellow soldier, but your messenger and the one who ministered to my need; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">ولكني حسبت من اللازم ان ارسل اليكم ابفرودتس اخي والعامل معي والمتجند معي ورسولكم والخادم لحاجتي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Sementara itu kuanggap perlu mengirimkan Epafroditus kepadamu, yaitu saudaraku dan teman sekerja serta teman seperjuanganku, yang kamu utus untuk melayani aku dalam keperluanku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26"> since he was longing for you all, and was distressed because you had heard that he was sick. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">اذ كان مشتاقا الى جميعكم ومغموما لانكم سمعتم انه كان مريضا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">Karena ia sangat rindu kepada kamu sekalian dan susah juga hatinya, sebab kamu mendengar bahwa ia sakit.</language></verse>
			<verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27"> For indeed he was sick almost unto death; but God had mercy on him, and not only on him but on me also, lest I should have sorrow upon sorrow. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">فانه مرض قريبا من الموت لكن الله رحمه وليس اياه وحده بل اياي ايضا لئلا يكون لي حزن على حزن.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">Memang benar ia sakit dan nyaris mati, tetapi Allah mengasihani dia, dan bukan hanya dia saja, melainkan aku juga, supaya dukacitaku jangan bertambah-tambah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="28"><language id="English" verse="28"> Therefore I sent him the more eagerly, that when you see him again you may rejoice, and I may be less sorrowful. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="28">فارسلته اليكم باوفر سرعة حتى اذا رأيتموه تفرحون ايضا واكون انا اقل حزنا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="28">Itulah sebabnya aku lebih cepat mengirimkan dia, supaya bila kamu melihat dia, kamu dapat bersukacita pula dan berkurang dukacitaku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="29"><language id="English" verse="29"> Receive him therefore in the Lord with all gladness, and hold such men in esteem; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="29">فاقبلوه في الرب بكل فرح وليكن مثله مكرّما عندكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="29">Jadi sambutlah dia dalam Tuhan dengan segala sukacita dan hormatilah orang-orang seperti dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="30"><language id="English" verse="30"> because for the work of Christ he came close to death, not regarding his life, to supply what was lacking in your service toward me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="30">لانه من اجل عمل المسيح قارب الموت مخاطرا بنفسه لكي يجبر نقصان خدمتكم لي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="30">Sebab oleh karena pekerjaan Kristus ia nyaris mati dan ia mempertaruhkan jiwanya untuk memenuhi apa yang masih kurang dalam pelayananmu kepadaku.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="3">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Finally, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord. For me to write the same things to you [is] not tedious, but for you [it is] safe. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">اخيرا يا اخوتي افرحوا في الرب. كتابة هذه الامور اليكم ليست عليّ ثقيلة واما لكم فهي مؤمّنة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Akhirnya, saudara-saudaraku, bersukacitalah dalam Tuhan. (3-1b) Menuliskan hal ini lagi kepadamu tidaklah berat bagiku dan memberi kepastian kepadamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Beware of dogs, beware of evil workers, beware of the mutilation! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">انظروا الكلاب انظروا فعلة الشر انظروا القطع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Hati-hatilah terhadap anjing-anjing, hati-hatilah terhadap pekerja-pekerja yang jahat, hati-hatilah terhadap penyunat-penyunat yang palsu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> For we are the circumcision, who worship God in the Spirit, rejoice in Christ Jesus, and have no confidence in the flesh, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">لاننا نحن الختان الذين نعبد الله بالروح ونفتخر في المسيح يسوع ولا نتكل على الجسد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">karena kitalah orang-orang bersunat, yang beribadah oleh Roh Allah, dan bermegah dalam Kristus Yesus dan tidak menaruh percaya pada hal-hal lahiriah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> though I also might have confidence in the flesh. If anyone else thinks he may have confidence in the flesh, I more so: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">مع ان لي ان اتكل على الجسد ايضا. ان ظن واحد آخر ان يتكل على الجسد فانا بالأولى.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Sekalipun aku juga ada alasan untuk menaruh percaya pada hal-hal lahiriah. Jika ada orang lain menyangka dapat menaruh percaya pada hal-hal lahiriah, aku lebih lagi:</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> circumcised the eighth day, of the stock of Israel, [of] the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew of the Hebrews; concerning the law, a Pharisee; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">من جهة الختان مختون في اليوم الثامن من جنس اسرائيل من سبط بنيامين عبراني من العبرانيين. من جهة الناموس فريسي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">disunat pada hari kedelapan, dari bangsa Israel, dari suku Benyamin, orang Ibrani asli, tentang pendirian terhadap hukum Taurat aku orang Farisi,</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> concerning zeal, persecuting the church; concerning the righteousness which is in the law, blameless. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">من جهة الغيرة مضطهد الكنيسة. من جهة البر الذي في الناموس بلا لوم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">tentang kegiatan aku penganiaya jemaat, tentang kebenaran dalam mentaati hukum Taurat aku tidak bercacat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> But what things were gain to me, these I have counted loss for Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">لكن ما كان لي ربحا فهذا قد حسبته من اجل المسيح خسارة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Tetapi apa yang dahulu merupakan keuntungan bagiku, sekarang kuanggap rugi karena Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Yet indeed I also count all things loss for the excellence of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord, for whom I have suffered the loss of all things, and count them as rubbish, that I may gain Christ </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">بل اني احسب كل شيء ايضا خسارة من اجل فضل معرفة المسيح يسوع ربي الذي من اجله خسرت كل الاشياء وانا احسبها نفاية لكي اربح المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Malahan segala sesuatu kuanggap rugi, karena pengenalan akan Kristus Yesus, Tuhanku, lebih mulia dari pada semuanya. Oleh karena Dialah aku telah melepaskan semuanya itu dan menganggapnya sampah, supaya aku memperoleh Kristus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> and be found in Him, not having my own righteousness, which [is] from the law, but that which [is] through faith in Christ, the righteousness which is from God by faith; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">واوجد فيه وليس لي بري الذي من الناموس بل الذي بايمان المسيح البر الذي من الله بالايمان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">dan berada dalam Dia bukan dengan kebenaranku sendiri karena mentaati hukum Taurat, melainkan dengan kebenaran karena kepercayaan kepada Kristus, yaitu kebenaran yang Allah anugerahkan berdasarkan kepercayaan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> that I may know Him and the power of His resurrection, and the fellowship of His sufferings, being conformed to His death, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لاعرفه وقوة قيامته وشركة آلامه متشبها بموته.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Yang kukehendaki ialah mengenal Dia dan kuasa kebangkitan-Nya dan persekutuan dalam penderitaan-Nya, di mana aku menjadi serupa dengan Dia dalam kematian-Nya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> if, by any means, I may attain to the resurrection from the dead. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لعلي ابلغ الى قيامة الاموات.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">supaya aku akhirnya beroleh kebangkitan dari antara orang mati.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Not that I have already attained, or am already perfected; but I press on, that I may lay hold of that for which Christ Jesus has also laid hold of me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ليس اني قد نلت او صرت كاملا ولكني اسعى لعلي ادرك الذي لاجله ادركني ايضا المسيح يسوع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Bukan seolah-olah aku telah memperoleh hal ini atau telah sempurna, melainkan aku mengejarnya, kalau-kalau aku dapat juga menangkapnya, karena akupun telah ditangkap oleh Kristus Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Brethren, I do not count myself to have apprehended; but one thing [I do,] forgetting those things which are behind and reaching forward to those things which are ahead, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ايها الاخوة انا لست احسب نفسي اني قد ادركت. ولكني افعل شيئا واحدا اذ انا انسى ما هو وراء وامتد الى ما هو قدام</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Saudara-saudara, aku sendiri tidak menganggap, bahwa aku telah menangkapnya, tetapi ini yang kulakukan: aku melupakan apa yang telah di belakangku dan mengarahkan diri kepada apa yang di hadapanku,</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> I press toward the goal for the prize of the upward call of God in Christ Jesus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">اسعى نحو الغرض لاجل جعالة دعوة الله العليا في المسيح يسوع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">dan berlari-lari kepada tujuan untuk memperoleh hadiah, yaitu panggilan sorgawi dari Allah dalam Kristus Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Therefore let us, as many as are mature, have this mind; and if in anything you think otherwise, God will reveal even this to you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فليفتكر هذا جميع الكاملين منا وان افتكرتم شيئا بخلافه فالله سيعلن لكم هذا ايضا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Karena itu marilah kita, yang sempurna, berpikir demikian. Dan jikalau lain pikiranmu tentang salah satu hal, hal itu akan dinyatakan Allah juga kepadamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> Nevertheless, to [the degree] that we have already attained, let us walk by the same rule, let us be of the same mind. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">واما ما قد ادركناه فلنسلك بحسب ذلك القانون عينه ونفتكر ذلك عينه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Tetapi baiklah tingkat pengertian yang telah kita capai kita lanjutkan menurut jalan yang telah kita tempuh.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Brethren, join in following my example, and note those who so walk, as you have us for a pattern. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">كونوا متمثلين بي معا ايها الاخوة ولاحظوا الذين يسيرون هكذا كما نحن عندكم قدوة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Saudara-saudara, ikutilah teladanku dan perhatikanlah mereka, yang hidup sama seperti kami yang menjadi teladanmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> For many walk, of whom I have told you often, and now tell you even weeping, [that they are] the enemies of the cross of Christ: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">لان كثيرين يسيرون ممن كنت اذكرهم لكم مرارا والآن اذكرهم ايضا باكيا وهم اعداء صليب المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Karena, seperti yang telah kerap kali kukatakan kepadamu, dan yang kunyatakan pula sekarang sambil menangis, banyak orang yang hidup sebagai seteru salib Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> whose end [is] destruction, whose god [is their] belly, and [whose] glory [is] in their shame -- who set their mind on earthly things. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">الذين نهايتهم الهلاك الذين الههم بطنهم ومجدهم في خزيهم الذين يفتكرون في الارضيات.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Kesudahan mereka ialah kebinasaan, Tuhan mereka ialah perut mereka, kemuliaan mereka ialah aib mereka, pikiran mereka semata-mata tertuju kepada perkara duniawi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> For our citizenship is in heaven, from which we also eagerly wait for the Savior, the Lord Jesus Christ, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">فان سيرتنا نحن هي في السموات التي منها ايضا ننتظر مخلّصا هو الرب يسوع المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Karena kewargaan kita adalah di dalam sorga, dan dari situ juga kita menantikan Tuhan Yesus Kristus sebagai Juruselamat,</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> who will transform our lowly body that it may be conformed to His glorious body, according to the working by which He is able even to subdue all things to Himself. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">الذي سيغيّر شكل جسد تواضعنا ليكون على صورة جسد مجده بحسب عمل استطاعته ان يخضع لنفسه كل شيء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">yang akan mengubah tubuh kita yang hina ini, sehingga serupa dengan tubuh-Nya yang mulia, menurut kuasa-Nya yang dapat menaklukkan segala sesuatu kepada diri-Nya.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="4">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Therefore, my beloved and longed-for brethren, my joy and crown, so stand fast in the Lord, beloved. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">اذا يا اخوتي الاحباء والمشتاق اليهم يا سروري واكليلي اثبتوا هكذا في الرب ايها الاحباء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Karena itu, saudara-saudara yang kukasihi dan yang kurindukan, sukacitaku dan mahkotaku, berdirilah juga dengan teguh dalam Tuhan, hai saudara-saudaraku yang kekasih!</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> I implore Euodia and I implore Syntyche to be of the same mind in the Lord. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اطلب الى افودية واطلب الى سنتيخي ان تفتكرا فكرا واحدا في الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Euodia kunasihati dan Sintikhe kunasihati, supaya sehati sepikir dalam Tuhan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> And I urge you also, true companion, help these women who labored with me in the gospel, with Clement also, and the rest of my fellow workers, whose names [are] in the Book of Life. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">نعم اسألك انت ايضا يا شريكي المخلص ساعد هاتين اللتين جاهدتا معي في الانجيل مع اكليمندس ايضا وباقي العاملين معي الذين اسماؤهم في سفر الحياة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Bahkan, kuminta kepadamu juga, Sunsugos, temanku yang setia: tolonglah mereka. Karena mereka telah berjuang dengan aku dalam pekabaran Injil, bersama-sama dengan Klemens dan kawan-kawanku sekerja yang lain, yang nama-namanya tercantum dalam kitab kehidupan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Rejoice in the Lord always. Again I will say, rejoice! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">افرحوا في الرب كل حين واقول ايضا افرحوا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Bersukacitalah senantiasa dalam Tuhan! Sekali lagi kukatakan: Bersukacitalah!</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Let your gentleness be known to all men. The Lord [is] at hand. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">ليكن حلمكم معروفا عند جميع الناس. الرب قريب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Hendaklah kebaikan hatimu diketahui semua orang. Tuhan sudah dekat!</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Be anxious for nothing, but in everything by prayer and supplication, with thanksgiving, let your requests be made known to God; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لا تهتموا بشيء بل في كل شيء بالصلاة والدعاء مع الشكر لتعلم طلباتكم لدى الله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Janganlah hendaknya kamu kuatir tentang apapun juga, tetapi nyatakanlah dalam segala hal keinginanmu kepada Allah dalam doa dan permohonan dengan ucapan syukur.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> and the peace of God, which surpasses all understanding, will guard your hearts and minds through Christ Jesus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">وسلام الله الذي يفوق كل عقل يحفظ قلوبكم وافكاركم في المسيح يسوع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Damai sejahtera Allah, yang melampaui segala akal, akan memelihara hati dan pikiranmu dalam Kristus Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Finally, brethren, whatever things are true, whatever things [are] noble, whatever things [are] just, whatever things [are] pure, whatever things [are] lovely, whatever things [are] of good report, if [there is] any virtue and if [there is] anything praiseworthy -- meditate on these things. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">اخيرا ايها الاخوة كل ما هو حق كل ما هو جليل كل ما هو عادل كل ما هو طاهر كل ما هو مسرّ كل ما صيته حسن ان كانت فضيلة وان كان مدح ففي هذه افتكروا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Jadi akhirnya, saudara-saudara, semua yang benar, semua yang mulia, semua yang adil, semua yang suci, semua yang manis, semua yang sedap didengar, semua yang disebut kebajikan dan patut dipuji, pikirkanlah semuanya itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> The things which you learned and received and heard and saw in me, these do, and the God of peace will be with you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">وما تعلمتموه وتسلمتموه وسمعتموه ورأيتموه فيّ فهذا افعلوا واله السلام يكون معكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Dan apa yang telah kamu pelajari dan apa yang telah kamu terima, dan apa yang telah kamu dengar dan apa yang telah kamu lihat padaku, lakukanlah itu. Maka Allah sumber damai sejahtera akan menyertai kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> But I rejoiced in the Lord greatly that now at last your care for me has flourished again; though you surely did care, but you lacked opportunity. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">ثم اني فرحت بالرب جدا لانكم الآن قد ازهر ايضا مرة اعتناؤكم بي الذي كنتم تعتنونه ولكن لم تكن لكم فرصة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Aku sangat bersukacita dalam Tuhan, bahwa akhirnya pikiranmu dan perasaanmu bertumbuh kembali untuk aku. Memang selalu ada perhatianmu, tetapi tidak ada kesempatan bagimu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Not that I speak in regard to need, for I have learned in whatever state I am, to be content: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ليس اني اقول من جهة احتياج فاني قد تعلمت ان اكون مكتفيا بما انا فيه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Kukatakan ini bukanlah karena kekurangan, sebab aku telah belajar mencukupkan diri dalam segala keadaan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> I know how to be abased, and I know how to abound. Everywhere and in all things I have learned both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to suffer need. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">اعرف ان اتضع واعرف ايضا ان استفضل. في كل شيء وفي جميع الاشياء قد تدربت ان اشبع وان اجوع وان استفضل وان انقص.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Aku tahu apa itu kekurangan dan aku tahu apa itu kelimpahan. Dalam segala hal dan dalam segala perkara tidak ada sesuatu yang merupakan rahasia bagiku; baik dalam hal kenyang, maupun dalam hal kelaparan, baik dalam hal kelimpahan maupun dalam hal kekurangan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> I can do all things through Christ who strengthens me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">استطيع كل شيء في المسيح الذي يقويني.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Segala perkara dapat kutanggung di dalam Dia yang memberi kekuatan kepadaku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Nevertheless you have done well that you shared in my distress. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">غير انكم فعلتم حسنا اذ اشتركتم في ضيقتي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Namun baik juga perbuatanmu, bahwa kamu telah mengambil bagian dalam kesusahanku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Now you Philippians know also that in the beginning of the gospel, when I departed from Macedonia, no church shared with me concerning giving and receiving but you only. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">وانتم ايضا تعلمون ايها الفيلبيون انه في بداءة الانجيل لما خرجت من مكدونية لم تشاركني كنيسة واحدة في حساب العطاء والاخذ الا انتم وحدكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Kamu sendiri tahu juga, hai orang-orang Filipi; pada waktu aku baru mulai mengabarkan Injil, ketika aku berangkat dari Makedonia, tidak ada satu jemaatpun yang mengadakan perhitungan hutang dan piutang dengan aku selain dari pada kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> For even in Thessalonica you sent [aid] once and again for my necessities. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فانكم في تسالونيكي ايضا ارسلتم اليّ مرة ومرتين لحاجتي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Karena di Tesalonikapun kamu telah satu dua kali mengirimkan bantuan kepadaku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Not that I seek the gift, but I seek the fruit that abounds to your account. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ليس اني اطلب العطية بل اطلب الثمر المتكاثر لحسابكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Tetapi yang kuutamakan bukanlah pemberian itu, melainkan buahnya, yang makin memperbesar keuntunganmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> Indeed I have all and abound. I am full, having received from Epaphroditus the things [sent] from you, a sweet-smelling aroma, an acceptable sacrifice, well pleasing to God. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">ولكني قد استوفيت كل شيء واستفضلت. قد امتلأت اذ قبلت من ابفرودتس الاشياء التي من عندكم نسيم رائحة طيبة ذبيحة مقبولة مرضية عند الله.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Kini aku telah menerima semua yang perlu dari padamu, malahan lebih dari pada itu. Aku berkelimpahan, karena aku telah menerima kirimanmu dari Epafroditus, suatu persembahan yang harum, suatu korban yang disukai dan yang berkenan kepada Allah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> And my God shall supply all your need according to His riches in glory by Christ Jesus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">فيملأ الهي كل احتياجكم بحسب غناه في المجد في المسيح يسوع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Allahku akan memenuhi segala keperluanmu menurut kekayaan dan kemuliaan-Nya dalam Kristus Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> Now to our God and Father [be] glory forever and ever. Amen. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">وللّه وابينا المجد الى دهر الداهرين. آمين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Dimuliakanlah Allah dan Bapa kita selama-lamanya! Amin.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> Greet every saint in Christ Jesus. The brethren who are with me greet you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">سلموا على كل قديس في المسيح يسوع. يسلم عليكم الاخوة الذين معي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Sampaikanlah salamku kepada tiap-tiap orang kudus dalam Kristus Yesus. Salam kepadamu dari saudara-saudara, yang bersama-sama dengan aku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> All the saints greet you, but especially those who are of Caesar's household. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">يسلم عليكم جميع القديسين ولا سيما الذين من بيت قيصر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Salam kepadamu dari segala orang kudus, khususnya dari mereka yang di istana Kaisar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. Amen. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">نعمة ربنا يسوع المسيح مع جميعكم آمين. كتبت الى اهل فيلبي من رومية على يد ابفرودتس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Kasih karunia Tuhan Yesus Kristus menyertai rohmu!</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>