<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Paul, a prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timothy [our] brother, To Philemon our beloved [friend] and fellow laborer, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">بولس اسير يسوع المسيح وتيموثاوس الاخ الى فليمون المحبوب والعامل معنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Dari Paulus, seorang hukuman karena Kristus Yesus dan dari Timotius saudara kita, kepada Filemon yang kekasih, teman sekerja kami</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> to the beloved Apphia, Archippus our fellow soldier, and to the church in your house: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">والى ابفيّة المحبوبة وارخبّس المتجند معنا والى الكنيسة التي في بيتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">dan kepada Apfia saudara perempuan kita dan kepada Arkhipus, teman seperjuangan kita dan kepada jemaat di rumahmu:</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">نعمة لكم وسلام من الله ابينا والرب يسوع المسيح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Kasih karunia dan damai sejahtera dari Allah, Bapa kita dan dari Tuhan Yesus Kristus menyertai kamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> I thank my God, making mention of you always in my prayers, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">اشكر الهي كل حين ذاكرا اياك في صلواتي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Aku mengucap syukur kepada Allahku, setiap kali aku mengingat engkau dalam doaku,</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> hearing of your love and faith which you have toward the Lord Jesus and toward all the saints, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">سامعا بمحبتك والايمان الذي لك نحو الرب يسوع ولجميع القديسين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">karena aku mendengar tentang kasihmu kepada semua orang kudus dan tentang imanmu kepada Tuhan Yesus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> that the sharing of your faith may become effective by the acknowledgment of every good thing which is in you in Christ Jesus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لكي تكون شركة ايمانك فعّالة في معرفة كل الصلاح الذي فيكم لاجل المسيح يسوع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Dan aku berdoa, agar persekutuanmu di dalam iman turut mengerjakan pengetahuan akan yang baik di antara kita untuk Kristus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> For we have great joy and consolation in your love, because the hearts of the saints have been refreshed by you, brother. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">لان لنا فرحا كثيرا وتعزية بسبب محبتك لان احشاء القديسين قد استراحت بك ايها الاخ</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Dari kasihmu sudah kuperoleh kegembiraan besar dan kekuatan, sebab hati orang-orang kudus telah kauhiburkan, saudaraku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Therefore, though I might be very bold in Christ to command you what is fitting, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لذلك وان كان لي بالمسيح ثقة كثيرة ان آمرك بما يليق</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Karena itu, sekalipun di dalam Kristus aku mempunyai kebebasan penuh untuk memerintahkan kepadamu apa yang harus engkau lakukan,</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> [yet] for love's sake I rather appeal [to you -- being] such a one as Paul, the aged, and now also a prisoner of Jesus Christ -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">من اجل المحبة اطلب بالحري اذ انا انسان هكذا نظير بولس الشيخ والآن اسير يسوع المسيح ايضا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">tetapi mengingat kasihmu itu, lebih baik aku memintanya dari padamu. Aku, Paulus, yang sudah menjadi tua, lagipula sekarang dipenjarakan karena Kristus Yesus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> I appeal to you for my son Onesimus, whom I have begotten [while] in my chains, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">اطلب اليك لاجل ابني انسيمس الذي ولدته في قيودي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">mengajukan permintaan kepadamu mengenai anakku yang kudapat selagi aku dalam penjara, yakni Onesimus</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> who once was unprofitable to you, but now is profitable to you and to me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">الذي كان قبلا غير نافع لك ولكنه الآن نافع لك ولي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">--dahulu memang dia tidak berguna bagimu, tetapi sekarang sangat berguna baik bagimu maupun bagiku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> I am sending him back. You therefore receive him, that is, my own heart, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">الذي رددته. فاقبله الذي هو احشائي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Dia kusuruh kembali kepadamu--dia, yaitu buah hatiku--.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> whom I wished to keep with me, that on your behalf he might minister to me in my chains for the gospel. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">الذي كنت اشاء ان امسكه عندي لكي يخدمني عوضا عنك في قيود الانجيل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Sebenarnya aku mau menahan dia di sini sebagai gantimu untuk melayani aku selama aku dipenjarakan karena Injil,</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> But without your consent I wanted to do nothing, that your good deed might not be by compulsion, as it were, but voluntary. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ولكن بدون رأيك لم ارد ان افعل شيئا لكي لا يكون خيرك كانه على سبيل الاضطرار بل على سبيل الاختيار.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">tetapi tanpa persetujuanmu, aku tidak mau berbuat sesuatu, supaya yang baik itu jangan engkau lakukan seolah-olah dengan paksa, melainkan dengan sukarela.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> For perhaps he departed for a while for this [purpose,] that you might receive him forever, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">لانه ربما لاجل هذا افترق عنك الى ساعة لكي يكون لك الى الابد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Sebab mungkin karena itulah dia dipisahkan sejenak dari padamu, supaya engkau dapat menerimanya untuk selama-lamanya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> no longer as a slave but more than a slave -- a beloved brother, especially to me but how much more to you, both in the flesh and in the Lord. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لا كعبد في ما بعد بل افضل من عبد اخا محبوبا ولا سيما اليّ فكم بالحري اليك في الجسد والرب جميعا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">bukan lagi sebagai hamba, melainkan lebih dari pada hamba, yaitu sebagai saudara yang kekasih, bagiku sudah demikian, apalagi bagimu, baik secara manusia maupun di dalam Tuhan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> If then you count me as a partner, receive him as [you would] me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فان كنت تحسبني شريكا فاقبله نظيري.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Kalau engkau menganggap aku temanmu seiman, terimalah dia seperti aku sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> But if he has wronged you or owes anything, put that on my account. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">ثم ان كان قد ظلمك بشيء او لك عليه دين فاحسب ذلك عليّ.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Dan kalau dia sudah merugikan engkau ataupun berhutang padamu, tanggungkanlah semuanya itu kepadaku--</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> I, Paul, am writing with my own hand. I will repay -- not to mention to you that you owe me even your own self besides. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">انا بولس كتبت بيدي. انا اوفي. حتى لا اقول لك انك مديون لي بنفسك ايضا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">aku, Paulus, menjaminnya dengan tulisan tanganku sendiri: Aku akan membayarnya--agar jangan kukatakan: "Tanggungkanlah semuanya itu kepadamu!" --karena engkau berhutang padaku, yaitu dirimu sendiri.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> Yes, brother, let me have joy from you in the Lord; refresh my heart in the Lord. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">نعم ايها الاخ ليكن لي فرح بك في الرب. ارح احشائي في الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Ya saudaraku, semoga engkau berguna bagiku di dalam Tuhan: Hiburkanlah hatiku di dalam Kristus!</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> Having confidence in your obedience, I write to you, knowing that you will do even more than I say. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">اذ انا واثق باطاعتك كتبت اليك عالما انك تفعل ايضا اكثر مما اقول</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Dengan percaya kepada ketaatanmu, kutuliskan ini kepadamu. Aku tahu, lebih dari pada permintaanku ini akan kaulakukan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> But, meanwhile, also prepare a guest room for me, for I trust that through your prayers I shall be granted to you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">ومع هذا اعدد لي ايضا منزلا لاني ارجو انني بصلواتكم سأوهب لكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Dalam pada itu bersedialah juga memberi tumpangan kepadaku, karena aku harap oleh doamu aku akan dikembalikan kepadamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> Epaphras, my fellow prisoner in Christ Jesus, greets you, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">يسلم عليك ابفراس المأسور معي في المسيح يسوع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Salam kepadamu dari Epafras, temanku sepenjara karena Kristus Yesus,</language></verse>
			<verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24"> [as do] Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, Luke, my fellow laborers. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">ومرقس وارسترخس وديماس ولوقا العاملون معي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">dan dari Markus, Aristarkhus, Demas dan Lukas, teman-teman sekerjaku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25"> The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ [be] with your spirit. Amen. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">نعمة ربنا يسوع المسيح مع روحكم. آمين. الى فليمون كتبت من رومية على يد انسيمس الخادم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Kasih karunia Tuhan Yesus Kristus menyertai roh kamu!</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>