<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book book="Prayer of Manasseh">
<chapter num="1">
<verse num="1">
<language id="English" verse="1">
            O Lord Almighty, God of our fathers, of Abraham and Isaac and Jacob, and of their righteous seed,
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">
            O Lord Almighty, God of our fathers, of Abraham and Isaac and Jacob, and of their righteous seed,
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="1">
            أيُّها الربُّ الضابطُ الكُلَّ، إلهُ آبائِنا، ابراهيمَ واسحقَ ويعقوبَ، ونَسْلِهم الصدّيق، 
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="2">
<language id="English" verse="2">
            You Who have made heaven and earth with all their adornment,
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">
            You Who have made heaven and earth with all their adornment,
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="2">
            يا صانعَ السّماءِ والأرضِ وكلِّ عالَمِهِما،
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="3">
<language id="English" verse="3">
            You Who have bound the sea by the word of your command, You Who have shut the deep, and sealed it with your fearsome and glorious Name,
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">
            You Who have bound the sea by the word of your command, You Who have shut the deep, and sealed it with your fearsome and glorious Name,
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="3">
            يا مَن قَيَّدْتَ البحرَ بِكَلِمَةِ أمْرِكَ، يا مَن قَفَلْتَ اللجَّةَ وخَتَمْتَها باسمِكَ المَرهوب المجيد، 
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="4">
<language id="English" verse="4">
            You at whom all things shudder, and tremble before Your power,
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">
            You at whom all things shudder, and tremble before Your power,
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="4">
            يا مَن يَرْهَبُ الكلُّ ويَرتَعِدُ مِن وجهِ قُدرتِهِ، 
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="5">
<language id="English" verse="5">
            for unbearable is the magnificence of Your glory, and not to be withstood is the anger of Your threat toward sinners,
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">
            for unbearable is the magnificence of Your glory, and not to be withstood is the anger of Your threat toward sinners,
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="5">
            لأنَّ عِظَمَ جلالِ مجدِكَ لا يُحتَمَل، وسَخَطُكَ بالوَعيدِ على الخطأَةِ لا قوامَ لهُ، 
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="6">
<language id="English" verse="6">
            and unmeasurable and inscrutable is the mercy of Your promise,
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">
            and unmeasurable and inscrutable is the mercy of Your promise,
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="6">
            ورحمَةَ موعِدكَ لا تُحصَى ولا يُستَقْصَى أثرُها.
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="7">
<language id="English" verse="7">
            for You are the Lord Most High, compassionate, patient, and merciful, repenting from the evil deeds of people. You, O Lord, according to the fullness of Your clemency, promised repentance and forgiveness to those who have sinned against You, and in the fullness of Your mercies, You have appointed repentance for sinners toward salvation.
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">
            for You are the Lord Most High, compassionate, patient, and merciful, repenting from the evil deeds of people. You, O Lord, according to the fullness of Your clemency, promised repentance and forgiveness to those who have sinned against You, and in the fullness of Your mercies, You have appointed repentance for sinners toward salvation.
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="7">
            لأنَّكَ أنتَ الربُّ العليُّ المتحنِّنُ، الطويلُ الأناة والجزيلُ الرحمة، والتوّابُ على مساوِئِ النّاسِ. أنتَ يا ربُّ على حَسَبِ كَثرَةِ صلاحِكَ، وَعَدْتَ بالتوبَةِ والغُفران للمُخطِئين إليك، وبِكَثرةِ رأَفَتِكَ حَدَّدْتَ توبةً للخطأةِ للخلاص.
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="8">
<language id="English" verse="8">
            Therefore, You, O Lord, God of the righteous, have not given repentance for the righteous, for Abraham and Isaac and Jacob, who had not sinned against You, but you have given repentance for me, the sinner.
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">
            Therefore, You, O Lord, God of the righteous, have not given repentance for the righteous, for Abraham and Isaac and Jacob, who had not sinned against You, but you have given repentance for me, the sinner.
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="8">
            فأنتَ أيُّها الربُّ إلهُ القوّاتِ، لمْ تَضَعِ التَّوبَةَ للصدّيقينَ: لابراهيمَ واسحقَ ويعقوبَ، الذينَ لم يَخطأوا إليكَ؛ بل وضَعْتَ التَّوبَةَ لي أنا الخاطئ،
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="9">
<language id="English" verse="9">
            For I have sinned more than the number of sand of the sea; my lawless deeds are multiplied, O Lord, multiplied, and I am not worthy to look and see the heights of heaven because of the multitude of my unrighteous deeds.
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">
            For I have sinned more than the number of sand of the sea; my lawless deeds are multiplied, O Lord, multiplied, and I am not worthy to look and see the heights of heaven because of the multitude of my unrighteous deeds.
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="9">
            فإنّي قد أَخطأْتُ أكثرَ مِن عدَدِ رَملِ البحرِ. قد تَكاثَرَتْ آثامي يا ربُّ، قد تكاثَرَتْ آثامي، ولسْتُ أنا بِأَهْلٍ أنْ أَتَفَرَّسَ وأنظُرَ عُلُوَّ السماءِ من كَثْرَةِ ظُلْمي،
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="10">
<language id="English" verse="10">
            I am bent down by too many a bond of iron for the lifting of my head because of my sins, and there is no relief for me, for I have provoked Your wrath and done evil before You. I have set up abominations and multiplied provocations (idols).
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">
            I am bent down by too many a bond of iron for the lifting of my head because of my sins, and there is no relief for me, for I have provoked Your wrath and done evil before You. I have set up abominations and multiplied provocations (idols).
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="10">
            وأنا مُنْحَنٍ بكَثْرَةِ قيودِ الحديدِ لِئَلاّ أَرْفَعَ رأسي، وليسَتْ لي راحةٌ، لأنّي أغْضَبْتُ غَضَبَكَ، والشرَّ قُدّامَكَ صَنَعْتُ، إذْ لمْ أَصْنَعْ مَشيئَتَكَ ولا حَفِظْتُ أوامِرَكَ.
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="11">
<language id="English" verse="11">
            And now I bend the knee of my heart, begging for Your clemency.
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">
            And now I bend the knee of my heart, begging for Your clemency.
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="11">
            فالآنَ أَحْني رُكبَةَ قَلبي مُبتَهِلاً إلى صلاحِكَ،
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="12">
<language id="English" verse="12">
            I have sinned, O Lord, I have sinned, and I know my lawless deeds.
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">
            I have sinned, O Lord, I have sinned, and I know my lawless deeds.
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="12">
            أخطَأْتُ يا ربُّ أخطأْتُ، وبآثامي أنا عارِفٌ،
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="13">
<language id="English" verse="13">
            I am asking, begging You: forgive me, O Lord, forgive me! Do not destroy me with my lawless deeds, nor for all ages keep angry with me, nor condemn me to the depths of the earth, for You, O Lord, are the God of those who repent.
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">
            I am asking, begging You: forgive me, O Lord, forgive me! Do not destroy me with my lawless deeds, nor for all ages keep angry with me, nor condemn me to the depths of the earth, for You, O Lord, are the God of those who repent.
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="13">
            لكنَّني أسأَلُكَ مُتَضَرِّعاً، اغْفِر لي يا ربُّ، اغْفِرْ لي، ولا تُهْلِكْني بآثامي، ولا إلى الأبدِ تَحقِدْ عليَّ حافِظاً عليَّ شُروري، ولا تَسْجُنّي في أسافِلِ الأرضِ، لأنَّك أنتَ هو اللهُ إلهُ التّائبينَ،
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="14">
<language id="English" verse="14">
            And in me You will display Your goodness, for, my being unworthy, You will save me according to Your great mercy.
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">
            And in me You will display Your goodness, for, my being unworthy, You will save me according to Your great mercy.
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="14">
            وفيَّ توضِحُ كلَّ صلاحِكَ، لأنّي أنا غيرُ مُستحِقٍّ فتُخلِّصْني على حسَبِ كَثرةِ رحمَتِكَ،
         </language>
</verse>
<verse num="15">
<language id="English" verse="15">
            And I will praise You throughout all the days of my life, for all the power of the heavens sing Your praise. For Yours is the glory, to the ages. Amen.
         </language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">
            And I will praise You throughout all the days of my life, for all the power of the heavens sing Your praise. For Yours is the glory, to the ages. Amen.
         </language>
<language id="Arabic" verse="15">
            وأُسبِّحُكَ كلَّ حينٍ جميعَ أيّامِ حياتي، لأنَّ إيّاكَ تُسبِّحُ كلَّ قُواتِ السماوات، ولكَ المجدَ إلى دهر الدّاهرين، آمين.
         </language>
</verse>
</chapter>
</book>