<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> The song of songs, which [is] Solomon's. THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">نشيد الانشاد الذي لسليمان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Kidung agung dari Salomo.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Let him kiss me with the kisses of his mouth -- For your love [is] better than wine. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">ليقبلني بقبلات فمه لان حبك اطيب من الخمر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">--Kiranya ia mencium aku dengan kecupan! Karena cintamu lebih nikmat dari pada anggur,</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Because of the fragrance of your good ointments, Your name [is] ointment poured forth; Therefore the virgins love you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">لرائحة ادهانك الطيبة اسمك دهن مهراق. لذلك احبتك العذارى.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">harum bau minyakmu, bagaikan minyak yang tercurah namamu, oleh sebab itu gadis-gadis cinta kepadamu!</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Draw me away! THE DAUGHTERS OF JERUSALEM We will run after you. THE SHULAMITE The king has brought me into his chambers. THE DAUGHTERS OF JERUSALEM We will be glad and rejoice in you. We will remember your love more than wine. THE SHULAMITE Rightly do they love you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">اجذبني وراءك فنجري . ادخلني الملك الى حجاله. نبتهج ونفرح بك. نذكر حبك اكثر من الخمر. بالحق يحبونك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Tariklah aku di belakangmu, marilah kita cepat-cepat pergi! Sang raja telah membawa aku ke dalam maligai-maligainya. Kami akan bersorak-sorai dan bergembira karena engkau, kami akan memuji cintamu lebih dari pada anggur! Layaklah mereka cinta kepadamu!</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> I [am] dark, but lovely, O daughters of Jerusalem, Like the tents of Kedar, Like the curtains of Solomon. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">انا سوداء وجميلة يا بنات اورشليم كخيام قيدار كشقق سليمان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Memang hitam aku, tetapi cantik, hai puteri-puteri Yerusalem, seperti kemah orang Kedar, seperti tirai-tirai orang Salma.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Do not look upon me, because I [am] dark, Because the sun has tanned me. My mother's sons were angry with me; They made me the keeper of the vineyards, [But] my own vineyard I have not kept. (TO HER BELOVED) </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لا تنظرن اليّ لكوني سوداء لان الشمس قد لوحتني. بنو امي غضبوا عليّ. جعلوني ناطورة الكروم . ‎اما كرمي فلم انطره.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Janganlah kamu perhatikan bahwa aku hitam, karena terik matahari membakar aku. Putera-putera ibuku marah kepadaku, aku dijadikan mereka penjaga kebun-kebun anggur; kebun anggurku sendiri tak kujaga.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Tell me, O you whom I love, Where you feed [your flock,] Where you make [it] rest at noon. For why should I be as one who veils herself By the flocks of your companions? THE BELOVED </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">أخبرني يا من تحبه نفسي اين ترعى اين تربض عند الظهيرة. لماذا انا اكون كمقنّعة عند قطعان اصحابك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Ceriterakanlah kepadaku, jantung hatiku, di mana kakanda menggembalakan domba, di mana kakanda membiarkan domba-domba berbaring pada petang hari. Karena mengapa aku akan jadi serupa pengembara dekat kawanan-kawanan domba teman-temanmu?</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> If you do not know, O fairest among women, Follow in the footsteps of the flock, And feed your little goats Beside the shepherds' tents. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ان لم تعرفي ايتها الجميلة بين النساء فاخرجي على آثار الغنم وارعي جداءك عند مساكن الرعاة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">--Jika engkau tak tahu, hai jelita di antara wanita, ikutilah jejak-jejak domba, dan gembalakanlah anak-anak kambingmu dekat perkemahan para gembala.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> I have compared you, my love, To my filly among Pharaoh's chariots. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لقد شبهتك يا حبيبتي بفرس في مركبات فرعون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">--Dengan kuda betina dari pada kereta-kereta Firaun kuumpamakan engkau, manisku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Your cheeks are lovely with ornaments, Your neck with chains [of gold.] THE DAUGHTERS OF JERUSALEM </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">ما اجمل خديك بسموط وعنقك بقلائد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Moleklah pipimu di tengah perhiasan-perhiasan dan lehermu di tengah kalung-kalung.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> We will make you ornaments of gold With studs of silver. THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">نصنع لك سلاسل من ذهب مع جمان من فضة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Kami akan membuat bagimu perhiasan-perhiasan emas dengan manik-manik perak.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> While the king [is] at his table, My spikenard sends forth its fragrance. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ما دام الملك في مجلسه افاح نارديني رائحته.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">--Sementara sang raja duduk pada mejanya, semerbak bau narwastuku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> A bundle of myrrh [is] my beloved to me, That lies all night between my breasts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">صرة المرّ حبيبي لي. بين ثديي يبيت.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Bagiku kekasihku bagaikan sebungkus mur, tersisip di antara buah dadaku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> My beloved [is] to me a cluster of henna [blooms] In the vineyards of En Gedi. THE BELOVED </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">طاقة فاغية حبيبي لي في كروم عين جدي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Bagiku kekasihku setangkai bunga pacar di kebun-kebun anggur En-Gedi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Behold, you [are] fair, my love! Behold, you [are] fair! You [have] dove's eyes. THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ها انت جميلة يا حبيبتي ها انت جميلة. عيناك حمامتان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">--Lihatlah, cantik engkau, manisku, sungguh cantik engkau, bagaikan merpati matamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> Behold, you [are] handsome, my beloved! Yes, pleasant! Also our bed [is] green. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">ها انت جميل يا حبيبي وحلو وسريرنا اخضر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">--Lihatlah, tampan engkau, kekasihku, sungguh menarik; sungguh sejuk petiduran kita.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> The beams of our houses [are] cedar, [And] our rafters of fir. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">جوائز بيتنا ارز وروافدنا سرو</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Dari kayu aras balok-balok rumah kita, dari kayu eru papan dinding-dinding kita.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="2">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> I [am] the rose of Sharon, [And] the lily of the valleys. THE BELOVED </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">انا نرجس شارون سوسنة الاودية</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Bunga mawar dari Saron aku, bunga bakung di lembah-lembah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Like a lily among thorns, So is my love among the daughters. THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">كالسوسنة بين الشوك كذلك حبيبتي بين البنات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">--Seperti bunga bakung di antara duri-duri, demikianlah manisku di antara gadis-gadis.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Like an apple tree among the trees of the woods, So [is] my beloved among the sons. I sat down in his shade with great delight, And his fruit [was] sweet to my taste. THE SHULAMITE TO THE DAUGHTERS OF JERUSALEM </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">كالتفاح بين شجر الوعر كذلك حبيبي بين البنين. تحت ظله اشتهيت ان اجلس وثمرته حلوة لحلقي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">--Seperti pohon apel di antara pohon-pohon di hutan, demikianlah kekasihku di antara teruna-teruna. Di bawah naungannya aku ingin duduk, buahnya manis bagi langit-langitku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> He brought me to the banqueting house, And his banner over me [was] love. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ادخلني الى بيت الخمر وعلمه فوقي محبة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Telah dibawanya aku ke rumah pesta, dan panjinya di atasku adalah cinta.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Sustain me with cakes of raisins, Refresh me with apples, For I [am] lovesick. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">اسندوني باقراص الزبيب انعشوني بالتفاح فاني مريضة حبا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Kuatkanlah aku dengan penganan kismis, segarkanlah aku dengan buah apel, sebab sakit asmara aku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> His left hand [is] under my head, And his right hand embraces me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">شماله تحت راسي ويمينه تعانقني.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Tangan kirinya ada di bawah kepalaku, tangan kanannya memeluk aku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> I charge you, O daughters of Jerusalem, By the gazelles or by the does of the field, Do not stir up nor awaken love Until it pleases. THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">احلفكن يا بنات اورشليم بالظباء وبأيائل الحقول ألا تيقظن ولا تنبهن الحبيب حتى يشاء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Kusumpahi kamu, puteri-puteri Yerusalem, demi kijang-kijang atau demi rusa-rusa betina di padang: jangan kamu membangkitkan dan menggerakkan cinta sebelum diingininya!</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> The voice of my beloved! Behold, he comes Leaping upon the mountains, Skipping upon the hills. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">صوت حبيبي. هوذا آت طافرا على الجبال قافزا على التلال.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Dengarlah! Kekasihku! Lihatlah, ia datang, melompat-lompat di atas gunung-gunung, meloncat-loncat di atas bukit-bukit.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> My beloved is like a gazelle or a young stag. Behold, he stands behind our wall; He is looking through the windows, Gazing through the lattice. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">حبيبي هو شبيه بالظبي او بغفر الأيائل. هوذا واقف وراء حائطنا يتطلع من الكوى يوصوص من الشبابيك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Kekasihku serupa kijang, atau anak rusa. Lihatlah, ia berdiri di balik dinding kita, sambil menengok-nengok melalui tingkap-tingkap dan melihat dari kisi-kisi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> My beloved spoke, and said to me: "Rise up, my love, my fair one, And come away. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">اجاب حبيبي وقال لي قومي يا حبيبتي يا جميلتي وتعالي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Kekasihku mulai berbicara kepadaku: "Bangunlah manisku, jelitaku, marilah!</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> For lo, the winter is past, The rain is over [and] gone. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لان الشتاء قد مضى والمطر مرّ وزال.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Karena lihatlah, musim dingin telah lewat, hujan telah berhenti dan sudah lalu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> The flowers appear on the earth; The time of singing has come, And the voice of the turtledove Is heard in our land. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">الزهور ظهرت في الارض. بلغ اوان القضب وصوت اليمامة سمع في ارضنا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Di ladang telah nampak bunga-bunga, tibalah musim memangkas; bunyi tekukur terdengar di tanah kita.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> The fig tree puts forth her green figs, And the vines [with] the tender grapes Give a good smell. Rise up, my love, my fair one, And come away! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">التينة اخرجت فجّها وقعال الكروم تفيح رائحتها. قومي يا حبيبتي يا جميلتي وتعالي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Pohon ara mulai berbuah, dan bunga pohon anggur semerbak baunya. Bangunlah, manisku, jelitaku, marilah!</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> "O my dove, in the clefts of the rock, In the secret [places] of the cliff, Let me see your face, Let me hear your voice; For your voice [is] sweet, And your face [is] lovely." HER BROTHERS </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">يا حمامتي في محاجئ الصخر في ستر المعاقل أريني وجهك اسمعيني صوتك لان صوتك لطيف ووجهك جميل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Merpatiku di celah-celah batu, di persembunyian lereng-lereng gunung, perlihatkanlah wajahmu, perdengarkanlah suaramu! Sebab merdu suaramu dan elok wajahmu!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Catch us the foxes, The little foxes that spoil the vines, For our vines [have] tender grapes. THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">خذوا لنا الثعالب الثعالب الصغار المفسدة الكروم لان كرومنا قد أقعلت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Tangkaplah bagi kami rubah-rubah itu, rubah-rubah yang kecil, yang merusak kebun-kebun anggur, kebun-kebun anggur kami yang sedang berbunga!</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> My beloved [is] mine, and I [am] his. He feeds [his flock] among the lilies. (TO HER BELOVED) </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">حبيبي لي وانا له الراعي بين السوسن.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Kekasihku kepunyaanku, dan aku kepunyaan dia yang menggembalakan domba di tengah-tengah bunga bakung.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Until the day breaks And the shadows flee away, Turn, my beloved, And be like a gazelle Or a young stag Upon the mountains of Bether. THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">الى ان يفيح النهار وتنهزم الظلال ارجع واشبه يا حبيبي الظبي او غفر الأيائل على الجبال المشعّبة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Sebelum angin senja berembus dan bayang-bayang menghilang, kembalilah, kekasihku, berlakulah seperti kijang, atau seperti anak rusa di atas gunung-gunung tanaman rempah-rempah!</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="3">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> By night on my bed I sought the one I love; I sought him, but I did not find him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">في الليل على فراشي طلبت من تحبه نفسي طلبته فما وجدته.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Di atas ranjangku pada malam hari kucari jantung hatiku. Kucari, tetapi tak kutemui dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> "I will rise now," [I said,] "And go about the city; In the streets and in the squares I will seek the one I love." I sought him, but I did not find him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اني اقوم واطوف في المدينة في الاسواق وفي الشوارع اطلب من تحبه نفسي. طلبته فما وجدته.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Aku hendak bangun dan berkeliling di kota; di jalan-jalan dan di lapangan-lapangan kucari dia, jantung hatiku. Kucari, tetapi tak kutemui dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> The watchmen who go about the city found me; [I said,] "Have you seen the one I love?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">وجدني الحرس الطائف في المدينة فقلت أرأيتم من تحبه نفسي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Aku ditemui peronda-peronda kota. "Apakah kamu melihat jantung hatiku?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Scarcely had I passed by them, When I found the one I love. I held him and would not let him go, Until I had brought him to the house of my mother, And into the chamber of her who conceived me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فما جاوزتهم الا قليلا حتى وجدت من تحبه نفسي فامسكته ولم ارخه حتى ادخلته بيت امي وحجرة من حبلت بي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Baru saja aku meninggalkan mereka, kutemui jantung hatiku; kupegang dan tak kulepaskan dia, sampai kubawa dia ke rumah ibuku, ke kamar orang yang melahirkan aku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> I charge you, O daughters of Jerusalem, By the gazelles or by the does of the field, Do not stir up nor awaken love Until it pleases. THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">احلفكن يا بنات اورشليم بالظباء وبأيائل الحقل ألا تيقظن ولا تنبهن الحبيب حتى يشاء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Kusumpahi kamu, puteri-puteri Yerusalem, demi kijang-kijang atau demi rusa-rusa betina di padang: jangan kamu membangkitkan dan menggerakkan cinta sebelum diingininya!</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Who [is] this coming out of the wilderness Like pillars of smoke, Perfumed with myrrh and frankincense, With all the merchant's fragrant powders? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">من هذه الطالعة من البرية كاعمدة من دخان معطرة بالمر واللبان وبكل اذرّة التاجر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Apakah itu yang membubung dari padang gurun seperti gumpalan-gumpalan asap tersaput dengan harum mur dan kemenyan dan bau segala macam serbuk wangi dari pedagang?</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Behold, it [is] Solomon's couch, [With] sixty valiant men around it, Of the valiant of Israel. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">هوذا تخت سليمان حوله ستون جبارا من جبابرة اسرائيل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Lihat, itulah joli Salomo, dikelilingi oleh enam puluh pahlawan dari antara pahlawan-pahlawan Israel.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> They all hold swords, [Being] expert in war. Every man [has] his sword on his thigh Because of fear in the night. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">كلهم قابضون سيوفا ومتعلمون الحرب. كل رجل سيفه على فخذه من هول الليل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Semua membawa pedang, terlatih dalam perang, masing-masing dengan pedang pada pinggang karena kedahsyatan malam.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Of the wood of Lebanon Solomon the King Made himself a palanquin: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">الملك سليمان عمل لنفسه تختا من خشب لبنان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Raja Salomo membuat bagi dirinya suatu tandu dari kayu Libanon.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> He made its pillars [of] silver, Its support [of] gold, Its seat [of] purple, Its interior paved [with] love By the daughters of Jerusalem. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">عمل اعمدته فضة وروافده ذهبا ومقعده ارجوانا ووسطه مرصوفا محبة من بنات اورشليم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Tiang-tiangnya dibuatnya dari perak, sandarannya dari emas, tempat duduknya berwarna ungu, bagian dalamnya dihiasi dengan kayu arang. Hai puteri-puteri Yerusalem,</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Go forth, O daughters of Zion, And see King Solomon with the crown With which his mother crowned him On the day of his wedding, The day of the gladness of his heart. THE BELOVED </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">اخرجن يا بنات صهيون وانظرن الملك سليمان بالتاج الذي توجته به امه في يوم عرسه وفي يوم فرح قلبه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">puteri-puteri Sion, keluarlah dan tengoklah raja Salomo dengan mahkota yang dikenakan kepadanya oleh ibunya pada hari pernikahannya, pada hari kesukaan hatinya.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="4">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Behold, you [are] fair, my love! Behold, you [are] fair! You [have] dove's eyes behind your veil. Your hair [is] like a flock of goats, Going down from Mount Gilead. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ها انت جميلة يا حبيبتي ها انت جميلة عيناك حمامتان من تحت نقابك. شعرك كقطيع معز رابض على جبل جلعاد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Lihatlah, cantik engkau, manisku, sungguh cantik engkau! Bagaikan merpati matamu di balik telekungmu. Rambutmu bagaikan kawanan kambing yang bergelombang turun dari pegunungan Gilead.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Your teeth [are] like a flock of shorn [sheep] Which have come up from the washing, Every one of which bears twins, And none [is] barren among them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اسنانك كقطيع الجزائز الصادرة من الغسل اللواتي كل واحدة متئم وليس فيهنّ عقيم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Gigimu bagaikan kawanan domba yang baru saja dicukur, yang keluar dari tempat pembasuhan, yang beranak kembar semuanya, yang tak beranak tak ada.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Your lips [are] like a strand of scarlet, And your mouth is lovely. Your temples behind your veil [Are] like a piece of pomegranate. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">شفتاك كسلكة من القرمز. وفمك حلو. خدك كفلقة رمانة تحت نقابك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Bagaikan seutas pita kirmizi bibirmu, dan elok mulutmu. Bagaikan belahan buah delima pelipismu di balik telekungmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Your neck [is] like the tower of David, Built for an armory, On which hang a thousand bucklers, All shields of mighty men. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">عنقك كبرج داود المبني للاسلحة. الف مجن علق عليه كلها اتراس الجبابرة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Lehermu seperti menara Daud, dibangun untuk menyimpan senjata. Seribu perisai tergantung padanya dan gada para pahlawan semuanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Your two breasts [are] like two fawns, Twins of a gazelle, Which feed among the lilies. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">ثدياك كخشفتي ظبية توأمين يرعيان بين السوسن.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Seperti dua anak rusa buah dadamu, seperti anak kembar kijang yang tengah makan rumput di tengah-tengah bunga bakung.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Until the day breaks And the shadows flee away, I will go my way to the mountain of myrrh And to the hill of frankincense. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">الى ان يفيح النهار وتنهزم الظلال اذهب الى جبل المرّ والى تل اللبان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Sebelum angin senja berembus dan bayang-bayang menghilang, aku ingin pergi ke gunung mur dan ke bukit kemenyan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> You [are] all fair, my love, And [there is] no spot in you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">كلك جميل يا حبيبتي ليس فيك عيبة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Engkau cantik sekali, manisku, tak ada cacat cela padamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Come with me from Lebanon, [my] spouse, With me from Lebanon. Look from the top of Amana, From the top of Senir and Hermon, From the lions' dens, From the mountains of the leopards. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">هلمي معي من لبنان يا عروس معي من لبنان. انظري من راس امانة من راس شنير وحرمون من خدور الأسود من جبال النمور.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Turunlah kepadaku dari gunung Libanon, pengantinku, datanglah kepadaku dari gunung Libanon, turunlah dari puncak Amana, dari puncak Senir dan Hermon, dari liang-liang singa, dari pegunungan tempat macan tutul!</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> You have ravished my heart, My sister, [my] spouse; You have ravished my heart With one [look] of your eyes, With one link of your necklace. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">قد سبيت قلبي يا اختي العروس قد سبيت قلبي باحدى عينيك بقلادة واحدة من عنقك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Engkau mendebarkan hatiku, dinda, pengantinku, engkau mendebarkan hati dengan satu kejapan mata, dengan seuntai kalung dari perhiasan lehermu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> How fair is your love, My sister, [my] spouse! How much better than wine is your love, And the scent of your perfumes Than all spices! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">ما احسن حبك يا اختي العروس كم محبتك اطيب من الخمر وكم رائحة ادهانك اطيب من كل الاطياب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Betapa nikmat kasihmu, dinda, pengantinku! Jauh lebih nikmat cintamu dari pada anggur, dan lebih harum bau minyakmu dari pada segala macam rempah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Your lips, O [my] spouse, Drip as the honeycomb; Honey and milk [are] under your tongue; And the fragrance of your garments [Is] like the fragrance of Lebanon. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">شفتاك يا عروس تقطران شهدا. تحت لسانك عسل ولبن ورائحة ثيابك كرائحة لبنان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Bibirmu meneteskan madu murni, pengantinku, madu dan susu ada di bawah lidahmu, dan bau pakaianmu seperti bau gunung Libanon.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> A garden enclosed [Is] my sister, [my] spouse, A spring shut up, A fountain sealed. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">اختي العروس جنة مغلقة عين مقفلة ينبوع مختوم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Dinda, pengantinku, kebun tertutup engkau, kebun tertutup dan mata air termeterai.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Your plants [are] an orchard of pomegranates With pleasant fruits, Fragrant henna with spikenard, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">اغراسك فردوس رمان مع اثمار نفيسة فاغية وناردين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Tunas-tunasmu merupakan kebun pohon-pohon delima dengan buah-buahnya yang lezat, bunga pacar dan narwastu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Spikenard and saffron, Calamus and cinnamon, With all trees of frankincense, Myrrh and aloes, With all the chief spices -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ناردين وكركم. قصب الذريرة وقرفة مع كل عود اللبان. مر وعود مع كل انفس الاطياب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">narwastu dan kunyit, tebu dan kayu manis dengan segala macam pohon kemenyan, mur dan gaharu, beserta pelbagai rempah yang terpilih.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> A fountain of gardens, A well of living waters, And streams from Lebanon. THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ينبوع جنات بئر مياه حية وسيول من لبنان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">O, mata air di kebun, sumber air hidup, yang mengalir dari gunung Libanon!</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> Awake, O north [wind,] And come, O south! Blow upon my garden, [That] its spices may flow out. Let my beloved come to his garden And eat its pleasant fruits. THE BELOVED </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">استيقظي يا ريح الشمال وتعالي يا ريح الجنوب. هبي على جنتي فتقطر اطيابها. ليأت حبيبي الى جنته ويأكل ثمره النفيس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">--Bangunlah, hai angin utara, dan marilah, hai angin selatan, bertiuplah dalam kebunku, supaya semerbaklah bau rempah-rempahnya! Semoga kekasihku datang ke kebunnya dan makan buah-buahnya yang lezat.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="5">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> I have come to my garden, my sister, [my] spouse; I have gathered my myrrh with my spice; I have eaten my honeycomb with my honey; I have drunk my wine with my milk. (TO HIS FRIENDS) Eat, O friends! Drink, yes, drink deeply, O beloved ones! THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">قد دخلت جنتي يا اختي العروس. قطفت مري مع طيبي. اكلت شهدي مع عسلي. شربت خمري مع لبني. كلوا ايها الاصحاب اشربوا واسكروا ايها الاحباء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">--Aku datang ke kebunku, dinda, pengantinku, kukumpulkan mur dan rempah-rempahku, kumakan sambangku dan maduku, kuminum anggurku dan susuku. Makanlah, teman-teman, minumlah, minumlah sampai mabuk cinta!</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> I sleep, but my heart is awake; [It is] the voice of my beloved! He knocks, [saying,] "Open for me, my sister, my love, My dove, my perfect one; For my head is covered with dew, My locks with the drops of the night." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">انا نائمة وقلبي مستيقظ. صوت حبيبي قارعا. افتحي لي يا اختي يا حبيبتي يا حمامتي يا كاملتي لان راسي امتلأ من الطل وقصصي من ندى الليل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Aku tidur, tetapi hatiku bangun. Dengarlah, kekasihku mengetuk. "Bukalah pintu, dinda, manisku, merpatiku, idam-idamanku, karena kepalaku penuh embun, dan rambutku penuh tetesan embun malam!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> I have taken off my robe; How can I put it on [again?] I have washed my feet; How can I defile them? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">قد خلعت ثوبي فكيف البسه. قد غسلت رجليّ فكيف اوسخهما.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">"Bajuku telah kutanggalkan, apakah aku akan mengenakannya lagi? Kakiku telah kubasuh, apakah aku akan mengotorkannya pula?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> My beloved put his hand By the latch [of the door,] And my heart yearned for him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">حبيبي مدّ يده من الكوّة فانّت عليه احشائي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Kekasihku memasukkan tangannya melalui lobang pintu, berdebar-debarlah hatiku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> I arose to open for my beloved, And my hands dripped [with] myrrh, My fingers with liquid myrrh, On the handles of the lock. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">قمت لافتح لحبيبي ويداي تقطران مرّا واصابعي مر قاطر على مقبض القفل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Aku bangun untuk membuka pintu bagi kekasihku, tanganku bertetesan mur; bertetesan cairan mur jari-jariku pada pegangan kancing pintu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> I opened for my beloved, But my beloved had turned away [and] was gone. My heart leaped up when he spoke. I sought him, but I could not find him; I called him, but he gave me no answer. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فتحت لحبيبي لكن حبيبي تحول وعبر. نفسي خرجت عندما ادبر. طلبته فما وجدته دعوته فما اجابني.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Kekasihku kubukakan pintu, tetapi kekasihku sudah pergi, lenyap. Seperti pingsan aku ketika ia menghilang. Kucari dia, tetapi tak kutemui, kupanggil, tetapi tak disahutnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> The watchmen who went about the city found me. They struck me, they wounded me; The keepers of the walls Took my veil away from me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">وجدني الحرس الطائف في المدينة. ضربوني جرحوني. حفظة الاسوار رفعوا ازاري عني.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Aku ditemui peronda-peronda kota, dipukulinya aku, dilukainya, selendangku dirampas oleh penjaga-penjaga tembok.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> I charge you, O daughters of Jerusalem, If you find my beloved, That you tell him I [am] lovesick! THE DAUGHTERS OF JERUSALEM </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">احلفكنّ يا بنات اورشليم ان وجدتنّ حبيبي ان تخبرنه باني مريضة حبا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Kusumpahi kamu, puteri-puteri Yerusalem: bila kamu menemukan kekasihku, apakah yang akan kamu katakan kepadanya? Katakanlah, bahwa sakit asmara aku!</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> What [is] your beloved More than [another] beloved, O fairest among women? What [is] your beloved More than [another] beloved, That you so charge us? THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ما حبيبك من حبيب ايتها الجميلة بين النساء ما حبيبك من حبيب حتى تحلفينا هكذا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">--Apakah kelebihan kekasihmu dari pada kekasih yang lain, hai jelita di antara wanita? Apakah kelebihan kekasihmu dari pada kekasih yang lain, sehingga kausumpahi kami begini?</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> My beloved [is] white and ruddy, Chief among ten thousand. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">حبيبي ابيض واحمر. معلم بين ربوة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">--Putih bersih dan merah cerah kekasihku, menyolok mata di antara selaksa orang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> His head [is like] the finest gold; His locks [are] wavy, [And] black as a raven. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">راسه ذهب ابريز. قصصه مسترسلة حالكة كالغراب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Bagaikan emas, emas murni, kepalanya, rambutnya mengombak, hitam seperti gagak.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> His eyes [are] like doves By the rivers of waters, Washed with milk, [And] fitly set. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">عيناه كالحمام على مجاري المياه مغسولتان باللبن جالستان في وقبيهما.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Matanya bagaikan merpati pada batang air, bermandi dalam susu, duduk pada kolam yang penuh.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> His cheeks [are] like a bed of spices, Banks of scented herbs. His lips [are] lilies, Dripping liquid myrrh. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">خداه كخميلة الطيب واتلام رياحين ذكية. شفتاه سوسن تقطران مرا مائعا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Pipinya bagaikan bedeng rempah-rempah, petak-petak rempah-rempah akar. Bunga-bunga bakung bibirnya, bertetesan cairan mur.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> His hands [are] rods of gold Set with beryl. His body [is] carved ivory Inlaid [with] sapphires. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">يداه حلقتان من ذهب مرصعتان بالزبرجد. بطنه عاج ابيض مغلف بالياقوت الازرق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Tangannya bundaran emas, berhiaskan permata Tarsis, tubuhnya ukiran dari gading, bertabur batu nilam.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> His legs [are] pillars of marble Set on bases of fine gold. His countenance [is] like Lebanon, Excellent as the cedars. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ساقاه عمودا رخام مؤسسان على قاعدتين من ابريز. طلعته كلبنان. فتى كالارز.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Kakinya adalah tiang-tiang marmar putih, bertumpu pada alas emas murni. Perawakannya seperti gunung Libanon, terpilih seperti pohon-pohon aras.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> His mouth [is] most sweet, Yes, he [is] altogether lovely. This [is] my beloved, And this [is] my friend, O daughters of Jerusalem! THE DAUGHTERS OF JERUSALEM </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">حلقه حلاوة وكله مشتهيات. هذا حبيبي وهذا خليلي يا بنات اورشليم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Kata-katanya manis semata-mata, segala sesuatu padanya menarik. Demikianlah kekasihku, demikianlah temanku, hai puteri-puteri Yerusalem.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="6">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Where has your beloved gone, O fairest among women? Where has your beloved turned aside, That we may seek him with you? THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">اين ذهب حبيبك ايتها الجميلة بين النساء اين توجه حبيبك فنطلبه معك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">--Ke mana perginya kekasihmu, hai jelita di antara wanita? Ke jurusan manakah kekasihmu pergi, supaya kami mencarinya besertamu?</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> My beloved has gone to his garden, To the beds of spices, To feed [his flock] in the gardens, And to gather lilies. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">حبيبي نزل الى جنته الى خمائل الطيب ليرعى في الجنات ويجمع السوسن.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">--Kekasihku telah turun ke kebunnya, ke bedeng rempah-rempah untuk menggembalakan domba dalam kebun dan memetik bunga bakung.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> I [am] my beloved's, And my beloved [is] mine. He feeds [his flock] among the lilies. THE BELOVED </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">انا لحبيبي وحبيبي لي. الراعي بين السوسن</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Aku kepunyaan kekasihku, dan kepunyaanku kekasihku, yang menggembalakan domba di tengah-tengah bunga bakung.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> O my love, you [are as] beautiful as Tirzah, Lovely as Jerusalem, Awesome as [an army] with banners! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">انت جميلة يا حبيبتي كترصة حسنة كاورشليم مرهبة كجيش بألوية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Cantik engkau, manisku, seperti kota Tirza, juita seperti Yerusalem, dahsyat seperti bala tentara dengan panji-panjinya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Turn your eyes away from me, For they have overcome me. Your hair [is] like a flock of goats Going down from Gilead. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">حولي عني عينيك فانهما قد غلبتاني. شعرك كقطيع المعز الرابض في جلعاد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Palingkanlah matamu dari padaku, sebab aku menjadi bingung karenanya. Rambutmu bagaikan kawanan kambing yang bergelombang turun dari Gilead.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Your teeth [are] like a flock of sheep Which have come up from the washing; Every one bears twins, And none [is] barren among them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">اسنانك كقطيع نعاج صادرة من الغسل اللواتي كل واحدة متئم وليس فيها عقيم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Gigimu bagaikan kawanan domba, yang keluar dari tempat pembasuhan, yang beranak kembar semuanya, yang tak beranak tak ada.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Like a piece of pomegranate [Are] your temples behind your veil. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">كفلقة رمانة خدك تحت نقابك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Bagaikan belahan buah delima pelipismu di balik telekungmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> There are sixty queens And eighty concubines, And virgins without number. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">هنّ ستون ملكة وثمانون سرية وعذارى بلا عدد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Permaisuri ada enam puluh, selir delapan puluh, dan dara-dara tak terbilang banyaknya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> My dove, my perfect one, Is the only one, The only one of her mother, The favorite of the one who bore her. The daughters saw her And called her blessed, The queens and the concubines, And they praised her. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">واحدة هي حمامتي كاملتي. الوحيدة لامها هي. عقيلة والدتها هي. رأتها البنات فطوّبنها. الملكات والسراري فمدحتها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Tetapi dialah satu-satunya merpatiku, idam-idamanku, satu-satunya anak ibunya, anak kesayangan bagi yang melahirkannya; puteri-puteri melihatnya dan menyebutnya bahagia, permaisuri-permaisuri dan selir-selir memujinya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Who is she who looks forth as the morning, Fair as the moon, Clear as the sun, Awesome as [an army] with banners? THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">من هي المشرفة مثل الصباح جميلة كالقمر طاهرة كالشمس مرهبة كجيش بألوية</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">"Siapakah dia yang muncul laksana fajar merekah, indah bagaikan bulan purnama, bercahaya bagaikan surya, dahsyat seperti bala tentara dengan panji-panjinya?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> I went down to the garden of nuts To see the verdure of the valley, To see whether the vine had budded [And] the pomegranates had bloomed. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">نزلت الى جنة الجوز لانظر الى خضر الوادي ولانظر هل أقعل الكرم هل نور الرمان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Ke kebun kenari aku turun melihat kuntum-kuntum di lembah, melihat apakah pohon anggur berkuncup dan pohon-pohon delima berbunga.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Before I was even aware, My soul had made me [As] the chariots of my noble people. THE BELOVED AND HIS FRIENDS </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فلم اشعر الا وقد جعلتني نفسي بين مركبات قوم شريف</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Tak sadar diri aku; kerinduanku menempatkan aku di atas kereta orang bangsawan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Return, return, O Shulamite; Return, return, that we may look upon you! THE SHULAMITE What would you see in the Shulamite -- As it were, the dance of the two camps? THE BELOVED </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ارجعي ارجعي يا شولميث ارجعي ارجعي فننظر اليك ماذا ترون في شولميث مثل رقص صفين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Kembalilah, kembalilah, ya gadis Sulam, kembalilah, kembalilah, supaya kami dapat melihat engkau! Mengapa kamu senang melihat gadis Sulam itu seperti melihat tari-tarian perang?</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="7">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> How beautiful are your feet in sandals, O prince's daughter! The curves of your thighs [are] like jewels, The work of the hands of a skillful workman. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ما اجمل رجليك بالنعلين يا بنت الكريم. دوائر فخذيك مثل الحلي صنعة يدي صناع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Betapa indah langkah-langkahmu dengan sandal-sandal itu, puteri yang berwatak luhur! Lengkung pinggangmu bagaikan perhiasan, karya tangan seniman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Your navel [is] a rounded goblet; It lacks no blended beverage. Your waist [is] a heap of wheat Set about with lilies. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">سرتك كاس مدورة لا يعوزها شراب ممزوج. بطنك صبرة حنطة مسيجة بالسوسن.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Pusarmu seperti cawan yang bulat, yang tak kekurangan anggur campur. Perutmu timbunan gandum, berpagar bunga-bunga bakung.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Your two breasts [are] like two fawns, Twins of a gazelle. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">ثدياك كخشفتين توأمي ظبية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Seperti dua anak rusa buah dadamu, seperti anak kembar kijang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Your neck [is] like an ivory tower, Your eyes [like] the pools in Heshbon By the gate of Bath Rabbim. Your nose [is] like the tower of Lebanon Which looks toward Damascus. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">عنقك كبرج من عاج. عيناك كالبرك في حشبون عند باب بث ربيم. انفك كبرج لبنان الناظر تجاه دمشق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Lehermu bagaikan menara gading, matamu bagaikan telaga di Hesybon, dekat pintu gerbang Batrabim; hidungmu seperti menara di gunung Libanon, yang menghadap ke kota Damsyik.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Your head [crowns] you like [Mount] Carmel, And the hair of your head [is] like purple; A king [is] held captive by [your] tresses. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">راسك عليك مثل الكرمل وشعر راسك كارجوان. ملك قد أسر بالخصل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Kepalamu seperti bukit Karmel, rambut kepalamu merah lembayung; seorang raja tertawan dalam kepang-kepangnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> How fair and how pleasant you are, O love, with your delights! </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ما اجملك وما احلاك ايتها الحبيبة باللذّات.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Betapa cantik, betapa jelita engkau, hai tercinta di antara segala yang disenangi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> This stature of yours is like a palm tree, And your breasts [like] its clusters. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">قامتك هذه شبيهة بالنخلة وثدياك بالعناقيد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Sosok tubuhmu seumpama pohon korma dan buah dadamu gugusannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> I said, "I will go up to the palm tree, I will take hold of its branches." Let now your breasts be like clusters of the vine, The fragrance of your breath like apples, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">قلت اني اصعد الى النخلة وامسك بعذوقها. وتكون ثدياك كعناقيد الكرم ورائحة انفك كالتفاح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Kataku: "Aku ingin memanjat pohon korma itu dan memegang gugusan-gugusannya Kiranya buah dadamu seperti gugusan anggur dan nafas hidungmu seperti buah apel.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> And the roof of your mouth like the best wine. THE SHULAMITE [The wine] goes [down] smoothly for my beloved, Moving gently the lips of sleepers. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">وحنكك كأجود الخمر--لحبيبي السائغة المرقرقة السائحة على شفاه النائمين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Kata-katamu manis bagaikan anggur!" Ya, anggur itu mengalir kepada kekasihku dengan tak putus-putusnya, melimpah ke bibir orang-orang yang sedang tidur!</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> I [am] my beloved's, And his desire [is] toward me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">انا لحبيبي واليّ اشتياقه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Kepunyaan kekasihku aku, kepadaku gairahnya tertuju.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Come, my beloved, Let us go forth to the field; Let us lodge in the villages. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">تعال يا حبيبي لنخرج الى الحقل ولنبت في القرى.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Mari, kekasihku, kita pergi ke padang, bermalam di antara bunga-bunga pacar!</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Let us get up early to the vineyards; Let us see if the vine has budded, [Whether] the grape blossoms are open, [And] the pomegranates are in bloom. There I will give you my love. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">لنبكرنّ الى الكروم لننظر هل ازهر الكرم هل تفتح القعال هل نور الرمان. هنالك اعطيك حبي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Mari, kita pergi pagi-pagi ke kebun anggur dan melihat apakah pohon anggur sudah berkuncup, apakah sudah mekar bunganya, apakah pohon-pohon delima sudah berbunga! Di sanalah aku akan memberikan cintaku kepadamu!</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> The mandrakes give off a fragrance, And at our gates [are] pleasant [fruits,] All manner, new and old, Which I have laid up for you, my beloved. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">اللفاح يفوح رائحة وعند ابوابنا كل النفائس من جديدة وقديمة ذخرتها لك يا حبيبي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Semerbak bau buah dudaim; dekat pintu kita ada pelbagai buah-buah yang lezat, yang telah lama dan yang baru saja dipetik. Itu telah kusimpan bagimu, kekasihku!</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="8">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Oh, that you were like my brother, Who nursed at my mother's breasts! [If] I should find you outside, I would kiss you; I would not be despised. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ليتك كاخ لي الراضع ثديي امي فاجدك في الخارج واقبلك ولا يخزونني.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">O, seandainya engkau saudaraku laki-laki, yang menyusu pada buah dada ibuku, akan kucium engkau bila kujumpai di luar, karena tak ada orang yang akan menghina aku!</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> I would lead you [and] bring you Into the house of my mother, She [who] used to instruct me. I would cause you to drink of spiced wine, Of the juice of my pomegranate. (TO THE DAUGHTERS OF JERUSALEM) </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">واقودك وادخل بك بيت امي وهي تعلمني فاسقيك من الخمر الممزوجة من سلاف رماني.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Akan kubimbing engkau dan kubawa ke rumah ibuku, supaya engkau mengajar aku. Akan kuberi kepadamu anggur yang harum untuk diminum, air buah delimaku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> His left hand [is] under my head, And his right hand embraces me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">شماله تحت راسي ويمينه تعانقني.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Tangan kirinya ada di bawah kepalaku, tangan kanannya memeluk aku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> I charge you, O daughters of Jerusalem, Do not stir up nor awaken love Until it pleases. A RELATIVE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">احلفكن يا بنات اورشليم ألا تيقظن ولا تنبهن الحبيب حتى يشاء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Kusumpahi kamu, puteri-puteri Yerusalem: mengapa kamu membangkitkan dan menggerakkan cinta sebelum diingininya?</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Who [is] this coming up from the wilderness, Leaning upon her beloved? I awakened you under the apple tree. There your mother brought you forth; There she [who] bore you brought [you] forth. THE SHULAMITE TO HER BELOVED </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">من هذه الطالعة من البرية مستندة على حبيبها تحت شجرة التفاح شوقتك هناك خطبت لك امك هناك خطبت لك والدتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Siapakah dia yang muncul dari padang gurun, yang bersandar pada kekasihnya? --Di bawah pohon apel kubangunkan engkau, di sanalah ibumu telah mengandung engkau, di sanalah ia mengandung dan melahirkan engkau.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Set me as a seal upon your heart, As a seal upon your arm; For love [is as] strong as death, Jealousy [as] cruel as the grave; Its flames [are] flames of fire, A most vehement flame. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">اجعلني كخاتم على قلبك كخاتم على ساعدك. لان المحبة قوية كالموت. الغيرة قاسية كالهاوة. لهيبها لهيب نار لظى الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">--Taruhlah aku seperti meterai pada hatimu, seperti meterai pada lenganmu, karena cinta kuat seperti maut, kegairahan gigih seperti dunia orang mati, nyalanya adalah nyala api, seperti nyala api TUHAN!</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Many waters cannot quench love, Nor can the floods drown it. If a man would give for love All the wealth of his house, It would be utterly despised. THE SHULAMITE's BROTHERS </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">مياه كثيرة لا تستطيع ان تطفئ المحبة والسيول لا تغمرها. ان اعطى الانسان كل ثروة بيته بدل المحبة تحتقر احتقارا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Air yang banyak tak dapat memadamkan cinta, sungai-sungai tak dapat menghanyutkannya. Sekalipun orang memberi segala harta benda rumahnya untuk cinta, namun ia pasti akan dihina.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> We have a little sister, And she has no breasts. What shall we do for our sister In the day when she is spoken for? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لنا اخت صغيرة ليس لها ثديان. فماذا نصنع لاختنا في يوم تخطب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">--Kami mempunyai seorang adik perempuan, yang belum mempunyai buah dada. Apakah yang akan kami perbuat dengan adik perempuan kami pada hari ia dipinang?</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> If she [is] a wall, We will build upon her A battlement of silver; And if she [is] a door, We will enclose her With boards of cedar. THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ان تكن سورا فنبني عليها برج فضة. وان تكن بابا فنحصرها بألواح ارز</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Bila ia tembok, akan kami dirikan atap perak di atasnya; bila ia pintu, akan kami palangi dia dengan palang kayu aras.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> I [am] a wall, And my breasts like towers; Then I became in his eyes As one who found peace. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">انا سور وثدياي كبرجين. حينئذ كنت في عينيه كواجدة سلامة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">--Aku adalah suatu tembok dan buah dadaku bagaikan menara. Dalam matanya ketika itu aku bagaikan orang yang telah mendapat kebahagiaan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Solomon had a vineyard at Baal Hamon; He leased the vineyard to keepers; Everyone was to bring for its fruit A thousand silver coins. (TO SOLOMON) </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">كان لسليمان كرم في بعل هامون. دفع الكرم الى نواطير كل واحد يؤدي عن ثمره الفا من الفضة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Salomo mempunyai kebun anggur di Baal-Hamon. Diserahkannya kebun anggur itu kepada para penjaga, masing-masing memberikan seribu keping perak untuk hasilnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> My own vineyard [is] before me. You, O Solomon, [may have] a thousand, And those who tend its fruit two hundred. THE BELOVED </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">كرمي الذي لي هو امامي. الالف لك يا سليمان ومئتان لنواطير الثمر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Kebun anggurku, yang punyaku sendiri, ada di hadapanku; bagimulah seribu keping itu, raja Salomo, dan dua ratus bagi orang-orang yang menjaga hasilnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> You who dwell in the gardens, The companions listen for your voice -- Let me hear it! THE SHULAMITE </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ايتها الجالسة في الجنات الاصحاب يسمعون صوتك فأسمعيني</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">--Hai, penghuni kebun, teman-teman memperhatikan suaramu, perdengarkanlah itu kepadaku!</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Make haste, my beloved, And be like a gazelle Or a young stag On the mountains of spices. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">اهرب يا حبيبي وكن كالظبي او كغفر الايائل على جبال الاطياب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">--Cepat, kekasihku, berlakulah seperti kijang, atau seperti anak rusa di atas gunung-gunung tanaman rempah-rempah.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>