<book>
    <chapter num="1">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">The book of the words of Tobit, son of Tobiel, the son of Ananiel, the son of Aduel, the son of Gabael, of the seed of Asael, of the tribe of Nephthali;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">كان طوبيا وهو من سبط ومدينة نفتالي التي في الجليل الاعلى فوق نحشون وراء الطريق الاخذ غربا والى يسارها مدينة صفت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Kitab kisah Tobit bin Tobiel bin Ananiel bin Aduel bin Gabael bin Rafael bin Raguel dari keturunan Asiel dari suku Naftali.</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">Who in the time of Enemessar king of the Assyrians was led captive out of Thisbe, which is at the right hand of that city, which is called properly Nephthali in Galilee above Aser.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">قد جلي في عهد شلمناسر ملك اشور الا انه مع كونه في الجلاء لم يفارق سبيل الحق</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Di zaman Salmaneser, raja orang-orang Asyur, Tobit diangkut tertawan dari Tisbe yang terletak di sebelah selatan Kudios-Naftali di Galilea atas di atas Hazor, yakni di sebelah barat, dan di sebelah utara Fogor.</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">I Tobit have walked all the days of my life in the ways of truth and justice, and I did many almsdeeds to my brethren, and my nation, who came with me to Nineve, into the land of the Assyrians.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">حتى كان كل ما يتيسر له يقسمه كل يوم على من جلي معه من اخوانه الذين من جنسه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Aku, Tobit menempuh jalan kebenaran dan kesalehan seumur hidupku dan banyak melakukan kebajikan kepada para saudara dan segenap bangsaku yang bersama dengan daku telah berangkat ke pembuangan, ke negeri Asyur ke kota Niniwe.</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">And when I was in mine own country, in the land of Israel being but young, all the tribe of Nephthali my father fell from the house of Jerusalem, which was chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, that all the tribes should sacrifice there, where the temple of the habitation of the most High was consecrated and built for all ages.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ومع انه كان احدث الجميع في سبط نفتالي لم يكن على شيء من شؤون الاحداث</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Waktu aku masih tinggal di tanah airku, yaitu di tanah Israel, dan ketika aku masih muda, maka seluruh suku Naftali moyangku memberontak terhadap keluarga Daud bapaku dan terhadap Yerusalem, kota yang telah dipilih dari antara semua suku Israel, supaya di sana semua suku mempersembahkan korban.</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">Now all the tribes which together revolted, and the house of my father Nephthali, sacrificed unto the heifer Baal.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">وكان اذا قصدوا كلهم عجول الذهب التي عملها ياربعام ملك اسرائيل يتخلف وحده عن سائرهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Memang di sanalah Bait Tuhan, yaitu kediaman Allah, telah dibangun dan ditahbiskan untuk segala keturunan sepanjang sekalian abad.</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">But I alone went often to Jerusalem at the feasts, as it was ordained unto all the people of Israel by an everlasting decree, having the firstfruits and tenths of increase, with that which was first shorn; and them gave I at the altar to the priests the children of Aaron.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فيمضي الى اورشليم الى هيكل الرب وهناك كان يسجد للرب اله اسرائيل ويوفي جميع بواكيره واعشاره</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Tetapi semua saudaraku dan juga rumah bapaku Naftali mempersembahkan korban kepada anak lembu yang telah dibuat Yerobeam, raja Israel, di kota Dan yang terletak di pegunungan Galilea.</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">The first tenth part of all increase I gave to the sons of Aaron, who ministered at Jerusalem: another tenth part I sold away, and went, and spent it every year at Jerusalem:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">واذا كانت السنة الثالثة كان يجعل جميع اعشاره للدخلاء والغرباء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Pada hari-hari raya sering kali hanya aku seorang diri sajalah yang pergi ke Yerusalem, sebagaimana yang tersurat bagi segenap Israel sebagai hukum abadi.</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">And the third I gave unto them to whom it was meet, as Debora my father's mother had commanded me, because I was left an orphan by my father.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">وعلى هذا وامثاله كان مثابرا منذ صبوته على وفق شريعة الله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Pergilah aku ke Yerusalem dengan membawa buah bungaran dan anak sulung dari ternak serta bagian sepersepuluh dari hewan dan lagi guntingan pertama bulu domba.</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">Furthermore, when I was come to the age of a man, I married Anna of mine own kindred, and of her I begat Tobias.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ولما ان صار رجلا اتخذ له امراة من سبطه اسمها حنة فولد له منها ولد فسماه باسمه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Semuanya kuberikan kepada para imam, keturunan Harun, untuk mezbah.</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">And when we were carried away captives to Nineve, all my brethren and those that were of my kindred did eat of the bread of the Gentiles.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">وادبه منذ صغره على تقوى الله واجتناب كل خطيئة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Bagian sepersepuluh dari gandum, anggur, minyak, buah zaitun, buah delima dan hasil bumi lainnya kuberikan kepada kaum Lewi yang menyelenggarakan kebaktian di Yerusalem.</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">But I kept myself from eating;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ولما جلي مع امراته وولده الى مدينة نينوى حيث كانت كل عشيرته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Selama enam tahun akupun memungut bagian sepersepuluh yang kedua dan setiap tahun aku pergi membiayakannya di Yerusalem.</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">Because I remembered God with all my heart.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">وقد كانوا كلهم ياكلون من اطعمة الامم كان هو يصون نفسه ولم يتنجس قط بماكولاتهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Adapun bagian sepersepuluh yang ketiga kuberikan kepada para yatim piatu, para janda dan kaum perantau yang tinggal di tengah-tengah orang Israel.</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">And the most High gave me grace and favour before Enemessar, so that I was his purveyor.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ولاجل انه كان يذكر الرب بكل قلبه اتاه الله حظوة لدى الملك شلمناسر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Tiga tahun sekali bagian sepersepuluh itu kubawa untuk diberikan kepada mereka.</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">And I went into Media, and left in trust with Gabael, the brother of Gabrias, at Rages a city of Media ten talents of silver.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فاطلق له ان يذهب حيثما شاء ويفعل ما يريد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Itupun kami makan pula menurut aturan yang ditetapkan perihal mereka dalam hukum Taurat Musa dan sesuai dengan perintah yang telah diberikan Debora, yaitu ibu Ananiel ayahku.</language></verse>
        <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">Now when Enemessar was dead, Sennacherib his son reigned in his stead; whose estate was troubled, that I could not go into Media.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فكان يطوف على كل من كان في الجلاء ويرشدهم بنصائح الخلاص</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Sebab waktu berpulang ayahku meninggalkan aku sebagai yatim piatu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">And in the time of Enemessar I gave many alms to my brethren, and gave my bread to the hungry,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">ثم انه قدم راجيس مدينة ماداي وكان معه مما اثره به الملك عشرة قناطير من الفضة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Setelah menjadi dewasa aku mengambil isteri dari keluarga kami sendiri, Hana namanya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">And my clothes to the naked: and if I saw any of my nation dead, or cast about the walls of Nineve, I buried him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فراى بين الجمهور الغفير الذي من جنسه رجلا من سبطه يقال له غابيلوس في فاقة فدفع اليه الزنة المذكورة من الفضة بصك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Dari padanya kuperanakkan seorang anak laki-laki yang kunamai Tobia.</language></verse>
        <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">And if the king Sennacherib had slain any, when he was come, and fled from Judea, I buried them privily; for in his wrath he killed many; but the bodies were not found, when they were sought for of the king.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و كان بعد ايام كثيرة ان مات الملك شلمناسر فملك سنحاريب ابنه مكانه فوقع بنو اسرائيل عنده موقع الكراهة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Ketika diangkut tertawan dan diasingkan ke negeri Asyur aku pergi ke kota Niniwe.</language></verse>
        <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">And when one of the Ninevites went and complained of me to the king, that I buried them, and hid myself; understanding that I was sought for to be put to death, I withdrew myself for fear.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">وكان طوبيا يطوف كل يوم على جميع عشيرته ويعزيهم ويؤاسي كل واحد من امواله على قدر وسعه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Semua saudaraku dan kaum sekeluarga makan makanan bangsa asing, tetapi aku mencegah diriku jangan makan makanan itu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">Then all my goods were forcibly taken away, neither was there any thing left me, beside my wife Anna and my son Tobias.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">فيطعم الجياع ويكسو العراة ويدفن الموتى والقتلى بغيرة شديدة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Sebab dengan segenap hatiku aku ingat kepada Allah.</language></verse>
        <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">And there passed not five and fifty days, before two of his sons killed him, and they fled into the mountains of Ararath; and Sarchedonus his son reigned in his stead; who appointed over his father's accounts, and over all his affairs, Achiacharus my brother Anael's son.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">ولما قفل الملك سنحاريب من ارض يهوذا هاربا من الضربة التي حاقه الله بها بسبب تجديفه وطفق لحنقه يقتل كثيرين من بني اسرائيل كان طوبيا يدفن اجسادهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Oleh Yang Mahatinggi dianugerahkan kepadaku kerelaan dan penghormatan dari pihak raja Salmaneser.</language></verse>
        <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">And Achiacharus intreating for me, I returned to Nineve. Now Achiacharus was cupbearer, and keeper of the signet, and steward, and overseer of the accounts: and Sarchedonus appointed him next unto him: and he was my brother's son.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">فنما ذلك الى الملك فامر بقتله وضبط جميع ماله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Maka aku menjadi pembelanja segala sesuatunya yang diperlukan raja.</language></verse>
    </chapter>

   <chapter num="2">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Now when I was come home again, and my wife Anna was restored unto me, with my son Tobias, in the feast of Pentecost, which is the holy feast of the seven weeks, there was a good dinner prepared me, in the which I sat down to eat.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وكان بعد ذلك في يوم عيد الرب ان صنعت مادبة عظيمة في بيت طوبيا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Di masa pemerintahan Esarhadon aku kembali ke rumahku. Juga isteriku Hana dan anakku Tobia diserahkan kembali kepadaku.</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">And when I saw abundance of meat, I said to my son, Go and bring what poor man soever thou shalt find out of our brethren, who is mindful of the Lord; and, lo, I tarry for thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فقال لابنه هلم فادع بعضا من سبطنا من المتقين لله لياكلوا معنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Sekali peristiwa pada hari raya Pentakosta, yaitu hari raya Tujuh Minggu, disajikanlah kepadaku suatu jamuan makan yang baik.</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">But he came again, and said, Father, one of our nation is strangled, and is cast out in the marketplace.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فانطلق ثم عاد فاخبره ان واحدا من بني اسرائيل مذبوح ملقى في السوق فلما سمع طوبيا نهض من موضعه مسرعا وترك العشاء وبلغ الجثة وهو صائم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Akupun telah duduk untuk makan. Sebuah meja ditempatkan di hadapanku dan kepadaku disajikan banyak hidangan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">Then before I had tasted of any meat, I started up, and took him up into a room until the going down of the sun.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فرفعها وحملها الى بيته سرا ليدفنها بالتحفظ بعد مغيب الشمس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Tetapi berkatalah aku kepada anakku Tobia: "Nak, pergilah dan jika kaujumpai seorang miskin dari saudara-saudara kita yang diangkut tertawan ke Niniwe dan yang dengan segenap hati ingat kepada Tuhan, bawalah ke mari, supaya ikut makan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">Then I returned, and washed myself, and ate my meat in heaviness,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">وبعد ان خبا الجثة اكل الطعام باكيا مرتعدا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Aku hendak menunggu, anakku, hingga engkau kembali."</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">Remembering that prophecy of Amos, as he said, Your feasts shall be turned into mourning, and all your mirth into lamentation.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فذكر الكلام الذي تكلم به الرب على لسان عاموس النبي ايام اعيادكم تتحول الى عويل ونحيب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Maka keluarlah Tobia untuk mencari seorang saudara kita yang miskin.</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">Therefore I wept: and after the going down of the sun I went and made a grave, and buried him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">ولما غربت الشمس ذهب ودفنها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Sepulangnya berkatalah ia: "Pak!" Sahutku: "Ada apa, nak?" Jawabnya: "Salah seorang dari bangsa kita sudah dibunuh.</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">But my neighbours mocked me, and said, This man is not yet afraid to be put to death for this matter: who fled away; and yet, lo, he burieth the dead again.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">وكان جميع ذوي قرابته يلومونه قائلين لاجل هذا امر بقتلك وما كدت تنجو من قضاء الموت حتى عدت تدفن الموتى</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Ia dicekik dan dibuang di pasar. Masih ada di situ juga!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">The same night also I returned from the burial, and slept by the wall of my courtyard, being polluted and my face was uncovered:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">و اما طوبيا فاذ كان خوفه من الله اعظم من خوفه من الملك كان لا يزال يخطف جثث القتلى ويخباها في بيته فيدفنها عند انتصاف الليل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Aku melonjak berdiri dan jamuan itu kutinggalkan sebelum kukecap.</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">And I knew not that there were sparrows in the wall, and mine eyes being open, the sparrows muted warm dung into mine eyes, and a whiteness came in mine eyes: and I went to the physicians, but they helped me not: moreover Achiacharus did nourish me, until I went into Elymais.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">و اتفق في بعض الايام وقد تعب من دفن الموتى انه وافى بيته فرمى بنفسه الى جانب الحائط ونام</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Mayat itu kuangkat dari lapangan dan kutaruh di dalam salah satu rumah hingga matahari terbenam, untuk kukuburkan nanti.</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">And my wife Anna did take women's works to do.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فوقع ذرق من عش خطاف في عينيه وهو سخن فعمي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Kemudian aku pulang, membasuh diriku, lalu makan dengan sedih hati.</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">And when she had sent them home to the owners, they paid her wages, and gave her also besides a kid.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">و انما اذن الرب ان تعرض له هذه التجربة لتكون لمن بعده قدوة صبره كايوب الصديق</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Maka teringatlah aku kepada firman yang diucapkan nabi Amos mengenai kota Betel ini: "Hari-hari rayamu akan berubah menjadi hari sedih dan segala nyanyianmu akan menjadi ratap!" Lalu menangislah aku.</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">And when it was in my house, and began to cry, I said unto her, From whence is this kid? is it not stolen? render it to the owners; for it is not lawful to eat any thing that is stolen.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فانه اذ كان لم ينفك عن تقوى الله منذ صغره وحافظا لوصاياه لم يكن يتذمر على الله لما ناله من بلوى العمى</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Setelah matahari terbenam aku pergi menggali liang lalu mayat itu kukuburkan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">But she replied upon me, It was given for a gift more than the wages. Howbeit I did not believe her, but bade her render it to the owners: and I was abashed at her. But she replied upon me, Where are thine alms and thy righteous deeds? behold, thou and all thy works are known.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و لكنه ثبت في خوف الله شاكرا له طول ايام حياته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Para tetangga menertawakan aku, katanya: "Ia belum juga takut! Sudah pernah ia dicari untuk dibunuh karena perkara yang sama.</language></verse>
    </chapter>

    <!-- CHAPTER 3 (17 verses) -->
    <chapter num="3">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Then I being grieved did weep, and in my sorrow prayed, saying,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">حينئذ ان طوبيا وطفق يصلي بدموع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Maka aku sedih hati, mengeluh dan menangis. Dengan keluh kesah aku angkat doa begini:</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">O Lord, thou art just, and all thy works and all thy ways are mercy and truth, and thou judgest truly and justly for ever.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">و قال عادل انت ايها الرب وجميع احكامك مستقيمة وطرقك كلها رحمة وحق وحكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">"Engkaulah adil, ya Tuhan, semua perbuatanMupun adil pula; semua tindakan-Mu belas kasihan dan kebenaran, dan dunia semesta diadili oleh-Mu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">Remember me, and look on me, punish me not for my sins and ignorances, and the sins of my fathers, who have sinned before thee:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فالان اذكرني يا رب ولا تنتقم عن خطاياي ولا تذكر ذنوبي ولا ذنوب ابائي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Oleh sebab itu, ya Tuhan, ingatlah kepadaku, pandangilah aku! Jangan aku Kauhukum sekedar segala dosaku dan setimpal dengan kekhilafanku kepadaMu, atau sekedar dosa yang diperbuat nenek moyangku!</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">For they obeyed not thy commandments: wherefore thou hast delivered us for a spoil, and unto captivity, and unto death, and for a proverb of reproach to all the nations among whom we are dispersed.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">لانا لم نطع اوامرك فلاجل ذلك اسلمنا الى النهب والجلاء والموت واصبحنا احدوثة وعارا في جميع الامم التي بددتنا بينها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Aku telah tidak taat kepada segala perintah-Mu, maka kami Kauserahkan untuk dirampasi, dan untuk ditawan dan dibunuh, dan untuk menjadi sindiran, tertawaan dan orang ternista di tengah sekalian bangsa di mana kami Kaucerai-beraikan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">And now thy judgments are many and true: deal with me according to my sins and my fathers': because we have not kept thy commandments, neither have walked in truth before thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فالان يا رب عظيمة احكامك لانا لم نعمل بحسب وصاياك ولا سلكنا بخلوص امامك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Segala hukuman-Mu memang benar, apabila kini aku Kauperlakukan sekedar segala dosaku. Karena kami tidak memenuhi perintah-perintah-Mu, dan tidak berjalan benar di hadapan-Mu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">Now therefore deal with me as seemeth best unto thee, and command my spirit to be taken from me, that I may be dissolved, and become earth: for it is profitable for me to die rather than to live, because I have heard false reproaches, and have much sorrow: command therefore that I may now be delivered out of this distress, and go into the everlasting place: turn not thy face away from me.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">و الان يارب بحسب مشيئتك اصنع بي ومر ان تقبض روحي بسلام لان الموت لي خير من الحياة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Kini berbuatlah kepadaku menurut apa yang berkenan kepada-Mu, dan sudilah mencabut nyawaku, sehingga lenyaplah aku dari muka bumi dan kembali menjadi debu. Sebab mati lebih berguna bagiku dari hidup, karena aku mesti mendengar nista dan fitnah dan sangat sedih rasa hatiku. Ya Tuhan, suruhlah supaya aku lepas dari susah ini, biarlah aku lenyap menuju tempat abadi; janganlah wajah-Mu Kaupalingkan dari padaku, ya Tuhan. Sebab lebih bergunalah mati saja dari pada melihat banyak susah dalam hidupku. Nista tidak dapat kudengar lagi!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">It came to pass the same day, that in Ecbatane a city of Media Sara the daughter of Raguel was also reproached by her father's maids;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">و اتفق في ذلك اليوم عينه ان سارة بنة رعوئيل في راجيس مدينة الماديين سمعت هي ايضا تعييرا من احدى جواري ابيها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Pada hari yang sama terjadilah bahwa Sara anak perempuan Raguel di kota Ekbatana di negeri Media mendengar nista dari pihak seorang pelayan perempuan ayahnya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Because that she had been married to seven husbands, whom Asmodeus the evil spirit had killed, before they had lain with her. Dost thou not know, said they, that thou hast strangled thine husbands? thou hast had already seven husbands, neither wast thou named after any of them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لانه كان قد عقد لها على سبعة رجال وكان شيطان اسمه ازموداوس يقتلهم على اثر دخولهم عليها في الحال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Adapun Sara itu sudah diperisterikan kepada tujuh laki-laki. Tetapi mereka semua sudah dibunuh oleh Asmodeus, setan jahat itu, sebelum Sara bersetubuh dengan mereka, sebagaimana pantasnya bagi para isteri. Kata pelayan itu kepada Sara: "Engkau sendirilah yang membunuh para suamimu! Engkau sudah diperisterikan kepada tujuh orang, tetapi tidak ada seorangpun yang engkau nikmati juga!</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">Wherefore dost thou beat us for them? if they be dead, go thy ways after them, let us never see of thee either son or daughter.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">و اذ كانت تنتهر الجارية لذنب اجابتها قائلة لا راينا لك ابنا ولا ابنة على الارض يا قاتلة ازواجها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Masakan kami kaucambuki karena mereka mati! Baiklah engkau menyusul mereka saja, supaya seorang anak laki-laki atau perempuan dari engkau jangan pernah kami lihat!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">When she heard these things, she was very sorrowful, so that she thought to have strangled herself; and she said, I am the only daughter of my father, and if I do this, it shall be a reproach unto him, and I shall bring his old age with sorrow unto the grave.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">اتريدين ان تقتليني كما قتلت سبعة رجال فلما سمعت هذا الكلام صعدت الى علية بيتها فاقامت ثلاثة ايام وثلاث ليال لا تاكل ولا تشرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Maka pada hari itu juga Sara sangat sedih hati, lalu menangis tersedu-sedu. Kemudian ia naik ke bilik atas kepunyaan ayahnya dengan maksud menggantung diri.</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Then she prayed toward the window, and said, Blessed art thou, O Lord my God, and thine holy and glorious name is blessed and honourable for ever: let all thy works praise thee for ever.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">بل استمرت تصلي وتتضرع الى الله بدموع ان يكشف عنها هذا العار</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Segera tangan dikedangkannya ke arah jendela, lalu berdoa. Katanya: "Terpujilah Engkau, ya Allah penyayang! Moga-moga terpujilah nama-Mu selama-lamanya, dan semoga segala buatan-Mu memuji Engkau selama-lamanya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">And now, O Lord, I set I mine eyes and my face toward thee,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">و لما اتمت صلاتها في اليوم الثالث وباركت الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Kini kuangkat mukaku kepada-Mu dan kuarahkan mataku.</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">And say, Take me out of the earth, that I may hear no more the reproach.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">قالت تبارك اسمك يا اله ابائنا الذي بعد غضبه يصنع الرحمة وفي زمان البؤس يغفر الخطايا للذين يدعونه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Aku mohon: Biarlah aku dilenyapkan dari muka bumi ini, nista tidak mau kudengar lagi.</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">Thou knowest, Lord, that I am pure from all sin with man,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">اليك يا رب اقبل بوجهي واليك اصرف ناظري</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Sebab Engkau tahu, ya Tuhan, bahwa aku bersih dari segala pencemaran oleh seorang laki-laki,</language></verse>
        <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">And that I never polluted my name, nor the name of my father, in the land of my captivity: I am the only daughter of my father, neither hath he any child to be his heir, neither any near kinsman, nor any son of his alive, to whom I may keep myself for a wife: my seven husbands are already dead; and why should I live? but if it please not thee that I should die, command some regard to be had of me, and pity taken of me, that I hear no more reproach.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">اتوسل اليك يارب ان تحلني من وثاق هذا العار او تاخذني عن الارض</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">bahwa namakupun tidak kunodai dan tidak pula nama ayahku di tanah pembuanganku. Aku ini anak tunggal ayahku dan ia tidak mempunyai anak lain sebagai waris; tiadapun seorang saudara padanya dan tidak pula sanak saudara lain, sehingga aku mesti memelihara diriku untuk menjadi isterinya. Aku sudah kehilangan tujuh orang; apa lagi gunanya hidup bagiku? Apabila Engkau tidak berkenan membiarkan aku mati, maka dengarkanlah nistaku ini, ya Tuhan!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">So the prayers of them both were heard before the majesty of the great God.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">انك يارب عالم باني لم اشته رجلا قط واني قد صنت نفسي منزهة عن كل شهوة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Pada saat itu juga kedua orang itu, yakni Tobit dan Sara, dikabulkan permohonannya di hadapan kemuliaan Allah.</language></verse>
        <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">And Raphael was sent to heal them both, that is, to scale away the whiteness of Tobit's eyes, and to give Sara the daughter of Raguel for a wife to Tobias the son of Tobit; and to bind Asmodeus the evil spirit; because she belonged to Tobias by right of inheritance. The selfsame time came Tobit home, and entered into his house, and Sara the daughter of Raguel came down from her upper chamber.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">و لم اكن قط امازج ارباب الملاهي ولا اعاشر السالكين بالطيش</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Diutuslah Rafael untuk menyembuhkan kedua-duanya, yaitu dengan menghapus bintik-bintik putih dari mata Tobit sehingga ia dapat melihat cahaya Allah dengan matanya sendiri, dan dengan memberikan Sara anak perempuan Raguel kepada Tobia bin Tobit sebagai isteri dan dengan melepaskannya dari Asmodeus, setan jahat itu. Memang Tobia lebih berhak memperoleh Sara dari semua orang lain yang ingin mengambilnya. Pada saat yang sama Tobit kembali dari pelataran itu masuk ke rumahnya dan Sara anak Raguel turun dari bilik atas itu.</language></verse>
    </chapter>

   <!-- CHAPTER 4 (21 verses) -->
    <chapter num="4">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">In that day Tobit remembered the money which he had committed to Gabael in Rages of Media,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">و اذ خال طوبيا ان قد استجيبت صلاته وتهيا له ان يموت استدعى اليه طوبيا ابنه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Pada hari itu juga Tobit ingat kepada uang yang pernah dititipkannya pada Gabael di Ragai di negeri Media itu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">And said with himself, I have wished for death; wherefore do I not call for my son Tobias that I may signify to him of the money before I die?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">و قال له اسمع يا بني كلمات في واجعلها في قلبك مثل الاساس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Lalu ia berpikir: "Aku sudah sampai meminta kematian bagi diriku. Mengapa gerangan tidak kupanggil anakku Tobia untuk kuberi petunjuk mengenai uang itu sebelum aku meninggal?"</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">And when he had called him, he said, My son, when I am dead, bury me; and despise not thy mother, but honour her all the days of thy life, and do that which shall please her, and grieve her not.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">اذا قبض الله نفسي فادفن جسدي واكرم والدتك جميع ايام حياتها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Maka dipanggilnya anaknya Tobia yang segera datang juga. Lalu kata Tobit: "Nak, apabila aku sudah mati nanti, kuburkanlah aku sebagaimana mestinya. Hormatilah ibumu dan jangan kautinggalkan sepanjang umur hidupnya. Lakukanlah apa yang menyenangkan hatinya dan jangan hatinya kausedihkan dengan kelakuanmu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">Remember, my son, that she saw many dangers for thee, when thou wast in her womb: and when she is dead, bury her by me in one grave.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و اذكر ما المشقات التي عانتها لاجلك في جوفها وما كان اشدها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Ingatlah, nak, bahwa oleh karena engkau telah ditanggungnya banyak bahaya, yaitu waktu engkau masih dalam kandungannya. Setelah ibumu meninggal, kuburkanlah di sampingku dalam satu kubur.</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">My son, be mindful of the Lord our God all thy days, and let not thy will be set to sin, or to transgress his commandments: do uprightly all thy life long, and follow not the ways of unrighteousness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">و متى استوفت هي ايضا زمان حياتها فادفنها الى جانبي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Nak, ingatlah juga kepada Tuhan; sepanjang umur hidupmu jangan sampai berdosa dan melanggar perintah-perintah-Nya. Hendaklah berbuat baik sepanjang hidupmu dan jangan menempuh jalan kelaliman.</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">For if thou deal truly, thy doings shall prosperously succeed to thee, and to all them that live justly.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">و انت فليكن الله في قلبك جميع ايام حياتك واحذر ان ترضى بالخطيئة وتتعدى وصايا الرب الهنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Sebab orang yang menjalankan kebenaran akan berhasil dalam segala usahanya,</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">Give alms of thy substance; and when thou givest alms, let not thine eye be envious, neither turn thy face from any poor, and the face of God shall not be turned away from thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">تصدق من مالك ولا تحول وجهك عن فقير وحينئذ فوجه الرب لا يحول عنك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">sebagaimana halnya dengan semua orang yang berbuat baik. Berilah sedekah dari harta milikmu. Matamu jangan menyesal apabila engkau memberikan sedekah. Muka jangan kaupalingkan dari seorang miskin, niscaya wajah Allahpun tidak akan dipalingkan dari padamu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">If thou hast abundance give alms accordingly: if thou have but a little, be not afraid to give according to that little:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">كن رحيما على قدر طاقتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Berikanlah sedekah sesuai dengan besarnya kekayaanmu. Jika engkau hanya mempunyai sedikit, jangan takut memberikan sedekah seadanya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">For thou layest up a good treasure for thyself against the day of necessity.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ان كان لك كثير فابذل كثيرا وان كان لك قليل فاجتهد ان تبذل القليل عن نفس طيبة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Dengan jalan itu kautimbun simpanan bagi dirimu untuk masa darurat.</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">Because that alms do deliver from death, and suffereth not to come into darkness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فانك تدخر لك ثوابا جميلا الى يوم الضرورة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Memang sedekah melepaskan dari maut dan tidak membiarkan orang masuk ke dalam kegelapan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">For alms is a good gift unto all that give it in the sight of the most High.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لان الصدقة تنجي من كل خطيئة ومن الموت ولا تدع النفس تصير الى الظلمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Sedekah merupakan persembahan yang baik ke hadapan Yang Mahatinggi bagi semua orang yang memberikannya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">Beware of all whoredom, my son, and chiefly take a wife of the seed of thy fathers, and take not a strange woman to wife, which is not of thy father's tribe: for we are the children of the prophets, Noe, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob: remember, my son, that our fathers from the beginning, even that they all married wives of their own kindred, and were blessed in their children, and their seed shall inherit the land.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ان الصدقة هي رجاء عظيم عند الله العلي لجميع صانعيها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Nak, jauhilah percabulan. Lebih-lebih, ambillah isteri dari keturunan nenek moyangmu. Jangan mengambil isteri luar yang tidak berasal dari suku ayahmu. Sebab kita ini adalah keturunan para nabi - Nuh, Abraham, Ishak, Yakub, nenek moyang kita dari abad-abad yang lampau - Ingatlah, nak, bahwa mereka sekalian mengambil isteri dari kaum kerabat mereka sendiri. Maka mereka diberkati dalam anak-anaknya. Ingatlah pula bahwa keturunan mereka akan mewarisi tanah yang telah dijanjikan Tuhan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">Now therefore, my son, love thy brethren, and despise not in thy heart thy brethren, the sons and daughters of thy people, in not taking a wife of them: for in pride is destruction and much trouble, and in lewdness is decay and great want: for lewdness is the mother of famine.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">احذر لنفسك يا بني من كل زنى ولا تتجاوز امراتك مستبيحا معرفة الاثم ابدا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Oleh sebab itu, nak, cintailah sanak saudaramu dan jangan meninggikan hatimu terhadap sanak saudaramu serta anak-anak lelaki dan perempuan bangsamu, sehingga engkau enggan mengambil isterimu dari kalangan mereka. Sebab di dalam kecongkakan terletaklah kebinasaan dan banyak kegelisahan, dan dalam kemalasan terletak kepapaan dan kekurangan besar. Memang kemalasan adalah ibu kelaparan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">Let not the wages of any man, which hath wrought for thee, tarry with thee, but give him it out of hand: for if thou serve God, he will also repay thee: be circumspect my son, in all things thou doest, and be wise in all thy conversation.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و لا تدع الكبر يستولي على افكارك واقوالك لان الكبر مبدا كل هلاك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Janganlah upah orang manapun yang bekerja padamu sampai bermalam padamu. Sebaliknya bayarkanlah segera kepadanya. Apabila engkau mengabdi kepada Allah, niscaya engkau mendapat ganjaran. Berjaga-jagalah, nak, dalam segala pekerjaanmu dan hendaklah berlaku sebagai seorang yang terdidik baik dalam segenap tingkah lakumu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">Do that to no man which thou hatest: drink not wine to make thee drunken: neither let drunkenness go with thee in thy journey.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">و كل من خدمك بشيء فاوفه اجرته لساعته واجرة اجيرك لا تبق عندك ابدا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Apa yang tidak kausukai sendiri, janganlah kauperbuat kepada siapapun. Jangan minum anggur sampai mabuk dan kemabukan jangan menyertai dirimu di jalan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">Give of thy bread to the hungry, and of thy garments to them that are naked; and according to thine abundance give alms: and let not thine eye be envious, when thou givest alms.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">كل ما تكره ان يفعله غيرك بك فاياك ان تفعله انت بغيرك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Dari makananmu sendiri berikanlah kepada yang lapar dan dari pakaianmu sendiri kepada yang telanjang. Apa yang berlebih-lebihan padamu berikanlah sebagai sedekah; dan matamu jangan menyesal apabila engkau memberikan sedekah.</language></verse>
        <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">Pour out thy bread on the burial of the just, but give nothing to the wicked.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">كل خبزك مع الجياع والمساكين واكس العراة من ثيابك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Sajikanlah dengan berlimpah-limpah makanan di atas kubur orang benar, tetapi jangan kauberikan kepada orang-orang berdosa.</language></verse>
        <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">Ask counsel of all that are wise, and despise not any counsel that is profitable.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">ضع خبزك وخمرك على مدفن البار ولا تاكل ولا تشرب منهما مع الخطاة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Mintalah nasehat dari setiap orang yang arif dan jangan kauhina nasehat yang bermanfaat.</language></verse>
        <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">Bless the Lord thy God alway, and desire of him that thy ways may be directed, and that all thy paths and counsels may prosper: for every nation hath not counsel; but the Lord himself giveth all good things, and he humbleth whom he will, as he will; now therefore, my son, remember my commandments, neither let them be put out of thy mind.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">التمس مشورة الحكيم دائما</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Pujilah Tuhan Allah setiap waktu dan mintalah kepada-Nya, supaya segala jalan hidupmu menjadi lurus dan supaya segala usaha serta rencanamu berhasil baik. Sebab tiada bangsa satupun mempunyai nasehat, melainkan segala nasehat yang baik diberikan oleh Tuhan. Tetapi kalau Tuhan mau maka Ia merendahkan sampai ke lubuk dunia orang mati, sebagaimana yang dikehendaki-Nya. Dan kini, nak, ingatlah kepada segala petunjukku dan jangan sampai terhapus dari hatimu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">And now I signify this to they that I committed ten talents to Gabael the son of Gabrias at Rages in Media.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">و بارك الله في كل حين واسترشده لتقويم سبلك واقرار كل مشوراتك فيه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Oleh sebab itu, nak, aku hendak memberitahukan kepadamu tentang sepuluh talenta perak yang telah kutitipkan pada Gabael bin Gabria di Ragai di negeri Media.</language></verse>
        <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">And fear not, my son, that we are made poor: for thou hast much wealth, if thou fear God, and depart from all sin, and do that which is pleasing in his sight.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">ثم اعلم يا بني اني قد اعطيت وانت صغير عشرة قناطير من الفضة لغابيلوس في راجيس مدينة الماديين ومعي بها صك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Jangan takut-takut, nak, oleh karena kita sudah jatuh miskin. Memang harta milikmu banyak, apabila engkau takut akan Allah dan menjauhkan diri dari setiap dosa lagi melakukan apa yang berkenan pada Tuhan Allahmu."</language></verse>
    </chapter>

    <!-- CHAPTER 5 (22 verses) -->
    <chapter num="5">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Tobias then answered and said, Father, I will do all things which thou hast commanded me:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">فاجاب طوبيا اباه وقال يا ابت كل ما امرتني به افعله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Maka menjawablah Tobia kepada Tobit, ayahnya: "Pak, semuanya yang telah bapak perintahkan kepadaku hendak kulakukan juga.</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">But how can I receive the money, seeing I know him not?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">و اما هذا المال فما ادري كيف احصله فان الرجل لا يعرفني وانا لا اعرفه فما العلامة التي اعطيها له بل الطريق التي تؤدي الى هناك لا اعرفها ايضا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Tetapi bagaimana aku dapat mengambil uang itu dari Gabael? Ia tidak mengenal aku dan akupun tidak mengenal orang itu pula. Tanda apa yang mesti kuberikan kepadanya, supaya ia mengenal aku, percaya kepadaku dan uang itu diserahkannya. Aku tidak mengenal pula jalan-jalan di negeri Media yang harus kutempuh."</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">Then he gave him the handwriting, and said unto him, Seek thee a man which may go with thee, whiles I yet live, and I will give him wages: and go and receive the money.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فاجابه ابوه وقال ان عندي صكه فاذا عرضته عليه فانه يؤدي عاجلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Maka jawab Tobit kepada anaknya Tobia: "Gabael telah memberikan tanda tangan kepadaku yang dibubuh pada sebuah naskah dan demikian akupun kepadanya pula. Naskah itu telah kubagikan jadi dua dan kami masing-masing mengambil separuhnya. Lalu kutitipkan uang itu kepadanya. Sekarang sudah dua puluh tahun sejak uang itu kutitipkan. Lagi, anakku, carilah untukmu seseorang yang dapat dipercaya dan yang mau pergi bersama denganmu. Kita memang akan memberikan upah kepadanya hingga engkau kembali. Kemudian pergilah mengambil uang itu dari pada Gabael."</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">Therefore when he went to seek a man, he found Raphael that was an angel.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و الان هلم فالتمس لك رجلا ثقة يصحبك باجرته حتى تستوفي المال وانا حي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Maka keluarlah Tobia untuk mencari seseorang yang mau pergi bersama dengannya ke negeri Media dan yang tahu jalannya. Didapatinya malaekat Rafael yang berdiri di hadapan Tobia. Hanya Tobia tidak tahu bahwa dia itu seorang malaekat Tuhan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">But he knew not; and he said unto him, Canst thou go with me to Rages? and knowest thou those places well?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فبينما خرج طوبيا اذا بفتى بهي قد وقف مشمرا كانه متاهب للمسير</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Berkatalah Tobia kepadanya: "Dari mana engkau, hai pemuda?" Sahutnya: "Dari saudara-saudaramu, orang Israel. Aku datang ke mari untuk mencari pekerjaan." Tobiapun lalu bertanya kepadanya: "Tahukah engkau jalan ke negeri Media?"</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">To whom the angel said, I will go with thee, and I know the way well: for I have lodged with our brother Gabael.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فسلم عليه وهو يجهل انه ملاك الله وقال من اين اقبلت يا فتى الخير</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Jawabnya: "Aku tahu! Sering kali aku ke sana dan akupun mengenal segala jalan juga. Sudah kerap kali aku pergi ke negeri Media dan aku sudah pernah menginap pada Gabael, saudara kita yang bertempat tinggal di Ragai, di negeri Media, yang terletak di pegunungan. Perjalanannya dari kota Ekbatana hingga ke kota Ragai dua hari biasa."</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">Then Tobias said unto him, Tarry for me, till I tell my father.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">قال انا من بني اسرائيل فقال له طوبيا هل تعرف الطريق الاخذة الى بلاد الماديين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Lalu kata Tobia kepadanya: "Tunggu dahulu, hai pemuda. Aku hendak mengatakannya kepada ayahku di rumah. Perlulah kiranya engkau pergi bersama dengan daku. Upahpun akan kuberikan kepadamu juga."</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Then he said unto him, Go and tarry not. So he went in and said to his father, Behold, I have found one which will go with me. Then he said, Call him unto me, that I may know of what tribe he is, and whether he be a trusty man to go with thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">قال اعرفها وقد سلكت جميع طرقها مرارا كثيرة وكنت نازلا باخينا غابيلوس المقيم براجيس مدينة الماديين التي في جبل احمتا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Sahut Rafael kepadanya: "Aku akan menunggu, tetapi jangan lama-lama!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">So he called him, and he came in, and they saluted one another.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فقال له طوبيا انتظرني حتى اخبر ابي بهذا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Maka Tobia masuk dan memberitahu ayahnya Tobit. Katanya: "Sudah pak, aku sudah mendapat seseorang dari antara saudara-saudara kita, orang Israel." Sahut Tobit kepadanya: "Panggilkanlah aku orang itu, nak, supaya aku tahu bangsa apa ia dan dari suku mana dan apa ia boleh dipercaya untuk pergi bersama denganmu."</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">Then Tobit said unto him, Brother, shew me of what tribe and family thou art.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">و دخل طوبيا واخبر اباه بجميع ذلك فتعجب ابوه وطلب ان يدخل عليه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Tobiapun keluarlah dan memanggil dia. Katanya: "Pemuda, ayahku memanggilmu." Rafael masuk dan oleh Tobit diberi salam dahulu. Ia menjawab dengan banyak-banyak salam pula. Lalu Tobit menyambung: "Apakah aku masih mendapat salam juga? Aku ini orang yang rusak matanya dan cahaya langit tidaklah kulihat. Melainkan duduklah aku dalam kegelapan seperti orang mati yang tidak memandang cahaya. Hidupku berada di tengah-tengah orang mati. Suara manusia kudengar, tetapi mereka tidak kulihat!" Sahut Rafael kepadanya: "Tetapkan hati! Penyembuhan dari Allah sudah dekat. Tetapkan hati!" Lalu Tobit berkata kepadanya: "Anakku Tobia mau pergi ke negeri Media. Adakah engkau dapat pergi bersama dengannya dan mengantar dia? Dan lagi, saudara, engkau akan kuberi upahmu juga!" Sahut Rafael: "Aku mau pergi bersama dengannya. Semua jalan kukenal baik-baik. Sudah sering kali aku pergi ke negeri Media dan menjelajahi dataran-dataran dan pegunungannya. Segala jalannya kuketahui."</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">To whom he said, Dost thou seek for a tribe or family, or an hired man to go with thy son? Then Tobit said unto him, I would know, brother, thy kindred and name.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فدخل وسلم عليه وقال ليكن لك فرح دائم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Tobit menyambung pula: "Saudara dari keluarga mana dan dari suku mana? Nyatakanlah kepadaku, saudara!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">Then he said, I am Azarias, the son of Ananias the great, and of thy brethren.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فاجاب طوبيا واي فرح يكون لي انا المقيم في الظلام لا ابصر ضوء السماء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Sahut Rafael: "Apa perlunya suku itu?" Tobitpun lalu berkata kepadanya: "Aku hanya mau tahu kebenaran saja, siapa engkau dan siapa namamu."</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">Then Tobit said, Thou art welcome, brother; be not now angry with me, because I have enquired to know thy tribe and thy family; for thou art my brother, of an honest and good stock: for I know Ananias and Jonathas, sons of that great Samaias, as we went together to Jerusalem to worship, and offered the firstborn, and the tenths of the fruits; and they were not seduced with the error of our brethren: my brother, thou art of a good stock.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فقال له الفتى كن طيب القلب فانك عن قليل تنال البرء من لدن الله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Sahut Rafael: "Aku ini Azarya bin Ananias yang besar, seorang saudaramu."</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">But tell me, what wages shall I give thee? wilt thou a drachm a day, and things necessary, as to mine own son?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فقال له طوبيا هل لك ان تبلغ ابني الى غابيلوس في راجيس مدينة الماديين وانا اوفيك اجرتك متى رجعت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Maka Tobit berkata: "Selamat datang saudara, dan banyak salam! Jangan kecil hati, saudara, karena aku ingin tahu kebenaran tentang keluargamu. Kebetulan engkau kerabat kami juga. Engkau sungguh dari keluarga mulia dan baik. Ananias dan Natan, kedua anak Semeya yang besar kukenal. Bersama dengan aku mereka dahulu pergi ke Yerusalem dan bersembah sujud di sana. Mereka tidak menyimpang dari jalan yang baik. Saudara-saudaramu sungguh-sungguh orang yang baik. Engkau berasal dari akar yang baik. Selamat datang!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">Yea, moreover, if ye return safe, I will add something to thy wages.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فقال له الملاك اخذه واعود به اليك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Tobit menyambung lagi: "Aku hendak memberikan upah kepadamu sedirham sehari dan penghidupan seperti penghidupan anakku sendiri.</language></verse>
        <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">So they were well pleased. Then said he to Tobias, Prepare thyself for the journey, and God send you a good journey. And when his son had prepared all things far the journey, his father said, Go thou with this man, and God, which dwelleth in heaven, prosper your journey, and the angel of God keep you company. So they went forth both, and the young man's dog with them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فقال له طوبيا اخبرني من اي عشيرة ومن اي سبط انت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Hendaklah pergi bersama dengan anakku, maka aku akan menambah lagi upahmu itu."</language></verse>
        <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">But Anna his mother wept, and said to Tobit, Why hast thou sent away our son? is he not the staff of our hand, in going in and out before us?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فقال له رافائيل الملاك افي نسب الاجير حاجتك ام في الاجير الذي يذهب مع ابنك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Sahut Rafael: "Aku mau pergi bersama dengan anakmu. Jangan kuatir! Kami berangkat dengan sehat walafiat dan dengan sehat walafiat kami nanti kembali pula! Sebab jalannya aman." Sahut Tobit: "Tuhan memberkati engkau, saudara." Kemudian dipanggilnya anaknya dan berkatalah ia kepadanya: "Bersiap-siaplah, nak, untuk perjalanan itu dan pergilah bersama dengan saudaramu ini. Semoga Allah yang ada di sorga melindungi kamu berdua di sana dan mengantar kamu kembali kepadaku dengan sehat walafiat. Semoga malaikat Tuhan menyertai kamu di jalan dengan perlindungannya." Maka keluarlah Tobia untuk berangkat. Ia memeluk ayah serta ibunya. Berkatalah Tobit kepadanya: "Selamat jalan!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">Be not greedy to add money to money: but let it be as refuse in respect of our child.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و لكن لكي لا اقلق بالك انا عزريا بن حننيا العظيم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Tetapi ibunya menangis dan berkata kepada Tobit: "Mengapa anakku kausuruh pergi? Bukankah ia penopang kita yang sudah lanjut usia, oleh karena tetap dapat melayani kita?</language></verse>
        <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">For that which the Lord hath given us to live with doth suffice us.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">فقال له طوبيا انك من نسب كريم غير اني ارجو ان لا يسوءك كوني طلبت معرفة نسبك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Uang sebenarnya tidak lebih dari uang saja. Masakan uang itu menjadi pengganti anak kita!</language></verse>
        <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">Then said Tobit to her, Take no care, my sister; he shall return in safety, and thine eyes shall see him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">فقال له الملاك هاءنذا اخذ ابنك سالما وساعود به اليك سالما</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Cukuplah bagi kita hidup sebagaimana dianugerahkan Tuhan kepada kita."</language></verse>
        <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">For the good angel will keep him company, and his journey shall be prosperous, and he shall return safe.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">قال طوبيا انطلقا بسلام وليكن الله في طريقكما وملاكه يرافقكما</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Sahut Tobit: "Jangan berkhayal, adinda! Anak kita berangkat dengan sehat walafiat dan dengan sehat walafiat ia nanti kembali pula. Dengan mata kepala sendiri adinda akan melihat dia pada hari ia kembali kepada adinda dengan sehat walafiat!</language></verse>
        <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">Then she made an end of weeping.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">حينئذ اخذا كل ما ارادا اخذه من اهبة الطريق وودع طوبيا اباه وامه وسارا كلاهما معا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Jangan berkhayal, jangan takut-takut, adinda, oleh karena mereka. Sebab malaikat baik menyertai anak kita dan perjalanannya akan berlangsung dengan baik. Nanti ia kembali dengan sehat walafiat."</language></verse>
    </chapter>

  <!-- CHAPTER 6 (18 verses) -->
    <chapter num="6">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">And as they went on their journey, they came in the evening to the river Tigris, and they lodged there.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">و سافر طوبيا والكلب يتبعه فبات اول منزلة بجانب نهر دجلة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Adapun anak muda itu berangkat dengan disertai malaikat itu. Anjingpun ikut serta dengan mereka. Mereka berdua berjalan terus. Ketika menjadi malam pada hari pertama bermalamlah mereka di dekat sungai Tigris.</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">And when the young man went down to wash himself, a fish leaped out of the river, and would have devoured him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">و خرج ليغسل رجليه فاذا بحوت عظيم قد خرج ليفترسه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Pemuda itu turun untuk membasuh kakinya di sungai Tigris. Tetapi dari dalam airnya melonkatlah seekor ikan besar mau menelan kaki pemuda itu. Maka menjeritlah ia.</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">Then the angel said unto him, Take the fish. And the young man laid hold of the fish, and drew it to land.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فارتاع طوبيا وصرخ بصوت عظيم قائلا يا مولاي قد اقتحمني</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Tetapi kata malaikat itu kepadanya: "Tangkaplah dan peganglah ikan itu!" Ikan itupun lalu digagahi oleh pemuda itu dan dihelanya ke darat.</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">To whom the angel said, Open the fish, and take the heart and the liver and the gall, and put them up safely.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فقال له الملاك امسك بخيشومه واجتذبه اليك ففعل كذلك واجتذبه الى اليبس فاخذ يختبط عند رجليه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Kemudian malaikat itu menyuruh: "Siatlah ikan itu, ambillah kantung empedu, jantung dan hatinya dan simpanlah. Isi perutnya hendaklah kaubuang. Sebab empedu, jantung dan hatinya adalah obat mujarab."</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">So the young man did as the angel commanded him; and when they had roasted the fish, they did eat it: then they both went on their way, till they drew near to Ecbatane.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فقال له الملاك شق جوف الحوت واحتفظ بقلبه ومرارته وكبده فان لك بها منفعة لعلاج مفيد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Maka disiatlah ikan itu oleh pemuda itu dan dipungutnya kantung empedu, jantung dan hati. Ikan itu dipanggangnya, lalu dimakannya dan sebagian diasinkannya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">Then the young man said to the angel, Brother Azarias, to what use is the heart and the liver and the gall of the fish?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ففعل كذلك ثم شوى من لحمه فاخذا للطريق وملحا سائره حتى يكون لهما ما يكفيهما الى ان يبلغا راجيس مدينة الماديين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Lalu berjalanlah mereka terus bersama sampai di dekat negeri Media.</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">And he said unto him, Touching the heart and the liver, if a devil or an evil spirit trouble any, we must make a smoke thereof before the man or the woman, and the party shall be no more vexed.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">ثم ان طوبيا سال الملاك وقال له نشدتك يا اخي عزريا ان تخبرني ما العلاج الذي يؤخذ من هذه الاشياء التي امرتني ان اذخرها من الحوت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Maka bertanyalah pemuda itu kepada malaikat itu: "Saudara Azarya, obat apa ada di dalam jantung dan hati ikan itu dan di dalam empedunya?"</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">As for the gall, it is good to anoint a man that hath whiteness in his eyes, and he shall be healed.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فاجابه الملاك قائلا اذا القيت شيئا من قلبه على الجمر فدخانه يطرد كل جنس من الشياطين في رجل كان او امراة بحيث لا يعود يقربهماابدا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Sahut malaikat itu: "Jantung dan hati itu boleh diasapkan di depan laki-laki atau perempuan yang kerasukan setan atau roh jahat. Lalu segenap gangguan lenyap dari padanya dan tidak tinggal lagi padanya untuk selama-lamanya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">And when they were come near to Rages,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">و المرارة تنفع لمسح العيون التي عليها غشاء فتبرا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Empedu itu hendaknya diurapkan pada orang yang matanya kena bintik-bintik putih, niscaya bintik-bintik itupun hanya tinggal ditiupi saja lalu sembuh pulalah orang itu."</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">The angel said to the young man, Brother, today we shall lodge with Raguel, who is thy cousin; he also hath one only daughter, named Sara; I will speak for her, that she may be given thee for a wife.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">و قال طوبيا اين تريد ان ننزل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Mereka memasuki negeri Media dan sudah sampai di dekat kota Ekbatana.</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">For to thee doth the right of her appertain, seeing thou only art of her kindred.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فقال الملاك ان هنا رجلا اسمه رعوئيل من ذوي قرابتك من سبطك وله بنت اسمها سارة وليس له من ذكر ولا انثى سواها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Lalu berkatalah Rafael kepada pemuda Tobia: "Hai saudara Tobia!" Sahutnya: "Ada apa?" Rafael menyambung pula: "Malam ini kita harus bermalam pada Raguel. Dia itu seorang kerabatmu dan mempunyai seorang anak perempuan yang bernama Sara.</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">And the maid is fair and wise: now therefore hear me, and I will speak to her father; and when we return from Rages we will celebrate the marriage: for I know that Raguel cannot marry her to another according to the law of Moses, but he shall be guilty of death, because the right of inheritance doth rather appertain to thee than to any other.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فجميع ماله مستحق لك ولا بد لك ان تتخذها زوجة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Kecuali Sara ia tidak mempunyai anak laki-laki atau perempuan. Maka dari itu saudaralah kerabatnya yang paling dekat. Lebih dari siapapun saudara berhak untuk memperoleh anaknya sebagai isteri dan juga berhak untuk mewarisi apa saja yang ada pada ayahnya. Gadis itu berbudi, berani dan sangat cantik. Ayahnyapun baik hati pula."</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">Then the young man answered the angel, I have heard, brother Azarias, that this maid hath been given to seven men, who all died in the marriage chamber.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فاخطبها الى ابيها فانه يزوجها منك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Katanya lagi: "Engkau sungguh berhak mengambil dia. Saudara, dengarkanlah aku. Pada malam ini juga aku hendak berbicara dengan ayahnya tentang gadis itu, supaya kauperoleh bagimu sebagai mempelai. Setelah kembali dari Ragai kita akan merayakan nikahnya. Aku yakin bahwa Raguel tidak dapat menolak atau menunangkannya kepada orang lain. Sebab kalau demikian maka ia patut dihukum mati menurut ketetapan Kitab Musa setelah diketahuinya bahwa engkaulah yang lebih berhak dari orang manapun untuk memperoleh anaknya sebagai isteri. Jadi, saudara, dengarkanlah aku. Malam ini juga kita akan berbicara tentang gadis itu dan kita pinang bagimu. Setelah nanti kembali dari Ragai akan kita ambil dan kita antarkan dia ke rumahmu."</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">And now I am the only son of my father, and I am afraid, lest if I go in unto her, I die, as the other before: for a wicked spirit loveth her, which hurteth no body, but those which come unto her; wherefore I also fear lest I die, and bring my father's and my mother's life because of me to the grave with sorrow: for they have no other son to bury them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فاجاب طوبيا وقال اني سمعت انه قد عقد لها على سبعة ازواج فماتوا وقد سمعت ايضا ان الشيطان قتلهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Tobiapun lalu menjawab kepada Rafael: "Saudara Azarya, telah kudengar bahwa gadis itu sudah diberikan kepada tujuh laki-laki. Tetapi mereka mati semua di kamar tidur. Pada malam mereka datang padanya mereka mati seketika juga. Kudengar orang berkata bahwa mereka dibunuh oleh seorang setan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">Then the angel said unto him, Dost thou not remember the precepts which thy father gave thee, that thou shouldest marry a wife of thine own kindred? wherefore hear me, O my brother; for she shall be given thee to wife; and make thou no reckoning of the evil spirit; for this same night shall she be given thee in marriage.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فلاجل هذا اخاف ان يصيبني مثل ذلك وانا وحيد لابوي فانزل شيخوختهما الى الجحيم بالحزن</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Dari sebab itu aku sekarang takut-takut, sebab setan itu tidak berbuat jahat kepada gadis itu sendiri, tetapi apabila seseorang mau menghampiri dia maka dibunuh seketika oleh setan itu. Aku ini anak tunggal ayahku dan aku tidak mau mati dan begitu membawa hidup ayah dan ibuku ke liang kubur karena kesedihan atas diriku. Anak lain tidak ada pada mereka untuk menguburkannya."</language></verse>
        <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">And when thou shalt come into the marriage chamber, thou shalt take the ashes of perfume, and shalt lay upon them some of the heart and liver of the fish, and shalt make a smoke with it:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فقال له الملاك رافائيل استمع فاخبرك من هم الذين يستطيع الشيطان ان يقوى عليهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Maka berkatalah malaikat itu kepadanya: "Tidakkah engkau ingat akan perintah-perintah ayahmu; bahwa ia memerintahkan kepadamu untuk mengambil isteri dari keluarga ayahmu? Maka dari itu, saudara, dengarkanlah aku! Jangan ambil pusing tentang setan itu; ambil saja gadis itu! Memang aku tahu bahwa malam ini juga gadis itu diberikan kepada saudara sebagai isteri.</language></verse>
        <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">And the devil shall smell it, and flee away, and never come again any more: but when thou shalt come to her, rise up both of you, and pray to God which is merciful, who will have pity on you, and save you: fear not, for she is appointed unto thee from the beginning; and thou shalt preserve her, and she shall go with thee. Moreover I suppose that she shall bear thee children.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ان الذين يتزوجون فينفون الله من قلوبهم ويتفرغون لشهوتهم كالفرس والبغل اللذين لا فهم لهما اولئك للشيطان عليهم سلطان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Kalau nanti masuk ke dalam kamar tidur ambillah sedikit dari hati dan jantung ikan itu dan taruhlah di atas bara pedupaan. Harumnya akan semerbak dan segera setelah dihirup oleh setan itu maka ia akan lari dan tak pernah muncul lagi pada gadis itu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">Now when Tobias had heard these things, he loved her, and his heart was effectually joined to her.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فانت اذا تزوجتها ودخلت المخدع فامسك عنها ثلاثة ايام ولا تتفرغ معها الا للصلوات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Waktu engkau mau bersatu dengannya hendaklah kamu berdua berdiri dahulu untuk berdoa. Mohonlah kepada Tuhan semesta langit, moga-moga Ia berbelas kasihan kepada kamu dan melindungi kamu. Jangan takut, gadis itu diuntukkan bagimu sejak sediakala dan engkaulah yang akan menyelamatkannya. Ia pasti akan berangkat bersama denganmu dan kukira engkau mendapat anak dari padanya, yang seolah-olah akan menjadi saudara-saudaramu. Jangan ambil pusing!"</language></verse>
    </chapter>

    <!-- CHAPTER 7 (16 verses) -->
    <chapter num="7">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">And when they were come to Ecbatane, they came to the house of Raguel, and Sara met them: and after they had saluted one another, she brought them into the house.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ثم دخلا على رعوئيل فتلقاهما رعوئيل بالمسرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Ketika mereka tiba di kota Ekbatana berkatalah Tobia kepada temannya: "Saudara Azarya, antarkanlah aku langsung ke rumah Raguel saudara kami." Iapun lalu mengantarkannya ke rumah Raguel. Raguel didapati mereka duduk pada pintu pelataran rumahnya. Mereka memberikan salam dahulu kepadanya dan dibalas oleh Raguel. Katanya: "Banyak-banyak salam, saudara-saudara. Selamat datang!" Mereka dipersilakannya masuk ke rumah.</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">Then said Raguel to Edna his wife, How like is this young man to Tobit my cousin!</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">و اذ نظر رعوئيل الى طوبيا قال لحنة زوجته ما اشبه هذا الرجل بذي قرابتي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Kemudian kata Raguel kepada Edna, isterinya: "Alangkah miripnya pemuda itu dengan saudaraku Tobit!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">And Raguel asked them, From whence are ye, brethren? To whom they said, We are of the sons of Nephthalim, which are captives in Nineve.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و بعد هذا الكلام قال رعوئيل من اين انتما ايها الاخوان الفتيان فقالا له من سبط نفتالي من جلاء نينوى</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Ednapun lalu bertanya kepada mereka: "Dari mana kalian, hai saudara-saudara?" Sahut mereka: "Dari bani Naftali, dari kaum buangan di kota Niniwe."</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">Then he said to them, Do ye know Tobit our kinsman? And they said, We know him. Then said he, Is he in good health?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فقال لهما رعوئيل هل تعرفان طوبيا اخي فقالا نعرفه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Maka berkatalah Edna kepada mereka: "Kenalkah kamu Tobit, saudara kami?" Jawab mereka: "Kami kenal."</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">And they said, He is both alive, and in good health: and Tobias said, He is my father.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فلما اكثر من الثناء عليه قال الملاك لرعوئيل ان طوبيا الذي انت تسال عنه هو ابو هذا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Edna bertanya pula kepada mereka: "Sehat walafiatkah ia?" Sahut mereka: "Ia masih hidup dan sehat walafiat." Lalu berkatalah Tobia: "Ia adalah ayahku."</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">Then Raguel leaped up, and kissed him, and wept,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فالقى رعوئيل بنفسه وقبله بدموع وبكى على عنقه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Maka melonjaklah Raguel. Ia memeluk Tobia sambil menangis lalu berkata: "Tuhan memberkati engkau, nak! Engkau adalah anak orang yang mulia dan baik! Alangkah celakanya orang yang benar dan penderma itu menjadi buta!" Iapun mendekap Tobia, saudaranya, sambil menangis.</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">And blessed him, and said unto him, Thou art the son of an honest and good man. But when he had heard that Tobit was blind, he was sorrowful, and wept.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">و قال بركة لك يا بني انك ابن رجل صالح فاضل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Pun pula isterinya Edna dan anak mereka Sara menangis.</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">And likewise Edna his wife and Sara his daughter wept. Moreover they entertained them cheerfully; and after that they had killed a ram of the flock, they set store of meat on the table. Then said Tobias to Raphael, Brother Azarias, speak of those things of which thou didst talk in the way, and let this business be dispatched.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">و بكت حنة امراته وسارة ابنتهما ايضا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Kemudian Raguel menyembelih seekor domba betina dari kawanannya dan disambutnyalah mereka dengan ramah.</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">So he communicated the matter with Raguel: and Raguel said to Tobias, Eat and drink, and make merry:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">و بعد ان تحادثوا امر رعوئيل ان يذبح كبش وتهيا مادبة ودعاهما ان يتكئا للغذاء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Setelah mereka mencuci dan membasuh diri dan sudah duduk makan maka berkatalah Tobia kepada Rafael: "Saudara Azarya, katakanlah kepada Raguel, supaya saudariku Sara diberikannya kepadaku."</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">For it is meet that thou shouldest marry my daughter: nevertheless I will declare unto thee the truth.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فقال طوبيا اني لا اكل اليوم طعاما ههنا ولا اشرب ما لم تجيبني الى ما انا سائله وتعدني ان تعطيني سارة ابنتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Mendengar perkataan itu berkatalah Raguel kepada pemuda itu: "Makan dan minumlah dan bersenang-senanglah malam ini. Memang, saudara, tiada seorangpun lebih berhak mengambil Sara, anakku, sebagai isterinya dari padamu. Karena itupun aku tidak berwenang lagi memberikannya kepada seseorang kecuali kepadamu. Sebab engkaulah yang paling karib. Tetapi, anakku, aku mesti memberitahukan kebenaran!</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">I have given my daughter in marriage to seven men, who died that night they came in unto her: nevertheless for the present be merry. But Tobias said, I will eat nothing here, till we agree and swear one to another.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فلما سمع رعوئيل هذا الكلام ارتعد لمعرفته بما اصاب السبعة الرجال الذين دخلوا عليها وخاف ان يصيب هذا ما اصابهم وفيما هو متردد ولم يردد عليه جوابا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Sudah kuberikan Sara kepada tujuh laki-laki dari antara saudara kita, tetapi pada malam ia mereka hampiri matilah mereka semua. Maka, anakku, baiklah sekarang makan dan minum saja. Tuhan akan mengambil tindakan bagimu."</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">Raguel said, Then take her from henceforth according to the manner, for thou art her cousin, and she is thine, and the merciful God give you good success in all things.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">قال له الملاك لا تخف ان تعطيها لهذا فان ابنتك له ينبغي ان تكون زوجة لانه يخاف الله ولذلك لم يقدر غيره ان ياخذها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Tetapi sahut Tobia: "Aku tidak akan makan atau minum apa-apa, sampai engkau mengambil keputusan tentang diriku." Menjawablah Raguel: "Baiklah! Ia diberikan kepadamu sesuai dengan ketetapan Kitab Musa. Dari Sorga sudah diputuskan, bahwa ia harus diberikan kepadamu. Maka hendaklah menerima saudarimu ini. Mulai sekarang ini engkau menjadi saudaranya dan iapun menjadi saudarimu pula. Semenjak hari ini ia diberikan kepadamu untuk selama-lamanya. Dan, anakku, semoga kamu pada malam ini juga dianugerahi oleh Tuhan semesta langit. Semoga Ia menurunkan kasih setia dan damai sejahtera atas diri kamu."</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">Then he called his daughter Sara, and she came to her father, and he took her by the hand, and gave her to be wife to Tobias, saying, Behold, take her after the law of Moses, and lead her away to thy father. And he blessed them;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">حينئذ قال رعوئيل لا اشك ان الله قد تقبل صلواتي ودموعي امامه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Lalu Raguel memanggil Sara anaknya dan iapun datang kepadanya pula. Tangan Sara dipegang oleh Raguel dan demikian Sara diserahkannya kepada Tobia. Dalam pada itu berkatalah Raguel: "Sungguh, sesuai dengan hukum Taurat ia kupercayakan kepadamu dan seturut ketetapan yang tersurat dalam Kitab Musa kuberikan kepadamu menjadi isterimu. Ambillah dia dan antarkanlah kepada ayahmu dengan sehat walafiat. Moga-moga Yang Berkuasa di Sorga menganugerahkan damai sejahtera kepada kamu berdua."</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">And called Edna his wife, and took paper, and did write an instrument of covenants, and sealed it.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و لعله لاجل ذلك ساقكما الله الى حتى تتزوج هذه بذي قرابتها على حسب شريعة موسى والان لا تشك اني اعطيكها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Lalu dipanggilnya ibu Sara untuk mengambil sepucuk gulungan. Ditulisnya perjanjian perkawinan dan dengan demikian Sara diserahkannya menjadi isteri Tobia, sesuai dengan ketetapan Taurat Musa. Sesudah itu mulailah mereka makan minum.</language></verse>
        <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">Then they began to eat.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ثم اخذ بيمين ابنته سارة وسلمها الى يمين طوبيا قائلا اله ابراهيم واله اسحق واله يعقوب يكون معكما وهو يقرنكما ويتم بركته عليكما</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Raguel memanggil Edna, isterinya, lalu berkata kepadanya: "Dinda, siapkanlah sebuah kamar yang lain lalu antarkanlah Sara masuk."</language></verse>
        <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">After Raguel called his wife Edna, and said unto her, Sister, prepare another chamber, and bring her in thither.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">ثم اخذوا صحيفة وكتبوا فيها عقد الزواج</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Maka pergilah Edna menyediakan sebuah kamar sebagaimana dikatakan kepadanya, lalu mengantar Sara masuk ke dalam. Ia menangis oleh karena anaknya, lalu diusapnyalah air matanya dan berkatalah ia kepada Sara:</language></verse>
    </chapter>



        <!-- CHAPTER 8 (21 verses) -->
    <chapter num="8">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">And when they had supped, they brought Tobias in unto her.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">و لما فرغوا من العشاء ادخلوا عليها الفتى</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Selesai makan minum mereka mau pergi tidur semua. Pemuda itu diantar ke luar untuk masuk ke kamar tersebut.</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">And as he went, he remembered the words of Raphael, and took the ashes of the perfumes, and put the heart and the liver of the fish thereupon, and made a smoke therewith.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فذكر طوبيا كلام الملاك فاخرج من كيسه فلذة من الكبد والقاها على الجمر المشتعل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Maka ingatlah Tobia kepada perkataan Rafael. Diambilnya hati serta jantung ikan itu dari dalam buntilnya yang dibawanya, lalu ditaruhnya di atas bara pedupaan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">The which smell when the evil spirit had smelled, he fled into the utmost parts of Egypt, and the angel bound him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">حينئذ قبض الملاك رافائيل على الشيطان واوثقه في برية مصر العليا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Harum ikan itu mengganggu setan itu, yang segera lari ke dataran tinggi negeri Mesir. Adapun Rafael pergi mengikat kakinya dan segera dikebatnya juga.</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">And after that they were both shut in together, Tobias rose out of the bed, and said, Sister, arise, and let us pray that God would have pity on us.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و وعظ طوبيا البكر وقال لها يا سارة قومي نصلي الى الله اليوم وغدا وبعد غد فانا في هذه الليالي الثلاث نتحد بالله وبعد انقضاء الليلة الثالثة نكون في زواجنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Maka keluarlah semua orang dari kamar itu dan pintunya dikunci. Kemudian Tobia bangkit dari tempat tidur dan berkata kepada Sara: "Bangunlah, adinda, mari kita berdoa dan mohon kepada Tuhan kita, semoga dianugerahkan-Nya belas kasihan serta perlindungan."</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">Then began Tobias to say, Blessed art thou, O God of our fathers, and blessed is thy holy and glorious name for ever; let the heavens bless thee, and all thy creatures.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">لانا بنو القديسين فلا ينبغي لنا ان نقترن اقتران الامم الذين لا يعرفون الله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Maka bangunlah Sara dan mereka berdua mulai berdoa dan mohon, supaya mereka mendapat perlindungan. Mereka angkat doa sebagai berikut: "Terpujilah Engkau, ya Allah nenek moyang kami, dan terpujilah nama-Mu sepanjang sekalian abad. Hendaknya sekalian langit memuji Engkau dan juga segenap ciptaan-Mu untuk selama-lamanya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">Thou madest Adam, and gavest him Eve his wife for an helper and stay: of them came mankind: thou hast said, It is not good that man should be alone; let us make unto him an aid like unto himself.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فقاما معا وصليا كلاهما بحرارة حتى يعافيهما</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Engkaulah yang telah menjadikan Adam dan baginya telah Kaubuat Hawa isterinya sebagai pembantu serta penopang; dari mereka berdua lahirlah umat manusia seluruhnya. Engkaupun bersabda pula: Tidak baik, kalau manusia itu seorang diri saja, mari Kita menjadikan penolong baginya, yang sepadan dengan dia.</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">And now, O Lord, I take not this my sister for lust, but uprightly: therefore mercifully ordain that we may become aged together.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">و قال طوبيا ايها الرب اله ابائنا لتباركك السماوات والارض والبحر والينابيع والانهار وجميع خلائقك التي فيها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Bukan karena nafsu berahi sekarang kuambil saudariku ini, melainkan dengan hati benar. Sudilah kiranya mengasihani aku ini dan dia dan membuat kami menjadi tua bersama."</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">And she said with him, Amen.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">انت جبلت ادم من تراب الارض واتيته حواء عونا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Serentak berkatalah mereka: "Amin! Amin!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">So they slept both that night. And Raguel arose, and went and made a grave,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">و الان يارب انت تعلم اني لا لسبب الشهوة اتخذ اختي زوجة وانما رغبة في النسل الذي يبارك فيه اسمك الى دهر الدهور</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Kemudian mereka tidur semalam-malaman.</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">Saying, I fear lest he also be dead.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">و قالت سارة ايضا ارحمنا يا رب ارحمنا حتى نشيخ كلانا معا في عافية</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Tetapi Raguel bangun dan dipanggilnya beberapa bujangnya yang pergi menggali kubur. Sebab Raguel berpikir: "Tidak boleh tidak Tobia mati. Nanti kami menjadi tertawaan dan orang ternista!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">But when Raguel was come into his house,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">و كان نحو وقت صياح الديك ان رعوئيل امر ان يجمع اليه غلمانه فانطلقوا معه واحتفروا قبرا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Selesai menggali kubur itu Raguel masuk rumah dan dipanggilnya isterinya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">He said unto his wife Edna, Send one of the maids, and let her see whether he be alive: if he be not, that we may bury him, and no man know it.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">لانه قال اخشى ان يصيبه ما اصاب غيره من الرجال السبعة الذين دخلوا عليها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Katanya: "Suruhlah seorang sahaya masuk untuk melihat apa ia masih hidup. Kalau sudah mati kita kuburkan tanpa diketahui seorangpun."</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">So the maid opened the door, and went in, and found them both asleep,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فلما اعدوا القبر رجع رعوئيل الى زوجته وقال لها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Sahaya itupun lalu disuruh, lampu dipasang dan pintu dibuka. Masuklah sahaya itu dan didapatinya mereka tertidur dengan nyenyaknya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">And came forth, and told them that he was alive.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ابعثي واحدة من جواريك لترى هل مات حتى اواريه قبل ضوء النهار</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Maka sahaya itu keluar dan diberitahukannya kepada Raguel serta isterinya bahwa Tobia masih hidup dan tidak terjadi apa-apa.</language></verse>
        <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">Then Raguel praised God, and said, O God, thou art worthy to be praised with all pure and holy praise; therefore let thy saints praise thee with all thy creatures; and let all thine angels and thine elect praise thee for ever.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فانفذت احدى جواريها فدخلت المخدع فاذا هما سالمان معافيان وهما نائمان معا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Maka mereka memuji Yang Berkuasa di Sorga, katanya: "Terpujilah Engkau, ya Allah, dengan segala pujian yang murni, hendaklah Engkau dipuji untuk selama-lamanya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">Thou art to be praised, for thou hast made me joyful; and that is not come to me which I suspected; but thou hast dealt with us according to thy great mercy.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فعادت واخبرت بهذه البشرى فبارك رعوئيل وحنة زوجته الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Terpujilah Engkau, karena aku telah Kaugembirakan; apa yang kusangka tidaklah terjadi. Sebaliknya kami telah Kauperlakukan menurut belas kasihan-Mu yang besar.</language></verse>
        <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">Thou art to be praised because thou hast had mercy of two that were the only begotten children of their fathers: grant them mercy, O Lord, and finish their life in health with joy and mercy.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">قائلين نباركك ايها الرب اله اسرائيل من اجل انه لم يصبنا ما كنا نتوقعه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Terpujilah Engkau, karena kedua anak tunggal itu telah Kaukasihani. Berilah mereka, ya Tuhan, belas kasihan dan perlindungan, dan biarlah mereka meneruskan hidup mereka dengan senang dan belas kasihan!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">Then Raguel bade his servants to fill the grave.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فانك قد اتيتنا رحمتك وحبست عنا العدو الذي يضطهدنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Kemudian disuruhnya bujang-bujang itu menimbus kubur itu sebelum fajar menyingsing.</language></verse>
        <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">And he kept the wedding feast fourteen days.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">و رحمت الوحيدين فاجعلهما يارب يباركانك اتم بركة ويقدمان لك قربان تسبيحك وعافيتهما حتى تعلم الامم كافة انك انت الاله الواحد في الارض كلها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Raguel menyuruh isterinya membuat banyak roti. Ia sendiri pergi ke kawanan dan diambilnya dua lembu jantan dan empat domba jantan yang disuruhnya disediakan. Maka mulailah orang dengan persiapan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">For before the days of the marriage were finished, Raguel had said unto him by an oath, that he should not depart till the fourteen days of the marriage were expired;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">و للحال امر رعوئيل غلمانه ان يردموا القبر الذي حفروه قبل ضوء الصباح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Kemudian Raguel memanggil Tobia dan berkata kepadanya: "Selama empat belas hari ini sekali-kali tidak boleh engkau berangkat dari sini, melainkan engkau harus tinggal di sini untuk makan minum. Engkau mesti menggembirakan hati anakku yang telah sedih pedih.</language></verse>
        <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">And then he should take the half of his goods, and go in safety to his father; and should have the rest when I and my wife be dead.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">ثم اوعز الى زوجته ان تعد وليمة وتصلح ما ينبغي للمسافرين من الزاد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Kemudian barulah dapat engkau mengambil separuh dari milikku di sini dan pulang dengan selamat kepada ayahmu. Separuh lainnya dari milikku menjadi kepunyaanmu juga setelah aku serta isteriku meninggal. Tetapkanlah hatimu, nak! Akulah bapamu dan Edna ibumu. Kami menjadi kerabat dengan engkau seperti kami kerabat dengan saudarimu, mulai sekarang sampai selama-lamanya. Tetapkanlah hati, nak!"</language></verse>
    </chapter>

    <!-- CHAPTER 9 (6 verses) -->
    <chapter num="9">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Then Tobias called Raphael, and said unto him,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ثم ان طوبيا استدعى الملاك الذي كان يحسبه انسانا وقال له يا اخي عزريا اسالك ان تسمع كلامي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Kemudian Tobia memanggil Rafael dan berkata kepadanya:</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">Brother Azarias, take with thee a servant, and two camels, and go to Rages of Media to Gabael, and bring me the money, and bring him to the wedding.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اني لو جعلت نفسي عبدا لك لما وفيت بعنايتك حق الوفاء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">"Saudara Azarya, hendaklah engkau mengambil sertamu empat orang bujang dan dua ekor unta. Baiklah engkau berangkat ke kota Ragai dan pergi ke Gabael. Hendaklah engkau menyerahkan kepadanya surat bukti ini lalu memungut uang itu. Dan lagi hendaklah engkau membawa dia sertamu ke pernikahan nanti.</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">For Raguel hath sworn that I shall not depart.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و لكني مع ذلك اسالك ان تاخذ دواب وغلمانا وتنطلق الى غابيلوس في راجيس مدينة الماديين وترد عليه صكه وتقبض منه الفضة وتدعوه الى عرسي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Engkau tahu bahwa ayahku membilang-bilang hari. Apabila aku berayal-ayalan, niscaya ayahku sangat sedih hati.</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">But my father counteth the days; and if I tarry long, he will be very sorry.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">لانك تعلم ان ابي يحسب الايام فان زدت في ابطائي يوما واحدا حزنت نفسه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Dan engkaupun tahu baik-baik apa yang telah dijanjikan oleh Raguel dengan sumpah dan sumpah itu tidak dapat kulanggar."</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">So Raphael went out, and lodged with Gabael, and gave him the handwriting: who brought forth bags which were sealed up, and gave them to him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">و انت ترى ان رعوئيل قد استحلفني ولست استطيع ان استخف بحلفه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Maka berangkatlah Rafael dengan disertai empat bujang dan dua ekor unta itu ke kota Ragai di negeri Media. Ia bermalam pada Gabael. Kepadanya diserahkannya surat bukti tadi dan diberitahukannya tentang Tobia bin Tobit, yakni bahwasanya ia telah mengambil isteri, dan ia mengundang Gabael juga ke pernikahan itu. Maka Gabael bangkit dan dibilangnya kantung-kantung yang masih bermeterai itu. Lalu dimuatkannya semua.</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">And early in the morning they went forth both together, and came to the wedding: and Tobias blessed his wife.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">حينئذ اخذ رافائيل اربعة من غلمان رعوئيل وجملين وسافر الى راجيس مدينة الماديين ولقي غابيلوس فدفع اليه صكه واستوفى منه المال كله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Pagi-pagi benar berangkatlah mereka berdua dan kemudian tiba pada pesta pernikahan itu. Mereka masuk ke rumah Raguel dan mendapati Tobia sedang makan. Maka Tobia melonjak berdiri, lalu diberi salam oleh Gabael. Gabael memberkati Tobia sambil menangis, katanya: "Anak mulia dan baik dari bapak yang mulia dan baik, benar dan penderma! Moga-moga Tuhan semesta langit memberkati engkau serta isterimu, ayah dan ibu isterimu. Terpujilah Allah, karena aku telah dapat melihat gambaran Tobit, saudara sepupuku!"</language></verse>
    </chapter>

<!-- CHAPTER 10 (13 verses) -->
    <chapter num="10">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Now Tobit his father counted every day: and when the days of the journey were expired, and they came not,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">و لما ابطا طوبيا هناك لسبب العرس قلق ابوه طوبيا وقال لماذا ترى ابطا ابني وما الذي عاقه هناك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Dalam pada itu Tobit hari demi hari menghitung waktu yang diperlukan untuk pergi pulang. Setelah waktu itu genap dan anaknya belum tiba juga</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">Then Tobit said, Are they detained? or is Gabael dead, and there is no man to give him the money?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">العل غابيلوس قد مات وليس من يرد له المال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">maka pikirnya: "Boleh jadi ia tertahan di sana? Atau barangkali Gabael sudah meninggal, sehingga tidak ada seorang pun menyerahkan uang itu kepadanya?"</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">Therefore he was very sorry.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و اخذه حزن شديد هو وحنة امراته وطفق كلاهما يبكيان لتخلف ابنهما عن الرجوع في يوم الميعاد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Dan ia mulai merasa sedih.</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">Then his wife said unto him, My son is dead, seeing he stayeth long; and she began to bewail him, and said,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و كانت امه تبكي بدموع لا تنقطع وهي تقول اه اوه يا بني لماذا ارسلناك في الغربة يا نور ابصارنا وعكازة شيخوختنا وعزاء عيشتنا ورجاء عقبنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Hana, isterinya, berkata kepada Tobit: "Memang anakku sudah jatuh binasa dan tidak ada lagi di tengah-tengah orang-orang yang hidup!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">Now I care for nothing, my son, since I have let thee go, the light of mine eyes.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">لقد كان لنا فيك وحدك كل شيء فلم يكن ينبغي لنا ان نرسلك عنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Ia mulai menangisi serta meratapi anaknya, katanya: "Celakalah aku ini, hai anakku, oleh karena kubiarkan engkau pergi, engkau yang menjadi cahaya mataku!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">To whom Tobit said, Hold thy peace, take no care, for he is safe.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فكان طوبيا يقول لها اسكتي ولا تقلقي ان ابننا سالم والرجل الذي ارسلناه معه ثقة جدا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Maka berkatalah Tobit kepadanya: "Diamlah, jangan berkhayal, adinda. Ia sehat walafiat! Memang mereka terhalang di sana. Orang yang berangkat serta Tobia dapat dipercaya. Ia adalah seorang dari antara saudara-saudara kita. Jangan sedih hati oleh karena anak kita, adinda. Nanti ia muncul!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">But she said, Hold thy peace, and deceive me not; my son is dead. And she went out every day into the way which they went, and did eat no meat on the daytime, and ceased not whole nights to bewail her son Tobias, until the fourteen days of the wedding were expired, which Raguel had sworn that he should spend there. Then Tobias said to Raguel, Let me go, for my father and my mother look no more to see me.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فلم يكن ذلك يفيدها ادنى تعزية وكانت كل يوم تقوم مسرعة فتتشوف من كل جهة وتنظر في جميع الطرق التي كانت تظن ان ابنها يرجع منها لعلها تراه عن بعد مقبلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Tetapi Hana menyahut kepadanya: "Diam! Jangan memperdayakan aku! Anakku binasa sudah!" Setiap hari berulang-ulang Hana ke luar untuk menengok jalan yang telah ditempuh anaknya waktu pergi. Ia tidak percaya lagi pada siapa pun. Setelah matahari terbenam barulah ia pulang, tetapi semalam-malaman ia meratap dan menangis dan tidak dapat tidur.</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">But his father in law said unto him, Tarry with me, and I will send to thy father, and they shall declare unto him how things go with thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">و اما رعوئيل فقال لصهره امكث ههنا وانا انفذ الى طوبيا ابيك من يخبره بسلامتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Setelah genaplah empat belas hari pesta pernikahan itu yang dengan sumpah dijanjikan Raguel untuk dirayakan bagi anaknya, maka datanglah Tobia kepadanya, katanya: "Izinkanlah aku pulang, sebab aku tahu bahwa ayah ibuku sudah tidak berharap lagi akan melihat aku. Dan sekarang aku mohon bapak, supaya bapak membiarkan aku pulang kepada ayahku. Sudah kuberitahukan kepadamu, bagaimana ayahku kutinggalkan."</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">But Tobias said, No; but let me go to my father.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فقال له طوبيا اني لاعلم ان ابي وامي يحسبان الايام وارواحهما معذبة قلقا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Tetapi sahut Raguel kepada Tobia: "Tinggal saja, nak, tinggal padaku di sini. Aku akan mengutus pesuruh kepada Tobit, ayahmu, untuk memberitahukan tentang keadaanmu." Tetapi Tobia menyahut: "Jangan, pak, aku mohon, supaya engkau membiarkan aku pulang dari sini kepada ayahku."</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">Then Raguel arose, and gave him Sara his wife, and half his goods, servants, and cattle, and money:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">و بعد ان اكثر رعوئيل من الالحاح على طوبيا فابى ان يسمع بوجه من الوجوه اعطاه سارة ونصف امواله كلها من غلمان وجوار ومواش وابل وبقر وفضة كثيرة وصرفه من عنده بسلام فرحا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Maka bangkitlah Raguel dan diserahkannya kepada Tobia Sara, isterinya, dan separuh dari miliknya, yaitu budak sahaya, lembu jantan dan domba, keledai dan unta, pakaian, uang dan perabot.</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">And he blessed them, and sent them away, saying, The God of heaven give you a prosperous journey, my children.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">قائلا ملاك الرب القدوس يكون في طريقكما ويبلغكما سالمين وتجدان كل شيء عند ابويكما بخير وترى عيناي بنيكما قبل موتي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Demikianlah mereka diizinkannya pergi dengan sehat walafiat. Ia memberikan salam kepada mereka, katanya: "Salam, nak, selamat jalan! Moga-moga Tuhan semesta langit menganugerahi engkau serta Sara, isterimu. Dan moga-moga aku masih melihat anak-anak kamu, sebelum aku meninggal."</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">And he said to his daughter, Honour thy father and thy mother in law, which are now thy parents, that I may hear good report of thee. And he kissed her. Edna also said to Tobias, The Lord of heaven restore thee, my dear brother, and grant that I may see thy children of my daughter Sara before I die, that I may rejoice before the Lord: behold, I commit my daughter unto thee of special trust; where are do not entreat her evil.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">و اقبل الوالدان على ابنتهما يقبلانها ثم صرفاها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Kepada anaknya Sara pun ia berkata juga: "Pergilah kepada mertuamu. Sebab mulai sekarang ini merekalah orang tuamu, seolah-olah melahirkan engkau. Pergi dengan selamat, nak; biarlah aku mendengar kabar baik tentang dirimu selama aku hidup!" Lalu ia dipeluknya dan dibiarkannya mereka pergi.</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">Wherefore now, my son, consider what alms doeth, and how righteousness doth deliver.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">و اوصياها ان تكرم حمويها وتحب بعلها وتدبر عيالها وتسوس بيتها وتحفظ نفسها غير ملومة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Adapun Edna berkata kepada Tobia: "Anak dan saudaraku yang tercinta, moga-moga Tuhan mengantar engkau pulang dan mudah-mudahan aku masih melihat selama hidupku anak-anakmu dan anak-anak Sara, anakku, sebelum aku meninggal. Di hadapan Tuhan anakku kupercayakan kepadamu sebagai petaruh. Jangan menyedihkan hatinya sepanjang umur hidupmu. Pergilah dengan selamat, anakku! Mulai sekarang ini akulah ibumu dan Sara menjadi saudarimu. Moga-moga kita sekalian hidup bahagia sepanjang umur hidup kita, seperti halnya sekarang ini." Lalu diberinya salam kepada mereka dan dibiarkannya mereka pergi.</language></verse>
    </chapter>

    <!-- CHAPTER 11 (19 verses) -->
    <chapter num="11">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">After these things Tobias went his way, praising God that he had given him a prosperous journey, and blessed Raguel and Edna his wife, and went on his way till they drew near unto Nineve.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">و فيما هم راجعون وقد بلغوا الى حاران التي في وسط الطريق جهة نينوى في اليوم الحادي عشر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Ketika mereka mendekati daerah Kaserin yang letaknya berhadapan dengan Niniwe berkatalah Rafael:</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">Then Raphael said to Tobias, Thou knowest, brother, how thou didst leave thy father:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">قال الملاك يا اخي طوبيا انك تعلم كيف فارقت اباك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">"Engkau tahu dalam keadaan manakah kita meninggalkan ayahmu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">Let us haste before thy wife, and prepare the house.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فلنتقدم نحن ان احببت والعيال وزوجتك يلحقوننا على مهل مع المواشي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Karena itu baiklah kita berdua mendahului isterimu untuk menyiapkan rumah itu, sedangkan yang lain-lain meneruskan perjalanannya."</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">And take in thine hand the gall of the fish. So they went their way, and the dog went after them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و اذ توافقا على المضي قال رافائيل لطوبيا خذ معك من مرارة الحوت فان لنا بها حاجة فاخذ طوبيا من المرارة وانطلقا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Maka bertolaklah mereka berdua. Rafaelpun sudah berkata pula kepada Tobia: "Bawalah empedu itu juga." Adapun anjing itu juga mengikuti Rafael dan Tobia.</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">Now Anna sat looking about toward the way for her son.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">و اما حنة فكانت كل يوم تجلس عند الطريق على راس الجبل حيث كانت تستطيع ان تنظر على بعد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Dalam pada itu duduklah Hana mengamati jalan yang harus ditempuh anaknya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">And when she espied him coming, she said to his father, Behold, thy son cometh, and the man that went with him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فلما كانت تتشوف ذات يوم من ذلك الموضع نظرت على بعد وللوقت عرفت انه ابنها قادما فبادرت واخبرت بعلها قائلة هوذا ابنك ات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Iapun telah mendapat firasat bahwa anaknya tengah datang. Berkatalah Hana kepada ayah Tobia: "Sungguh anakmu tengah datang dan juga orang yang menyertainya."</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">Then said Raphael, I know, Tobias, that thy father will open his eyes.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">و قال رافائيل لطوبيا اذا دخلت بيتك فاسجد في الحال للرب الهك واشكر له ثم ادن من ابيك وقبله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Sebelum Tobia mendekati ayahnya berkatalah Rafael kepadanya: "Aku yakin bahwa mata ayahmu akan dibuka.</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Therefore anoint thou his eyes with the gall, and being pricked therewith, he shall rub, and the whiteness shall fall away, and he shall see thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">و اطل لساعتك عينيه بمرارة الحوت هذه التي معك واعلم انه للحين تنفتح عيناه ويرى ابوك ضوء السماء ويفرح برؤيتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Sapukanlah empedu ikan itu kepada matanya. Obat itu akan memakan dahulu, lalu mengelupaskan bintik-bintik putih itu dari matanya. Maka ayahmu akan melihat lagi dan memandang cahaya."</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">Then Anna ran forth, and fell upon the neck of her son, and said unto him, Seeing I have seen thee, my son, from henceforth I am content to die. And they wept both.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">حينئذ سبق الكلب الذي كان معه في الطريق وكان كانه بشير يبدي مسرته ببصبصة ذنبه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Adapun Hana bergegas-gegas mendekap anaknya, lalu berkatalah ia kepadanya: "Setelah engkau kulihat, anakku, maka mulai sekarang aku dapat mati." Maka ia menangis.</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">Tobit also went forth toward the door, and stumbled: but his son ran unto him,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فقام ابوه وهو اعمى وجعل يجري وهو يتعثر برجليه فناول يده لغلام وخرج لملاقاة ابنه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Tobitpun berdiri dan meskipun kakinya tersandung namun ia keluar dari pintu pelataran rumah.</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">And took hold of his father: and he strake of the gall on his fathers' eyes, saying, Be of good hope, my father.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">و استقبله وقبله هو وامراته وطفق كلاهما يبكيان من الفرح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Tobia menghampirinya dengan empedu ikan itu di tangan lalu ditiupinya mata Tobit, ditopangnya ayahnya dan kemudian berkatalah ia kepadanya: "Tetapkan hati, pak!" Selanjutnya obat itu dikenakannya padanya dan dibiarkannya sebentar.</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">And when his eyes began to smart, he rubbed them;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ثم سجدوا لله وشكروا له وجلسوا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Lalu dengan kedua tangannya dikelupaskannya sesuatu dari ujung-ujung matanya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">And the whiteness pilled away from the corners of his eyes: and when he saw his son, he fell upon his neck.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فاخذ طوبيا من مرارة الحوت وطلى عيني ابيه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Maka Tobit mendekap Tobia sambil menangis. Katanya: "Aku melihat engkau, anakku, cahaya mataku!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">And he wept, and said, Blessed art thou, O God, and blessed is thy name for ever; and blessed are all thine holy angels:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و مكث مقدار نصف ساعة فبدا يخرج من عينيه غشاوة كغرقئ البيض</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Ia menyambung pula: "Terpujilah Allah, terpujilah nama-Nya yang besar, terpujilah para malaikat-Nya yang kudus. Hendaklah nama Tuhan yang besar ada di atas kita dan terpujilah hendaknya segala malaikat untuk selama-lamanya. Sungguh aku telah disiksa oleh Tuhan, tetapi kulihat anakku Tobia!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">For thou hast scourged, and hast taken pity on me: for, behold, I see my son Tobias. And his son went in rejoicing, and told his father the great things that had happened to him in Media.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فامسكها طوبيا وسحبها من عينيه وللوقت عاد الى طوبيا بصره</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Kemudian masuklah Tobia ke rumah dengan sukacita sambil memuji Allah dengan segenap hatinya. Diceritakannya kepada ayahnya bahwa perjalanannya berhasil baik; bahwa ia telah membawa uang itu dan sudah mengambil Sara anak perempuan Raguel menjadi isterinya dan bahwa isterinya masih dalam perjalanan dan sudah dekat pada pintu gerbang kota Niniwe.</language></verse>
        <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">Then Tobit went out to meet his daughter in law at the gate of Nineve, rejoicing and praising God: and they which saw him go marvelled, because he had received his sight.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فمجد الله هو وامراته وكل من كان يعرفه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Maka keluarlah Tobit menjemput anak menantunya pada pintu gerbang kota Niniwe dengan sukacita seraya memuji Allah. Melihat Tobit berjalan dan maju dengan kekuatannya seperti dahulu tanpa diantar oleh siapapun maka tercengang-cenganglah penduduk kota Niniwe. Tobitpun lalu memaklumkan di hadapan mereka bahwa ia telah dikasihani oleh Allah yang telah mencelikkan matanya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">But Tobias gave thanks before them, because God had mercy on him. And when he came near to Sara his daughter in law, he blessed her, saying, Thou art welcome, daughter: God be blessed, which hath brought thee unto us, and blessed be thy father and thy mother. And there was joy among all his brethren which were at Nineve.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">و قال طوبيا اباركك ايها الرب اله اسرائيل لانك ادبتني وشفيتني وهاءنذا ارى طوبيا ولدي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Akhirnya Tobit mendekati Sara, isteri anaknya Tobia, lalu diberkatinya dengan berkata: "Selamat datang, anakku. Terpujilah Allahmu yang mengantar engkau kepada kami, hai anakku! Tuhan memberkati ayahmu, memberkati anakku Tobia dan memberkati engkau sendiri, hai anakku. Masuklah ke rumahmu dengan selamat, dengan berkat dan gembira! Masuklah, hai anakku!"</language></verse>
        <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">And Achiacharus, and Nasbas his brother's son, came:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و اما سارة كنته فوصلت بعد سبعة ايام هي وجميع العيال بسلام والغنم والابل ومال كثير مما للمراة مع المال الذي استوفاه من غابيلوس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Pada hari itu juga terjadilah kegembiraan untuk semua orang Yahudi yang diam di kota Niniwe.</language></verse>
        <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">And Tobias' wedding was kept seven days with great joy.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">و اخبر ابويه بجميع احسانات الله التي انعم بها عليه على يد ذلك الرجل الذي ذهب معه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Kemenakan Tobit, yaitu Ahikar dan Nadab, ikut bergembira pula dengan Tobit.</language></verse>
    </chapter>

 <!-- CHAPTER 12 (22 verses) -->
    <chapter num="12">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Then Tobit called his son Tobias, and said unto him, My son, see that the man have his wages, which went with thee, and thou must give him more.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">حينئذ دعا طوبيا ابنه اليه وقال له ماذا ترى نعطي هذا الرجل القديس الذي ذهب معك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Setelah perayaan nikah itu selesai maka Tobit memanggil anaknya Tobia. Berkatalah ia kepadanya: "Nak, ingatlah memberikan upahnya kepada orang yang telah menyertai engkau. Dan ingatlah menambah upahnya juga."</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">And Tobias said unto him, O father, it is no harm to me to give him half of those things which I have brought:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فاجاب طوبيا وقال لابيه يا ابت اي اجرة نعطيه واي شيء يكون موازيا لاحسانه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Sahut Tobia: "Berapa banyaknya upah yang harus kuberi, pak? Aku tidak menderita rugi sedikitpun, kalau kuberikan kepadanya separuh dari harta benda yang telah kubawa.</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">For he hath brought me again to thee in safety, and made whole my wife, and brought me the money, and likewise healed thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">اخذني ورجع بي سالما والمال هو استوفاه من عند غابيلوس وبه حصلت على زوجتي وهو كف عنها الشيطان وفرح ابويها وخلصني من افتراس الحوت واياك ايضا هو جعلك تبصر نور السماء وبه غمرنا بكل خير فماذا عسى ان نعطيه مما يكون موازيا لهذه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Dengan sehat walafiat aku telah diantar kembali olehnya, isteriku telah disembuhkan olehnya; iapun telah membawa uang itu bersama dengan aku dan ayah telah disembuhkannya pula. Berapa banyaknya upah yang mesti kuberikan karena itu?"</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">Then the old man said, It is due unto him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">لكني اسالك يا ابت ان نساله هل يرضى ان ياخذ النصف من كل ما جئنا به</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Berkatalah Tobit kepadanya: "Memang nak, sudah seadilnya ia diambilkan separuh dari segala sesuatunya yang telah dibawanya waktu datang."</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">So he called the angel, and he said unto him, Take half of all that ye have brought and go away in safety.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فدعاه الوالد وولده واخذاه ناحية وجعلا يسالانه ان يتنازل ويقبل النصف من جميع ما جاءا به</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Maka ia dipanggil dan Tobit berkata kepadanya: "Ambillah sebagai upahmu separuh dari segala sesuatunya yang kaubawa waktu datang, lalu engkau boleh pergi dengan selamat."</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">Then he took them both apart, and said unto them, Bless God, praise him, and magnify him, and praise him for the things which he hath done unto you in the sight of all that live. It is good to praise God, and exalt his name, and honourably to shew forth the works of God; therefore be not slack to praise him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">حينئذ خاطبهما سرا وقال باركا اله السماء واعترفا له امام جميع الاحياء لما اتاكما من مراحمه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Tetapi Rafael memanggil kedua orang itu sendiri-sendiri lalu berkata kepada mereka: "Pujilah Allah dan muliakanlah Dia di depan mata semua orang yang hidup karena segala anugerah yang telah diberikan-Nya kepada kamu. Pujilah nama-Nya dan bernyanyi-nyanyilah kepada-Nya. Wartakanlah kepada segala manusia perbuatan-perbuatan Allah sebagaimana layaknya. Jangan berayal memuliakan Dia.</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">It is good to keep close the secret of a king, but it is honourable to reveal the works of God. Do that which is good, and no evil shall touch you.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">اما سر الملك فخير ان يكتم واما اعمال الله فاذاعتها والاعتراف بها كرامة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Memang baiklah rahasia raja disembunyikan, tetapi pantaslah perbuatan Allah disingkapkan dan dimuliakan. Lakukanlah yang baik, niscaya malapetaka tidak akan menimpa kamu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Prayer is good with fasting and alms and righteousness. A little with righteousness is better than much with unrighteousness. It is better to give alms than to lay up gold:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">صالحة الصلاة مع الصوم والصدقة خير من ادخار كنوز الذهب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Lebih baiklah doa benar dan sedekah jujur daripada kekayaan yang lalim.</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">For alms doth deliver from death, and shall purge away all sin. Those that exercise alms and righteousness shall be filled with life:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لان الصدقة تنجي من الموت وتمحو الخطايا وتؤهل الانسان لنوال الرحمة والحياة الابدية</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Memang sedekah melepaskan dari maut dan menghapus setiap dosa. Orang yang melakukan sedekah akan menjadi puas dengan umurnya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">But they that sin are enemies to their own life.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">و اما الذين يعملون المعصية والاثم فهم اعداء لانفسهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Sebaliknya, orang yang berbuat dosa dan lalim menjadi seteru hidupnya sendiri.</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Surely I will keep close nothing from you. For I said, It was good to keep close the secret of a king, but that it was honourable to reveal the works of God.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">اما انا فاعلن لكما الحق وما اكتم عنكما امرا مستورا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Segenap kebenaran hendak kuwartakan kepada kamu dan tidak kusembunyikan apa-apa terhadap kamu. Sudah kutandaskan kepadamu: Baiklah rahasia raja disembunyikan, tetapi pantaslah perbuatan Allah disingkapkan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">Now therefore, when thou didst pray, and Sara thy daughter in law, I did bring the remembrance of your prayers before the Holy One: and when thou didst bury the dead, I was with thee likewise.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">انك حين كنت تصلي بدموع وتدفن الموتى وتترك طعامك وتخبا الموتى في بيتك نهارا وتدفنهم ليلا كنت انا ارفع صلاتك الى الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Makanya, ketika engkau dan Sara berdoa maka ingatan akan doamu itu kusampaikan ke hadapan kemuliaan Tuhan. Dan demikianpun waktu engkau menguburkan orang-orang mati.</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">And when thou didst not delay to rise up, and leave thy dinner, to go and cover the dead, thy good deed was not hid from me: but I was with thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">و اذ كنت مقبولا امام الله كان لا بد ان تمتحن بتجربة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Ketika engkau tidak ayal-ayalan dan bangkit serta meninggalkan makananmu untuk pergi mengapani mayat itu, maka aku diutus untuk mencobai engkau.</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">And now God hath sent me to heal thee and Sara thy daughter in law.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و الان فان الرب قد ارسلني لاشفيك واخلص سارة كنتك من الشيطان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Lagipula aku diutus oleh Allah untuk menyembuhkan baik engkau sendiri maupun Sara, menantumu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">I am Raphael, one of the seven holy angels, which present the prayers of the saints, and which go in and out before the glory of the Holy One.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فاني انا رافائيل الملاك احد السبعة الواقفين امام الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Aku ini Rafael, satu dari ketujuh malaikat yang melayani di hadapan Tuhan yang mulia."</language></verse>
        <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">Then they were both troubled, and fell upon their faces: for they feared.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فلما سمعا مقالته هذه ارتاعا وسقطا على اوجههما على الارض مرتعدين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Maka terperanjatlah kedua orang itu lalu sujud menyembah dan ketakutan.</language></verse>
        <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">But he said unto them, Fear not, for it shall go well with you; praise God therefore.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فقال لهما الملاك سلام لكم لا تخافوا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Tetapi berkatalah malaikat itu kepada mereka: "Jangan takut; damai sejahtera dengan kamu. Pujilah Allah selama-lamanya!</language></verse>
        <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">For not of any favour of mine, but by the will of our God I came; wherefore praise him for ever.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">لاني لما كنت معكم انما كنت بمشيئة الله فباركوه وسبحوه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Waktu aku ada dengan kamu, maka bukan karena kerelaanku sendirilah terjadi demikian, melainkan karena kehendak Allah. Maka pujilah Dia seumur hidup, bernyanyi-nyanyilah kepada-Nya!</language></verse>
        <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">All these days I did appear unto you; but I did neither eat nor drink, but ye did see a vision.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">و كان يظهر لكم اني اكل واشرب معكم وانما انا اتخذ طعاما غير منظور وشرابا لا يبصره بشر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Telah kamu perhatikan bahwa aku tidak makan apa-apa. Hanya suatu penglihatan yang kamu lihat.</language></verse>
        <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">Now therefore give God thanks: for I go up to him that sent me; but write all things which are done in a book.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">و الان قد حان ان ارجع الى من ارسلني وانتم فباركوا الله وحدثوا بجميع عجائبه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Oleh sebab itu, pujilah Tuhan di atas bumi dan muliakanlah Allah! Camkanlah! Aku naik kepada Dia yang telah mengutus aku. Tuliskanlah semuanya yang telah terjadi pada kamu." Maka iapun naik juga.</language></verse>
        <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">And when they arose, they saw him no more.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">و بعد ان قال هذا ارتفع عن ابصارهم فلم يعودوا يعاينونه بعد ذلك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Ketika bangkit mereka tidak dapat melihatnya lagi.</language></verse>
        <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">Then they confessed the great and wonderful works of God, and how the angel of the Lord had appeared unto them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">حينئذ لبثوا ثلاث ساعات منطرحين على وجوههم يباركون الله ثم نهضوا وحدثوا بجميع عجائبه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Kemudian mereka memuji Allah dan bernyanyi-nyanyi kepada-Nya serta memuliakan-Nya karena segala perbuatan-Nya yang besar itu. Sebab malaikat Allah telah menampakkan diri kepada mereka.</language></verse>
    </chapter>

    <!-- CHAPTER 13 (18 verses) -->
    <chapter num="13">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Then Tobit wrote a prayer of rejoicing, and said, Blessed be God that liveth for ever, and blessed be his kingdom.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">حينئذ فتح طوبيا الشيخ فاه مباركا للرب وقال عظيم انت يارب الى الابد وفي جميع الدهور ملكك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Tobit mengarang doa ini untuk menyatakan sukacitanya:</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">For he doth scourge, and hath mercy: he leadeth down to hell, and bringeth up again: neither is there any that can avoid his hand.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">لانك تجرح وتشفي وتحدر الى الجحيم وتصعد منه وليس من يفر من يدك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">"Terpujilah Allah yang hidup selama-lamanya, dan kerajaan-Nyapun tetap untuk sekalian abad. Memang Ia menyiksa tapi juga mengasihani, Ia menurunkan ke dunia orang mati, tetapi menaikkan daripadanya juga; tiada seorangpun luput dari tangan-Nya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">Confess him before the Gentiles, ye children of Israel: for he hath scattered us among them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">اعترفوا للرب يا بني اسرائيل وسبحوه امام جميع الامم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Muliakanlah Dia, hai orang Israel, di hadapan sekalian bangsa, sebab kita telah dicerai-beraikan-Nya di antara mereka.</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">There declare his greatness, and extol him before all the living: for he is our Lord, and he is the God our Father for ever.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فانه فرقكم بين الامم الذين يجهلونه لكي تخبروا بمعجزاته وتعرفوهم ان لا اله قادرا على كل شيء سواه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Wartakanlah kebesaran-Nya di sana, agungkanlah Dia di hadapan segala yang hidup. Sebab Dialah Tuhan kita dan Allah, Ia adalah Bapa kita untuk selama-lamanya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">And he will scourge us for our iniquities, and will have mercy again, and will gather us out of all nations, among whom he hath scattered us.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">هو ادبنا لاجل اثامنا وهو يخلصنا لاجل رحمته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Oleh karena kejahatan kita maka kita disiksa-Nya, tetapi kita dikasihani-Nya lagi dan dikumpulkan-Nya dari antara sekalian bangsa, di mana kamu terserak-serak.</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">If ye turn to him with your whole heart, and with your whole mind, and deal uprightly before him, then will he turn unto you, and will not hide his face from you. Therefore see what he will do with you, and confess him with your whole mouth, and praise the Lord of might, and extol the everlasting King. In the land of my captivity do I praise him, and declare his might and majesty to a sinful nation. O ye sinners, turn and do justice before him: who can tell if he will accept you, and have mercy on you?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">انظروا الان ما صنع لنا واعترفوا له بخوف ورعدة ومجدوا ملك الدهور باعمالكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Jika dengan segenap hati kamu berbalik kepada-Nya, dan dengan segenap jiwa berlaku benar di hadapan-Nya, niscaya Iapun berbalik kepada kamu, dan tidak disembunyikan-Nya wajah-Nya terhadap kamu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">I will extol my God, and my soul shall praise the King of heaven, and shall rejoice in his greatness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">اما انا ففي ارض جلائي اعترف له لانه اظهر جلاله في امة خاطئة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Maka pandanglah apa yang akan dikerjakan-Nya bagi kamu, muliakanlah Dia dengan segenap mulut. Pujilah Tuhan yang adil dan agungkanlah Raja kekal.</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Let all men speak, and let all praise him for his righteousness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ارجعوا الان ايها الخطاة واصنعوا امام الله برا واثقين بانه يصنع لكم رحمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Aku memuliakan Dia di tanah pembuanganku, dan kunyatakan kekuasaan serta kebesaran-Nya kepada kaum berdosa. Bertobatlah, hai orang-orang yang berdosa, dan lakukanlah apa yang benar di hadapan-Nya. Siapa tahu kalau-kalau Ia berkenan kepadamu dan menjalankan belas kasihan kepada kamu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">O Jerusalem, the holy city, he will scourge thee for thy children's works, and will have mercy again on the sons of the righteous.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">اما انا فنفسي تتهلل به</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Aku hendak mengagungkan Allahku dan Raja sorgawi dan hatiku hendak bersorak karena kebesaran-Nya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">Give praise to the Lord, for he is good: and praise the everlasting King, that his tabernacle may be builded in thee again with joy, and let him make joyful there in thee those that are captives, and love in thee for ever those that are miserable.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">باركوا الرب يا جميع مختاريه اقيموا ايام فرح واعترفوا له</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Dan hendaklah sekalian orang di Yerusalem menyebut serta memuliakan-Nya. Ya Yerusalem, kota yang suci, karena perbuatan anak-anakmu maka Allah menyiksa, tetapi kembali Ia mengasihani anak-anak orang benar.</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Many nations shall come from far to the name of the Lord God with gifts in their hands, even gifts to the King of heaven; all generations shall praise thee with great joy.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">يا اورشليم مدينة الله ان الرب ادبك باعمال يديك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Muliakanlah Tuhan selayaknya dan pujilah Raja kekal, supaya bagimu Kemah-Nya dibangun kembali dengan gembira.</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">Cursed are all they which hate thee, and blessed shall all be which love thee for ever.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">اشكري لله نعمته عليك وباركي اله الدهور حتى يعود فيشيد مسكنه فيك ويرد اليك جميع اهل الجلاء وتبتهجي الى دهر الدهور</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Maka Allah menggembirakan kaum buangan di dalam dirimu, dan yang payah di dalam dirimu akan dikasihi-Nya turun-temurun sepanjang sekalian abad.</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">Rejoice and be glad for the children of the just: for they shall be gathered together, and shall bless the Lord of the just.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">تتلالئين بسنى بهيج وجميع شعوب الارض لك يسجدون</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Dari jauh banyak bangsa akan datang ke hadapan nama Tuhan Allah dengan membawa persembahan di tangan, yaitu upeti untuk Raja sorgawi; turun-temurun sorak-sorainya dilambungkan kepadamu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">O blessed are they which love thee, for they shall rejoice in thy peace: blessed are they which have been sorrowful for all thy scourges; for they shall rejoice for thee, when they have seen all thy glory, and shall be glad for ever.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">يزورك الامم من الاقاصي بقرابينهم ويسجدون فيك للرب ويعتدون ارضك ارضا مقدسة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Para pembencimu terkutuklah hendaknya, tetapi mereka yang mengasihi engkau akan diberkati selama-lamanya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">Let my soul bless God the great King.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">لانهم فيك يدعون الاسم العظيم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Bersukacitalah dan bersorak-sorailah karena anak-anak orang yang benar, sebab mereka akan dikumpulkan dan akan memuji Tuhan orang benar. Berbahagialah orang-orang yang mengasihi engkau, mereka yang bersukacita karena damai sejahteramu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">For Jerusalem shall be built up with sapphires and emeralds, and precious stone: thy walls and towers and battlements with pure gold.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">ملعونين يكونون الذين استهانوا بك والذين جدفوا عليك يدانون ويباركك الذين يبنونك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Berbahagialah orang yang berdukacita karena siksaanmu, sebab mereka nanti bergembira karena engkau apabila mereka mengagumi segenap kemuliaanmu; maka bersukacitalah mereka selama-lamanya. Hai jiwaku, pujilah Allah, Raja agung.</language></verse>
        <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">And the streets of Jerusalem shall be paved with beryl and carbuncle and stones of Ophir.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">اما انت فتفرحين ببنيك لانهم يباركون كافة والى الرب يحتشدون</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Sebab Yerusalem akan dibangun dengan nilakandi dan zamrud, tembok-temboknya dengan permata, menara-menaranya serta benteng-bentengnya dari mas murni; lapangan-lapangan Yerusalem akan diturap dengan arzak, manikam kumala dan permata dari Ofir.</language></verse>
        <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">And all her streets shall say, Alleluia; and they shall praise him, saying, Blessed be God, which hath extolled it for ever.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">طوبى للذين يحبونك ويفرحون لك بالسلام</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Maka semua jalannya akan berseru: Haleluya. Bernyanyilah mereka semua dengan berkata: Terpujilah Allah yang meninggikan engkau untuk selama-lamanya."</language></verse>
    </chapter>

    <chapter num="14">
        <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">So Tobit made an end of praising God.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">و فرغ طوبيا من كلامه وعاش طوبيا بعدما عاد بصيرا اثنتين واربعين سنة وراى بني حفدته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Demikian Tobit mengakhiri lagu pujiannya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">And he was eight and fifty years old when he lost his sight, which was restored to him after eight years: and he gave alms, and he increased in the fear of the Lord God, and praised him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فتمت سنوه مئة واثنتين ودفن بكرامة في نينوى</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Adapun Tobit meninggal dengan tenteram waktu berumur seratus dua belas tahun. Ia dikuburkan di Niniwe sebagaimana mestinya. Waktu matanya menjadi rusak ia berumur enam puluh dua tahun dan setelah dapat melihat kembali ia hidup dengan sejahtera dan melakukan kebajikan. Iapun terus memuji Allah dan memuliakan kebesaran-Nya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">And when he was very aged he called his son, and the sons of his son, and said to him, My son, take thy children; for, behold, I am aged, and am ready to depart out of this life.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و كان حين ذهب بصره ابن ست وخمسين سنة وعاد يبصر وهو ابن ستين سنة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Ketika tiba ajalnya dipanggilnya anaknya Tobia dan disuruhnya: "Nak, ambillah semua anakmu</language></verse>
        <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">Go into Media my son, for I surely believe those things which Jonas the prophet spake of Nineve, that it shall be overthrown; and that for a time peace shall rather be in Media; and that our brethren shall lie scattered in the earth from that good land: and Jerusalem shall be desolate, and the house of God in it shall be burned, and shall be desolate for a time;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و قضى بقية حياته مسرورا واذ بلغ من تقوى الله غاية حسنة انتقل بسلام</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">dan pergilah ke negeri Media. Sebab aku yakin akan firman Allah mengenai kota Niniwe, sebagaimana yang telah diucapkan nabi Nahum. Semua akan terjadi, semua akan mendatangi bangsa Asyur dan kota Niniwe. Segala sesuatunya yang telah diucapkan oleh para nabi Israel yang diutus oleh Allah akan terjadi semua. Tiada sedikitpun dari ucapan itu yang tidak akan sampai; semua akan terjadi pada waktunya. Tetapi di negeri Media orang akan lebih aman daripada di negeri Asyur dan Babel. Aku tahu dan yakin benar bahwa semua yang telah difirmankan Allah akan terlaksana dan terjadi juga. Tiada satupun dari firman-Nya yang akan gagal. Adapun saudara-saudara kita yang masih tinggal di tanah Israel akan dicerai-beraikan dan diangkut tertawan dari tanah yang baik itu. Seluruh tanah Israel serta Samaria dan Yerusalem akan menjadi gurun belaka dan Bait Allah akan tinggal roboh dan hangus hingga waktu tertentu.</language></verse>
        <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">And that again God will have mercy on them, and bring them again into the land, where they shall build a temple, but not like to the first, until the time of that age be fulfilled; and afterward they shall return from all places of their captivity, and build up Jerusalem gloriously, and the house of God shall be built in it for ever with a glorious building, as the prophets have spoken thereof.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">و لما حضرته الوفاة دعا ابنه طوبيا وبني ابنه السبعة الفتيان وقال لهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Kemudian mereka akan dikasihani oleh Allah dan dikembalikan ke tanah Israel. Maka Bait Allah akan mereka bangun, meskipun tidak seperti yang dahulu, hingga tiba saatnya zaman dunia mencapai kegenapannya. Lalu mereka semua akan pulang dari pembuangannya dan Yerusalem akan dibangunkannya dengan mulianya. Bait Allahpun akan dibangun di dalamnya, sebagaimana yang telah dikatakan para nabi tentangnya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">And all nations shall turn, and fear the Lord God truly, and shall bury their idols.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">قد دنا دمار نينوى لان كلام الرب لا يذهب باطلا واخوتنا الذين تفرقوا من ارض اسرائيل يرجعون اليها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Semua bangsa di seluruh bumi akan bertobat dan benar-benar menakuti Tuhan Allah. Semua akan meninggalkan berhala mereka yang membuat mereka kembara dalam kesesatan. Dengan tulus hati mereka akan memuji Allah yang kekal.</language></verse>
        <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">So shall all nations praise the Lord, and his people shall confess God, and the Lord shall exalt his people; and all those which love the Lord God in truth and justice shall rejoice, shewing mercy to our brethren.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">و كل ارضها المقفرة ستمتلئ وبيت الله الذي احرق فيها سيستانف بناؤه وسيرجع الى هناك جميع خائفي الله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Semua orang Israel yang selamat pada masa itu dan yang ingat kepada Allah dengan tulus ikhlas akan berkumpul dan datang ke Yerusalem. Merekapun lalu akan mendiami tanah Abraham untuk selama-lamanya dan dengan aman sentosa. Negeri itu akan dianugerahkan kepada mereka. Allah akan mereka kasihi dengan tulus ikhlas dan mereka bergembira. Tetapi mereka yang berbuat dosa dan lalim akan lenyap dari muka bumi.</language></verse>
        <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">And now, my son, depart out of Nineve, because that those things which the prophet Jonas spake shall surely come to pass.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">و ستترك الامم اصنامها وترحل الى اورشليم فتقيم بها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">And now, my son, depart out of Nineve, because that those things which the prophet Jonas spake shall surely come to pass.</language></verse>
        <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">But keep thou the law and the commandments, and shew thyself merciful and just, that it may go well with thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">و تفرح فيها ملوك الارض كافة ساجدة لملك اسرائيل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">But keep thou the law and the commandments, and shew thyself merciful and just, that it may go well with thee.</language></verse>
        <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">And bury me decently, and thy mother with me; but tarry no longer at Nineve. Remember, my son, how Aman handled Achiacharus that brought him up, how out of light he brought him into darkness, and how he rewarded him again: yet Achiacharus was saved, but the other had his reward: for he went down into darkness. Manasses gave alms, and escaped the snares of death which they had set for him: but Aman fell into the snare, and perished.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">اسمعوا يا بني لابيكم اعبدوا الرب بحق وابتغوا عمل مرضاته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Nak, ingatlah kepada apa yang telah diperbuat Nadab kepada bapa pengasuhnya, yaitu Ahikar. Bukankah Ahikar hidup-hidup diturunkan ke bagian bawah bumi? Tetapi Allah telah membalas kelaliman Nadab ke atas kepalanya sendiri. Ahikar keluar menuju cahaya, sedangkan Nadab turun ke kegelapan kekal, oleh karena ia telah berusaha membunuh Ahikar. Karena melakukan kebajikan maka Ahikar luput dari jerat maut yang dipasang baginya oleh Nadab. Sedangkan Nadab jatuh ke dalam jerat maut yang juga membinasakannya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Wherefore now, my son, consider what alms doeth, and how righteousness doth deliver. When he had said these things, he gave up the ghost in the bed, being an hundred and eight and fifty years old; and he buried him honourably.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">و اوصوا بنيكم بعمل العدل والصدقات وان يذكروا الله ويباركوه كل حين بالحق وبكل طاقاتهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Makanya, anak-anakku, camkanlah apa yang dihasilkan oleh sedekah dan apa yang dihasilkan oleh kelaliman. Memang kelaliman membunuh. Tetapi aku kehabisan tenaga!" Maka Tobit berbaring di tempat tidurnya lalu meninggal. Ia dikuburkan dengan layak.</language></verse>
        <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">And when Anna his mother was dead, he buried her with his father. But Tobias departed with his wife and children to Ecbatane to Raguel his father in law,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">اسمعوا لي يا بني لا تقيموا ههنا بل اي يوم دفنتم والدتكم معي في قبر واحد ففي ذلك اليوم وجهوا خطواتكم للخروج من هذا الموضع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Setelah ibu Tobia meninggal maka dikuburkannya di samping ayahnya. Kemudian Tobia serta isterinya pergi ke negeri Media dan menetap di kota Ekbatana pada Raguel, mertuanya.</language></verse>
        <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">Where he became old with honour, and he buried his father and mother in law honourably, and he inherited their substance, and his father Tobit's.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فاني ارى ان اثمه سيهلكه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Masa tua Raguel serta isterinya dipelihara oleh Tobia sebagaimana mestinya lalu dikuburkannya mereka di kota Ekbatana di negeri Media. Tobiapun mewarisi baik harta milik Raguel maupun harta milik ayahnya sendiri.</language></verse>
        <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">And he died at Ecbatane in Media, being an hundred and seven and twenty years old.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فكان ان طوبيا بعد موت امه ارتحل عن نينوى بزوجته وبنيه وبني بنيه ورجع الى حمويه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Tobia sendiri meninggal sebagai orang terhormat dalam umur seratus tujuh belas tahun di kota Ekbatana di negeri Media.</language></verse>
        <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">But before he died he heard of the destruction of Nineve, which was taken by Nabuchodonosor and Assuerus: and before his death he rejoiced over Nineve.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فوجدهما سالمين بشيخوخة صالحة فاهتم بهما وهو اغمض اعينهما واحرز كل ميراث بيت رعوئيل وراى بني بنيه الى الجيل الخامس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Tetapi sebelum meninggal masih didengarnya tentang kebinasaan kota Niniwe dan melihat penduduknya ditawan dan dibuang ke negeri Media, yakni orang-orang yang diangkut tertawan oleh Siaksares, raja Media. Maka Tobia memuji Allah karena segala sesuatunya yang telah dilakukan-Nya kepada orang Niniwe dan Asyur. Sebelum meninggal Tobia masih bergembira oleh karena nasib kota Niniwe dan memuji Tuhan Allah untuk selama-lamanya.</language></verse>
    </chapter>
</book>