<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><book book="Tobit">
   <chapter num="1">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            Tobit was from the tribe and city of Naphtali (which is in the upper parts of Galilee above Asher, after the way, which leads to the west, that has on its left the city of Sephet).
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Tobit was from the tribe and city of Naphtali (which is in the upper parts of Galilee above Asher, after the way, which leads to the west, that has on its left the city of Sephet).
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            كَانَ طُوبِيَّا وَهُوَ مِنْ سِبْطِ وَمَدِينَةِ نَفْتَالِي الَّتِي فِي الْجَلِيلِ الأَعْلَى فَوْقَ نَحْشُونَ وَرَاءَ الطَّرِيقِ الآخِذِ غَرْباً وَإِلَى يَسَارِهَا مَدِينَةُ صَفَتَ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            Although he had been taken captive in the days of Shalmaneser, the king of the Assyrians, even in such a situation as captivity, he did not desert the way of truth.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Although he had been taken captive in the days of Shalmaneser, the king of the Assyrians, even in such a situation as captivity, he did not desert the way of truth.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            قَدْ جُلِيَ فِي عَهْدِ شَلْمَنْأَسَرَ مَلِكِ أَشُّورَ إِلاَّ أَنَّهُ مَعَ كَوْنِهِ فِي الْجَلاَءِ لَمْ يُفَارِقْ سَبِيلَ الْحَقِّ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            So then, every day, all that he was able to obtain, he bestowed on his fellow captive brothers, who were from his kindred.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            So then, every day, all that he was able to obtain, he bestowed on his fellow captive brothers, who were from his kindred.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            حَتَّى كَانَ كُلُّ مَا يَتَيَسَّرُ لَهُ يَقْسِمُهُ كُلَّ يَوْمٍ عَلَى مَنْ جُلِيَ مَعَهُ مِنْ إِخْوَانِهِ الَّذِينَ مِنْ جِنْسِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            And, when he was among the youngest of any in the tribe of Naphtali, he showed not so much as any childish behavior in his work.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And, when he was among the youngest of any in the tribe of Naphtali, he showed not so much as any childish behavior in his work.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَمَعَ أَنَّهُ كَانَ أَحْدَثَ الْجَمِيعِ فِي سِبْطِ نَفْتَالِيَ لَمْ يَكُنْ عَلَى شَيْءٍ مِنْ شُؤُونِ الأَحْدَاثِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            And then, when all went to the golden calves which Jeroboam, king of Israel, had made, he alone fled from the company of them all.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And then, when all went to the golden calves which Jeroboam, king of Israel, had made, he alone fled from the company of them all.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَانَ إِذَا قَصَدُوا كُلُّهُمْ عُجُولَ الذَّهَبِ الَّتِي عَمِلَهَا يَارُبْعَامُ مَلِكُ إِسْرَائِيلَ، يَتَخَلَّفُ وَحْدَهُ عَنْ سَائِرِهِمْ
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            Yet he continued on to Jerusalem, to the temple of the Lord, and there he adored the Lord God of Israel, offering faithfully all his first-fruits and his tithes.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Yet he continued on to Jerusalem, to the temple of the Lord, and there he adored the Lord God of Israel, offering faithfully all his first-fruits and his tithes.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَيَمْضِي إِلَى أُورُشَلِيمَ إِلَى هَيْكَلِ الرَّبِّ، وَهُنَاكَ كَانَ يَسْجُدُ لِلرَّبِّ إِلهِ إِسْرَائِيلَ، وَيُوفِي جَمِيعَ بَوَاكِيرِهِ وَأَعْشَارِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            So then, in the third year, he administered all his tithes to new converts and to new arrivals.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            So then, in the third year, he administered all his tithes to new converts and to new arrivals.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَإِذَا كَانَتِ السَّنَةُ الثَّالِثَةُ كَانَ يَجْعَلُ جَمِيعَ أَعْشَارِهِ لِلدُّخَلاَءِ وَالْغُرَبَاءِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            These and similar such things, even as a boy, he observed according to the law of God.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            These and similar such things, even as a boy, he observed according to the law of God.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَعَلَى هذَا وَأَمْثَالِهِ، كَانَ مُثَابِراً مُنْذُ صَبْوَتِهِ عَلَى وَفْقِ شَرِيعَةِ اللهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            Truly, when he had become a man, he received as wife Anna of his own tribe, and he conceived a son by her, to whom he assigned his own name.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Truly, when he had become a man, he received as wife Anna of his own tribe, and he conceived a son by her, to whom he assigned his own name.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَمَّا أَنْ صَارَ رَجُلاً، اتَّخَذَ لَهُ امْرَأَةً مِنْ سِبْطِهِ اسْمُهَا حَنَّةُ، فَوُلِدَ لَهُ مِنْهَا وَلَدٌ فَسَمَّاهُ بِاسْمِهِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            From his infancy, he taught him to fear God and to abstain from all sin.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            From his infancy, he taught him to fear God and to abstain from all sin.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَدَّبَهُ مُنْذُ صِغَرِهِ عَلَى تَقْوَى اللهِ وَاجْتِنَابِ كُلِّ خَطِيئَةٍ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            Therefore, when, during the captivity, he had arrived with his wife and son at the city of Nineveh, with all his tribe,
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Therefore, when, during the captivity, he had arrived with his wife and son at the city of Nineveh, with all his tribe,
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَمَّا جُلِيَ مَعَ امْرَأَتِهِ وَوَلَدِهِ إِلَى مَدِينَةِ نِينَوَى، حَيْثُ كَانَتْ كُلُّ عَشِيرَتِهِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            (even though they all ate from the foods of the Gentiles,) he guarded his soul and never was contaminated with their foods.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            (even though they all ate from the foods of the Gentiles,) he guarded his soul and never was contaminated with their foods.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَدْ كَانُوا كُلُّهُمْ يَأْكُلُونَ مِنْ أَطْعِمَةِ الأُمَمِ، كَانَ هُوَ يَصُونُ نَفْسَهُ وَلَمْ يَتَنَجَّسْ قَطُّ بِمَأْكُولاَتِهِمْ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            And because he was mindful of the Lord with his whole heart, God gave him favor in the sight of Shalmaneser the king.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And because he was mindful of the Lord with his whole heart, God gave him favor in the sight of Shalmaneser the king.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلأَجْلِ أَنَّهُ كَانَ يَذْكُرُ الرَّبَّ بِكُلِّ قَلْبِهِ، أَتَاهُ اللهُ حُظْوَةً لَدَى الْمَلِكِ شَلْمَنْأَسَرَ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            And he gave him the power to go wherever he would want, having the freedom to do whatever he wished.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And he gave him the power to go wherever he would want, having the freedom to do whatever he wished.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَطْلَقَ لَهُ أَنْ يَذْهَبَ حَيْثُمَا شَاءَ وَيَفْعَلَ مَا يُرِيدُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            Therefore, he continued on to all who were in captivity, and he gave them helpful advice.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Therefore, he continued on to all who were in captivity, and he gave them helpful advice.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَكَانَ يَطُوفُ عَلَى كُلِّ مَنْ كَانَ فِي الْجَلاَءِ، وَيُرْشِدُهُمْ بِنَصَائِحِ الْخَلاَصِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            But when he had arrived at Rages, a city of the Medes, he had ten talents of silver, from that which he had been given in honor by the king.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But when he had arrived at Rages, a city of the Medes, he had ten talents of silver, from that which he had been given in honor by the king.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            ثُمَّ إِنَّهُ قَدِمَ رَاجِيسَ مَدِينَةَ مَادَايَ، وَكَانَ مَعَهُ مِمَّا آثَرَهُ بِهِ الْمَلِكُ عَشَرَةُ قَنَاطِيرَ مِنَ الْفِضَّةِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            And when, in the midst of the great tumult of his kindred, he saw the destitution of Gabael, who was from his tribe, he loaned him, under a written agreement, the aforementioned weight of silver.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when, in the midst of the great tumult of his kindred, he saw the destitution of Gabael, who was from his tribe, he loaned him, under a written agreement, the aforementioned weight of silver.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَرَأَى بَيْنَ الْجُمْهُورِ الْغَفِيرِ الَّذِي مِنْ جِنْسِهِ رَجُلاً مِنْ سِبْطِهِ يُقَالُ لَهُ غَابِيلُوسُ فِي فَاقَةٍ، فَدَفَعَ إِلَيْهِ الزِّنَةَ الْمَذْكُورَةَ مِنَ الْفِضَّةِ بِصَكٍّ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="18">
         <language id="English">
            In truth, after a long time, Shalmaneser the king died, while Sennacherib his son reigned in his place, and he held a hatred for the sons of Israel.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            In truth, after a long time, Shalmaneser the king died, while Sennacherib his son reigned in his place, and he held a hatred for the sons of Israel.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَانَ بَعْدَ أَيَّامٍ كَثِيرَةٍ أَنْ مَاتَ الْمَلِكُ شَلْمَنْأَسَرُ فَمَلَكَ سَنْحَارِيبُ ابْنُهُ مَكَانَهُ، فَوَقَعَ بَنُو إِسْرَائِيلَ عِنْدَهُ مَوْقِعَ الْكَرَاهَةِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="19">
         <language id="English">
            Every day, Tobit traveled through all his own people, and he consoled them, and he distributed to each one as much as he could from his resources.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Every day, Tobit traveled through all his own people, and he consoled them, and he distributed to each one as much as he could from his resources.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَانَ طُوبِيَّا يَطُوفُ كُلَّ يَوْمٍ عَلَى جَمِيعِ عَشِيرَتِهِ وَيُعَزِّيهِمْ، وَيُؤَاسِي كُلَّ وَاحِدٍ مِنْ أَمْوَالِهِ عَلَى قَدْرِ وُسْعِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="20">
         <language id="English">
            He nourished the hungry, and he supplied clothes to the naked, and he showed concern for the burial of the dead and of the slain.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            He nourished the hungry, and he supplied clothes to the naked, and he showed concern for the burial of the dead and of the slain.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَيُطْعِمُ الْجِيَاعَ، وَيَكْسُو الْعُرَاةَ، وَيَدْفِنُ الْمَوْتَى وَالْقَتْلَى بِغَيْرَةٍ شَدِيدَةٍ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="21">
         <language id="English">
            And then, when king Sennacherib had returned from Judea, fleeing the scourge which God had caused all around him because of his blasphemy, and, being angry, he was slaughtering many from the sons of Israel, Tobit buried their bodies.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And then, when king Sennacherib had returned from Judea, fleeing the scourge which God had caused all around him because of his blasphemy, and, being angry, he was slaughtering many from the sons of Israel, Tobit buried their bodies.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَمَّا قَفَلَ الْمَلِكُ سَنْحَارِيبُ مِنْ أَرْضِ يَهُوذَا هَارِباً مِنَ الضَّرْبَةِ الَّتِي حَاقَهُ اللهُ بِهَا بِسَبَبِ تَجْدِيفِهِ، وَطَفِقَ لِحَنَقِهِ يَقْتُلُ كَثِيرِينَ مِنْ بَنِي إِسْرَائِيلَ؛ كَانَ طُوبِيَّا يدْفِنُ أَجْسَادَهُمْ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="22">
         <language id="English">
            And when it was reported to the king, he ordered him to be slain, and he took away all his belongings.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when it was reported to the king, he ordered him to be slain, and he took away all his belongings.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَنَمَى ذلِكَ إِلَى الْمَلِكِ، فَأَمَرَ بِقَتْلِهِ وَضَبَطَ جَمِيعَ مَالِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="23">
         <language id="English">
            In truth, Tobit, fleeing with nothing but his son and his wife, was able to remain hidden because many loved him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            In truth, Tobit, fleeing with nothing but his son and his wife, was able to remain hidden because many loved him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَهَرَبَ طُوبِيَّا بِوَلَدِهِ وَزَوْجَتِهِ عَارِياً وَاخْتَبَأَ لأَنَّ كَثِيرِينَ كَانُوا يُحِبُّونَهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="24">
         <language id="English">
            In truth, after forty-five days, the king was slain by his own sons,
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            In truth, after forty-five days, the king was slain by his own sons,
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَانَ بَعْدَ خَمْسَةٍ وَأَرْبَعِينَ يَوْماً أَنْ قَتَلَ الْمَلِكَ ابْنَاهُ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="25">
         <language id="English">
            and Tobit was able to return to his house, and all his resources were restored to him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            and Tobit was able to return to his house, and all his resources were restored to him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَعَادَ طُوبِيَّا إِلَى مَنْزِلِهِ، وَرُدَّ عَلَيْهِ كُلُّ مَالِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="2">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            In truth, after this, when there was a feast day of the Lord, and a good dinner had been prepared in the house of Tobit,
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            In truth, after this, when there was a feast day of the Lord, and a good dinner had been prepared in the house of Tobit,
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَانَ بَعْدَ ذلِكَ فِي يَوْمِ عِيدِ الرَّبِّ أَنْ صُنِعَتْ مَأْدُبَةٌ عَظِيمَةٌ فِي بَيْتِ طُوبِيَّا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            he said to his son: “Go, and bring some others who fear God from our tribe to feast with us.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            he said to his son: “Go, and bring some others who fear God from our tribe to feast with us.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لاِبْنِهِ: «هَلُمَّ فَادْعُ بَعْضاً مِنْ سِبْطِنَا مِنَ الْمُتَّقِينَ للهِ لِيَأْكُلُوا مَعَنَا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            And after he had gone, returning, he reported to him that one of the sons of Israel, with his throat cut, was lying in the street. And immediately, he leapt from his place reclining at table, left behind his dinner, and went forth with fasting to the body.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And after he had gone, returning, he reported to him that one of the sons of Israel, with his throat cut, was lying in the street. And immediately, he leapt from his place reclining at table, left behind his dinner, and went forth with fasting to the body.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَانْطَلَقَ ثُمَّ عَادَ فَأَخْبَرَهُ أَنَّ وَاحِداً مِنْ بَنِي إِسْرَائِيلَ مَذْبُوحٌ مُلْقًى فِي السُّوقِ. فَلَمَّا سَمِعَ طُوبِيَّا، نَهَضَ مِنْ مَوْضِعِهِ مُسْرِعاً، وَتَرَكَ الْعَشَاءَ، وَبَلَغَ الْجُثَّةَ وَهُوَ صَائِمٌ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            And taking it up, he carried it in secret to his house, so that, after the sun had set, he might bury him cautiously.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And taking it up, he carried it in secret to his house, so that, after the sun had set, he might bury him cautiously.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَرَفَعَهَا وَحَمَلَهَا إِلَى بَيْتِهِ سِرًّا لِيَدْفِنَهَا بِالتَّحَفُّظِ بَعْدَ مَغِيبِ الشَّمْسِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            And after he had hidden the body, he chewed his bread with mourning and fear,
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And after he had hidden the body, he chewed his bread with mourning and fear,
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَبَعْدَ أَنْ خَبَأَ الْجُثَّةَ أَكَلَ الطَّعَامَ بَاكِياً مُرْتَعِداً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            remembering the word that the Lord spoke through the prophet Amos: “Your feast days shall be turned into lamentation and mourning.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            remembering the word that the Lord spoke through the prophet Amos: “Your feast days shall be turned into lamentation and mourning.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَذَكَرَ الْكَلاَمَ الَّذِي تَكَلَّمَ بِهِ الرَّبُّ عَلَى لِسَانِ عَامُوسَ النَّبِيِّ: «أَيَّامُ أَعْيَادِكُمْ تَتَحَوَّلُ إِلَى عَوِيلٍ وَنَحِيبٍ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            Truly, when the sun had set, he went out, and he buried him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Truly, when the sun had set, he went out, and he buried him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَمَّا غَرَبَتِ الشَّمْسُ، ذَهَبَ وَدَفَنَهَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            Yet all his neighbors argued with him, saying: “Now, an order was given to execute you because of this matter, and you barely escaped a death sentence, and again you are burying the dead?”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Yet all his neighbors argued with him, saying: “Now, an order was given to execute you because of this matter, and you barely escaped a death sentence, and again you are burying the dead?”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَانَ جَمِيعُ ذَوِي قَرَابَتِهِ يَلُومُونَهُ قَائِلِينَ: «لأَجْلِ هذَا أُمِرَ بِقَتْلِكَ، وَمَا كِدْتَ تَنْجُو مِنْ قَضَاءِ الْمَوْتِ حَتَّى عُدْتَ تَدْفِنُ الْمَوْتَى».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            But Tobit, fearing God more than the king, stole away the bodies of the slain and concealed them in his house, and in the middle of the night, he buried them.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But Tobit, fearing God more than the king, stole away the bodies of the slain and concealed them in his house, and in the middle of the night, he buried them.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَمَّا طُوبِيَّا، فَإِذْ كَانَ خَوْفُهُ مِنَ اللهِ أَعْظَمَ مِنْ خَوْفِهِ مِنَ الْمَلِكِ، كَانَ لاَ يَزَالُ يَخْطَفُ جُثَثَ الْقَتْلَى وَيَخْبَأُهَا فِي بَيْتِهِ، فَيَدْفِنُهَا عِنْدَ انْتِصَافِ اللَّيْلِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            But it happened one day, being tired from burying the dead, he came into his house, and he threw himself down next to the wall, and he slept.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But it happened one day, being tired from burying the dead, he came into his house, and he threw himself down next to the wall, and he slept.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَاتَّفَقَ فِي بَعْضِ الأَيَّامِ، وَقَدْ تَعِبَ مِنْ دَفْنِ الْمَوْتَى، أَنَّهُ وَافَى بَيْتَهُ، فَرَمَى بِنَفْسِهِ إِلَى جَانِبِ الْحَائِطِ وَنَامَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            And, as he was sleeping, warm droppings from a swallow’s nest fell upon his eyes, and he was made blind.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And, as he was sleeping, warm droppings from a swallow’s nest fell upon his eyes, and he was made blind.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَوَقَعَ ذَرْقٌ مِنْ عُشِّ خُطَّافٍ فِي عَيْنَيْهِ وَهُوَ سُخْنٌ فَعَمِيَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            And so the Lord permitted this trial to befall him, in order that an example might be given to posterity of his patience, which is even like that of holy Job.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so the Lord permitted this trial to befall him, in order that an example might be given to posterity of his patience, which is even like that of holy Job.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَإِنَّمَا أَذِنَ الرَّبُّ أَنْ تَعْرِضَ لَهُ هذِهِ التَّجْرِبَةُ لِتَكُونَ لِمَنْ بَعْدَهُ قُدْوَةَ صَبْرِهِ كَأَيُّوبَ الصِّدِّيقِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            For, even from his infancy, he had always feared God and kept his commandments, so he was not discouraged before God because of the scourge of blindness that had befallen him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For, even from his infancy, he had always feared God and kept his commandments, so he was not discouraged before God because of the scourge of blindness that had befallen him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَإِنَّهُ إِذْ كَانَ لَمْ يَنْفَكَّ عَنْ تَقْوَى اللهِ مُنْذُ صِغَرِهِ وَحَافِظاً لِوَصَايَاهُ، لَمْ يَكُنْ يَتَذَمَّرُ عَلَى اللهِ لِمَا نَالَهُ مِنْ بَلْوَى الْعَمَى،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            But he remained immoveable in the fear of God, giving thanks to God all the days of his life.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But he remained immoveable in the fear of God, giving thanks to God all the days of his life.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلكِنَّهُ ثَبَتَ فِي خَوْفِ اللهِ، شَاكِراً لَهُ طُولَ أَيَّامِ حَيَاتِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            For just as kings have mocked blessed Job, so also his relatives and acquaintances ridiculed his life, saying:
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For just as kings have mocked blessed Job, so also his relatives and acquaintances ridiculed his life, saying:
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَمَا كَانَ الْقِدِّيسُ أَيُّوبُ يُعَيِّرُهُ الْمُلُوكُ، كَانَ أَنْسِبَاءُ هذَا وَذَوُوهُ يَسْخَرُونَ مِنْ عِيشَتِهِ قَائِلِينَ:
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            “Where is your hope, on behalf of which you gave alms and buried the dead?”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            “Where is your hope, on behalf of which you gave alms and buried the dead?”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            «أَيْنَ رَجَاؤُكَ الَّذِي لأَجْلِهِ كُنْتَ تَبْذُلُ الصَّدَقَاتِ وَتَدْفِنُ الْمَوْتَى؟»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            In truth, Tobit corrected them, saying: “Do not speak in this way,
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            In truth, Tobit corrected them, saying: “Do not speak in this way,
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَيَزْجُرُهُمْ طُوبِيَّا قَائِلاً: «لاَ تَتَكَلَّمُوا كَذَا،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="18">
         <language id="English">
            for we are the sons of the holy ones, and we look forward to that life which God will give to those who never change in their faith before him.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            for we are the sons of the holy ones, and we look forward to that life which God will give to those who never change in their faith before him.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَإِنَّمَا نَحْنُ بَنُو الْقِدِّيسِينَ، وَإِنَّمَا نَنْتَظِرُ تِلْكَ الْحَيَاةَ الَّتِي يَهَبُهَا اللهُ لِلَّذِينَ لاَ يَصْرِفُونَ إِيمَانَهُمْ عَنْهُ أَبَداً».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="19">
         <language id="English">
            In truth, his wife Anna went out to weaving work daily, and she brought back the provisions that she was able to obtain by the labor of her hands.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            In truth, his wife Anna went out to weaving work daily, and she brought back the provisions that she was able to obtain by the labor of her hands.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَانَتْ حَنَّةُ امْرَأَتُهُ تَذْهَبُ كُلَّ يَوْمٍ إِلَى الْحَاكَةِ وَتَأْتِي مِنْ تَعَبِ يَدَيْهَا بِمَا يَتَأَتَّى لَهَا تَحْصِيلُهُ مِنَ الْمِيرَةِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="20">
         <language id="English">
            Whereupon it happened that, having received a young goat, she brought it home.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Whereupon it happened that, having received a young goat, she brought it home.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَاتَّفَقَ أَنَّهَا أَخَذَتْ جَدْياً وَحَمَلَتْهُ إِلَى الْبَيْتِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="21">
         <language id="English">
            When her husband heard the sound of its bleating, he said, “Look, so that it might not be stolen, return it to its owners, for it is not lawful for us either to eat, or to touch, anything stolen.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            When her husband heard the sound of its bleating, he said, “Look, so that it might not be stolen, return it to its owners, for it is not lawful for us either to eat, or to touch, anything stolen.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلَمَّا سَمِعَ بَعْلُهَا صَوْتَ ثُغَاءِ الْجَدْيَ قَالَ: «انْظُرُوا لَعَلَّهُ يَكُونُ مَسْرُوقاً فَرُدُّوهُ عَلَى أَرْبَابِهِ، إِذْ لاَ يَحِلُّ لَنَا أَنْ نَأْكُلَ وَلاَ نَلْمُسَ شَيْئاً مَسْرُوقاً».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="22">
         <language id="English">
            At this, his wife, being angry, answered, “Clearly, your hope has become vanity, and the manner of your almsgiving has become apparent.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            At this, his wife, being angry, answered, “Clearly, your hope has become vanity, and the manner of your almsgiving has become apparent.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَجَابَتْهُ امْرَأَتُهُ وَهِيَ مُغْضَبَةٌ: «قَدْ وَضَحَ بُطْلاَنُ رَجَائِكَ، وَصَدَقَاتُكَ الآنَ قَدْ عُرِفَتْ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="23">
         <language id="English">
            And with these and other similar such words, she reproached him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And with these and other similar such words, she reproached him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَبِهذَا الْكَلاَمِ وَمِثْلِهِ كَانَتْ تُعَيِّرُهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="3">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            Then Tobit sighed, and he began to pray with tears,
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Tobit sighed, and he began to pray with tears,
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            حِينَئِذٍ أَنَّ طُوبِيَّا وَطَفِقَ يُصَلِّي بِدُمُوعٍ
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            saying, “O Lord, you are just and all your judgments are just, and all your ways are mercy, and truth, and judgment.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            saying, “O Lord, you are just and all your judgments are just, and all your ways are mercy, and truth, and judgment.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَالَ: «عَادِلٌ أَنْتَ أَيُّهَا الرَّبُّ وَجَمِيعُ أَحْكَامِكَ مُسْتَقِيمَةٌ وَطُرْقُكَ كُلُّهَا رَحْمَةٌ وَحَقٌّ وَحُكْمٌ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            And now, O Lord, remember me, and do not take vengeance for my sins, and do not call to mind my offenses, nor those of my parents.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And now, O Lord, remember me, and do not take vengeance for my sins, and do not call to mind my offenses, nor those of my parents.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَالآنَ اذْكُرْنِي يَا رَبِّ، وَلاَ تَنْتَقِمْ عَنْ خَطَايَايَ، وَلاَ تَذْكُرْ ذُنُوبِي وَلاَ ذُنُوبَ آبَائِي،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            For we have not obeyed your precepts, and so we have been handed over to plundering and to captivity, and to death, and to mockery, and as a disgrace before all the nations, among which you have dispersed us.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For we have not obeyed your precepts, and so we have been handed over to plundering and to captivity, and to death, and to mockery, and as a disgrace before all the nations, among which you have dispersed us.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنَّا لَمْ نُطِعْ أَوَامِرَكَ، فَلأَجْلِ ذلِكَ أُسْلِمْنَا إِلَى النَّهْبِ وَالْجَلاَءِ وَالْمَوْتِ، وَأَصْبَحْنَا أُحْدُوثَةً وَعَاراً فِي جَمِيعِ الأُمَمِ الَّتِي بَدَّدْتَنَا بَيْنَهَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            And now, O Lord, great are your judgments. For we have not acted according to your precepts, and we have not walked sincerely before you.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And now, O Lord, great are your judgments. For we have not acted according to your precepts, and we have not walked sincerely before you.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَالآنَ يَا رَبِّ، عَظِيمَةٌ أَحْكَامُكَ، لأَنَّا لَمْ نَعْمَلْ بِحَسَبِ وَصَايَاكَ، وَلاَ سَلَكْنَا بِخُلُوصٍ أَمَامَكَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            And now, O Lord, do with me according to your will, and order my spirit to be received in peace. For it is more expedient for me to die, than to live.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And now, O Lord, do with me according to your will, and order my spirit to be received in peace. For it is more expedient for me to die, than to live.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَالآنَ يَا رَبِّ، بِحَسَبِ مَشِيئَتِكَ اصْنَعْ بِي وَمُرْ أَنْ تُقْبَضَ رُوحِي بِسَلاَمٍ لأَنَّ الْمَوْتَ لِي خَيْرٌ مِنَ الْحَيَاةِ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            And so, on the same day, it happened that Sarah, the daughter of Raguel, in Rages, a city of the Medes, also heard a reproach from one of her father’s servant maids.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, on the same day, it happened that Sarah, the daughter of Raguel, in Rages, a city of the Medes, also heard a reproach from one of her father’s servant maids.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَاتَّفَقَ فِي ذلِكَ الْيَوْمِ عَيْنِهِ أَنَّ سَارَةَ بْنَةَ رَعُوئِيلَ فِي رَاجِيسَ مَدِينَةِ الْمَادِيِّينَ سَمِعَتْ هِيَ أَيْضاً تَعْيِيراً مِنْ إِحْدَى جَوَارِي أَبِيهَا،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            For she had been given to seven husbands, and a demon named Asmodeus had killed them, as soon as they had approached her.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For she had been given to seven husbands, and a demon named Asmodeus had killed them, as soon as they had approached her.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنَّهُ كَانَ قَدْ عُقَدِ لَهَا عَلَى سَبْعَةِ رِجَالٍ، وَكَانَ شَيْطَانٌ اسْمُهُ أَزْمُودَاوُسُ يَقْتُلُهُمْ عَلَى أَثَرِ دُخُولِهِمْ عَلَيْهَا فِي الْحَالِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            Therefore, when she corrected the maid for her fault, she answered her, saying, “May we never see son or daughter from you upon the earth, you murderess of your husbands.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Therefore, when she corrected the maid for her fault, she answered her, saying, “May we never see son or daughter from you upon the earth, you murderess of your husbands.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَإِذْ كَانَتْ تَنْتَهِرُ الْجَارِيَةَ لِذَنْبٍ أَجَابَتْهَا قَائِلَةً: «لاَ رَأَيْنَا لَكِ ابْنَا وَلاَ ابْنَةً عَلَى الأَرْضِ، يَا قَاتِلَةَ أَزْوَاجِهَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            Would you also kill me, just as you have already killed seven husbands?” At these words, she proceeded to an upper room of her house. And for three days and three nights, she did not eat or drink.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Would you also kill me, just as you have already killed seven husbands?” At these words, she proceeded to an upper room of her house. And for three days and three nights, she did not eat or drink.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَتُرِيدِينَ أَنْ تَقْتُلِينِي كَمَا قَتَلْتِ سَبْعَةَ رِجَالٍ». فَلَمَّا سَمِعَتْ هذَا الْكَلاَمَ صَعِدَتْ إِلَى عُلِّيَّةِ بَيْتِهَا، فَأَقَامَتْ ثَلاَثَةَ أَيَّامٍ وَثَلاَثَ لَيَالٍ لاَ تَأْكُلُ وَلاَ تَشْرَبُ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            But, continuing in prayer with tears, she beseeched God, so that he would liberate her from this reproach.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But, continuing in prayer with tears, she beseeched God, so that he would liberate her from this reproach.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            بَلِ اسْتَمَرَّتْ تُصَلِّي وَتَتَضَرَّعُ إِلَى اللهِ بِدُمُوعٍ أَنْ يَكْشِفَ عَنْهَا هذَا الْعَارَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            And it happened on the third day, while she was completing her prayer, blessing the Lord,
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And it happened on the third day, while she was completing her prayer, blessing the Lord,
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَمَّا أَتَمَّتْ صَلاَتَهَا فِي الْيَوْمِ الثَّالِثِ وَبَارَكَتِ الرَّبَّ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            that she said: “Blessed is your name, O God of our fathers, who, though you had been angry, will show mercy. And in time of tribulation, you dismiss the sins of those who call upon you.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            that she said: “Blessed is your name, O God of our fathers, who, though you had been angry, will show mercy. And in time of tribulation, you dismiss the sins of those who call upon you.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            قَالَت: «تَبَارَكَ اسْمُكَ يَا إِلهَ آبَائِنَا الَّذِي بَعْدَ غَضَبِهِ يَصْنَعُ الرَّحْمَةَ، وَفِي زَمَانِ الْبُؤْسِ يَغْفِرُ الْخَطَايَا لِلَّذِينَ يَدْعُونَهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            To you, O Lord, I turn my face; to you, I direct my eyes.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            To you, O Lord, I turn my face; to you, I direct my eyes.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            إِلَيْكَ يَا رَبِّ أُقْبِلُ بِوَجْهِي، وَإِلَيْكَ أَصْرِفُ نَاظِرَيَّ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            I beg you, O Lord, that you may absolve me from the chains of this reproach, or at least take me away from the earth.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            I beg you, O Lord, that you may absolve me from the chains of this reproach, or at least take me away from the earth.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَتَوَسَّلُ إِلَيْكَ يَا رَبِّ أَنْ تَحُلَّنِي مِنْ وِثَاقِ هذَا الْعَارِ أَوْ تَأْخُذَنِي عَنِ الأَرْضِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            You know, O Lord, that I have never coveted a husband, and I have preserved my soul clean from all impure desire.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            You know, O Lord, that I have never coveted a husband, and I have preserved my soul clean from all impure desire.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَنَّك يَا رَبِّ عَالِمٌ بَأَنِي لَمْ أَشْتَهِ رَجُلاً قَطُّ، وَأَنِّي قَدْ صُنْتُ نَفْسِي مُنَزَّهَةً عَنْ كُلِّ شَهْوَةٍ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            I have never mingled myself with those who play. And I have not presented myself as a participant with those who walk with levity.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            I have never mingled myself with those who play. And I have not presented myself as a participant with those who walk with levity.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَمْ أَكُنْ قَطُّ أُمَازِجُ أَرْبَابَ الْمَلاَهِي، وَلاَ أُعَاشِرُ السَّالِكِينَ بِالطَّيْشِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="18">
         <language id="English">
            But I consented to accept a husband, in your fear, not in my lust.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But I consented to accept a husband, in your fear, not in my lust.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَإِنَّمَا رَضِيتُ بِأَنْ أَتَّخِذَ رَجُلاً لِخَوْفِكَ لاَ لِشَهْوَتِي.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="19">
         <language id="English">
            And, either I was unworthy of them, or they perhaps were not worthy of me. For perhaps you have preserved me for another husband.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And, either I was unworthy of them, or they perhaps were not worthy of me. For perhaps you have preserved me for another husband.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَعَلِّي لَمْ أَكُنْ مُسْتَأْهِلَةً لَهُمْ أَوْ لَمْ يَكُونُوا مُسْتَحِقِّينَ لِي، فَلَعَلَّكَ أَبْقَيْتَنِي لِبَعْلٍ آخَرَ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="20">
         <language id="English">
            For your counsel is not within the ability of man.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For your counsel is not within the ability of man.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنَّ مَشُورَتَكَ لاَ يُدْرِكُهَا إِنْسَانٌ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="21">
         <language id="English">
            But all who worship you are certain of this: that one’s life, if it should be tested, shall be crowned, and if it should be in tribulation, shall be delivered, and if it should be corrected, shall be permitted to approach your mercy.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But all who worship you are certain of this: that one’s life, if it should be tested, shall be crowned, and if it should be in tribulation, shall be delivered, and if it should be corrected, shall be permitted to approach your mercy.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            عَلَى أَنَّ مَنْ يَعْبُدُكَ يُوقِنُ أَنَّ حَيَاتَهُ إِنِ انْقَضَتْ بِالْمِحَنِ فَسَتَفُوزُ بِإِكْلِيلِهَا، وَإِنْ حَلَّتْ بِهِ شِدَّةٌ فَسَيُنْقَذُ، وَإِنْ عُرِضَ عَلَى التَّأْدِيبِ فَلَهُ أَنْ يَرْجِعَ إِلَى رحمتك
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="22">
         <language id="English">
            For you are not delighted with our perdition. For, after a storm, you create tranquility, and after tears and weeping, you pour out exultation.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For you are not delighted with our perdition. For, after a storm, you create tranquility, and after tears and weeping, you pour out exultation.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنَّكَ لاَ تُسَرُّ بِهَلاَكِنَا، فَتُلْقِي السَّكِينَةَ بَعْدَ الْعَاصِفَةِ، وَبَعْدَ الْبُكَاءِ وَالنَّحِيبِ تُفِيضُ التَّهَلُّلَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="23">
         <language id="English">
            May your name, O God of Israel, be blessed forever.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            May your name, O God of Israel, be blessed forever.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلْيَكُنِ اسْمُكَ يَا إِلهَ إِسْرَائِيلَ مُبَارَكاً مَدَى الدُّهُورِ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="24">
         <language id="English">
            At that time, the prayers of them both were heard in the sight of the glory of the most high God.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            At that time, the prayers of them both were heard in the sight of the glory of the most high God.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فِي ذلِكَ الْحِينِ اسْتُجِيبَتْ صَلَوَاتُ الاِثْنَيْنِ أَمَامَ مَجْدِ اللهِ الْعَلِيِّ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="25">
         <language id="English">
            And the holy Angel of the Lord, Raphael, was sent to care for both of them, whose prayers were recited at the same time in the sight of the Lord.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the holy Angel of the Lord, Raphael, was sent to care for both of them, whose prayers were recited at the same time in the sight of the Lord.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَرْسَلَ الرَّبُّ مَلاَكَهُ الْقِدِّيسَ رَافَائِيلَ لِيَشْفِيَ كِلاَ الاِثْنَيْنِ اللَّذَيْنَ رُفِعَتْ صَلَوَاتُهُمَا فِي وَقْتٍ وَاحِدٍ إِلَى حَضْرَةِ الرَّبِّ.
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="4">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            Therefore, when Tobit considered that his prayer was heard, so that he might be able to die, he called his son Tobias to him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Therefore, when Tobit considered that his prayer was heard, so that he might be able to die, he called his son Tobias to him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَإِذْ خَالَ طُوبِيَّا أَنْ قَدِ اسْتُجِيبَتْ صَلاَتُهُ، وَتَهَيَّأَ لَهُ أَنْ يَمُوتَ، اسْتَدْعَى إِلَيْهِ طُوبِيَّا ابْنَهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            And he said to him: “My son, hear the words of my mouth, and set them, like a foundation, in your heart.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And he said to him: “My son, hear the words of my mouth, and set them, like a foundation, in your heart.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَالَ لَهُ: «اسْمَعْ يَا بُنَيَّ كَلِمَاتِ فِيَّ، وَاجْعَلْهَا فِي قَلْبِكَ مِثْلَ الأَسَاسِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            When God will receive my soul, bury my body. And you shall honor your mother, all the days of her life.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            When God will receive my soul, bury my body. And you shall honor your mother, all the days of her life.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            إِذَا قَبَضَ اللهُ نَفْسِي، فَادْفِنْ جَسَدِي، وَأَكْرِمْ وَالِدَتَكَ جَمِيعَ أَيَّامِ حَيَاتِهَا،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            For you are obliged to be mindful of what great perils she suffered because of you in her womb.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For you are obliged to be mindful of what great perils she suffered because of you in her womb.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَاذْكُرْ مَا الْمَشَقَّاتُ الَّتِي عَانَتْهَا لأَجْلِكَ فِي جَوْفِهَا وَمَا كَانَ أَشَدَّهَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            But when she too will have completed the time of her life, bury her near me.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But when she too will have completed the time of her life, bury her near me.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَمَتَى اسْتَوْفَتْ هِيَ أَيْضاً زَمَانَ حَيَاتِهَا، فَادْفِنْهَا إِلَى جَانِبِي.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            Yet, for all the days of your life, have God in your mind. And be careful that you never consent to sin, nor overlook the precepts of the Lord our God.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Yet, for all the days of your life, have God in your mind. And be careful that you never consent to sin, nor overlook the precepts of the Lord our God.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَنْتَ فَلْيَكُنِ اللهُ فِي قَلْبِكَ جَمِيعَ أَيَّامِ حَيَاتِكَ، وَاحْذَرْ أَنْ تَرْضَى بِالْخَطِيئَةِ وَتَتَعَدَّى وَصَايَا الرَّبِّ إِلهِنَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            Give alms from your substance, and do not turn away your face from any pauper. For so it shall be that neither will the face of the Lord be turned away from you.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Give alms from your substance, and do not turn away your face from any pauper. For so it shall be that neither will the face of the Lord be turned away from you.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            تَصَدَّقَ مِنْ مَالِكَ وَلاَ تُحَوِّلْ وَجْهَكَ عَنْ فَقِيرٍ، وَحِينَئِذٍ فَوَجْهُ الرَّبِّ لاَ يُحَوَّلُ عَنْكَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            In whatever way that you are able, so shall you be merciful.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            In whatever way that you are able, so shall you be merciful.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            كُنْ رَحِيماً عَلَى قَدْرِ طَاقَتِكَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            If you have much, distribute abundantly. If you have little, nevertheless strive to bestow a little freely.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            If you have much, distribute abundantly. If you have little, nevertheless strive to bestow a little freely.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            إِنْ كَانَ لَكَ كَثِيرٌ، فَابْذُلْ كَثِيراً؛ وَإِنْ كَانَ لَكَ قَلِيلٌ، فَاجْتَهِدْ أَنْ تَبْذُلَ الْقَلِيلَ عَنْ نَفْسٍ طَيِّبَةٍ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            For you store up for yourself a good reward for the day of necessity.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For you store up for yourself a good reward for the day of necessity.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَإِنَّكَ تَدَّخِرُ لَكَ ثَوَاباً جَمِيلاً إِلَى يَوْمِ الضَّرُورَةِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            For almsgiving liberates from every sin and from death, and it will not suffer the soul to go into darkness.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For almsgiving liberates from every sin and from death, and it will not suffer the soul to go into darkness.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنَّ الصَّدَقَةَ تُنَجِّي مِنْ كُلِّ خَطِيئَةٍ وَمِنَ الْمَوْتِ، وَلاَ تَدَعُ النَّفْسَ تَصِيرُ إِلَى الظُّلْمَةِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            Almsgiving will be a great act of faith before the most high God, for all those who practice it.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Almsgiving will be a great act of faith before the most high God, for all those who practice it.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            إِنَّ الصَّدَقَةَ هِيَ رَجَاءٌ عَظِيمٌ عِنْدَ اللهِ الْعَلِيِّ لِجَمِيعِ صَانِعِيهَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            Take care to keep yourself, my son, from all fornication, and, except for your wife, never permit yourself to know such an offense.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Take care to keep yourself, my son, from all fornication, and, except for your wife, never permit yourself to know such an offense.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            اِحْذَرْ لِنَفْسِكَ يَا بُنَيَّ مِنْ كُلِّ زِنًى، وَلاَ تَتَجَاوَزِ امْرَأَتَكَ مُسْتَبِيحاً مَعْرِفَةَ الإِثْمِ أَبَداً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            Never permit arrogance to rule in your mind or in your words. For in it, all perdition had its beginning.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Never permit arrogance to rule in your mind or in your words. For in it, all perdition had its beginning.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلاَ تَدَعِ الْكِبْرَ يَسْتَوْلِي عَلَى أَفْكَارِكَ أَوْ أَقْوَالِكَ، لأَنَّ الْكِبْرَ مَبْدَأُ كُلِّ هلاك
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            And whoever has done any kind of work for you, immediately pay him his wages, and do not let the wages of your hired hand remain with you at all.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And whoever has done any kind of work for you, immediately pay him his wages, and do not let the wages of your hired hand remain with you at all.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكُلُّ مَنْ خَدَمَكَ بِشَيْءٍ فَأَوْفِهِ أُجْرَتَهُ لِسَاعَتِهِ، وَأُجْرَةُ أَجِيرِكَ لاَ تَبْقَ عِنْدَكَ أَبَداً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            Whatever you would hate to have done to you by another, see that you never do so to another.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Whatever you would hate to have done to you by another, see that you never do so to another.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            كُلُّ مَا تَكْرَهُ أَنْ يَفْعَلَهُ غَيْرُكَ بِكَ فَإِيَّاكَ أَنْ تَفْعَلَهُ أَنْتَ بِغَيْرِكَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            Eat your bread with the hungry and the needy, and cover the naked with your own garments.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Eat your bread with the hungry and the needy, and cover the naked with your own garments.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            كُلْ خُبْزَكَ مَعَ الْجِيَاعِ وَالْمَسَاكِينِ، وَاكْسُ الْعُرَاةَ مِنْ ثِيَابِكَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="18">
         <language id="English">
            Set out your bread and your wine at the burial of a just man, and do not eat and drink from it with sinners.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Set out your bread and your wine at the burial of a just man, and do not eat and drink from it with sinners.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            ضَعْ خُبْزَكَ وَخَمْرَكَ عَلَى مَدْفِنِ الْبَارِّ، وَلاَ تَأْكُلْ وَلاَ تَشْرَبْ مِنْهُمَا مَعَ الْخَطَأَةِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="19">
         <language id="English">
            Always seek the counsel of a wise man.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Always seek the counsel of a wise man.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            اِلْتَمِسْ مَشُورَةَ الْحَكِيمِ دَائِماً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="20">
         <language id="English">
            Bless God at all times. And petition him that he direct your ways and that all your counsels may remain in him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Bless God at all times. And petition him that he direct your ways and that all your counsels may remain in him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَبَارِكِ اللهَ فِي كُلِّ حِينٍ وَاسْتَرْشِدْهُ لِتَقْوِيمِ سُبُلِكَ وَإِقْرَارِ كُلِّ مَشُورَاتِكِ فِيهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="21">
         <language id="English">
            And now, I reveal to you, my son, that I lent ten talents of silver, while you were still a young child, to Gabael, in Rages, a city of the Medes, and I have his written agreement with me.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And now, I reveal to you, my son, that I lent ten talents of silver, while you were still a young child, to Gabael, in Rages, a city of the Medes, and I have his written agreement with me.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            ثُمَّ اعْلَمْ يَا بُنَيَّ، أَنِّي قَدْ أَعْطَيْتُ، وَأَنْتَ صَغِيرٌ، عَشَرَةَ قَنَاطِيرَ مِنَ الْفِضَّةِ لِغَابِيلُوسَ فِي رَاجِيسَ مَدِينَةِ الْمَادِيِّينَ، وَمَعِي بِهَا صَكٌّ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="22">
         <language id="English">
            And so, inquire how you may travel to him and receive from him the aforementioned weight of silver, and return to him the written agreement.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, inquire how you may travel to him and receive from him the aforementioned weight of silver, and return to him the written agreement.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَحَيْثُ ذلِكَ، فَانْظُرْ كَيْفَ تَتَوَصَّلُ إِلَيْهِ، فَتَقْبِضُ مِنْهُ الزِّنَةَ الْمَذْكُورَةَ مِنَ الْفِضَّةِ، وَتَرُدُّ عَلَيْهِ صَكَّهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="23">
         <language id="English">
            Do not be afraid, my son. We do indeed lead a poor life, but we will have many good things: if we fear God, and withdraw from all sin, and do what is good.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Do not be afraid, my son. We do indeed lead a poor life, but we will have many good things: if we fear God, and withdraw from all sin, and do what is good.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلاَ تَخَفْ يَا وَلَدَي، فَإِنَّا نَعِيشُ عِيشَةَ الْفُقَرَاءِ، وَلكِنْ سَيَكُونُ لَنَا خَيْرٌ كَثِيرٌ إِذَا اتَّقَيْنَا اللهَ وَابْتَعَدْنَا عَنْ كُلِّ خَطِيئَةٍ وَفَعَلْنَا خَيْراً».
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="5">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            Then Tobias responded to his father, and he said: “I will do everything just as you have instructed me, father.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Tobias responded to his father, and he said: “I will do everything just as you have instructed me, father.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَجَابَ طُوبِيَّا أَبَاهُ وَقَالَ: «يَا أَبَتِ كُلُّ مَّا أَمَرْتَنِي بِهِ أَفْعَلُهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            But I do not know how to obtain this money. He does not know me, and I do not know him. What proof shall I give to him? And I do not know any part of the way, which leads to that place.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But I do not know how to obtain this money. He does not know me, and I do not know him. What proof shall I give to him? And I do not know any part of the way, which leads to that place.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَمَّا هذَا الْمَالُ فَمَا أَدْرِي كَيْفَ أُحَصِّلُهُ، فَإِنَّ الرَّجُلَ لاَ يَعْرِفُنِي، وَأَنَا لاَ أَعْرِفُهُ؛ فَمَا الْعَلاَمَةُ الَّتِي أُعْطِيهَا لَهُ؟ بَلِ الطَّرِيقُ الَّتِي تُؤَدِّي إِلَى هُنَاكَ لاَ أَعْرِفُهَا أَيْضاً».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            Then his father answered him, and he said: “Indeed, I have a written agreement about that in my possession, which, when you show it to him, he will immediately repay it.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then his father answered him, and he said: “Indeed, I have a written agreement about that in my possession, which, when you show it to him, he will immediately repay it.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَجَابَهُ أَبُوهُ وَقَالَ: «إِنَّ عِنْدِي صَكَّهُ، فَإِذَا عَرَضْتَهُ عَلَيْهِ فَإِنَّهُ يُؤَدِّي عَاجِلاً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            But go out now, and inquire after some faithful man, who would go with you to keep you safe in return for his wages, so that you may receive it while I am still alive.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But go out now, and inquire after some faithful man, who would go with you to keep you safe in return for his wages, so that you may receive it while I am still alive.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَالآنَ هَلُمَّ فَالْتَمِسْ لَكَ رَجُلاً ثِقَةً يَصْحَبُكَ بِأُجْرَتِهِ حَتَّى تَسْتَوْفِيَ الْمَالَ وَأَنَا حَيٌّ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            Then Tobias, departing, found a splendid young man, standing girded and seemingly ready for travel.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Tobias, departing, found a splendid young man, standing girded and seemingly ready for travel.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَبَيْنَمَا خَرَجَ طُوبِيَّا، إِذَا بِفَتًى بَهِيٍّ قَدْ وَقَفَ مُشَمِّراً كَأَنَّهُ مُتَأَهِّبٌ لِلْمَسِيرِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            And not knowing that he was an Angel of God, he greeted him, and he said, “Where are you from, good young man?”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And not knowing that he was an Angel of God, he greeted him, and he said, “Where are you from, good young man?”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَسَلَّمَ عَلَيْهِ وَهُوَ يَجْهَلُ أَنَّهُ مَلاَكُ اللهِ وَقَالَ: «مِنْ أَيْنَ أَقْبَلْتَ يَا فَتَى الْخَيْرِ؟»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            And so he answered, “From the sons of Israel.” And Tobias said to him, “Do you know the way that leads to the region of the Medes?”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so he answered, “From the sons of Israel.” And Tobias said to him, “Do you know the way that leads to the region of the Medes?”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            قَالَ: «أَنَا مِنْ بَنِي إِسْرَائِيلَ». فَقَالَ لَهُ طُوبِيَّا: «هَلْ تَعْرِفُ الطَّرِيقَ الآخِذَةَ إِلَى بِلاَدِ الْمَادِيِّينَ؟»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            And he answered: “I know it. And I have frequently walked through all its paths, and I stayed with Gabael, our brother, who lives in Rages, a city of the Medes, which is situated at the mount of Ecbatana.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And he answered: “I know it. And I have frequently walked through all its paths, and I stayed with Gabael, our brother, who lives in Rages, a city of the Medes, which is situated at the mount of Ecbatana.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            قَالَ: «أَعْرِفُهَا، وَقَدْ سَلَكْتُ جَمِيعَ طُرُقِهَا مِرَاراً كَثِيرَةً، وَكُنْتُ نَازِلاً بِأَخِينَا غَابِيلُوسَ الْمُقِيمِ بِرَاجِيسِ مَدِينَةِ الْمَادِيِّينَ الَّتِي فِي جَبَلِ أَحْمَتَا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            Tobias said to him, “I implore you, wait here for me, until I tell these same things to my father.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Tobias said to him, “I implore you, wait here for me, until I tell these same things to my father.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ طُوبِيَّا: «انْتَظِرْنِي حَتَّى أُخْبِرَ أَبِي بِهذَا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            Then Tobias, entering, revealed all these things to his father. Upon which, his father, in admiration, asked that he would enter to him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Tobias, entering, revealed all these things to his father. Upon which, his father, in admiration, asked that he would enter to him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَدَخَلَ طُوبِيَّا وَأَخْبَرَ أَبَاهُ بِجَمِيعِ ذلِكَ، فَتَعَجَّبَ أَبُوهُ، وَطَلَبَ أَنْ يَدْخُلَ عَلَيْهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            And so, entering, he greeted him, and he said, “May gladness be always with you.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, entering, he greeted him, and he said, “May gladness be always with you.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَدَخَلَ وَسَلَّمَ عَلَيْهِ وَقَالَ: «لِيَكُنْ لَكَ فَرَحٌ دَائِمٌ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            And Tobit said, “What kind of gladness will be for me, since I sit in darkness and do not see the light of heaven?”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Tobit said, “What kind of gladness will be for me, since I sit in darkness and do not see the light of heaven?”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَجَابَ طُوبِيَّا: «وَأَيُّ فَرَحٍ يَكُونُ لِي أَنَا الْمُقِيمَ فِي الظَّلاَمِ لاَ أُبْصِرُ ضَوْءَ السَّمَاءِ؟»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            And the young man said to him, “Be steadfast in soul. Your cure from God is near.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the young man said to him, “Be steadfast in soul. Your cure from God is near.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ الْفَتَى: «كُنْ طَيِّبَ الْقَلْبِ فَإِنَّكَ عَنْ قَلِيلٍ تَنَالُ الْبُرْءَ مِنْ لَدُنِ اللهِ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            And so Tobit said to him, “Are you able to lead my son to Gabael in Rages, a city of the Medes? And when you return, I will pay you your wages.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so Tobit said to him, “Are you able to lead my son to Gabael in Rages, a city of the Medes? And when you return, I will pay you your wages.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ طُوبِيَّا: «هَلْ لَكَ أَنْ تُبَلِّغَ ابْنِي إِلَى غَابِيلُوسَ فِي رَاجِيسَ مَدِينَةِ الْمَادِيِّينَ، وَأَنَا أُوفِيكَ أُجْرَتَكَ مَتَى رَجَعْتَ؟»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            And the Angel said to him, “I will lead him, and I will bring him back to you.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the Angel said to him, “I will lead him, and I will bring him back to you.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ المَلاَكُ: «آخُذُهُ وَأَعُودُ بِهِ إِلَيْكَ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            And Tobit responded to him, “I ask you to tell me: which family or which tribe are you from?”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Tobit responded to him, “I ask you to tell me: which family or which tribe are you from?”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ طُوبِيَّا: «أَخْبِرْنِي مِنْ أَيِّ عَشِيرَةٍ وَمِنْ أَيِّ سِبْطٍ أَنْتَ؟»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            And Raphael the Angel said, “Do you seek the family of the one you hire, or else the hired hand himself, to go with your son?
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Raphael the Angel said, “Do you seek the family of the one you hire, or else the hired hand himself, to go with your son?
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ رَافَائِيلُ الْمَلاَكُ: «أَفِي نَسَبِ الأَجِيرِ حَاجَتُكَ أَمْ فِي الأَجِيرِ الَّذِي يَذْهَبُ مَعَ ابْنِكَ؟
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="18">
         <language id="English">
            But, lest perhaps I cause you to worry: I am Azariah, the son of Hananiah the great.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But, lest perhaps I cause you to worry: I am Azariah, the son of Hananiah the great.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلكِنْ لِكَيْ لاَ أُقْلِقَ بَالَكَ، أَنَا عَزَرْيَا بْنُ حَنَنْيَا الْعَظِيمِ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="19">
         <language id="English">
            And Tobit responded, “You are from a great family. But I ask you, do not be angry that I wanted to know your family.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Tobit responded, “You are from a great family. But I ask you, do not be angry that I wanted to know your family.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ طُوبِيَّا: «إِنَّكَ مِنْ نَسَبٍ كَرِيمٍ غَيْرَ أَنِّي أَرْجُو أَنْ لاَ يَسُوءَكَ كَوْنِي طَلَبْتُ مَعْرِفَةَ نَسَبِكَ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="20">
         <language id="English">
            But the Angel said to him, “I will lead your son safely, and I will bring him back safely to you.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But the Angel said to him, “I will lead your son safely, and I will bring him back safely to you.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ الْمَلاَكُ: «هَأَنَذَا آخُذَ ابْنَكَ سَالِماً، وَسَأَعُودُ بِهِ إِلَيْكَ سَالِماً».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="21">
         <language id="English">
            And so Tobit, answering, said, “May you walk well, and may God be with you on your journey, and may his Angel accompany you.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so Tobit, answering, said, “May you walk well, and may God be with you on your journey, and may his Angel accompany you.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            قَالَ طُوبِيَّا: «انْطَلِقَا بِسَلاَمٍ، وَلِيَكُنِ اللهُ فِي طَرِيقِكُمَا وَمَلاَكُهُ يُرَافِقُكُمَا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="22">
         <language id="English">
            Then, when all things were ready which were to be carried on their journey, Tobias said farewell to his father, and to his mother, and the two of them walked together.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then, when all things were ready which were to be carried on their journey, Tobias said farewell to his father, and to his mother, and the two of them walked together.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            حِينَئِذٍ أَخَذَا كُلَّ مَا أَرَادَا أَخْذَهُ مِنْ أُهْبَةِ الطَّرِيقِ، وَوَدَّعَ طُوبِيَّا أَبَاهُ وَأُمَّهُ، وَسَارَا كِلاَهُمَا مَعاً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="23">
         <language id="English">
            And when they had set out, his mother began to weep, and to say: “You have taken the staff of our old age, and you have sent him away from us.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when they had set out, his mother began to weep, and to say: “You have taken the staff of our old age, and you have sent him away from us.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلَمَّا فَصَلاَ، جَعَلَتْ أُمُّهُ تَبْكِي وَتَقُولُ: «قَدْ أَخَذْتَ عُكَّازَةَ شَيْخُوخَتِنَا وَأَبْعَدْتَهَا عَنَّا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="24">
         <language id="English">
            I wish that the money, for which you sent him, had never been.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            I wish that the money, for which you sent him, had never been.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لاَ كَانَ هذَا الْمَالُ الَّذِي أَرْسَلْتَهُ لأَجْلِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="25">
         <language id="English">
            For our poverty has been sufficient for us, so that we might count it as riches that we saw our son.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For our poverty has been sufficient for us, so that we might count it as riches that we saw our son.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لَقَدْ كَانَ فِي رِزْقِنَا الْقَلِيلِ مَا يَكْفِي لأَنْ نَعُدَّ النَّظَرَ إِلَى وَلَدِنَا غِنًى عَظِيماً».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="26">
         <language id="English">
            And Tobit said to her: “Do not weep. Our son will arrive safely, and he will return safely to us, and your eyes shall see him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Tobit said to her: “Do not weep. Our son will arrive safely, and he will return safely to us, and your eyes shall see him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهَا طُوبِيَّا: «لاَ تَبْكِي، إِنَّ وَلَدَنَا سَيَصِلُ سَالِماً وَيَعُودُ إِلَيْنَا سَالِماً، وَعَيْنَاكِ تُبْصِرَانِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="27">
         <language id="English">
            For I believe that the good Angel of God accompanies him and that he orders all things well which occur around him, such that he will be returned to us with gladness.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For I believe that the good Angel of God accompanies him and that he orders all things well which occur around him, such that he will be returned to us with gladness.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَإِنِّي وَاثِقٌ بِأَنَّ مَلاَكَ اللهِ الصَّالِحَ يَصْحَبُهُ وَيُدَبِّرُهُ فِي جَمِيعِ أَحْوَالِهِ حَتَّى يَرْجِعَ إِلَيْنَا بِفَرَحٍ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="28">
         <language id="English">
            At these words, his mother ceased weeping, and she was silent.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            At these words, his mother ceased weeping, and she was silent.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَكَفَّتْ أُمُّهُ عَنِ الْبُكَاءِ عِنْدَ هذَا الْكَلاَمِ وَسَكَتَتْ.
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="6">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            And so Tobias continued on, and the dog was following him, and he stayed at the first stopping point, near the river Tigris.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so Tobias continued on, and the dog was following him, and he stayed at the first stopping point, near the river Tigris.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَسَافَرَ طُوبِيَّا وَالْكَلْبُ يَتْبَعُهُ، فَبَاتَ أَوَّلَ مَنْزِلَةٍ بِجَانِبِ نَهْرِ دِجْلَةَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            And he went out to wash his feet, and behold, an immense fish came out to devour him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And he went out to wash his feet, and behold, an immense fish came out to devour him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَخَرَجَ لِيَغْسِلَ رِجْلَيْهِ، فَإِذَا بِحُوتٍ عَظِيمٍ قَدْ خَرَجَ لِيَفْتَرِسَهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            And Tobias, being frightened of it, cried out with a loud voice, saying, “Sir, it is attacking me!”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Tobias, being frightened of it, cried out with a loud voice, saying, “Sir, it is attacking me!”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَارْتَاعَ طُوبِيَّا وَصَرَخَ بِصَوْتٍ عَظِيمٍ قَائِلاً: «يَا مَوْلاَيَ قَدِ اقْتَحَمَنِي».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            And the Angel said to him, “Catch it by the gills, and draw it to you.” And when he had done so, he pulled it onto dry land, and it began to thrash before his feet.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the Angel said to him, “Catch it by the gills, and draw it to you.” And when he had done so, he pulled it onto dry land, and it began to thrash before his feet.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ الْمَلاَكُ: «أَمْسِكْ بِخَيْشُومِهِ وَاجْتَذِبْهُ إِلَيْكَ». فَفَعَلَ كَذلِكَ وَاجْتَذَبَهُ إِلَى الْيَبْسِ، فَأَخَذَ يَخْتَبِطُ عِنْدَ رِجْلَيْهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            Then the Angel said to him: “Disembowel this fish, and put aside his heart, and his gall, and his liver for yourself. For these things are necessary as useful medicines.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then the Angel said to him: “Disembowel this fish, and put aside his heart, and his gall, and his liver for yourself. For these things are necessary as useful medicines.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ الْمَلاَكُ: «شُقَّ جَوْفَ الْحُوتِ، وَاحْتَفِظْ بِقَلْبِهِ وَمَرَارَتِهِ وَكَبِدِهِ، فَإِنَّ لَكَ بِهَا مَنْفَعَةً لِعِلاَجٍ مُفِيدٍ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            And when he had done so, he roasted its flesh, and they took it with them on the way. The rest they salted, so that it might be sufficient for them, until they would arrive at Rages, a city of the Medes.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when he had done so, he roasted its flesh, and they took it with them on the way. The rest they salted, so that it might be sufficient for them, until they would arrive at Rages, a city of the Medes.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَفَعَلَ كَذلِكَ، ثُمَّ شَوَى مِنْ لَحْمِهِ، فَأَخَذَا لِلطَّرِيقِ، وَمَلَّحَا سَائِرَهُ حَتَّى يَكُونَ لَهُمَا مَا يَكْفِيهِمَا إِلَى أَنْ يَبْلُغَا رَاجِيسَ مَدِينَةَ الْمَادِيِّينَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            Then Tobias questioned the Angel, and he said to him, “I implore you, brother Azariah, to tell me what remedies these things hold, which you have told me to retain from the fish?”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Tobias questioned the Angel, and he said to him, “I implore you, brother Azariah, to tell me what remedies these things hold, which you have told me to retain from the fish?”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            ثُمَّ إِنَّ طُوبِيَّا سَأَلَ الْمَلاَكَ وَقَالَ لَهُ: «نَشَدْتُكَ يَا أَخِي عَزَرْيَا أَنْ تُخْبِرَنِي مَا الْعِلاَجُ الَّذِي يُؤْخَذُ مِنْ هذِهِ الأَشْيَاءِ الَّتِي أَمَرْتَنِي أَنْ أَذْخَرَهَا مِنَ الْحُوتِ؟»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            And the Angel, answering, said to him: “If you put a little piece of its heart on burning coals, its smoke will drive away all kinds of demons, whether from a man or from a woman, so that they will no longer approach them.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the Angel, answering, said to him: “If you put a little piece of its heart on burning coals, its smoke will drive away all kinds of demons, whether from a man or from a woman, so that they will no longer approach them.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَجَابَهُ الْمَلاَكُ قَائِلاً: «إِذَا أَلْقَيْتَ شَيْئاً مِنْ قَلْبِهِ عَلَى الْجَمْرِ فَدُخَانُهُ يَطْرُدُ كُلَّ جِنْسٍ مِنَ الشَيَّاطِينِ فِي رَجُلٍ كَانَ أَوِ امْرَأَةٍ بِحَيْثُ لاَ يَعُودُ يَقْرُبُهُمَا أَبَداً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            And the gall is useful for anointing the eyes, in which there may be a white speck, and they will be cured.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the gall is useful for anointing the eyes, in which there may be a white speck, and they will be cured.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَالْمَرَارَةُ تَنْفَعُ لِمَسْحِ الْعُيُونِ الَّتِي عَلَيْهَا غِشَاءٌ فَتَبْرَأُ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            And Tobias said to him, “Where do you prefer that we stay?”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Tobias said to him, “Where do you prefer that we stay?”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَالَ طُوبِيَّا: «أَيْنَ تُرِيدُ أَنْ نَنْزِلَ؟»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            And the Angel, responding, said: “Here is one named Raguel, a man closely related to you from your tribe, and he has a daughter named Sarah, but he has no other male or female, except her.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the Angel, responding, said: “Here is one named Raguel, a man closely related to you from your tribe, and he has a daughter named Sarah, but he has no other male or female, except her.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ الْمَلاَكُ إِنَّ هُنَا رَجُلاً اسْمُهُ رَعُوئِيلُ مِنْ ذَوِي قَرَابَتِكَ مِنْ سِبْطِكَ، وَلَهُ بِنْتٌ اسْمُهَا سَارَةُ، وَلَيْسَ لَهُ مِنْ ذَكَرٍ وَلاَ أُنْثَى سِوَاهَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            All his livelihood is dependent upon you, and you ought to take her to yourself in marriage.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            All his livelihood is dependent upon you, and you ought to take her to yourself in marriage.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَجَمِيعُ مَالِهِ مُسْتَحَقٌّ لَكَ، وَلاَ بُدَّ لَكَ أَنْ تَتَّخِذَهَا زَوْجَةً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            Therefore, ask for her from her father, and he will give her to you as wife.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Therefore, ask for her from her father, and he will give her to you as wife.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَاخْطُبْهَا إِلَى أَبِيهَا فَإِنَّهُ يُزَوِّجُهَا مِنْكَ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            Then Tobias responded, and he said: “I hear that she has been given to seven husbands, and they passed away. But I have even heard this: that a demon killed them.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Tobias responded, and he said: “I hear that she has been given to seven husbands, and they passed away. But I have even heard this: that a demon killed them.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَجَابَ طُوبِيَّا وَقَالَ: «إِنِّي سَمِعْتُ أَنَّهُ قَدْ عُقِدَ لَهَا عَلَى سَبْعَةِ أَزْوَاجٍ فَمَاتُوا، وَقَدْ سَمِعْتُ أَيْضاً أَنَّ الشَّيْطَانَ قَتَلَهُمْ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            Therefore, I am afraid, lest this may happen to me also. And since I am the only child of my parents, I might send their old age with sorrow to the grave.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Therefore, I am afraid, lest this may happen to me also. And since I am the only child of my parents, I might send their old age with sorrow to the grave.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلأَجْلِ هذَا أَخَافُ أَنْ يُصِيبَنِي مِثْلُ ذلِكَ، وَأَنَا وَحِيدٌ لأَبَوَيَّ، فَأَنْزِلُ شَيْخُوخَتَهُمَا إِلَى الْجَحِيمِ بِالْحُزْنِ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            Then the Angel Raphael said to him: “Listen to me, and I will reveal to you who they are, over whom the demon can prevail.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then the Angel Raphael said to him: “Listen to me, and I will reveal to you who they are, over whom the demon can prevail.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ الْمَلاَكُ رَافَائِيلُ: «اسْتَمِعْ فَأُخْبِرَكَ مَنْ هُمُ الَّذِينَ يَسْتَطِيعُ الشَّيْطَانُ أَنْ يَقْوَى عَلَيْهِمْ؟
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            For example, those who receive marriage in such manner as to exclude God from themselves and from their mind, and in such a manner as to empty themselves to their lust, like the horse and mule, which have no understanding, over them the demon has power.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For example, those who receive marriage in such manner as to exclude God from themselves and from their mind, and in such a manner as to empty themselves to their lust, like the horse and mule, which have no understanding, over them the demon has power.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            إِنَّ الَّذِينَ يَتَزَوَّجُونَ، فَيَنْفُونَ اللهَ مِنْ قُلُوبِهِمْ، وَيَتَفَرَّغُونَ لِشَهْوَتِهِمْ كَالْفَرَسِ وَالْبَغْلِ اللَّذَيْنِ لاَ فَهْمَ لَهُمَا؛ أُولئِكَ لِلشَّيْطَانِ عَلَيْهِمْ سُلْطَانٌ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="18">
         <language id="English">
            But you, when you will have accepted her, enter the bedroom and for three days keep yourself continent from her, and empty yourself to nothing other than prayers with her.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But you, when you will have accepted her, enter the bedroom and for three days keep yourself continent from her, and empty yourself to nothing other than prayers with her.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَنْتَ إِذَا تَزَوَّجْتَهَا وَدَخَلْتَ الْمُخْدَعَ، فَأَمْسِكْ عَنْهَا ثَلاَثَةَ أَيَّامٍ وَلاَ تَتَفَرَّغْ مَعَهَا إِلاَّ لِلصَّلَوَاتِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="19">
         <language id="English">
            Moreover, on that night, burn the liver of the fish like incense, and the demon will be put to flight.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Moreover, on that night, burn the liver of the fish like incense, and the demon will be put to flight.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَفِي تِلْكَ اللَّيْلَةِ، إِذَا أَحْرَقْتَ كَبِدَ الْحُوتِ، يَنْهَزِمُ الشَّيْطَانُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="20">
         <language id="English">
            In truth, on the second night, you will become ready to receive a physical union like that of the holy Patriarchs.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            In truth, on the second night, you will become ready to receive a physical union like that of the holy Patriarchs.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَفِي اللَّيْلَةِ الثَّانِيَةِ، تَكُونُ مَقْبُولاً فِي شَرِكَةِ الآبَاءِ الْقِدِّيسِينَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="21">
         <language id="English">
            And then, on the third night, you will obtain a blessing, so that healthy children may be procreated from you both.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And then, on the third night, you will obtain a blessing, so that healthy children may be procreated from you both.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَفِي اللَّيْلَةِ الثَّالِثَةِ، تَنَالُ الْبَرَكَةَ حَتَّى يُولَدَ لَكُمَا بَنُونَ سَالِمُونَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="22">
         <language id="English">
            And so, the third night having been accomplished, you will receive the virgin with the fear of the Lord, led more by love of children than by physical desire, so that, as the offspring of Abraham, you will then obtain a blessing in children.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, the third night having been accomplished, you will receive the virgin with the fear of the Lord, led more by love of children than by physical desire, so that, as the offspring of Abraham, you will then obtain a blessing in children.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَبَعْدَ انْقِضَاءِ اللَّيْلَةِ الثَّالِثَةِ، تَتَّخِذُ الْبِكْرَ بِخَوْفِ الرَّبِّ وَأَنْتَ رَاغِبٌ فِي الْبَنِينَ أَكْثَرَ مِنَ الشَّهْوَةِ، لِكَيْ تَنَالَ بَرَكَةَ ذُرِّيَّةِ إِبْرَاهِيمَ
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="7">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            And so they went to Raguel, and Raguel received them with gladness.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so they went to Raguel, and Raguel received them with gladness.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            ثُمَّ دَخَلاَ عَلَى رَعُوئِيلَ، فَتَلَقَّاهُمَا رَعُوئِيلُ بِالْمَسَرَّةِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            And Raguel, gazing upon Tobias, said to Anna his wife, “How much like my cousin is this young man!”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Raguel, gazing upon Tobias, said to Anna his wife, “How much like my cousin is this young man!”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَإِذْ نَظَرَ رَعُوئِيلُ إِلَى طُوبِيَّا قَالَ لِحَنَّةَ زَوْجَتِهِ: «مَا أَشْبَهَ هذَا الرَّجُلَ بِذِي قَرَابَتِي!»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            And when he had spoken this, he said, “Which of our brethren are you from, young men?”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when he had spoken this, he said, “Which of our brethren are you from, young men?”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَبَعْدَ هذَا الْكَلاَمِ قَالَ رَعُوئِيلُ: «مِنْ أَيْنَ أَنْتُمَا أَيُّهَا الأَخَوَانِ الْفِتْيَانِ؟» فَقَالاَ لَهُ: «مِنْ سِبْطِ نَفْتَالِيَ مِنْ جَلاَءِ نِينَوَى».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            But they said, “We are from the tribe of Naphtali, from the captivity of Nineveh.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But they said, “We are from the tribe of Naphtali, from the captivity of Nineveh.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُمَا رَعُوئِيلُ: «هَلْ تَعْرِفَانِ طُوبِيَّا أَخِي؟» فَقَالاَ: «نَعْرِفُهُ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            And Raguel said to them, “Do you know my brother Tobit?” They said to him, “We know him.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Raguel said to them, “Do you know my brother Tobit?” They said to him, “We know him.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلَمَّا أَكْثَرَ مِنَ الثَّنَاءِ عَلَيْهِ، قَالَ الْمَلاَكُ لِرَعُوئِيلَ: «إِنَّ طُوبِيَّا الَّذِي أَنْتَ تَسْأَلُ عَنْهُ هُوَ أَبُو هذَا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            And since he was saying many good things about him, the Angel said to Raguel, “The Tobit about whom you inquire is the father of this young man.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And since he was saying many good things about him, the Angel said to Raguel, “The Tobit about whom you inquire is the father of this young man.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَلْقَى رَعُوئِيلُ بِنَفْسِهِ، وَقَبَّلَهُ بِدُمُوعٍ، وَبَكَى عَلَى عُنُقِهِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            And Raguel threw himself towards him and kissed him with tears and weeping upon his neck, saying, “May a blessing be upon you, my son, because you are the son of a good and most noble man.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Raguel threw himself towards him and kissed him with tears and weeping upon his neck, saying, “May a blessing be upon you, my son, because you are the son of a good and most noble man.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَالَ: «بَرَكَةٌ لَكَ يَا بُنَيَّ، إِنَّكَ ابْنُ رَجُلٍ صَالِحٍ فَاضِلٍ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            And his wife Anna, and their daughter Sarah, were weeping.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And his wife Anna, and their daughter Sarah, were weeping.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَبَكَتْ حَنَّةُ امْرَأَتُهُ وَسَارَةُ ابْنَتُهُمَا أَيْضاً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            And so, after they had spoken, Raguel instructed a sheep to be killed, and a feast to be prepared. And when he exhorted them to recline for dinner,
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, after they had spoken, Raguel instructed a sheep to be killed, and a feast to be prepared. And when he exhorted them to recline for dinner,
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَبَعْدَ أَنْ تَحَادَثُوا، أَمَرَ رَعُوئِيلُ أَنْ يُذْبَحَ كَبْشٌ، وَتُهَيَّأَ مَأْدُبَةٌ وَدَعَاهُمَا أَنْ يَتَّكِئَا لِلْغَدَاءِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            Tobias said, “Here, today, I will not eat or drink, unless you first confirm my petition, and promise to give Sarah your daughter to me.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Tobias said, “Here, today, I will not eat or drink, unless you first confirm my petition, and promise to give Sarah your daughter to me.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ طُوبِيَّا: «إِنِّي لاَ آكُلُ الْيَوْمَ طَعَاماً ههُنَا وَلاَ أَشْرَبُ مَا لَمْ تُجِبْنِي إِلَى مَا أَنَا سَائِلُهُ، وَتَعِدْنِي أَنْ تُعْطِيَنِي سَارَةَ ابْنَتَكَ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            When Raguel heard this word, he became afraid, knowing what had befallen those seven men, who had approached her. And he began to fear, lest it might happen to him also in the same way. And, since he wavered and gave no further response to the petition,
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            When Raguel heard this word, he became afraid, knowing what had befallen those seven men, who had approached her. And he began to fear, lest it might happen to him also in the same way. And, since he wavered and gave no further response to the petition,
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلَمَّا سَمِعَ رَعُوئِيلُ هذَا الْكَلاَمَ، ارْتَعَدَ لِمَعْرِفَتِهِ بِمَا أَصَابَ السَّبْعَةَ الرِّجَالَ الَّذِينَ دَخَلُوا عَلَيْهَا، وَخَافَ أَنْ يُصِيبَ هذَا مَا أَصَابَهُمْ وَفِيمَا هُوَ مُتَرَدِّدٌ وَلَمْ يَرْدُدْ عَلَيْهِ جَوَاباً،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            the Angel said to him: “Do not be afraid to give her to this one, because this one fears God. He is obliged to be joined to your daughter. Because of this, no other one could have her.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            the Angel said to him: “Do not be afraid to give her to this one, because this one fears God. He is obliged to be joined to your daughter. Because of this, no other one could have her.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            قَالَ لَهُ الْمَلاَكُ: «لاَ تَخَفْ أَنْ تُعْطِيَهَا لِهذَا، فَإِنَّ ابْنَتَكَ لَهُ يَنْبَغِي أَنْ تَكُونَ زَوْجَةً لأَنَّهُ يَخَافُ اللهَ، وَلِذلِكَ لَمْ يَقْدِرْ غَيْرُهُ أَنْ يَأْخُذَهَا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            Then Raguel said: “I do not doubt that God has admitted my prayers and tears before his sight.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Raguel said: “I do not doubt that God has admitted my prayers and tears before his sight.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            حِينَئِذٍ قَالَ رَعُوئِيلُ: «لاَ أَشُكُّ أَنَّ اللهَ قَدْ تَقَبَّلَ صَلَوَاتِي وَدُمُوعِي أَمَامَهُ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            And I believe, therefore, that he has caused you to come to me, so that this one might be joined in marriage to one of her own kindred, according to the law of Moses. And now, do not continue to doubt that I will give her to you.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And I believe, therefore, that he has caused you to come to me, so that this one might be joined in marriage to one of her own kindred, according to the law of Moses. And now, do not continue to doubt that I will give her to you.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَعَلَّهُ لأَجْلِ ذلِكَ سَاقَكُمَا اللهُ إِلَيَّ حَتَّى تَتَزَوَّجَ هذِهِ بِذِي قَرَابَتِهَا عَلَى حَسَبِ شَرِيعَةِ مُوسَى. وَالآنَ لاَ تَشُكَّ أَنِّي أُعْطِيكَهَا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            And taking the right hand of his daughter, he gave it into the right hand of Tobias, saying, “May the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob be with you. And may he join you together in marriage and fulfill his blessing in you.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And taking the right hand of his daughter, he gave it into the right hand of Tobias, saying, “May the God of Abraham, and the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob be with you. And may he join you together in marriage and fulfill his blessing in you.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            ثُمَّ أَخَذَ بِيَمِينِ ابْنَتِهِ سَارَةَ وَسَلَّمَهَا إِلَى يَمِينِ طُوبِيَّا، قَائِلاً: «إِلهُ إِبْرَاهِيمَ وَإِلهُ إِسْحَاقَ وَإِلهُ يَعْقُوبَ يَكُونُ مَعَكُمَا، وَهُوَ يَقْرِنُكُمَا وَيُتِمُّ بَرَكَتَهُ عَلَيْكُمَا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            And taking paper, they made a written record of the marriage.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And taking paper, they made a written record of the marriage.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            ثُمَّ أَخَذُوا صَحِيفَةً وَكَتَبُوا فِيهَا عَقْدَ الزَّوَاجِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            And after this, they feasted, blessing God.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And after this, they feasted, blessing God.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَبَعْدَ ذلِكَ أَكَلُوا وَبَارَكُوا اللهَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="18">
         <language id="English">
            And Raguel called his wife Anna to him, and he instructed her to prepare another bedroom.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Raguel called his wife Anna to him, and he instructed her to prepare another bedroom.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَدَعَا رَعُوئِيلُ حَنَّةَ زَوْجَتَهُ وَأَمَرَهَا أَنْ تُهَيِّءَ مُخْدَعاً آخَرَ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="19">
         <language id="English">
            And she brought her daughter Sarah into it, and she was weeping.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And she brought her daughter Sarah into it, and she was weeping.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَدْخَلَتْهُ سَارَةَ ابْنَتَهَا وَهِيَ بَاكِيَةٌ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="20">
         <language id="English">
            And she said to her, “Be steadfast in spirit, my daughter. May the Lord of heaven give you gladness in place of the grief that you have had to endure.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And she said to her, “Be steadfast in spirit, my daughter. May the Lord of heaven give you gladness in place of the grief that you have had to endure.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَالَتْ لَهَا: «تَشَجَّعِي يَا بُنَيَّةُ، وَرَبُّ السَّمَاءِ يُؤْتِيكِ فَرَحاً بَدَلَ الْغَمِّ الَّذِي قَاسَيْتِهِ».
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="8">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            In truth, after they had dined, they introduced the young man to her.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            In truth, after they had dined, they introduced the young man to her.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَمَّا فَرَغُوا مِنَ الْعَشَاءِ، أَدْخَلُوا عَلَيْهَا الْفَتَى،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            And so, Tobias, remembering the word of the Angel, took part of the liver from his bag, and he placed it over the live coals.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, Tobias, remembering the word of the Angel, took part of the liver from his bag, and he placed it over the live coals.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَذَكَرَ طُوبِيَّا كَلاَمَ الْمَلاَكِ، فَأَخْرَجَ مِنْ كِيسِهِ فِلْذَةً مِنَ الْكَبِدِ، وَأَلْقَاهَا عَلَى الْجَمْرِ الْمُشْتَعِلِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            Then the Angel Raphael caught the demon, and bound him in the desert of upper Egypt.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then the Angel Raphael caught the demon, and bound him in the desert of upper Egypt.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            حِينَئِذٍ قَبَضَ الْمَلاَكُ رَافَائِيلُ عَلَى الشَّيْطَانِ وَأَوْثَقَهُ فِي بَرِّيَّةِ مِصْرَ الْعُلْيَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            Then Tobias exhorted the virgin, and he said to her: “Sarah, get up and let us pray to God this day, and tomorrow, and the following day. For, during these three nights, we are being joined to God. And then, when the third night has passed, we ourselves will be joined together.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Tobias exhorted the virgin, and he said to her: “Sarah, get up and let us pray to God this day, and tomorrow, and the following day. For, during these three nights, we are being joined to God. And then, when the third night has passed, we ourselves will be joined together.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَوَعَظَ طُوبِيَّا الْبِكْرَ وَقَالَ لَهَا: «يَا سَارَةُ قُومِي نُصَلِّي إِلَى اللهِ الْيَوْمَ وَغَدًا وَبَعْدَ غَدٍ، فَإِنَّا فِي هذِهِ اللَّيَالِي الثَّلاَثِ نَتَّحِدُ بِاللهِ وَبَعْدَ انْقِضَاءِ اللَّيْلَةِ الثَّالِثَةِ نَكُونُ فِي زَوَاجِنَا،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            For certainly, we are the children of the saints, and we must not be joined together in such a manner as the heathens, who are ignorant of God.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For certainly, we are the children of the saints, and we must not be joined together in such a manner as the heathens, who are ignorant of God.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنَّا بَنُو الْقِدِّيسِينَ فَلاَ يَنْبَغِي لَنَا أَنْ نَقْتَرِنَ اقْتِرَانَ الأُمَمِ الَّذِينَ لاَ يَعْرِفُونَ اللهَ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            And so, rising up together, they both prayed earnestly, at the same time, that health might be given to them.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, rising up together, they both prayed earnestly, at the same time, that health might be given to them.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَامَا مَعاً وَصَلَّيَا كِلاَهُمَا بِحَرَارَةٍ حَتَّى يُعَافِيَهُمَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            And Tobias said: “Lord, the God of our fathers, may the heavens and the earth bless you, and the sea, and the fountains, and the rivers, and all your creatures that are in them.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Tobias said: “Lord, the God of our fathers, may the heavens and the earth bless you, and the sea, and the fountains, and the rivers, and all your creatures that are in them.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَالَ طُوبِيَّا: «أَيُّهَا الرَّبُّ إِلهُ آبَائِنَا، لِتُبَارِكُكَ السَّمَوَاتُ وَالأَرْضُ وَالْبَحْرُ وَالْيَنَابِيعُ وَالأَنْهَارُ وَجَمِيعُ خَلاَئِقِكَ الَّتِي فِيهَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            You formed Adam from the mud of the earth, and you gave Eve to him as a helper.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            You formed Adam from the mud of the earth, and you gave Eve to him as a helper.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَنْتَ جَبَلْتَ آدَمَ مِنْ تُرَابِ الأَرْضِ وَأَتَيْتَهُ حَوَّاءَ عَوْناً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            And now, O Lord, you know that I take my sister in conjugal union, not by reason of worldly pleasure, but solely for the love of posterity, in which your name may be blessed forever and ever.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And now, O Lord, you know that I take my sister in conjugal union, not by reason of worldly pleasure, but solely for the love of posterity, in which your name may be blessed forever and ever.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَالآنَ يَا رَبِّ، أَنْتَ تَعْلَمُ أَنِّي لاَ لِسَبَبِ الشَّهْوَةِ أَتَّخِذُ أُخْتِي زَوْجَةً، وَإِنَّمَا رَغْبَةً فِي النَّسْلِ الَّذِي يُبَارَكُ فِيهِ اسْمُكَ إِلَى دَهْرِ الدُّهُورِ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            Sarah likewise said, “Be merciful to us, O Lord, be merciful to us. And let us both grow old together in health.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Sarah likewise said, “Be merciful to us, O Lord, be merciful to us. And let us both grow old together in health.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَالَتْ سَارَةُ أَيْضاً: «ارْحَمْنَا يَا رَبِّ ارْحَمْنَا حَتَّى نَشِيخَ كِلاَنَا مَعاً فِي عَافِيَةٍ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            And it happened, about the time of the rooster’s crowing, that Raguel ordered his servants to be summoned, and they went out with him together to dig a grave.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And it happened, about the time of the rooster’s crowing, that Raguel ordered his servants to be summoned, and they went out with him together to dig a grave.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَانَ نَحْوَ وَقْتِ صِيَاحِ الدِّيكِ، أَنَّ رَعُوئِيلَ أَمَرَ أَنْ يُجْمَعَ إِلَيْهِ غِلْمَانُهُ، فَانْطَلَقُوا مَعَهُ وَاحْتَفَرُوا قَبْراً،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            For he said, “Lest perhaps, in the same way, it may have happened to him, as it did also to the other seven men who approached her.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For he said, “Lest perhaps, in the same way, it may have happened to him, as it did also to the other seven men who approached her.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنَّهُ قَالَ: «أَخْشَى أَنْ يُصِيبَهُ مَا أَصَابَ غَيْرَهُ مِنَ الرِّجَالِ السَّبْعَةِ الَّذِينَ دَخَلُوا عَلَيْهَا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            And when they had prepared the pit, Raguel returned to his wife, and he said to her,
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when they had prepared the pit, Raguel returned to his wife, and he said to her,
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلَمَّا أَعَدُّوا الْقَبْرَ، رَجَعَ رَعُوئِيلُ إِلَى زَوْجَتِهِ، وَقَالَ لَهَا:
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            “Send one of your maids, and let her see if he is dead, so that I may bury him before the dawn of day.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            “Send one of your maids, and let her see if he is dead, so that I may bury him before the dawn of day.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            «ابْعَثِي وَاحِدَةً مِنْ جَوَارِيكِ لِتَرَى هَلْ مَاتَ حَتَّى أُوَارِيَهُ قَبْلَ ضَوْءِ النَّهَارِ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            And so, she sent one of her maidservants, who entered the bedroom and discovered them safe and unharmed, sleeping both together.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, she sent one of her maidservants, who entered the bedroom and discovered them safe and unharmed, sleeping both together.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَنْفَذَتْ إِحْدَى جَوَارِيهَا، فَدَخَلَتِ الْمُخْدَعَ، فَإِذَا هُمَا سَالِمَانِ مُعَافَيَانِ، وَهُمَا نَائِمَانِ مَعاً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            And returning, she reported the good news. And they blessed the Lord: Raguel, especially, and his wife Anna.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And returning, she reported the good news. And they blessed the Lord: Raguel, especially, and his wife Anna.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَعَادَتْ وَأَخْبَرَتْ بِهذِهِ الْبُشْرَى. فَبَارَكَ رَعُوئِيلُ وَحَنَّةُ زَوْجَتُهُ الرَّبَّ
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            And they said: “We bless you, Lord God of Israel, because it has not happened in the way that we thought it might.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And they said: “We bless you, Lord God of Israel, because it has not happened in the way that we thought it might.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            قَائِلَيْنِ: «نُبَارِكُكَ أَيُّهَا الرَّبُّ إِلهُ إِسْرَائِيلَ مِنْ أَجْلِ أَنَّهُ لَمْ يُصِبْنَا مَا كُنَّا نَتَوَقَّعُهُ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="18">
         <language id="English">
            For you have acted in your mercy toward us, and you have excluded from us the enemy who pursued us.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For you have acted in your mercy toward us, and you have excluded from us the enemy who pursued us.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَإِنَّكَ قَدْ آتَيْتَنَا رَحْمَتَكَ وَحَبَسْتَ عَنَّا الْعَدُوَ الَّذِي يَضْطَهِدُنَا،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="19">
         <language id="English">
            Moreover, you have had compassion on two only children. Make them, O Lord, able to bless you more fully and to offer you a sacrifice of your praise and of their health, so that all peoples everywhere may know that you alone are God in all the earth.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Moreover, you have had compassion on two only children. Make them, O Lord, able to bless you more fully and to offer you a sacrifice of your praise and of their health, so that all peoples everywhere may know that you alone are God in all the earth.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَرَحِمْتَ الْوَحِيدَيْنِ. فَاجْعَلْهُمَا يَا رَبِّ يُبَارِكَانِكَ أَتَمَّ بَرَكَةٍ، وَيُقَدِّمَانِ لَكَ قُرْبَانَ تَسْبِيحِكَ وَعَافِيَتِهِمَا حَتَّى تَعْلَمَ الأُمَمُ كَافَّةً أَنَّكَ أَنْتَ الإِلهُ الْوَاحِدُ فِي الأَرْضِ كُلِّهَا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="20">
         <language id="English">
            And immediately Raguel instructed his servants to refill the pit, which they had made, before daylight.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And immediately Raguel instructed his servants to refill the pit, which they had made, before daylight.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلِلْحَالِ أَمَرَ رَعُوئِيلُ غِلْمَانَهُ أَنْ يَرْدِمُوا الْقَبْرَ الَّذِي حَفَرُوهُ قَبْلَ ضَوْءِ الصَّبَاحِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="21">
         <language id="English">
            And then he told his wife to make ready a feast, and to prepare all the provisions that are necessary for those who undertake a journey.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And then he told his wife to make ready a feast, and to prepare all the provisions that are necessary for those who undertake a journey.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            ثُمَّ أَوْعَزَ إِلَى زَوْجَتِهِ أَنْ تُعِدَّ وَلِيمَةً وَتُصْلِحَ مَا يَنْبَغِي لِلْمُسَافِرِينَ مِنَ الزَّادِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="22">
         <language id="English">
            Likewise, he caused two fat cows and four rams to be killed, and a banquet to be prepared for all his neighbors and every one of his friends.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Likewise, he caused two fat cows and four rams to be killed, and a banquet to be prepared for all his neighbors and every one of his friends.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَمَرَ بِذَبْحِ بَقَرَتَيْنِ سَمِينَتَيْنِ وَأَرْبَعَةِ أَكْبُشٍ، وَأَنْ تُهَيَّأَ وَلِيمَةٌ لِجَمِيعِ جِيرَانِهِ وَأَصْدِقَائِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="23">
         <language id="English">
            And Raguel pleaded with Tobias to delay with him for two weeks.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Raguel pleaded with Tobias to delay with him for two weeks.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَاسْتَحْلَفَ رَعُوئِيلُ طُوبِيَّا أَنْ يُقِيمَ عِنْدَهُ أُسْبُوعَيْنِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="24">
         <language id="English">
            Moreover, of all the things that Raguel possessed, he gave one half part to Tobias, and he made a writing, so that the half that remained should also pass into the ownership of Tobias, after their deaths.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Moreover, of all the things that Raguel possessed, he gave one half part to Tobias, and he made a writing, so that the half that remained should also pass into the ownership of Tobias, after their deaths.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَعْطَى رَعُوئِيلُ لِطُوبِيَّا نِصْفَ مَالِهِ كُلِّهِ، وَكَتَبَ لِطُوبِيَّا صَكًّا بِالنِّصْفِ الْبَاقِي أَنْ يَسْتَوْلِيَ عَلَيْهِ بَعْدَ مَوْتِهِمَا.
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="9">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            Then Tobias called the Angel to him, whom he indeed considered to be a man, and he said to him: “Brother Azariah, I implore you to listen to my words:
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Tobias called the Angel to him, whom he indeed considered to be a man, and he said to him: “Brother Azariah, I implore you to listen to my words:
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            ثُمَّ إِنَّ طُوبِيَّا اسْتَدْعَى الْمَلاَكَ الَّذِي كَانَ يَحْسَبُهُ إِنْسَاناً، وَقَالَ لَهُ: «يَا أَخِي عَزَرْيَا أَسْأَلُكَ أَنْ تَسْمَعَ كَلاَمِي:
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            If I should give myself to be your servant, I would not be equally worthy of your providence.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            If I should give myself to be your servant, I would not be equally worthy of your providence.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            «إِنِّي لَوْ جَعَلْتُ نَفْسِي عَبْدَا لَكَ لَمَا وَفَيْتُ بِعِنَايَتِكَ حَقَّ الْوَفَاءِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            Even so, I beg you to take with you beasts or even servants, and to go to Gabael in Rages, the city of the Medes, and restore to him his handwritten note, and receive from him the money, and petition him to come to my wedding celebration.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Even so, I beg you to take with you beasts or even servants, and to go to Gabael in Rages, the city of the Medes, and restore to him his handwritten note, and receive from him the money, and petition him to come to my wedding celebration.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلكِنِّي مَعَ ذلِكَ أَسْأَلُكَ أَنْ تَأْخُذَ دَوَابَّ وَغِلْمَاناً، وَتَنْطَلِقَ إِلَى غَابِيلُوسَ فِي رَاجِيسَ مَدِينَةِ الْمَادِيِّينَ، وَتَرُدَّ عَلَيْهِ صَكَّهُ، وَتَقْبِضَ مِنْهُ الْفِضَّةَ، وَتَدْعُوَهُ إِلَى عُرْسِي،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            For you know that my father numbers the days. And if I delay one day more, his soul will be afflicted.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For you know that my father numbers the days. And if I delay one day more, his soul will be afflicted.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنَّكَ تَعْلَمُ أَنَّ أَبِي يَحْسُبُ الأَيَّامَ، فَإِنْ زِدْتُ فِي إِبْطَائِي يَوْماً وَاحِداً حَزِنَتْ نَفْسُهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            And surely you see how Raguel has obtained my oath, an oath that I am not able to spurn.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And surely you see how Raguel has obtained my oath, an oath that I am not able to spurn.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَنْتَ تَرَى أَنَّ رَعُوئِيلَ قَدِ اسْتَحْلَفَنِي، وَلَسْتُ أَسْتَطِيعُ أَنْ أَسْتَخِفَّ بِحَلِفِهِ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            Then Raphael borrowed four of the servants of Raguel, and two camels, and he traveled to Rages, the city of the Medes. And upon finding Gabael, he gave him his handwritten note, and he received from him all the money.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Raphael borrowed four of the servants of Raguel, and two camels, and he traveled to Rages, the city of the Medes. And upon finding Gabael, he gave him his handwritten note, and he received from him all the money.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            حِينَئِذٍ أَخَذَ رَافَائِيلُ أَرْبَعَةً مِنْ غِلْمَانِ رَعُوئِيلَ وَجَمَلَيْنِ وَسَافَرَ إِلَى رَاجِيسَ مَدِينَةِ الْمَادِيِّينَ وَلَقِيَ غَابِيلُوسَ، فَدَفَعَ إِلَيْهِ صَكَّهُ، وَاسْتَوْفَى مِنْهُ الْمَالَ كُلَّهُ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            And he revealed to him, concerning Tobias the son of Tobit, all that had been done. And he made him come with him to the wedding celebration.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And he revealed to him, concerning Tobias the son of Tobit, all that had been done. And he made him come with him to the wedding celebration.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَعَرَّفَهُ أَمْرَ طُوبِيَّا بْنِ طُوبِيَّا وَكُلَّ مَا وَقَعَ، وَأَتَى بِهِ مَعَهُ إِلَى الْعُرْسِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            And when he had entered into the house of Raguel, he discovered Tobias reclining at table. And leaping up, they kissed each other. And Gabael wept, and he blessed God.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when he had entered into the house of Raguel, he discovered Tobias reclining at table. And leaping up, they kissed each other. And Gabael wept, and he blessed God.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلَمَّا دَخَلَ بَيْتَ رَعُوئِيلَ، وَجَدَ طُوبِيَّا مُتَّكِئاً، فَنَهَضَ قَائِماً، وَقَبَّلاَ بَعْضُهُمَا بَعْضاً، وَبَكَى غَابِيلُوسُ وَبَارَكَ اللهَ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            And he said: “May the God of Israel bless you, for you are the son of a man most noble and just, fearing God and performing almsgiving.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And he said: “May the God of Israel bless you, for you are the son of a man most noble and just, fearing God and performing almsgiving.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَالَ: «يُبَارِكُكَ الرَّبُّ إِلهُ إِسْرَائِيلَ لأَنَّكَ ابْنُ رَجُلٍ صَالِحٍ جِدًّا بَارٍّ مُتَّقٍ للهِ صَانِعِ صَدَقَاتٍ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            And may a blessing be spoken over your wife and over your parents.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And may a blessing be spoken over your wife and over your parents.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَتَحِلُّ الْبَرَكَةُ عَلَى زَوْجَتِكَ وَعَلَى وَالِدَيْكُمَا،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            And may you see your sons, and the sons of your sons, even to the third and fourth generation. And may your offspring be blessed by the God of Israel, who reigns forever and ever.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And may you see your sons, and the sons of your sons, even to the third and fourth generation. And may your offspring be blessed by the God of Israel, who reigns forever and ever.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَتَرَيَانِ بَنِيكُمَا وَبَنِي بَنِيكُمَا إِلَى الْجِيلِ الثَّالِثِ وَالرَّابِعِ، وَيَكُونُ نَسْلُكُمَا مُبَارَكاً مِنْ إِلهِ إِسْرَائِيلَ الْمَالِكِ إِلَى دَهْرِ الدُّهُورِ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            And when all had said, “Amen,” they approached the feast. But they also celebrated the marriage feast with the fear of the Lord.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when all had said, “Amen,” they approached the feast. But they also celebrated the marriage feast with the fear of the Lord.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالُوا كُلُّهُمْ: «آمِينَ». ثُمَّ تَقَدَّمُوا إِلَى الْوَلِيمَةِ، إِلاَّ أَنَّهُمُ اتَّخَذُوا وَلِيمَةَ الْعُرْسِ بِخَوْفِ اللهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="10">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            In truth, when Tobias was delayed because of the marriage celebration, his father Tobit was worried, saying: “Why do you think my son is delayed, or why has he been detained there?
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            In truth, when Tobias was delayed because of the marriage celebration, his father Tobit was worried, saying: “Why do you think my son is delayed, or why has he been detained there?
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَمَّا أَبْطَأَ طُوبِيَّا هُنَاكَ لِسَبَبِ الْعُرْسِ، قَلِقَ أَبُوهُ طُوبِيَّا وَقَالَ: «لِمَاذَا تُرَى أَبْطَأَ ابْنِي؟ وَمَا الَّذِي عَاقَهُ هُنَاكَ؟
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            Do you think that Gabael has died, and that no one will repay him the money?”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Do you think that Gabael has died, and that no one will repay him the money?”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَلَعَلَّ غَابِيلُوسَ قَدْ مَاتَ وَلَيْسَ مَنْ يَرُدُّ لَهُ الْمَالَ؟»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            And so he began to be exceedingly sad, both he and his wife Anna with him. And they both began to weep together, because their son did not at least return to them on the appointed day.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so he began to be exceedingly sad, both he and his wife Anna with him. And they both began to weep together, because their son did not at least return to them on the appointed day.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَخَذَهُ حُزْنٌ شَدِيدٌ هُوَ وَحَنَّةَ امْرَأَتَهُ، وَطَفِقَا كِلاَهُمَا يَبْكِيَانِ لِتَخَلُّفِ ابْنِهِمَا عَنِ الرُّجُوعِ فِي يَوْمِ الْمِيعَادِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            But his mother wept inconsolable tears, and also said: “Woe, woe to me, O my son. Why did we send you to journey far away, you: the light of our eyes, the staff of our old age, the solace of our life, the hope of our posterity?
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But his mother wept inconsolable tears, and also said: “Woe, woe to me, O my son. Why did we send you to journey far away, you: the light of our eyes, the staff of our old age, the solace of our life, the hope of our posterity?
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَانَتْ أُمُّهُ تَبْكِي بِدُمُوعٍ لاَ تَنْقَطِعُ وَهِيَ تَقُولُ: «آهِ أَوْهِ يَا بُنَيَّ، لِمَاذَا أَرْسَلْنَاكَ فِي الْغُرْبَةِ يَا نُورَ أَبْصَارِنَا وَعُكَّازَةَ شَيْخُوخَتِنَا وَعَزَاءَ عِيشَتِنَا وَرَجَاءَ عَقِبِنَا؟
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            Having all things together as one in you, we ought not to have dismissed you from us.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Having all things together as one in you, we ought not to have dismissed you from us.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لَقَدْ كَانَ لَنَا فِيكَ وَحْدَكَ كُلُّ شَيْءٍ، فَلَمْ يَكُنْ يَنْبَغِي لَنَا أَنْ نُرْسِلَكَ عَنَّا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            And Tobit was saying to her: “Be calm, and do not be troubled. Our son is safe. That man, with whom we sent him, is faithful enough.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Tobit was saying to her: “Be calm, and do not be troubled. Our son is safe. That man, with whom we sent him, is faithful enough.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَكَانَ طُوبِيَّا يَقُولُ لَهَا: «اسْكُتِي وَلاَ تَتَقَلَّقِي، إِنَّ ابْنَنَا سَالِمٌ وَالرَّجُلَ الَّذِي أَرْسَلْنَاهُ مَعَهُ ثِقَةٌ جِدًّا».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            Yet she was by no means able to be consoled. But, leaping up every day, she looked all round, and traveled around all the ways, by which there seemed any hope that he might return, so that she might possibly see him coming from afar.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Yet she was by no means able to be consoled. But, leaping up every day, she looked all round, and traveled around all the ways, by which there seemed any hope that he might return, so that she might possibly see him coming from afar.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلَمْ يَكُنْ ذلِكَ يُفِيدُهَا أَدْنَى تَعْزِيَةٍ، وَكَانَتْ كُلَّ يَوْمٍ تَقُومُ مُسْرِعَةً فَتَتَشَوَّفُ مِنْ كُلِّ جِهَةٍ، وَتَنْظُرُ فِي جَمِيعِ الطُّرُقِ الَّتِي كَانَتْ تَظُنُّ أَنَّ ابْنَهَا يَرْجِعُ مِنْهَا لَعَلَّهَا تَرَاهُ عَنْ بُعْدٍ مُقْبِلاً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            In truth, Raguel said to his son-in-law, “Remain here, and I will send a message of your health to your father Tobit.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            In truth, Raguel said to his son-in-law, “Remain here, and I will send a message of your health to your father Tobit.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَمَّا رَعُوئِيلُ فَقَالَ لِصِهْرِهِ: «امْكُثْ ههُنَا وَأَنَا أُنْفِذُ إِلَى طُوبِيَّا أَبِيكَ مَنْ يُخْبِرُهُ بِسَلاَمَتِكَ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            And Tobias said to him, “I know that my father and my mother have now counted the days, and their spirit must be tortured within them.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Tobias said to him, “I know that my father and my mother have now counted the days, and their spirit must be tortured within them.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُ طُوبِيَّا: «إِنِّي لأَعْلَمُ أَنَّ أَبِي وَأُمِّي يَحْسُبَانِ الأَيَّامِ وَأَرْوَاحُهُمَا مُعَذَّبَةٌ قَلَقاً».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            And when Raguel had repeatedly petitioned Tobias, and he was by no means willing to listen to him, he delivered Sarah to him, and half of all his substance: with men and women servants, with sheep, camels, and cows, and with much money. And he dismissed him away, in safety and gladness, from him,
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when Raguel had repeatedly petitioned Tobias, and he was by no means willing to listen to him, he delivered Sarah to him, and half of all his substance: with men and women servants, with sheep, camels, and cows, and with much money. And he dismissed him away, in safety and gladness, from him,
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَبَعْدَ أَنْ أَكْثَرَ رَعُوئِيلُ مِنَ الإِلْحَاحِ عَلَى طُوبِيَّا، فَأَبَى أَنْ يَسْمَعَ بِوَجْهٍ مِنَ الْوُجُوهِ، أَعْطَاهُ سَارَةَ وَنِصْفَ أَمْوَالِهِ كُلِّهَا مِنْ غِلْمَانٍ وَجَوَارٍ وَمَوَاشٍ وَإِبِلٍ وَبَقَرٍ وَفِضَّةٍ كَثِيرَةٍ، وَصَرَفَهُ مِنْ عِنْدِهِ بِسَلاَمٍ فَرِحاً،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            saying: “May the holy Angel of the Lord be with your journey, and may he lead you through unharmed, and may you discover that all is right concerning your parents, and may my eyes see your sons before I die.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            saying: “May the holy Angel of the Lord be with your journey, and may he lead you through unharmed, and may you discover that all is right concerning your parents, and may my eyes see your sons before I die.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            قَائِلاً: «مَلاَكُ الرَّبِّ الْقُدُّوسُ يَكُونُ فِي طَرِيقِكُمَا، وَيُبَلِّغُكُمَا سَالِمَيْنِ، وَتَجِدَانِ كُلَّ شَيْءٍ عِنْدَ أَبَوَيْكُمَا بِخَيْرٍ، وَتَرَى عَيْنَايَ بَنِيكُمَا قَبْلَ مَوْتِي».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            And the parents, taking hold of their daughter, kissed her and let her go:
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the parents, taking hold of their daughter, kissed her and let her go:
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَقْبَلَ الْوَالِدَانِ عَلَى ابْنَتِهِمَا يُقَبِّلاَنِهَا ثُمَّ صَرَفَاهَا،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            admonishing her to honor her father-in-law, to love her husband, to guide the family, to govern the household, and to behave irreproachably herself.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            admonishing her to honor her father-in-law, to love her husband, to guide the family, to govern the household, and to behave irreproachably herself.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَوْصَيَاهَا أَنْ تُكْرِمَ حَمَوَيْهَا، وَتُحِبَّ بَعْلَهَا، وَتُدَبِّرَ عِيَالَهَا، وَتَسُوسَ بَيْتَهَا، وَتَحْفَظَ نَفْسَهَا غَيْرَ مَلُومَةٍ.
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="11">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            And as they were returning, they came through to Haran, which is in the middle of the journey, opposite Nineveh, on the eleventh day.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And as they were returning, they came through to Haran, which is in the middle of the journey, opposite Nineveh, on the eleventh day.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَفِيمَا هُمْ رَاجِعُونَ، وَقَدْ بَلَغُوا إِلَى حَارَانَ الَّتِي فِي وَسَطِ الطَّرِيقِ جِهَةَ نِينَوَى فِي الْيَوْمِ الْحَادِي عَشَرَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            And the Angel said: “Brother Tobias, you know how you left behind your father.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the Angel said: “Brother Tobias, you know how you left behind your father.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            قَالَ الْمَلاَكُ: «يَا أَخِي طُوبِيَّا إِنَّكَ تَعْلَمُ كَيْفَ فَارَقْتَ أَبَاكَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            And so, if it pleases you, let us go on ahead, and let the family follow after us with a slower step, together with your bride, and with the animals.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, if it pleases you, let us go on ahead, and let the family follow after us with a slower step, together with your bride, and with the animals.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلْنَتَقَدَّمْ نَحْنُ إِنْ أَحْبَبْتَ، وَالْعِيَالُ وَزَوْجَتُكَ يَلْحَقُونَنَا عَلَى مَهْلٍ مَعَ الْمَوَاشِي».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            And since it pleased him to go on in this way, Raphael said to Tobias, “Take with you from the gall of the fish, for it will be necessary.” And so, Tobias took from its gall, and he went ahead.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And since it pleased him to go on in this way, Raphael said to Tobias, “Take with you from the gall of the fish, for it will be necessary.” And so, Tobias took from its gall, and he went ahead.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَإِذْ تَوَافَقَا عَلَى الْمُضِيِّ، قَالَ رَافَائِيلُ لِطُوبِيَّا: «خُذْ مَعَكَ مِنْ مَرَارَةِ الْحُوتِ، فَإِنَّ لَنَا بِهَا حَاجَةً». فَأَخَذَ طُوبِيَّا مِنَ الْمَرَارَةِ، وَانْطَلَقَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            But Anna sat beside the way every day, on the top of a hill, from where she would be able to see for a long distance.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But Anna sat beside the way every day, on the top of a hill, from where she would be able to see for a long distance.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَمَّا حَنَّةُ فَكَانَتْ كُلَّ يَوْمٍ تَجْلِسُ عِنْدَ الطَّرِيقِ عَلَى رَأْسِ الْجَبَلِ حَيْثُ كَانَتْ تَسْتَطِيعُ أَنْ تَنْظُرَ عَلَى بُعْدٍ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            And while she was watching for his arrival from that place, she looked far off, and soon she realized that her son was approaching. And running, she reported it to her husband, saying: “Behold, your son arrives.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And while she was watching for his arrival from that place, she looked far off, and soon she realized that her son was approaching. And running, she reported it to her husband, saying: “Behold, your son arrives.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلَمَّا كَانَتْ تَتَشَوَّفُ ذَاتَ يَوْمٍ مِنْ ذلِكَ الْمَوْضِعِ، نَظَرَتْ عَلَى بُعْدٍ، وَلِلْوَقْتِ عَرَفَتْ أَنَّهُ ابْنُهَا قَادِماً، فَبَادَرَتْ وَأَخْبَرَتْ بَعْلَهَا قَائِلَةً: «هُوَذَا ابْنُكَ آتٍ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            And Raphael said to Tobias: “As soon as you enter into your house, immediately adore the Lord your God. And, giving thanks to him, approach your father, and kiss him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Raphael said to Tobias: “As soon as you enter into your house, immediately adore the Lord your God. And, giving thanks to him, approach your father, and kiss him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَالَ رَافَائِيلُ لِطُوبِيَّا: «إِذَا دَخَلْتَ بَيْتَكَ، فَاسْجُدْ فِي الْحَالِ لِلرَّبِّ إِلهِكَ وَاشْكُرْ لَهُ، ثُمَّ ادْنُ مِنْ أَبِيكَ وَقَبِّلْهُ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            And immediately anoint his eyes from this gall of the fish, which you carry with you. For you should know that his eyes will soon be opened, and your father will see the light of heaven, and he will rejoice at the sight of you.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And immediately anoint his eyes from this gall of the fish, which you carry with you. For you should know that his eyes will soon be opened, and your father will see the light of heaven, and he will rejoice at the sight of you.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَاطْلِ لِسَاعَتِكَ عَيْنَيْهِ بِمَرَارَةِ الْحُوتِ هذِهِ الَّتِي مَعَكَ، وَاعْلَمْ أَنَّهُ لِلْحِينِ تَنْفَتِحُ عَيْنَاهُ، وَيَرَى أَبُوكَ ضَوْءَ السَّمَاءِ، وَيَفْرَحُ بِرُؤْيَتِكَ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            Then the dog, which had been with them in the way, ran ahead, and, arriving like a messenger, he showed his joy by fawning and wagging his tail.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then the dog, which had been with them in the way, ran ahead, and, arriving like a messenger, he showed his joy by fawning and wagging his tail.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            حِينَئِذٍ سَبَقَ الْكَلْبُ الَّذِي كَانَ مَعَهُ فِي الطَّرِيقِ، وَكَانَ كَأَنَّهُ بَشِيرٌ يُبْدِي مَسَرَّتَهُ بِبَصْبَصَةِ ذَنَبِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            And rising up, his blind father began to run, stumbling with his feet. And giving his hand to a servant, he ran on to meet his son.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And rising up, his blind father began to run, stumbling with his feet. And giving his hand to a servant, he ran on to meet his son.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَامَ أَبُوهُ وَهُوَ أَعْمَى وَجَعَلَ يجْرِي وَهُوَ يَتَعَثَّرُ بِرِجْلَيْهِ، فَنَاوَلَ يَدَهُ لِغُلاَمٍ وَخَرَجَ لِمُلاَقَاةِ ابْنِهِ
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            And receiving him, he kissed him, as did his wife, and they both began to weep for joy.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And receiving him, he kissed him, as did his wife, and they both began to weep for joy.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَاسْتَقْبَلَهُ وَقَبَّلَهُ هُوَ وَامْرَأَتُهُ، وَطَفِقَا كِلاَهُمَا يَبْكِيَانِ مِنَ الْفَرَحِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            And when they had adored God and had given thanks, they sat down together.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when they had adored God and had given thanks, they sat down together.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            ثُمَّ سَجَدُوا للهِ وَشَكَرُوا لَهُ وَجَلَسُوا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            Then Tobias, taking from the gall of the fish, anointed his father’s eyes.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Tobias, taking from the gall of the fish, anointed his father’s eyes.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَخَذَ طُوبِيَّا مِنْ مَرَارَةِ الْحُوتِ وَطَلَى عَيْنَيْ أَبِيهِ
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            And about half an hour passed, and then a white film began to come out of his eyes, like the membrane of an egg.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And about half an hour passed, and then a white film began to come out of his eyes, like the membrane of an egg.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَمَكَثَ مِقْدَارَ نِصْفِ سَاعَةٍ، فَبَدَأَ يَخْرُجُ مِنْ عَيْنَيْهِ غِشَاوَةٌ كَغِرْقِئ الْبَيْضِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            So, taking hold of it, Tobias pulled it away from his eyes, and immediately he received his sight.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            So, taking hold of it, Tobias pulled it away from his eyes, and immediately he received his sight.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَمْسَكَهَا طُوبِيَّا وَسَحَبَهَا مِنْ عَيْنَيْهِ، وَلِلْوَقْتِ عَادَ إِلَى طُوبِيَّا بَصَرُهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            And they glorified God: Tobit especially, and his wife, and all those who knew him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And they glorified God: Tobit especially, and his wife, and all those who knew him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَمَجَّدَ اللهَ هُوَ وَامْرَأَتُهُ وَكُلُّ مَنْ كَانَ يَعْرِفُهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            And Tobit said, “I bless you, O Lord God of Israel, because you have chastised me, and you have saved me, and behold, I see my son Tobias.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And Tobit said, “I bless you, O Lord God of Israel, because you have chastised me, and you have saved me, and behold, I see my son Tobias.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَالَ طُوبِيَّا: «أُبَارِكُكَ أَيُّهَا الرَّبُّ إِلهُ إِسْرَائِيلَ، لأَنَّكَ أَدَّبْتَنِي وَشَفَيْتَنِي، وَهَأَنَذَا أَرَى طُوبِيَّا وَلَدِي».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="18">
         <language id="English">
            And then, after seven days, Sarah, the wife of his son, and all the family arrived safely, along with the sheep, and the camels, and much money from his wife, but also with that money which he had received from Gabael.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And then, after seven days, Sarah, the wife of his son, and all the family arrived safely, along with the sheep, and the camels, and much money from his wife, but also with that money which he had received from Gabael.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَمَّا سَارَةُ كَنَّتُهُ فَوَصَلَتْ بَعْدَ سَبْعَةِ أَيَّامٍ هِيَ وَجَمِيعُ الْعِيَالِ بِسَلاَمٍ وَالْغَنَمُ وَالإِبِلُ وَمَالٌ كَثِيرٌ مِمَّا لِلْمَرْأَةِ مَعَ الْمَالِ الَّذِي اسْتَوْفَاهُ مِنْ غَابِيلُوسَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="19">
         <language id="English">
            And he explained to his parents all the benefits from God, which he had produced all around him, by means of the man who had led him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And he explained to his parents all the benefits from God, which he had produced all around him, by means of the man who had led him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَخْبَرَ أَبَوَيْهِ بِجَمِيعِ إِحْسَانَاتِ اللهِ الَّتِي أَنْعَمَ بِهَا عَلَيْهِ عَلَى يَدِ ذلِكَ الرَّجُلِ الَّذِي ذَهَبَ مَعَهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="20">
         <language id="English">
            And then Ahikar and Nadab arrived, the maternal first cousins of Tobias, rejoicing for Tobias, and congratulating with him for all the good things that God had revealed all around him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And then Ahikar and Nadab arrived, the maternal first cousins of Tobias, rejoicing for Tobias, and congratulating with him for all the good things that God had revealed all around him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَوَفَدَ عَلَى طُوبِيَّا أَحْيُورُ وَنَبَاطُ وَهُمَا ذُوَا قَرَابَةٍ لَهُ فَرِحَيْنِ وَهَنَّآهُ بِجَمِيعِ مَا مَنَّ اللهُ بِهِ عَلَيْهِ مِنَ الْخَيْرِ
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="21">
         <language id="English">
            And for seven days they feasted, and all were rejoicing with great joy.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And for seven days they feasted, and all were rejoicing with great joy.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَعَمِلُوا وَلِيمَةً سَبْعَةَ أَيَّامٍ، وَفَرِحُوا كُلُّهُمْ فَرَحاً عَظِيماً.
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="12">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            Then Tobit called his son to him, and he said to him, “What are we able to give to this holy man, who accompanied you?”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then Tobit called his son to him, and he said to him, “What are we able to give to this holy man, who accompanied you?”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            حِينَئِذٍ دَعَا طُوبِيَّا ابْنَهُ إِلَيْهِ وَقَالَ لَهُ: «مَاذَا تُرَى نُعْطِي هذَا الرَّجُلَ الْقِدِّيسَ الَّذِي ذَهَبَ مَعَكَ؟»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            Tobias, answering, said to his father: “Father, what wages shall we give him? And what could be worthy of his benefits?
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Tobias, answering, said to his father: “Father, what wages shall we give him? And what could be worthy of his benefits?
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَأَجَابَ طُوبِيَّا وَقَالَ لأَبِيهِ: «يَا أَبَتِ، أَيَّ أُجْرَةٍ نُعْطِيهِ، وَأَيُّ شَيْءٍ يَكُونُ مُؤَازِياً لإِحْسَانِهِ؟
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            He led me and he brought me back safely. He received the money from Gabael. He caused me to have my wife. And he confined the demon away from her. He caused joy to her parents. Myself, he rescued from being devoured by the fish. As for you, he also caused you to see the light of heaven. And so, we have been filled with all good things through him. What could we possibly give to him that would be worthy of these things?
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            He led me and he brought me back safely. He received the money from Gabael. He caused me to have my wife. And he confined the demon away from her. He caused joy to her parents. Myself, he rescued from being devoured by the fish. As for you, he also caused you to see the light of heaven. And so, we have been filled with all good things through him. What could we possibly give to him that would be worthy of these things?
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَخَذَنِي وَرَجَعَ بِي سَالِماً، وَالْمَالَ هُوَ اسْتَوْفَاهُ مِنْ عِنْدِ غَابِيلُوسَ، وَبِهِ حَصَلْتُ عَلَى زَوْجَتِي، وَهُوَ كُفَّ عَنْهَا الشَّيْطَانَ، وَفَرَّحَ أَبَوَيْهَا، وَخَلَّصَنِي مِنِ افْتِرَاسِ الْحُوتِ، وَإِيَّاكَ أَيْضاً هُوَ جَعَلَكَ تُبْصِرُ نُورَ السَّمَاءِ، وَبِهِ غُمِرْنَا بِكُلِّ خَيْرٍ. فَمَاذَا عَسَى أَنْ نُعْطِيَهُ مِمَّا يَكُونُ مُؤَازِياً لِهذِهِ؟
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            But I implore you, my father, to ask him if he would perhaps deign to take for himself half of all the things that have been brought.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But I implore you, my father, to ask him if he would perhaps deign to take for himself half of all the things that have been brought.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لكِنِّي أَسْأَلُكَ يَا أَبَتِ، أَنْ تَسْأَلْهُ هَلْ يَرْضَى أَنْ يَأْخُذَ النِّصْفَ مِنْ كُلِّ مَا جِئْنَا بِهِ؟»
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            And calling him, the father especially, and the son, they took him aside. And they began to petition him, so that he would deign to accept ownership of one half part of all things that they had brought.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And calling him, the father especially, and the son, they took him aside. And they began to petition him, so that he would deign to accept ownership of one half part of all things that they had brought.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَدَعَاهُ الْوَالِدُ وَوَلَدُهُ وَأَخَذَاهُ نَاحِيَةً وَجَعَلاَ يَسْأَلاَنِهِ أَنْ يَتَنَازَلَ وَيَقْبَلَ النِّصْفَ مِنْ جَمِيعِ مَا جَاءَا بِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            Then he said to them privately: “Bless the God of heaven, and confess to him in the sight of all who live, for he has acted in his mercy toward you.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then he said to them privately: “Bless the God of heaven, and confess to him in the sight of all who live, for he has acted in his mercy toward you.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            حِينَئِذٍ خَاطَبَهُمَا سِرًّا وَقَالَ: «بَارِكَا إِلهَ السَّمَاءِ وَاعْتَرِفَا لَهُ أَمَامَ جَمِيعِ الأَحْيَاءِ لِمَا آتَاكُمَا مِنْ مَرَاحِمِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            For it is good to conceal the secret of a king, just as it is also honorable to reveal and to confess the works of God.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For it is good to conceal the secret of a king, just as it is also honorable to reveal and to confess the works of God.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَمَّا سِرُّ الْمَلِكِ فَخَيْرٌ أَنْ يُكْتَمَ، وَأَمَّا أَعْمَالُ اللهِ فَإِذَاعَتُهَا وَالاِعْتِرَافُ بِهَا كَرَامَةٌ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            Prayer with fasting is good, and almsgiving is better than hiding away gold in storage.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Prayer with fasting is good, and almsgiving is better than hiding away gold in storage.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            صَالِحَةٌ الصَّلاَةُ مَعَ الصَّوْمِ، وَالصَّدَقَةُ خَيْرٌ مِنِ ادِّخَارِ كُنُوزِ الذَّهَبِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            For almsgiving delivers from death, and the same is what purges sins and makes one able to find mercy and everlasting life.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For almsgiving delivers from death, and the same is what purges sins and makes one able to find mercy and everlasting life.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنَّ الصَّدَقَةَ تُنَجِّي مِنَ الْمَوْتِ وَتَمْحُو الْخَطَايَا وَتُؤَهِّلُ الإِنْسَانَ لِنَوَالِ الرَّحْمَةِ وَالْحَيَاةِ الأَبَدِيَّةِ
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            But those who commit sin and iniquity are enemies to their own soul.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But those who commit sin and iniquity are enemies to their own soul.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَمَّا الَّذِينَ يَعْمَلُونَ الْمَعْصِيَةَ وَالإِثْمَ فَهُمْ أَعْدَاءٌ لأَنْفُسِهِمْ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            Therefore, I reveal the truth to you, and I will not hide the explanation from you.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Therefore, I reveal the truth to you, and I will not hide the explanation from you.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَمَّا أَنَا فَأُعْلِنُ لَكُمَا الْحَقَّ وَمَا أَكْتُمُ عَنْكُمَا أَمْراً مَسْتُوراً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            When you prayed with tears, and buried the dead, and left behind your dinner, and hid the dead by day in your house, and buried them by night: I offered your prayer to the Lord.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            When you prayed with tears, and buried the dead, and left behind your dinner, and hid the dead by day in your house, and buried them by night: I offered your prayer to the Lord.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            إِنَّكَ حِينَ كُنْتَ تُصَلِّي بِدُمُوعٍ وَتَدْفِنُ الْمَوْتَى وَتَتْرُكُ طَعَامَكَ وَتَخْبَأُ الْمَوْتَى فِي بَيْتِكَ نَهَاراً وَتَدْفِنُهُمْ لَيْلاً، كُنْتُ أَنَا أَرْفَعُ صَلاَتَكَ إِلَى الرَّبِّ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            And because you were acceptable to God, it was necessary for you to be tested by trials.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And because you were acceptable to God, it was necessary for you to be tested by trials.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَإِذْ كُنْتَ مَقْبُولاً أَمَامَ اللهِ كَانَ لاَ بُدَّ أَنْ تُمْتَحَنَ بِتَجْرِبَةٍ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            And now, the Lord has sent me to cure you, and to free Sarah, your son’s wife, from the demon.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And now, the Lord has sent me to cure you, and to free Sarah, your son’s wife, from the demon.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَالآنَ فَإِنَّ الرَّبَّ قَدْ أَرْسَلَنِي لأَشْفِيَكَ، وَأُخَلِّصَ سَارَةَ كَنَّتَكَ مِنَ الشَّيْطَانِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            For I am the Angel Raphael, one of seven, who stand before the Lord.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For I am the Angel Raphael, one of seven, who stand before the Lord.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَإِنِّي أَنَا رَافَائِيلُ الْمَلاَكُ أَحَدُ السَّبْعَةِ الْوَاقِفِينَ أَمَامَ الرَّبِّ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            And when they had heard these things, they were troubled, and being seized with fear, they fell upon the ground on their face.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when they had heard these things, they were troubled, and being seized with fear, they fell upon the ground on their face.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَلَمَّا سَمِعَا مَقَالَتَهُ هذِهِ، ارْتَاعَا وَسَقَطَا عَلَى أَوْجُهِهِمَا عَلَى الأَرْضِ مُرْتَعِدَيْنِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            And the Angel said to them: “Peace be to you. Fear not.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the Angel said to them: “Peace be to you. Fear not.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَقَالَ لَهُمَا الْمَلاَكُ: «سَلاَمٌ لَكُمْ، لاَ تَخَافُوا،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="18">
         <language id="English">
            For when I was with you, I was there by the will of God. Bless him, and sing to him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For when I was with you, I was there by the will of God. Bless him, and sing to him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنِّي لَمَّا كُنْتُ مَعَكُمْ إِنَّمَا كُنْتُ بِمَشِيئَةِ اللهِ، فَبَارِكُوهُ وَسَبِّحُوهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="19">
         <language id="English">
            Indeed, I seemed to eat and drink with you, but I make use of an invisible food and drink, which cannot be seen by men.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Indeed, I seemed to eat and drink with you, but I make use of an invisible food and drink, which cannot be seen by men.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَانَ يَظْهَرُ لَكُمْ أَنِّي آكُلُ وَأَشْرَبُ مَعَكُمْ، وَإِنَّمَا أَنَا أَتَّخِذُ طَعَاماً غَيْرَ مَنْظُورٍ وَشَرَاباً لاَ يُبْصِرُهُ بَشَرٌ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="20">
         <language id="English">
            Therefore, it is time that I return to him who sent me. But as for you, bless God, and describe all his wonders.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Therefore, it is time that I return to him who sent me. But as for you, bless God, and describe all his wonders.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَالآنَ قَدْ حَانَ أَنْ أَرْجِعَ إِلَى مَنْ أَرْسَلَنِي، وَأَنْتُمْ فَبَارِكُوا اللهَ وَحَدِّثُوا بِجَمِيعِ عَجَائِبِهِ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="21">
         <language id="English">
            And when he had said these things, he was taken from their sight, and they were not able to see him any longer.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And when he had said these things, he was taken from their sight, and they were not able to see him any longer.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَبَعْدَ أَنْ قَالَ هذَا، ارْتَفَعَ عَنْ أَبْصَارِهِمْ، فَلَمْ يَعُودُوا يُعَايِنُونَهُ بَعْدَ ذلِكَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="22">
         <language id="English">
            Then, lying prostrate for three hours upon their face, they blessed God. And rising up, they described all his wonders.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Then, lying prostrate for three hours upon their face, they blessed God. And rising up, they described all his wonders.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            حِينَئِذٍ لَبِثُوا ثَلاَثَ سَاعَاتٍ مُنْطَرِحِينَ عَلَى وُجُوهِهِمْ يُبَارِكُونَ اللهَ، ثُمَّ نَهَضُوا وَحَدَّثُوا بِجَمِيعِ عَجَائِبِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="13">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            And so, the elder Tobit, opening his mouth, blessed the Lord, and he said: “O Lord, you are great in eternity and your kingdom is with all ages.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, the elder Tobit, opening his mouth, blessed the Lord, and he said: “O Lord, you are great in eternity and your kingdom is with all ages.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            حِينَئِذٍ فَتَحَ طُوبِيَّا الشَّيْخُ فَاهُ مُبَارِكاً لِلرَّبِّ وَقَالَ: «عَظِيمٌ أَنْتَ يَا رَبُّ إِلَى الأَبَدِ وَفِي جَمِيعِ الدُّهُورِ مُلْكُكَ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            For you scourge, and you save. You lead down to the grave, and you bring up again. And there is no one who can escape from your hand.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For you scourge, and you save. You lead down to the grave, and you bring up again. And there is no one who can escape from your hand.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنَّكَ تَجْرَحُ وَتَشْفِي وَتُحْدِرُ إِلَى الْجَحِيمِ وَتُصْعِدُ مِنْهُ، وَلَيْسَ مَنْ يَفِرُّ مِنْ يَدِكَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            Confess to the Lord, O sons of Israel, and praise him in the sight of the nations.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Confess to the Lord, O sons of Israel, and praise him in the sight of the nations.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            اِعْتَرِفُوا لِلرَّبِّ يَا بَنِي إِسْرَائِيلَ وَسَبِّحُوهُ أَمَامَ جَمِيعِ الأُمَمِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            For, indeed, he has dispersed you among the Gentiles, who are ignorant of him, that you may proclaim his wonders, and that you may cause them to know that there is no other almighty God, except him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For, indeed, he has dispersed you among the Gentiles, who are ignorant of him, that you may proclaim his wonders, and that you may cause them to know that there is no other almighty God, except him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَإِنَّهُ فَرَّقَكُمْ بَيْنَ الأُمَمِ الَّذِينَ يَجْهَلُونَهُ لِكَيْ تُخْبِرُوا بِمُعْجِزَاتِهِ وَتُعَرِّفُوهُمْ أَنْ لاَ إِلهَ قَادِراً عَلَى كُلِّ شَيْءٍ سِوَاهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            He has chastised us because of our iniquities, and he will save us because of his mercy.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            He has chastised us because of our iniquities, and he will save us because of his mercy.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            هُوَ أَدَّبَنَا لأَجْلِ آثَامِنَا، وَهُوَ يُخَلِّصُنَا لأَجْلِ رَحْمَتِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            Therefore, look upon what he has done for us, and, with fear and trembling, confess to him. And extol the King of all ages with your works.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Therefore, look upon what he has done for us, and, with fear and trembling, confess to him. And extol the King of all ages with your works.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            اُنْظُرُوا الآنَ مَا صَنَعَ لَنَا، وَاعْتَرِفُوا لَهُ بِخَوْفٍ وَرِعْدَةٍ، وَمَجِّدُوا مَلِكَ الدُّهُورِ بِأَعْمَالِكُمْ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            But as for me, I will confess him in the land of my captivity. For he has revealed his majesty within a sinful nation.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But as for me, I will confess him in the land of my captivity. For he has revealed his majesty within a sinful nation.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَمَّا أَنَا فَفِي أَرْضِ جَلاَئِي أَعْتَرِفُ لَهُ، لأَنَّهُ أَظْهَرَ جَلاَلَهُ فِي أُمَّةٍ خَاطِئَةٍ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            And so, be converted, you sinners, and do justice in the presence of God, believing that he will act in his mercy toward you.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, be converted, you sinners, and do justice in the presence of God, believing that he will act in his mercy toward you.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            اِرْجِعُوا الآنَ أَيُّهَا الْخُطَاةُ وَاصْنَعُوا أَمَامَ اللهِ بِرًّا، وَاثِقِينَ بِأَنَّهُ يَصْنَعُ لَكُمْ رَحْمَةً.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            But I and my soul will rejoice in him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But I and my soul will rejoice in him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَمَّا أَنَا فَنَفْسِي تَتَهَلَّلُ بِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            Bless the Lord, all you his elect. Keep days of rejoicing, and confess to him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Bless the Lord, all you his elect. Keep days of rejoicing, and confess to him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            بَارِكُوا الرَّبَّ يَا جَمِيعَ مُخْتَارِيهِ، أَقِيمُوا أَيَّامَ فَرَحٍ وَاعْتَرِفُوا لَهُ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            O Jerusalem, the city of God, the Lord has chastised you for the works of your hands.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            O Jerusalem, the city of God, the Lord has chastised you for the works of your hands.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            يَا أُورُشَلِيمُ مَدِينَةَ اللهِ إِنَّ الرَّبَّ أَدَّبَكِ بِأَعْمَالِ يَدَيْكِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            Confess to the Lord with your good things, and bless the God of all ages, so that he may rebuild his tabernacle in you, and he may recall all the captives to you, and you may be glad in all ages and forever.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Confess to the Lord with your good things, and bless the God of all ages, so that he may rebuild his tabernacle in you, and he may recall all the captives to you, and you may be glad in all ages and forever.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            اُشْكُرِي للهِ نِعْمَتَهُ عَلَيْكِ، وَبَارِكِي إِلهَ الدُّهُورِ حَتَّى يَعُودَ فَيُشَيِّدَ مَسْكِنَهُ فِيكِ، وَيَرُدَّ إِلَيْكِ جَمِيعَ أَهْلِ الْجَلاَءِ، وَتَبْتَهِجِي إِلَى دَهْرِ الدُّهُورِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            You will shine with a splendid light, and all the ends of the earth will adore by you.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            You will shine with a splendid light, and all the ends of the earth will adore by you.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            تَتَلأْلَئِينَ بِسَنًى بَهِيجٍ وَجَمِيعُ شُعُوبِ الأَرْضِ لَكِ يَسْجُدُونَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            Nations from far away will come to you, bringing gifts. And in you, they shall adore the Lord, and they will hold your land in sanctification.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Nations from far away will come to you, bringing gifts. And in you, they shall adore the Lord, and they will hold your land in sanctification.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            يَزُورُكِ الأُمَمُ مِنَ الأَقَاصِي بِقَرَابِينِهِمْ وَيَسْجُدُونَ فِيكِ لِلرَّبِّ وَيَعْتَدُّونَ أَرْضَكِ أَرْضاً مُقَدَّسَةً،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            For they will invoke the Great Name in you.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For they will invoke the Great Name in you.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            لأَنَّهُمْ فِيكِ يَدْعُونَ الاِسْمَ الْعَظِيمَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            Those who despise you will be cursed, and all those who blaspheme by you will be condemned, and those who build you up will be blessed.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Those who despise you will be cursed, and all those who blaspheme by you will be condemned, and those who build you up will be blessed.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            مَلْعُونِينَ يَكُونُونَ الَّذِينَ اسْتَهَانُوا بِكِ، وَالَّذِينَ جَدَّفُوا عَلَيْكِ يُدَانُونَ، وَيُبَارَكُ الَّذِينَ يَبْنُونَكِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            But you will rejoice in your sons, because they will all be blessed, and they will be gathered together for the Lord.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But you will rejoice in your sons, because they will all be blessed, and they will be gathered together for the Lord.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَمَّا أَنْتِ فَتَفْرَحِينَ بِبَنِيكِ، لأَنَّهُمْ يُبَارَكُونَ كَافَّةً، وَإِلَى الرَّبِّ يَحْتَشِدُونَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="18">
         <language id="English">
            Blessed are all those who love you and who rejoice in your peace.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Blessed are all those who love you and who rejoice in your peace.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            طُوبَى لِلَّذِينَ يُحِبُّونَكِ وَيَفْرَحُونَ لَكِ بِالسَّلاَمِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="19">
         <language id="English">
            Bless the Lord, O my soul, for the Lord our God has freed Jerusalem, his city, from every one of her tribulations.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Bless the Lord, O my soul, for the Lord our God has freed Jerusalem, his city, from every one of her tribulations.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            بَارِكِي يَا نَفْسِي الرَّبَّ، لأَنَّ الرَّبَّ إِلهَنَا خَلَّصَ أُورُشَلِيمَ مَدِينَتَهُ مِنْ جَمِيعِ شَدَائِدِهَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="20">
         <language id="English">
            Happy will I be, if any of my offspring will be left to see the brightness of Jerusalem.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Happy will I be, if any of my offspring will be left to see the brightness of Jerusalem.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            طُوبَى لِي إِنْ بَقِيَ مِنْ ذُرِّيَّتِي مَنْ يُبْصِرُ بَهَاءَ أُورُشَلِيمَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="21">
         <language id="English">
            The gates of Jerusalem will be built from sapphire and emerald, and all its walls will be surrounded with precious stones.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            The gates of Jerusalem will be built from sapphire and emerald, and all its walls will be surrounded with precious stones.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            أَبْوَابُ أُورُشَلِيمَ مِنْ يَاقُوتٍ وَزُمُرُّدٍ وَكُلُّ مُحِيطِ أَسْوَارِهَا مِنْ حَجَرٍ كَرِيمٍ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="22">
         <language id="English">
            All its streets will be paved with stones, white and clean. And ‘Alleluia’ will be sung throughout its neighborhoods.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            All its streets will be paved with stones, white and clean. And ‘Alleluia’ will be sung throughout its neighborhoods.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَجَمِيعُ أَسْوَاقِهَا مَفْرُوشَةٌ بِحَجَرٍ أَبْيَضَ نَقِيٍّ، وَفِي شَوَارِعِهَا يُنْشَدُ هَلِّلُويَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="23">
         <language id="English">
            Blessed be the Lord, who has exalted it, and may he reign over it, forever and ever. Amen.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Blessed be the Lord, who has exalted it, and may he reign over it, forever and ever. Amen.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            مُبَارَكٌ الرَّبُّ الَّذِي عَظَّمَهَا، وَلِيَكُنْ مُلْكُهُ فِيهَا إِلَى دَهْرِ الدُّهُورِ. آمِينَ».
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>

   <chapter num="14">
      <verse num="1">
         <language id="English">
            And the sermon of Tobit was completed. And after Tobit received his sight, he lived forty-two years, and he saw the sons of his grandchildren.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the sermon of Tobit was completed. And after Tobit received his sight, he lived forty-two years, and he saw the sons of his grandchildren.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَفَرَغَ طُوبِيَّا مِنْ كَلاَمِهِ وَعَاشَ طُوبِيَّا بَعْدَمَا عَادَ بَصِيراً اثْنَتَيْنِ وَأَرْبَعِينَ سَنَةً، وَرَأَى بَنِي حَفَدَتِهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="2">
         <language id="English">
            And so, having completed one hundred and two years, he was buried honorably at Nineveh.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And so, having completed one hundred and two years, he was buried honorably at Nineveh.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَتَمَّتْ سِنُوهُ مِئَةً وَاثْنَتَيْنِ وَدُفِنَ بِكَرَامَةٍ فِي نِينَوَى.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="3">
         <language id="English">
            For he was fifty-six years old, when he lost the light of his eyes, and he was sixty years old, when he truly received it again.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For he was fifty-six years old, when he lost the light of his eyes, and he was sixty years old, when he truly received it again.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكَانَ حِينَ ذَهَبَ بَصَرُهُ ابْنَ سِتَّ وَخَمْسِينَ سَنَةً، وَعَادَ يُبْصِرُ وَهُوَ ابْنُ سِتِّينَ سَنَةً،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="4">
         <language id="English">
            And, in truth, the remainder of his life was in gladness. And so, with the good accomplishment of the fear of God, he departed in peace.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And, in truth, the remainder of his life was in gladness. And so, with the good accomplishment of the fear of God, he departed in peace.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَقَضَى بَقِيَّةَ حَيَاتِهِ مَسْرُوراً. وَإِذْ بَلَغَ مِنْ تَقْوَى اللهِ غَايَةً حَسَنَةً، انْتَقَلَ بِسَلاَمٍ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="5">
         <language id="English">
            But, in the hour of his death, he called to himself his son Tobias, along with his sons, the seven youths who were his grandsons, and he said to them:
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But, in the hour of his death, he called to himself his son Tobias, along with his sons, the seven youths who were his grandsons, and he said to them:
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَمَّا حَضْرَتْهُ الْوَفَاةُ، دَعَا ابْنَهُ طُوبِيَّا وَبَنِي ابْنِهِ السَّبْعَةَ الْفِتْيَانَ وَقَالَ لَهُمْ:
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="6">
         <language id="English">
            “Nineveh will pass away soon. For the word of the Lord goes forward, and our brothers, who have been dispersed away from the land of Israel, shall return to it.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            “Nineveh will pass away soon. For the word of the Lord goes forward, and our brothers, who have been dispersed away from the land of Israel, shall return to it.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            «قَدْ دَنَا دَمَارُ نِينَوَى، لأَنَّ كَلاَمَ الرَّبِّ لاَ يَذْهَبُ بَاطِلاً، وَإِخْوَتُنَا الَّذِينَ تَفَرَّقُوا مِنْ أَرْضِ إِسْرَائِيلَ يَرْجِعُونَ إِلَيْهَا،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="7">
         <language id="English">
            Thus its deserted land will be entirely filled again. And the house of God, which was burned like incense within it, will be rebuilt again. And all those who fear God will return there.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Thus its deserted land will be entirely filled again. And the house of God, which was burned like incense within it, will be rebuilt again. And all those who fear God will return there.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَكُلُّ أَرْضِهَا الْمُقْفِرَةِ سَتَمْتَلِئُ، وَبَيْتُ اللهِ الَّذِي أُحْرِقَ فِيهَا سَيُسْتَأْنَفُ بِنَاؤُهُ، وَسَيَرْجِعُ إِلَى هُنَاكَ جَمِيعُ خَائِفِي اللهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="8">
         <language id="English">
            And the Gentiles will relinquish their idols, and they will enter into Jerusalem, and they will dwell in it.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And the Gentiles will relinquish their idols, and they will enter into Jerusalem, and they will dwell in it.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَسَتَتْرُكُ الأُمَمُ أَصْنَامَهَا وَتَرْحَلُ إِلَى أُورُشَلِيمَ فَتُقِيمُ بِهَا.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="9">
         <language id="English">
            And all the kings of the earth will rejoice in it, adoring the King of Israel.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And all the kings of the earth will rejoice in it, adoring the King of Israel.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَتَفْرَحُ فِيهَا مُلُوكُ الأَرْضِ كَافَّةً سَاجِدَةً لِمَلِكِ إِسْرَائِيلَ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="10">
         <language id="English">
            Therefore, my sons, listen to your father. Serve the Lord in truth, and seek to do the things that please him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            Therefore, my sons, listen to your father. Serve the Lord in truth, and seek to do the things that please him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            اِسْمَعُوا يَا بَنِيَّ لأَبِيكُمُ، اعْبُدُوا الرَّبَّ بِحَقٍّ، وَابْتَغُوا عَمَلَ مَرْضَاتِهِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="11">
         <language id="English">
            And command your sons, so that they may accomplish justice and almsgiving, and so that they may be mindful of God and may bless him at all times, in truth and with all their strength.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And command your sons, so that they may accomplish justice and almsgiving, and so that they may be mindful of God and may bless him at all times, in truth and with all their strength.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَأَوْصُوا بَنِيكُمْ بِعَمَلِ الْعَدْلِ وَالصَّدَقَاتِ، وَأَنْ يَذْكُرُوا اللهَ وَيُبَارِكُوهُ كُلَّ حِينٍ بِالْحَقِّ وَبِكُلِّ طَاقَتِهِمْ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="12">
         <language id="English">
            And now, sons, listen to me, and do not remain here. But, on whatever day you will bury your mother near me in one sepulcher, from that time, direct your steps to leave this place.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And now, sons, listen to me, and do not remain here. But, on whatever day you will bury your mother near me in one sepulcher, from that time, direct your steps to leave this place.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            اِسْمَعُوا لِي يَا بَنِيَّ، لاَ تُقِيمُوا ههُنَا، بَلْ أَيَّ يَوْمٍ دَفَنْتُمْ وَالِدَتَكُمْ مَعِي فِي قَبْرٍ وَاحِدٍ فَفِي ذلِكَ الْيَوْمِ وَجِّهُوا خَطَوَاتِكُمْ لِلْخُرُوجِ مِنْ هذَا الْمَوْضِعِ،
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="13">
         <language id="English">
            For I see that its iniquity will bring about its end.”
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            For I see that its iniquity will bring about its end.”
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَإِنِّي أَرَى أَنَّ إِثْمَهُ سَيُهْلِكُهُ».
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="14">
         <language id="English">
            And it happened that, after the death of his mother, Tobias withdrew from Nineveh, with his wife, and sons, and sons of sons, and he was returned to his father-in-law.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And it happened that, after the death of his mother, Tobias withdrew from Nineveh, with his wife, and sons, and sons of sons, and he was returned to his father-in-law.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَكَانَ أَنَّ طُوبِيَّا بَعْدَ مَوْتِ أُمِّهِ، ارْتَحَلَ عَنْ نِينَوَى بِزَوْجَتِهِ وَبَنِيهِ وَبَنِي بَنِيهِ، وَرَجَعَ إِلَى حَمَوَيْهِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="15">
         <language id="English">
            And he found them unharmed in a good old age. And he took care of them, and he closed their eyes. And all the inheritance of the house of Raguel passed to him. And he saw the sons of his sons to the fifth generation.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And he found them unharmed in a good old age. And he took care of them, and he closed their eyes. And all the inheritance of the house of Raguel passed to him. And he saw the sons of his sons to the fifth generation.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            فَوَجَدَهُمَا سَالِمَيْنِ بِشَيْخُوخَةٍ صَالِحَةٍ فَاهْتَمَّ بِهِمَا، وَهُوَ أَغْمَضَ أَعْيُنَهُمَا، وَأَحْرَزَ كُلَّ مِيرَاثِ بَيْتِ رَعُوئِيلَ، وَرَأَى بَنِي بَنِيهِ إِلَى الْجِيلِ الْخَامِسِ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="16">
         <language id="English">
            And, having completed ninety-nine years in the fear of the Lord, with joy, they buried him.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            And, having completed ninety-nine years in the fear of the Lord, with joy, they buried him.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَبَعْدَ أَنِ اسْتَوْفَى تِسْعاً وَتِسْعِينَ سَنَةً فِي مَخَافَةِ الرَّبِّ، دُفِنَ بِفَرَحٍ.
         </language>
      </verse>

      <verse num="17">
         <language id="English">
            But all his family and all his lineage continued with a good life and in holy conversation, so that they were acceptable both to God and to men, as well as to everyone who dwelt in the land.
         </language><language id="Indonesian">
            But all his family and all his lineage continued with a good life and in holy conversation, so that they were acceptable both to God and to men, as well as to everyone who dwelt in the land.
         </language>
         <language id="Arabic">
            وَلَبِثَ كُلُّ ذَوِي قَرَابَتِهِ وَجَمِيعُ أَعْقَابِهِ فِي عِيشَةٍ صَالِحَةٍ وَسِيرَةٍ مُقَدَّسَةٍ، وَكَانُوا مَرْضِيِّينَ لَدَى اللهِ وَالنَّاسِ وَجَمِيعِ سُكَّانِ الأَرْضِ.
         </language>
      </verse>
   </chapter>
</book>