<book>
  <!-- Chunk 1/10: Chapters 1-2 -->
  <chapter num="1">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Love righteousness, ye that be judges of the earth: think of the Lord with a good (heart,) and in simplicity of heart seek him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">احبوا العدل يا قضاة الارض واعتقدوا في الرب خيرا والتمسوه بقلب سليم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Kasihilah kebenaran, hai para penguasa dunia, hendaklah pikiranmu tertuju kepada Tuhan dengan tulus ikhlas, dan carilah Dia dengan tulus hati!</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">For he will be found of them that tempt him not; and sheweth himself unto such as do not distrust him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فانما يجده الذين لا يجربونه ويتجلى للذين لا يكفرون به</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Ia membiarkan diri-Nya ditemukan oleh yang tidak mencobai-Nya, dan menampakkan diri kepada semua yang tidak menaruh syak wasangka terhadap-Nya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">For froward thoughts separate from God: and his power, when it is tried, reproveth the unwise.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">لان الافكار الزائغة تقصي من الله واختبار قدرته يثقف الجهال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Pikiran bengkang-bengkung menjauhkan dari pada Allah, dan kekuasaan-Nya yang diuji mengenyahkan orang bodoh.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">For into a malicious soul wisdom shall not enter; nor dwell in the body that is subject unto sin.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ان الحكمة لا تلج النفس الساعية بالمكر ولا تحل في الجسد المسترق للخطية</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Sebab kebijaksanaan tidak masuk ke dalam hati keruh, dan tidak pula tinggal dalam tubuh yang dikuasai oleh dosa.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">For the holy spirit of discipline will flee deceit, and remove from thoughts that are without understanding, and will not abide when unrighteousness cometh in.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">لان روح التاديب القدوس يهرب من الغش ويتحول عن الافكار السفيهة وينهزم اذا حضر الاثم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Roh pendidik yang suci menghindarkan tipu daya, dan pikiran pandir dijauhinya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">For wisdom is a loving spirit; and will not acquit a blasphemer of his words: for God is witness of his reins, and a true beholder of his heart, and a hearer of his tongue.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ان روح الحكمة محب للانسان فلا يبرئ المجدف مما نطق لان الله ناظر لكليتيه ورقيب لقلبه لا يغفل وسامع لفمه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Sebab kebijaksanaan adalah roh yang sayang akan manusia, tetapi orang penghujat tidak dibiarkannya terluput dari hukuman karena ucapan bibirnya. Memang Allah menyaksikan hati sanubarinya, benar-benar mengawasi isi hatinya dan mendengarkan ucapan lidahnya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">For the Spirit of the Lord filleth the world: and that which containeth all things hath knowledge of the voice.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">لان روح الرب ملا المسكونة وواسع الكل عنده علم كل كلمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Sebab roh Tuhan memenuhi dunia semesta, dan Ia yang merangkum segala-galanya mengetahui apapun yang disuarakan.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Therefore he that speaketh unrighteous things cannot be hid: neither shall vengeance, when it punisheth, pass by him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فلذلك لا يخفى عليه ناطق بسوء ولا ينجو من القضاء المفحم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Maka tidaklah tersembunyi siapa saja yang fasik bicaranya, dan tidak dilewatkan keadilan penghukum.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">For inquisition shall be made into the counsels of the ungodly: and the sound of his words shall come unto the Lord for the manifestation of his wicked deeds.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لكن سيفحص عن افكار المنافق وكل ما سمع من اقواله يبلغ الى الرب فيحكم على اثامه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Rencana orang fasik akan diselidiki kelak, dan laporan tentang perkataannya sampai ke hadapan Tuhan, supaya pelanggaran-pelanggarannya dihukum.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">For the ear of jealousy heareth all things: and the noise of murmurings is not hid.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لان الاذن الغيرى تسمع كل شيء وصياح المتذمرين لا يخفى عليها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Sebab telinga-Nya dengan cemburu mendengar segala sesuatu, malah bunyi gerutupun tak tersembunyi.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Therefore beware of murmuring, which is unprofitable; and refrain your tongue from backbiting: for there is no word so secret, that shall go for nought: and the mouth that belieth slayeth the soul.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فاحترزوا من التذمر الذي لا خير فيه وكفوا السنتكم عن الثلب فان المنطوق به في الخفية لا يذهب سدى والفم الكاذب يقتل النفس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Jadi, waspadalah terhadap gerutu yang sia-sia, dan awasilah lidahmu agar jangan memfitnah. Karena omongan tersembunyipun pasti ada akibatnya, dan mulut yang berdusta mematikan orang.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">Seek not death in the error of your life: and pull not upon yourselves destruction with the works of your hands.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">لا تغاروا على الموت في ضلال حياتكم ولا تجلبوا عليكم الهلاك باعمال ايديكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Jangan mencari-cari maut dengan hidup sesat, dan kebinasaan jangan kamu tarik dengan perbuatan tanganmu.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">For God made not death: neither hath he pleasure in the destruction of the living.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">اذ ليس الموت من صنع الله ولا هلاك الاحياء يسره</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Memang maut tidak dibuat oleh Allah, dan Iapun tak bergembira karena yang hidup musnah lenyap.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">For he created all things, that they might have their being: and the generations of the world were healthful; and there is no poison of destruction in them, nor the kingdom of death upon the earth:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">لانه انما خلق الجميع للبقاء فمواليد العالم انما كونت معافاة وليس فيها سم مهلك ولا ولاية للجحيم على الارض</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Sebaliknya Ia menciptakan segala-galanya supaya ada, dan supaya makhluk-makhluk jagat menyelamatkan. Di antaranyapun tidak ada racun yang membinasakan, dan dunia orang mati tidak merajai bumi.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">(For righteousness is immortal:)</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">لان البر خالد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Maka kesucian mesti baka.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">But ungodly men with their works and words called it to them: for when they thought to have it their friend, they consumed to nought, and made a covenant with it, because they are worthy to take part with it.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لكن المنافقين هم استدعوا الموت بايديهم واقوالهم ظنوه حليفا لهم فاضمحلوا وانما عاهدوه لانهم اهل ان يكونوا من حزبه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Tetapi dengan perbuatan dan kata para fasik telah memanggil maut dan didambakannya sambil memandangnya sebagai sahabat. Mereka mengadakan perjanjian dengannya, oleh karena mereka patut menjadi bagiannya.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <chapter num="2">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">For the ungodly said, reasoning with themselves, but not aright, Our life is short and tedious, and in the death of a man there is no remedy: neither was there any man known to have returned from the grave.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">فانهم بزيغ افكارهم قالوا في انفسهم ان حياتنا قصيرة شقية وليس لممات الانسان من دواء ولم يعلم قط ان احدا رجع من الجحيم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Karena angan-angannya tidak tepat maka berkatalah mereka satu sama lain: "Pendek dan menyedihkan hidup kita ini, dan pada akhir hidup manusia tidak ada obat mujarab; seseorang yang kembali dari dunia orang mati tidak dikenal.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">For we are born at all adventure: and we shall be hereafter as though we had never been: for the breath in our nostrils is as smoke, and a little spark in the moving of our heart:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">انا ولدنا اتفاقا وسنكون من بعد كانا لم نكن قط لان النسمة في انافنا دخان والنطق شرارة من حركة قلوبنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Serba kebetulan kita dijadikan, dan kelak kita ini seolah-olah tak pernah ada. Asap sajalah nafas di dalam hidung kita, dan pikiran hanya merupakan bunga api dari denyut jantung kita.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">Which being extinguished, our body shall be turned into ashes, and our spirit shall vanish as the soft air,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فاذا انطفات عاد الجسم رمادا وانحل الروح كنسيم رقيق وزالت حياتنا كاثر غمامة واضمحلت مثل ضباب يسوقه شعاع الشمس ويسقط بحرها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Setelah padam maka tubuh akan menjadi abu, dan rohnya akan disebar-sebarkan bagaikan udara yang halus.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">And our name shall be forgotten in time, and no man shall have our works in remembrance, and our life shall pass away as the trace of a cloud, and shall be dispersed as a mist, that is driven away with the beams of the sun, and overcome with the heat thereof.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و بعد حين ينسى اسمنا ولا يذكر احد اعمالنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Maka lambat laun nama kitapun terlupa pula, dan pekerjaan kita tidak seorangpun ingat kepadanya. Laksana jejak awan hidup kita berlalu, bagaikan kabut menghilang, dan dienyahkan oleh sinar matahari terkena oleh panas teriknya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">For our time is a very shadow that passeth away; and after our end there is no returning: for it is fast sealed, so that no man cometh again.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">انما حياتنا ظل يمضي ولا مرجع لنا بعد الموت لانه يختم علينا فلا يعود احد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Umur hidup kita merupakan bayang-bayang yang berlalu, dan akhir hidup kita tak dapat ditunda, karena sudah dimeteraikan dan tak seorangpun dapat merubahnya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">Come on therefore, let us enjoy the good things that are present: and let us speedily use the creatures like as in youth.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فتعالوا نتمتع بالطيبات الحاضرة ونبتدر منافع الوجود ما دمنا في الشبيبة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Jadi, marilah kita menikmati hal-hal baik yang masih ada, dan bergegas menggunakan alam seperti di masa muda!</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">Let us fill ourselves with costly wine and ointments: and let no flower of the spring pass by us:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">و نترو من الخمر الفاخرة ونتضمخ بالادهان ولا تفتنا زهرة الاوان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Marilah kita manfaatkan air anggur yang mahal serta wangi-wangian sepuas-puasnya, dan bunga musim semi janganlah kita lewatkan!</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Let us crown ourselves with rosebuds, before they be withered:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">و نتكلل بالورد قبل ذبوله ولا يكن مرج الا تمر لنا فيه لذة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Marilah kita mengenakan karangan kuncup mawar sebelum jadi layu!</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">Let none of us go without his part of our voluptuousness: let us leave tokens of our joyfulness in every place: for this is our portion, and our lot is this.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">و لا يكن فينا من لا يشترك في لذاتنا ولنترك في كل مكان اثار الفرح فان هذا حظنا ونصيبنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Di antara kita jangan seorangpun mengelakkan diri dari kesukaan kita! Hendaklah di mana-mana kita tinggalkan tanda-tanda keriangan kita, sebab itulah bagian dan nasib kita!"</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">Let us oppress the poor righteous man, let us not spare the widow, nor reverence the ancient gray hairs of the aged.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لنجر على الفقير الصديق ولا نشفق على الارملة ولا نهب شيبة الشيخ الكثير الايام</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">"Mari kita menindas orang miskin yang benar, jangan kita mengasihani janda, dan jangan peduli akan uban orang yang lanjut usia.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Let our strength be the law of justice: for that which is feeble is found to be nothing worth.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">و لتكن قوتنا هي شريعة العدل فانه من الثابت ان الضعف لا يغني شيئا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Kekuatan kita hendaknya menjadi kaidah keadilan, sebab yang lemah ternyata tidak berguna.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">Therefore let us lie in wait for the righteous; because he is not for our turn, and he is clean contrary to our doings: he upbraideth us with our offending the law, and objecteth to our infamy the transgressings of our education.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">و لنكمن للصديق فانه ثقيل علينا يقاوم اعمالنا ويقرعنا على مخالفتنا للناموس ويفضح ذنوب سيرتنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Marilah kita menghadang orang yang baik, sebab bagi kita ia menjadi gangguan serta menentang pekerjaan kita. Pelanggaran-pelanggaran hukum dituduhkannya kepada kita, dan kepada kita dipersalahkannya dosa-dosa terhadap pendidikan kita.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">He professeth to have the knowledge of God: and he calleth himself the child of the Lord.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">يزعم ان عنده علم الله ويسمي نفسه ابن الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Ia membanggakan mempunyai pengetahuan tentang Allah, dan menyebut dirinya anak Tuhan.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">He was made to reprove our thoughts.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و قد صار لنا عذولا حتى على افكارنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Bagi kita ia merupakan celaan atas anggapan kita, hanya melihat dia saja sudah berat rasanya bagi kita.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">He is grievous unto us even to behold: for his life is not like other men's, his ways are of another fashion.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">بل منظره ثقيل علينا لان سيرته تخالف سيرة الناس وسبله تباين سبلهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Sebab hidupnya sungguh berlainan dari kehidupan orang lain, dan lain dari lainlah langkah lakunya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">We are esteemed of him as counterfeits: he abstaineth from our ways as from filthiness: he pronounceth the end of the just to be blessed, and maketh his boast that God is his father.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">قد حسبنا كزيوف فهو يجانب طرقنا مجانبة الرجس ويغبط موت الصديقين ويتباهى بان الله ابوه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Kita dianggap olehnya sebagai orang yang tidak sejati, dan langkah laku kita dijauhinya seolah-olah najis adanya. Akhir hidup orang benar dipujinya bahagia, dan ia bermegah-megah bahwa bapanya ialah Allah.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">Let us see if his words be true: and let us prove what shall happen in the end of him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فلننظر هل اقواله حق ولنختبر كيف تكون عاقبته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Coba kita lihat apakah perkataannya benar dan ujilah apa yang terjadi waktu ia berpulang.</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">For if the just man be the son of God, he will help him, and deliver him from the hand of his enemies.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فانه ان كان الصديق ابن الله فهو ينصره وينقذه من ايدي مقاوميه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Jika orang yang benar itu sungguh anak Allah, niscaya Ia akan menolong dia serta melepaskannya dari tangan para lawannya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">Let us examine him with despitefulness and torture, that we may know his meekness, and prove his patience.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">فلنمتحنه بالشتم والعذاب حتى نعلم حلمه ونختبر صبره</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Mari, kita mencobainya dengan aniaya dan siksa, agar kita mengenal kelembutannya serta menguji kesabaran hatinya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">Let us condemn him with a shameful death: for by his own saying he shall be respected.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">و لنقض عليه باقبح ميتة فانه سيفتقد كما يزعم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Hendaklah kita menjatuhkan hukuman mati keji terhadapnya, sebab menurut katanya ia pasti mendapat pertolongan."</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">Such things they did imagine, and were deceived: for their own wickedness hath blinded them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">هذا ما ارتاوه فضلوا لان شرهم اعماهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Demikianlah mereka berangan-angan, tapi mereka sesat, karena telah dibutakan oleh kejahatan mereka.</language></verse>
    <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">As for the mysteries of God, they knew them not: neither hoped they for the wages of righteousness, nor discerned a reward for blameless souls.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">فلم يدركوا اسرار الله ولم يرجوا جزاء القداسة ولم يعتبروا ثواب النفوس الطاهرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Maka mereka tidak tahu akan rahasia-rahasia Allah, tidak yakin akan ganjaran kesucian, dan tidak menghargakan kemuliaan bagi jiwa yang murni.</language></verse>
    <verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23">For God created man to be immortal, and made him to be an image of his own eternity.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">فان الله خلق الانسان خالدا وصنعه على صورة ذاته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Sebab Allah telah menciptakan manusia untuk kebakaan, dan dijadikan-Nya gambar hakekat-Nya sendiri.</language></verse>
    <verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24">Nevertheless through envy of the devil came death into the world: and they that do hold of his side do find it.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">لكن بحسد ابليس دخل الموت الى العالم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">Tetapi karena dengki setan maka maut masuk ke dunia, dan yang menjadi milik setan mencari maut itu.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <!-- Chunk 2/10: Chapters 3-4 -->
  <chapter num="3">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">But the souls of the righteous are in the hand of God, and there shall no torment touch them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">اما نفوس الصديقين فهي بيد الله فلا يمسها العذاب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Tetapi jiwa orang benar ada di tangan Allah, dan siksaan tiada menimpa mereka.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">In the sight of the unwise they seemed to die: and their departure is taken for misery,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">و في ظن الجهال انهم ماتوا وقد حسب خروجهم شقاء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Menurut pandangan orang bodoh mereka mati nampaknya, dan pulang mereka dianggap malapetaka,</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">And their going from us to be utter destruction: but they are in peace.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و ذهابهم عنا عطبا اما هم ففي السلام</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">dan kepergiannya dari kita dipandang sebagai kehancuran, namun mereka berada dalam ketenteraman.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">For though they be punished in the sight of men, yet is their hope full of immortality.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و مع انهم قد عوقبوا في عيون الناس فرجاؤهم مملوء خلودا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Kalaupun mereka disiksa menurut pandangan manusia, namun harapan mereka penuh kebakaan.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">And having been a little chastised, they shall be greatly rewarded: for God proved them, and found them worthy for himself.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">و بعد تاديب يسير لهم ثواب عظيم لان الله امتحنهم فوجدهم اهلا له</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Setelah disiksa sebentar mereka menerima anugerah yang besar, sebab Allah hanya menguji mereka, lalu mendapati mereka layak bagi diri-Nya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">As gold in the furnace hath he tried them, and received them as a burnt offering.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">محصهم كالذهب في البودقة وقبلهم كذبيحة محرقة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Laksana emas dalam dapur api diperiksalah mereka oleh-Nya, lalu diterima bagaikan korban bakaran.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">And in the time of their visitation they shall shine, and run to and fro like sparks among the stubble.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فهم في وقت افتقادهم يتلالاون ويسعون سعي الشرار بين القصب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Maka pada waktu pembalasan mereka akan bercahaya, dan laksana bunga api berlari-larian di ladang jerami.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">They shall judge the nations, and have dominion over the people, and their Lord shall reign for ever.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">و يدينون الامم ويتسلطون على الشعوب ويملك ربهم الى الابد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Mereka akan mengadili para bangsa dan memerintah sekalian rakyat, dan Tuhan berkenan memerintah mereka selama-lamanya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">They that put their trust in him shall understand the truth: and such as be faithful in love shall abide with him: for grace and mercy is to his saints, and he hath care for his elect.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">المتوكلون عليه سيفهمون الحق والامناء في المحبة سيلازمونه لان النعمة والرحمة لمختاريه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Orang yang telah percaya pada Allah akan memahami kebenaran, dan yang setia dalam kasih akan tinggal pada-Nya. Sebab kasih setia dan belas kasihan menjadi bagian orang-orang pilihan-Nya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">But the ungodly shall be punished according to their own imaginations, which have neglected the righteous, and forsaken the Lord.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">اما المنافقون فسينالهم العقاب الخليق بمشوراتهم اذ استهانوا بالصديق وارتدوا عن الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Tetapi para fasik mendapat hukuman sesuai dengan angan-angannya, oleh karena mereka tidak menghiraukan yang benar dan telah murtad dari pada Tuhan.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">For whoso despiseth wisdom and nurture, he is miserable, and their hope is vain, their labours unfruitful, and their works unprofitable:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لان مزدري الحكمة والتاديب شقي انما رجاؤهم باطل واتعابهم بلا ثمرة واعمالهم لا فائدة فيها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Sungguh celakalah orang yang menghina kebijaksanaan dan ketertiban, hampalah harapan mereka dan sia-sialah jerih payahnya, dan segenap pekerjaannya percuma adanya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">Their wives are foolish, and their children wicked:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">نساوهم سفيهات واولادهم اشرار</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Para isteri mereka adalah bodoh, dan buruklah anak-anak mereka, keturunannya terkutuk.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">Their offspring is cursed. Wherefore blessed is the barren that is undefiled, which hath not known the sinful bed: she shall have fruit in the visitation of souls.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">و نسلهم ملعون اما العاقر الطاهرة التي لم تعرف المضجع الفاحش فطوبى لها انها ستحوز ثمرتها في افتقاد النفوس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Tetapi berbahagialah perempuan mandul yang tak bercela dan tidak melanggar hukum di ranjang perkawinan; ia akan memetik buahnya pada hari pembalasan sekalian jiwa.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">And blessed is the eunuch, which with his hands hath wrought no iniquity, nor imagined wicked things against God: for unto him shall be given the special gift of faith, and an inheritance in the temple of the Lord more acceptable to his mind.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و طوبى للخصي الذي لم تباشر يده ماثما ولا افتكر قلبه بشر على الرب فانه سيعطى نعمة سامية لامانته وحظا شهيا في هيكل الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Demikianpun orang kebiri yang tangannya tidak berbuat jahat, dan yang tidak merencanakan yang buruk terhadap Tuhan. Untuk kesetiaannya ia akan diberi anugerah pilihan, dan bagian yang menyenangkan dalam Bait Tuhan.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">For glorious is the fruit of good labours: and the root of wisdom shall never fall away.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">لان ثمرة الاتعاب الصالحة فاخرة وجرثومة الفطنة راسخة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Sebab terpujilah buah hasil jerih payah yang baik, dan akar pengertianpun tak dapat binasa.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">As for the children of adulterers, they shall not come to their perfection, and the seed of an unrighteous bed shall be rooted out.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">اما اولاد الزناة فلا يبلغون اشدهم وذرية المضجع الاثيم تنقرض</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Sebaliknya anak orang berzinah tidak menjadi dewasa, dan keturunan dari ranjang tak halal akan lenyap.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">For though they live long, yet shall they be nothing regarded: and their last age shall be without honour.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ان طالت حياتهم فانهم يحسبون كلا شيء وفي اواخرهم تكون شيخوختهم بلا كرامة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Kalaupun mereka panjang umurnya, namun tidak dihargai sama sekali, dan hari tua mereka akhirnya tidak terhormat;</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">Or, if they die quickly, they have no hope, neither comfort in the day of trial.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و ان ماتوا سريعا فلا يكون لهم رجاء ولا عزاء في يوم الحساب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">jika mereka lekas mati, maka tidak ada harapan bagi mereka, dan pada hari penghakiman mereka tidak mendapat hiburan.</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">For horrible is the end of the unrighteous generation.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">لان عاقبة الجيل الاثيم هائلة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Sebab bangsa orang yang lalim beratlah ajalnya.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <chapter num="4">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Better it is to have no children, and to have virtue: for the memorial thereof is immortal: because it is known with God, and with men.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ان البتولية مع الفضيلة اجمل فان معها ذكرا خالدا لانها تبقى معلومة عند الله والناس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Dari pada begitu lebih baik tidak beranak tapi memiliki keutamaan, sebab kenangan akan keutamaan adalah baka, karena dikenal baik oleh Allah maupun oleh manusia.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">When it is present, men take example at it; and when it is gone, they desire it: it weareth a crown, and triumpheth for ever, having gotten the victory, striving for undefiled rewards.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اذا حضرت يقتدى بها واذا غابت يشتاق اليها ومدى الدهور تفتخر باكليل الظفر بعد انتصارها في ساحة المعارك الطاهرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Jika ada keutamaan maka diteladan, jika sudah lenyap maka dirindukan orang. Selama-lamanya ia jaya sambil memakai karangan, karena telah menang dalam gelanggang pertandingan yang tak bercela.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">But the multiplying brood of the ungodly shall not thrive, nor take deep rooting from bastard slips, nor lay any fast foundation.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">اما لفيف المنافقين الكثير التوالد فلا ينجح وفراخهم النغلة لا تتعمق اصولها ولا تقوم على ساق راسخة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Jumlah besar anak para fasik tak menguntungkan, dan mereka tidak berakar dalam karena berasal dari carang tak asli, tidak pula mendapat alas yang kokoh kuat.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">For though they flourish in branches for a time; yet standing not last, they shall be shaken with the wind, and through the force of winds they shall be rooted out.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و ان اخرجت فروعا الى حين فانها لعدم رسوخها تزعزعها الريح وتقتلعها الزوبعة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Kalaupun beberapa lamanya ranting-rantingnya subur, namun digoyah-goyahkan angin karena tidak tertanam kokoh kuat, lalu terbantun karena hebatnya angin.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">The imperfect branches shall be broken off, their fruit unprofitable, not ripe to eat, yea, meet for nothing.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فتنقصف فروعها قبل اناها وتكون ثمرتها خبيثة غير ناضجة للاكل ولا تصلح لشيء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Cabang-cabang itu dipatahkan sebelum selesai tumbuhnya, buah mereka tidak berguna, terlalu mentah untuk dimakan dan sia-sia belaka.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">For children begotten of unlawful beds are witnesses of wickedness against their parents in their trial.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">و المولودون من المضجع الاثيم يشهدون بفاحشة والديهم عند استنطاق حالهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Sebab anak-anak hasil seketiduran yang haram menjadi saksi keburukan bagi orang tuanya pada waktu pemeriksaan.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">But though the righteous be prevented with death, yet shall he be in rest.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">اما الصديق فانه وان تعجله الموت يستقر في الراحة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Tetapi orang benar akan mendapat istirahat, meskipun mati sebelum waktunya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">For honourable age is not that which standeth in length of time, nor that is measured by number of years.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لان الشيخوخة المكرمة ليست هي القديمة الايام ولا هي تقدر بعدد السنين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Sebab usia lanjut adalah terhormat bukan karena waktunya panjang dan bukan karena tahunnya berjumlah banyak.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">But wisdom is the gray hair unto men, and an unspotted life is old age.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">و لكن شيب الانسان هو الفطنة وسن الشيخوخة هي الحياة المنزهة عن العيب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Tetapi pengertian orang adalah uban, dan hidup yang tak bercela merupakan usia yang lanjut.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">He pleased God, and was beloved of him: so that living among sinners he was translated.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">انه كان مرضيا لله فاحبه وكان يعيش بين الخطاة فنقله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Karena berkenan pada Allah maka orang benar dikasihi, ia dipindahkan sedang masih hidup di tengah-tengah orang berdosa;</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Yea speedily was he taken away, lest that wickedness should alter his understanding, or deceit beguile his soul.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">خطفه لكي لا يغير الشر عقله ولا يطغي الغش نفسه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">ia disentak, supaya kejahatan jangan mengubah budinya, dan tipu daya jangan membujuk jiwanya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">For the bewitching of naughtiness doth obscure things that are honest; and the wandering of concupiscence doth undermine the simple mind.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">لان سحر الاباطيل يغشي الخير ودوار الشهوة يطيش العقل السليم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Sebab pengaruh dari yang buruk menyuramkan yang baik, dan tumpukan hawa nafsu mengubah roh yang tak bercela.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">He, being made perfect in a short time, fulfilled a long time:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">قد بلغ الكمال في ايام قليلة فكان مستوفيا سنين كثيرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Karena sempurna dalam waktu yang pendek, maka orang benar memenuhi waktu yang panjang.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">For his soul pleased the Lord: therefore hasted he to take him away from among the wicked.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و اذ كانت نفسه مرضية للرب فقد اخرج سريعا من بين الشرور اما الشعوب فابصروا ولم يفقهوا ولم يجعلوا هذا فيقلوبهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Tuhan berkenan kepada jiwanya, maka iapun diambil dari tengah-tengah kejahatan. Memang orang melihat tapi tak mengerti, dan tidak menaruh perhatian kepada yang berikut ini:</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">This the people saw, and understood it not, neither laid they up this in their minds, That his grace and mercy is with his saints, and that he hath respect unto his chosen.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ان نعمته ورحمته لمختاريه وافتقاده لقديسيه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Kasih setia dan belas kasihan menjadi bagian orang pilihan Allah, bagi orang suci tersedia perlindungan-Nya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">Thus the righteous that is dead shall condemn the ungodly which are living; and youth that is soon perfected the many years and old age of the unrighteous.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لكن الصديق الذي قد مات يحكم على المنافقين الباقين بعده الشبيبة السريعة الكمال تحكم على شيخوخة الاثيم الكثيرة السنين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Maka orang benar yang meninggal menghukum orang fasik yang hidup, dan masa muda yang lekas sempurna menghukum umur panjang orang yang lalim.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">For they shall see the end of the wise, and shall not understand what God in his counsel hath decreed of him, and to what end the Lord hath set him in safety.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فانهم يبصرون موت الحكيم ولا يفقهون ماذا اراد الرب به ولماذا نقله الى عصمته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Sungguhpun mereka melihat ajal orang yang bijak, tetapi tak mengerti apa yang direncanakan Tuhan baginya dan mengapa ia diamankan Tuhan.</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">They shall see him, and despise him; but God shall laugh them to scorn: and they shall hereafter be a vile carcase, and a reproach among the dead for evermore.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">يبصرون ويزدرون والرب يستهزئ بهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Orang fasik melihat lalu menghina, tetapi mereka akan ditertawakan Tuhan.</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">For he shall rend them, and cast them down headlong, that they shall be speechless; and he shall shake them from the foundation; and they shall be utterly laid waste, and be in sorrow; and their memorial shall perish.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">سيسقطون من بعد سقوطا مهينا ويكونون عارا بين الاموات مدى الدهور فانه يحطمهم وهم مبلسون مطرقون ويقتلعهم من الاسس ويتم خرابهم فيكونون في العذاب وذكرهم يهلك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Sesudahnya mereka menjadi mayat terhina, dan di tengah-tengah orang mati menjadi buah cemooh selama-lamanya. Terpelanting tak bersuara mereka dicampakkan Tuhan, dan digoyahkan-Nya dari dasar-dasarnya. Mereka akan dimusnahkan sama sekali, dan akan berada dalam sengsara. Maka kenangan kepada mereka akan lenyap.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">And when they cast up the accounts of their sins, they shall come with fear: and their own iniquities shall convince them to their face.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">يتقدمون فزعين من تذكر خطاياهم واثامهم تحجهم في وجوههم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Dengan cemas mereka akan tampil pada hari perhitungan dosa-dosa dan kejahatannya akan berhadapan dengan mereka sebagai penuduh.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <!-- Chunk 3/10: Chapters 5-6 -->
  <chapter num="5">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Then shall the righteous man stand in great boldness before the face of such as have afflicted him, and made no account of his labours.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">حينئذ يقوم الصديق بجراة عظيمة في وجوه الذين ضايقوه وجعلوا اتعابه باطلة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Pada waktu itu orang benar berdiri dengan kepercayaan besar berhadapan muka dengan para penganiayanya dan semua orang yang telah menghina jerih payahnya.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">When they see it, they shall be troubled with terrible fear, and shall be amazed at the strangeness of his salvation, so far beyond all that they looked for.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فاذا راوه يضطربون من شدة الجزع وينذهلون من خلاص لم يكونوا يظنونه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Melihat dia mereka akan gelisah karena ketakutan yang dahsyat, dan terperanjat karena keselamatannya yang tak terduga.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">And they repenting and groaning for anguish of spirit shall say within themselves, This was he, whom we had sometimes in derision, and a proverb of reproach:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و يقولون في انفسهم نادمين وهم ينوحون من ضيق صدرهم هذا الذي كنا حينا نتخذه سخرة ومثلا للعار</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Mereka menyesal dan berkata satu sama lain sambil mengeluh karena kerisauan hatinya:</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">We fools accounted his life madness, and his end to be without honour:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و كنا نحن الجهال نحسب حياته جنونا وموته هوانا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">"Dia itulah yang dahulu menjadi tertawaan kita, dan buah cercaan kita ini, orang-orang yang bodoh. Hidupnya kita pandang kegilaan belaka, dan ajalnya kita anggap tak terhormat.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">How is he numbered among the children of God, and his lot is among the saints!</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فكيف اصبح معدودا في بني الله وحظه بين القديسين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Bagaimana gerangan ia sampai terbilang di antara anak-anak Allah, dan bagiannya terdapat di antara para kudus?</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">Therefore have we erred from the way of truth, and the light of righteousness hath not shined unto us, and the sun of righteousness rose not upon us.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لقد ضللنا عن طريق الحق ولم يضئ لنا نور البر ولم تشرق علينا الشمس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Jadi kita inilah yang tersesat dari jalan kebenaran, dan cahaya kebenaran tidak menerangi kita, dan mataharipun tidak terbit bagi kita.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">We wearied ourselves in the way of wickedness and destruction: yea, we have gone through deserts, where there lay no way: but as for the way of the Lord, we have not known it.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">اعيينا في سبل الاثم والهلاك وهمنا في متايه لا طريق فيها ولم نعلم طريق الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Kita telah kekenyangan dengan menempuh lorong-lorong dosa yang membawa kebinasaan, dan kitapun telah menjelajahi padang gurun yang tak terjalani, sedangkan jalan Tuhan tidak kita kenal.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">What hath pride profited us? or what good hath riches with our vaunting brought us?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فماذا نفعتنا الكبرياء وماذا افادنا افتخارنا بالاموال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Apa gerangan faedahnya kecongkakan bagi kita, dan apa gerangan yang dibawa oleh kekayaan yang dibualkan?</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">All those things are passed away like a shadow, and as a post that hasted by;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">قد مضى ذلك كله كالظل وكالخبر السائر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Bagaikan bayang-bayang kesemuanya itu berlalu, laksana kabar yang melintas dengan cepatnya;</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">And as a ship that passeth over the waves of the water, which when it is gone by, the trace thereof cannot be found, neither the pathway of the keel in the waves;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">او كالسفينة الجارية على الماء المتموج التي بعد مرورها لا تجد اثرها ولا خط حيزومها في الامواج</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">seperti perahu yang mengarungi air yang bergelombang tidak terdapat bekas pelayarannya maupun jalan lunasnya di tengah-tengah ombak;</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Or as when a bird hath flown through the air, there is no token of her way to be found, but the light air being beaten with the stroke of her wings and parted with the violent noise and motion of them, is passed through, and therein afterwards no sign where she went is to be found;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">او كطائر يطير في الجو فلا يبقى دليل على مسيره يضرب الريح الخفيفة بقوادمه ويشق الهواء بشدة سرعته وبرفرفة جناحيه يعبر ثم لا تجد لمروره من علامة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">atau bagaikan burung yang terbang melintasi udara tiada terdapat lagi tanda lintasannya...</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">Or like as when an arrow is shot at a mark, it parteth the air, which immediately cometh together again, so that a man cannot know where it went through:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">او كسهم يرمى الى الهدف فيخرق به الهواء ولوقته يعود الى حاله حتى لا يعرف ممر السهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Or like as when an arrow is shot at a mark, it parteth the air, which immediately cometh together again, so that a man cannot know where it went through:</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">Even so we in like manner, as soon as we were born, began to draw to our end, and had no sign of virtue to shew; but were consumed in our own wickedness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">كذلك نحن ولدنا ثم اضمحللنا ولم يكن لنا ان نبدي علامة فضيلة بل فنينا في رذيلتنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Even so we in like manner, as soon as we were born, began to draw to our end, and had no sign of virtue to shew; but were consumed in our own wickedness.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">For the hope of the ungodly is like dust that is blown away with the wind; like a thin froth that is driven away with the storm; like as the smoke which is dispersed here and there with a tempest, and passeth away as the remembrance of a guest that tarrieth but a day.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">كذا قال الخطاة في الجحيم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">For the hope of the ungodly is like dust that is blown away with the wind; like a thin froth that is driven away with the storm; like as the smoke which is dispersed here and there with a tempest, and passeth away as the remembrance of a guest that tarrieth but a day.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">But the righteous live for evermore; their reward also is with the Lord, and the care of them is with the most High.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">لان رجاء المنافق كغبار تذهب به الريح وكزبد رقيق تطارده الزوبعة وكدخان تبدده الريح وكذكر ضيف نزل يوما ثم ارتحل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">But the righteous live for evermore; their reward also is with the Lord, and the care of them is with the most High.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">Therefore shall they receive a glorious kingdom, and a beautiful crown from the Lord's hand: for with his right hand shall he cover them, and with his arm shall he protect them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">اما الصديقون فسيحيون الى الابد وعند الرب ثوابهم ولهم عناية من لدن العلي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Therefore shall they receive a glorious kingdom, and a beautiful crown from the Lord's hand: for with his right hand shall he cover them, and with his arm shall he protect them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">He shall take to him his jealousy for complete armour, and make the creature his weapon for the revenge of his enemies.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فلذلك سينالون ملك الكرامة وتاج الجمال من يد الرب لانه يسترهم بيمينه وبذراعه يقيهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">He shall take to him his jealousy for complete armour, and make the creature his weapon for the revenge of his enemies.</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">He shall put on righteousness as a breastplate, and true judgment instead of an helmet.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">يتسلح بغيرته ويسلح الخلق للانتقام من الاعداء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">He shall put on righteousness as a breastplate, and true judgment instead of an helmet.</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">He shall take holiness for an invincible shield.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">يلبس البر درعا وحكم الحق خوذة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">He shall take holiness for an invincible shield.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">His severe wrath shall he sharpen for a sword, and the world shall fight with him against the unwise.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">و يتخذ القداسة ترسا لا يقهر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">His severe wrath shall he sharpen for a sword, and the world shall fight with him against the unwise.</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">Then shall the right aiming thunderbolts go abroad; and from the clouds, as from a well drawn bow, shall they fly to the mark.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">و يحدد غضبه سيفا ماضيا والعالم يحارب معه الجهال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Then shall the right aiming thunderbolts go abroad; and from the clouds, as from a well drawn bow, shall they fly to the mark.</language></verse>
    <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">And hailstones full of wrath shall be cast as out of a stone bow, and the water of the sea shall rage against them, and the floods shall cruelly drown them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">فتنطلق صواعق البروق انطلاقا لا يخطئ وعن قوس الغيوم المحكمة التوتير تطير الى الهدف</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">And hailstones full of wrath shall be cast as out of a stone bow, and the water of the sea shall rage against them, and the floods shall cruelly drown them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23">Yea, a mighty wind shall stand up against them, and like a storm shall blow them away: thus iniquity shall lay waste the whole earth, and ill dealing shall overthrow the thrones of the mighty.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">و سخطه يرجمهم ببرد ضخم ومياه البحار تستشيط عليهم والانهار تلتقي بطغيان شديد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Yea, a mighty wind shall stand up against them, and like a storm shall blow them away: thus iniquity shall lay waste the whole earth, and ill dealing shall overthrow the thrones of the mighty.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <chapter num="6">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Hear therefore, O ye kings, and understand; learn, ye that be judges of the ends of the earth.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">الحكمة خير من القوة والحكيم افضل من الجبار</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Hear therefore, O ye kings, and understand; learn, ye that be judges of the ends of the earth.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">Give ear, ye that rule the people, and glory in the multitude of nations.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">و انتم ايها الملوك فاسمعوا وتعقلوا ويا قضاة اقاصي الارض اتعظوا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Give ear, ye that rule the people, and glory in the multitude of nations.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">For power is given you of the Lord, and sovereignty from the Highest, who shall try your works, and search out your counsels.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">اصغوا ايها المتسلطون على الجماهير المفتخرون بجموع الامم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">For power is given you of the Lord, and sovereignty from the Highest, who shall try your works, and search out your counsels.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">Because, being ministers of his kingdom, ye have not judged aright, nor kept the law, nor walked after the counsel of God;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فان سلطانكم من الرب وقدرتكم من العلي الذي سيفحص اعمالكم ويستقصي نياتكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Because, being ministers of his kingdom, ye have not judged aright, nor kept the law, nor walked after the counsel of God;</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">Horribly and speedily shall he come upon you: for a sharp judgment shall be to them that be in high places.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فانكم انتم الخادمين لملكه لم تحكموا حكم الحق ولم تحفظوا الشريعة ولم تسيروا بحسب مشيئة الله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Horribly and speedily shall he come upon you: for a sharp judgment shall be to them that be in high places.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">For mercy will soon pardon the meanest: but mighty men shall be mightily tormented.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فسيطلع عليكم بغتة مطلعا مخيفا لانه سيمضى على الحكام قضاء شديد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">For mercy will soon pardon the meanest: but mighty men shall be mightily tormented.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">For he which is Lord over all shall fear no man's person, neither shall he stand in awe of any man's greatness: for he hath made the small and great, and careth for all alike.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فان الصغير اهل للرحمة اما ارباب القوة فبقوة يفحصون</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">For he which is Lord over all shall fear no man's person, neither shall he stand in awe of any man's greatness: for he hath made the small and great, and careth for all alike.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">But a sore trial shall come upon the mighty.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ورب الجميع لا يستثني احد ولا يهاب العظمة لان الصغير والعظيم كليهما صنعه على السواء وعنايته تعم الجميع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">But a sore trial shall come upon the mighty.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">Unto you therefore, O kings, do I speak, that ye may learn wisdom, and not fall away.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لكن على الاشداء امتحانا شديدا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Unto you therefore, O kings, do I speak, that ye may learn wisdom, and not fall away.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">For they that keep holiness holily shall be judged holy: and they that have learned such things shall find what to answer.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">اليكم ايها الملوك توجيه كلامي لكي تتعلموا الحكمة ولا تسقطوا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">For they that keep holiness holily shall be judged holy: and they that have learned such things shall find what to answer.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Wherefore set your affection upon my words; desire them, and ye shall be instructed.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فان الذين يحفظون بقداسة ما هو مقدس يقدسون والذين يتعلمون هذه يجدون ما يحتجون به</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Wherefore set your affection upon my words; desire them, and ye shall be instructed.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">Wisdom is glorious, and never fadeth away: yea, she is easily seen of them that love her, and found of such as seek her.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فابتغوا كلامي واحرصوا عليه فتتادبوا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Wisdom is glorious, and never fadeth away: yea, she is easily seen of them that love her, and found of such as seek her.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">She preventeth them that desire her, in making herself first known unto them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فان الحكمة ذات بهاء ونضرة لا تذبل ومشاهدتها متيسرة للذين يحبونها ووجدانها سهل على الذين يلتمسونها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">She preventeth them that desire her, in making herself first known unto them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">Whoso seeketh her early shall have no great travail: for he shall find her sitting at his doors.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فهي تسبق فتتجلى للذين يبتغونها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Whoso seeketh her early shall have no great travail: for he shall find her sitting at his doors.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">To think therefore upon her is perfection of wisdom: and whoso watcheth for her shall quickly be without care.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ومن ابتكر في طلبها لا يتعب لانه يجدها جالسة عند ابوابه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">To think therefore upon her is perfection of wisdom: and whoso watcheth for her shall quickly be without care.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">For she goeth about seeking such as are worthy of her, sheweth herself favourably unto them in the ways, and meeteth them in every thought.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فالتامل فيها كمال الفطنة ومن سهر لاجلها فلا يلبث له هم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">For she goeth about seeking such as are worthy of her, sheweth herself favourably unto them in the ways, and meeteth them in every thought.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">For the very true beginning of her is the desire of discipline; and the care of discipline is love;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">لانها تجول في طلب الذين هم اهل لها وتتمثل لهم في الطرق باسمة وتتلقاهم كلما تاملوا فيها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">For the very true beginning of her is the desire of discipline; and the care of discipline is love;</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">And love is the keeping of her laws; and the giving heed unto her laws is the assurance of incorruption;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فاولها الخلوص في ابتغاء التاديب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">And love is the keeping of her laws; and the giving heed unto her laws is the assurance of incorruption;</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">And incorruption maketh us near unto God:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">وتطلب التاديب هو المحبة والمحبة حفظ الشرائع ومراعاة الشرائع ثبات الطهارة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">And incorruption maketh us near unto God:</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">Therefore the desire of wisdom bringeth to a kingdom.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">والطهارة تقرب الى الله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Therefore the desire of wisdom bringeth to a kingdom.</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">If your delight be then in thrones and sceptres, O ye kings of the people, honour wisdom, that ye may reign for evermore.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">فابتغاء الحكمة يبلغ الى الملكوت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">If your delight be then in thrones and sceptres, O ye kings of the people, honour wisdom, that ye may reign for evermore.</language></verse>
    <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">As for wisdom, what she is, and how she came up, I will tell you, and will not hide mysteries from you: but will seek her out from the beginning of her nativity, and bring the knowledge of her into light, and will not pass over the truth.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">فان كنتم تلتذون بالعرش والصولجان يا ملوك الشعوب فاكرموا الحكمة لكي تملكوا الى الابد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">As for wisdom, what she is, and how she came up, I will tell you, and will not hide mysteries from you: but will seek her out from the beginning of her nativity, and bring the knowledge of her into light, and will not pass over the truth.</language></verse>
    <verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23">Neither will I go with consuming envy; for such a man shall have no fellowship with wisdom.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">واحبوا نور الحكمة يا حكام الشعوب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Neither will I go with consuming envy; for such a man shall have no fellowship with wisdom.</language></verse>
    <verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24">But the multitude of the wise is the welfare of the world: and a wise king is the upholding of the people.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">وانا اخبركم ما الحكمة وكيف صدرت ولا اكتم عنكم الاسرار لكن ابحث عنها من اول كونها واجعل معرفتها بينه ولا اتجاوز من الحق شيئا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">But the multitude of the wise is the welfare of the world: and a wise king is the upholding of the people.</language></verse>
    <verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25">Receive therefore instruction through my words, and it shall do you good.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">ولا اسير مع من يذوب حسدا لان مثل هذا لا حظ له في الحكمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Receive therefore instruction through my words, and it shall do you good.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <!-- Chunk 4/10: Chapters 7-8 -->
  <chapter num="7">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">I myself also am a mortal man, like to all, and the offspring of him that was first made of the earth,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">انما انا انسان يموت مشاكل لسائر الناس من جنس اول من جبل وقد صورت جسدا في جوف امي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">I myself also am a mortal man, like to all, and the offspring of him that was first made of the earth,</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">And in my mother's womb was fashioned to be flesh in the time of ten months, being compacted in blood, of the seed of man, and the pleasure that came with sleep.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">و في مدة عشرة اشهر صنعت من الدم بزرع الرجل واللذة التي تصاحب النوم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">And in my mother's womb was fashioned to be flesh in the time of ten months, being compacted in blood, of the seed of man, and the pleasure that came with sleep.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">And when I was born, I drew in the common air, and fell upon the earth, which is of like nature, and the first voice which I uttered was crying, as all others do.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و لما ولدت انتشيت هذا الهواء الشائع وسقطت على هذه الارض المشتركة واول ما استهللت بالبكاء على حد الجميع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">And when I was born, I drew in the common air, and fell upon the earth, which is of like nature, and the first voice which I uttered was crying, as all others do.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">I was nursed in swaddling clothes, and that with cares.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و ربيت في القمط وباهتمام كثير</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">I was nursed in swaddling clothes, and that with cares.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">For there is no king that had any other beginning of birth.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فانه ليس لملك بدء مولد غير هذا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">For there is no king that had any other beginning of birth.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">For all men have one entrance into life, and the like going out.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">بل دخول الجميع الى الحياة واحد وخروجهم سواء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">For all men have one entrance into life, and the like going out.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">Wherefore I prayed, and understanding was given me: I called upon God, and the spirit of wisdom came to me.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">حينئذ تمنيت فاوتيت الفطنة ودعوت فحل علي روح الحكمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Wherefore I prayed, and understanding was given me: I called upon God, and the spirit of wisdom came to me.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">I preferred her before sceptres and thrones, and esteemed riches nothing in comparison of her.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ففضلتها على الصوالجة والعروش ولم احسب الغنى شيئا بالقياس اليها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">I preferred her before sceptres and thrones, and esteemed riches nothing in comparison of her.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">Neither compared I unto her any precious stone, because all gold in respect of her is as a little sand, and silver shall be counted as clay before her.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">و لم اعدل بها الحجر الكريم لان جميع الذهب بازائها قليل من الرمل والفضة عندها تحسب طينا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Neither compared I unto her any precious stone, because all gold in respect of her is as a little sand, and silver shall be counted as clay before her.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">I loved her above health and beauty, and chose to have her instead of light: for the light that cometh from her never goeth out.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">و احببتها فوق العافية والجمال واتخذتها لي نورا لان ضوءها لا يغرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">I loved her above health and beauty, and chose to have her instead of light: for the light that cometh from her never goeth out.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">All good things together came to me with her, and innumerable riches in her hands.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فاوتيت معها كل صنف من الخير ونلت من يديها غنى لا يحصى</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">All good things together came to me with her, and innumerable riches in her hands.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">And I rejoiced in them all, because wisdom goeth before them: and I knew not that she was the mother of them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فتمتعت بهذه كلها لان الحكمة قائدة لها ولم اعلم انها ام جميعها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">And I rejoiced in them all, because wisdom goeth before them: and I knew not that she was the mother of them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">I learned diligently, and do communicate her liberally: I do not hide her riches.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">تعلمتها بغير مكر واشرك فيها بغير حسد وغناها لا استره</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">I learned diligently, and do communicate her liberally: I do not hide her riches.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">For she is a treasure unto men that never faileth: which they that use become the friends of God, being commended for the gifts that come from learning.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فانه كنز للناس لا ينقص والذين استفادوا منه اشركوا في محبة الله لان مواهب التاديب قربتهم اليه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">For she is a treasure unto men that never faileth: which they that use become the friends of God, being commended for the gifts that come from learning.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">God hath granted me to speak as I would, and to conceive as is meet for the things that are given me: because it is he that leadeth unto wisdom, and directeth the wise.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">و قد وهبني الله ان ابدي عما في نفسي وان اجري في خاطري ما يليق بمواهبه فانه هو المرشد الى الحكمة ومثقف الحكماء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">God hath granted me to speak as I would, and to conceive as is meet for the things that are given me: because it is he that leadeth unto wisdom, and directeth the wise.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">For in his hand are both we and our words; all wisdom also, and knowledge of workmanship.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">و في يده نحن واقوالنا والفطنة كلها ومعرفة ما يصنع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">For in his hand are both we and our words; all wisdom also, and knowledge of workmanship.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">For he hath given me certain knowledge of the things that are, namely, to know how the world was made, and the operation of the elements:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">و وهبني علما يقينا بالاكوان حتى اعرف نظام العالم وقوات العناصر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">For he hath given me certain knowledge of the things that are, namely, to know how the world was made, and the operation of the elements:</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">The beginning, ending, and midst of the times: the alterations of the turning of the sun, and the change of seasons:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و مبدا الازمنة ومنتهاها وما بينهما وتغير الاحوال وتحول الاوقات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">The beginning, ending, and midst of the times: the alterations of the turning of the sun, and the change of seasons:</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">The circuits of years, and the positions of stars:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">و مداور السنين ومراكز النجوم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">The circuits of years, and the positions of stars:</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">The natures of living creatures, and the furies of wild beasts: the violence of winds, and the reasonings of men: the diversities of plants and the virtues of roots:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">و طبائع الحيوان واخلاق الوحوش وعصوف الرياح وخواطر الناس وتباين الانبتة وقوى العقاقير</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">The natures of living creatures, and the furies of wild beasts: the violence of winds, and the reasonings of men: the diversities of plants and the virtues of roots:</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">And all such things as are either secret or manifest, them I know.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">فعلمت جميع المكنونات والظواهر لان الحكمة مهندسة كل شيء هي علمتني</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">And all such things as are either secret or manifest, them I know.</language></verse>
    <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">For wisdom, which is the worker of all things, taught me: for in her is an understanding spirit holy, one only, manifold, subtil, lively, clear, undefiled, plain, not subject to hurt, loving the thing that is good, quick, which cannot be letted, ready to do good,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">فان فيها الروح الفهم القدوس المولود الوحيد ذا المزايا الكثيرة اللطيف السريع الحركة الفصيح الطاهر النير السليم المحب للخير الحديد الحر المحسن</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">For wisdom, which is the worker of all things, taught me: for in her is an understanding spirit holy, one only, manifold, subtil, lively, clear, undefiled, plain, not subject to hurt, loving the thing that is good, quick, which cannot be letted, ready to do good,</language></verse>
    <verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23">Kind to man, steadfast, sure, free from care, having all power, overseeing all things, and going through all understanding, pure, and most subtil, spirits.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">المحب للبشر الثابت الراسخ المطمئن القدير الرقيب الذي ينفذ جميع الارواح الفهمة الطاهرة اللطيفة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Kind to man, steadfast, sure, free from care, having all power, overseeing all things, and going through all understanding, pure, and most subtil, spirits.</language></verse>
    <verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24">For wisdom is more moving than any motion: she passeth and goeth through all things by reason of her pureness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">لان الحكمة اسرع حركة من كل متحرك فهي لطهارتها تلج وتنفذ في كل شيء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">For wisdom is more moving than any motion: she passeth and goeth through all things by reason of her pureness.</language></verse>
    <verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25">For she is the breath of the power of God, and a pure influence flowing from the glory of the Almighty: therefore can no defiled thing fall into her.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">فانها بخار قوة الله وصدور مجد القدير الخالص فلذلك لا يشوبها شيء نجس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">For she is the breath of the power of God, and a pure influence flowing from the glory of the Almighty: therefore can no defiled thing fall into her.</language></verse>
    <verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26">For she is the brightness of the everlasting light, the unspotted mirror of the power of God, and the image of his goodness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">لانها ضياء النور الازلي ومراة عمل الله النقية وصورة جودته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">For she is the brightness of the everlasting light, the unspotted mirror of the power of God, and the image of his goodness.</language></verse>
    <verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27">And being but one, she can do all things: and remaining in herself, she maketh all things new: and in all ages entering into holy souls, she maketh them friends of God, and prophets.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">تقدر على كل شيء وهي واحدة وتجدد كل شيء وهي ثابتة في ذاتها وفي كل جيل تحل في النفوس القديسة فتنشئ احباء لله وانبياء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">And being but one, she can do all things: and remaining in herself, she maketh all things new: and in all ages entering into holy souls, she maketh them friends of God, and prophets.</language></verse>
    <verse num="28"><language id="English" verse="28">For God loveth none but him that dwelleth with wisdom.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="28">لان الله لا يحب احدا الا من يساكن الحكمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="28">For God loveth none but him that dwelleth with wisdom.</language></verse>
    <verse num="29"><language id="English" verse="29">For she is more beautiful than the sun, and above all the order of stars: being compared with the light, she is found before it.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="29">انها ابهى من الشمس واسمى من كل مركز للنجوم واذا قيست بالنور تقدمت عليه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="29">For she is more beautiful than the sun, and above all the order of stars: being compared with the light, she is found before it.</language></verse>
    <verse num="30"><language id="English" verse="30">For after this cometh night: but vice shall not prevail against wisdom.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="30">لان النور يعقبه الليل اما الحكمة فلا يغلبها الشر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="30">For after this cometh night: but vice shall not prevail against wisdom.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <chapter num="8">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Wisdom reacheth from one end to another mightily: and sweetly doth she order all things.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">انها تبلغ من غاية الى غاية بالقوة وتدبر كل شيء بالرفق</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Wisdom reacheth from one end to another mightily: and sweetly doth she order all things.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">I loved her, and sought her out from my youth, I desired to make her my spouse, and I was a lover of her beauty.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">لقد احببتها والتمستها منذ صبائي وابتغيت ان اتخذها لي عروسا وصرت لجمالها عاشقا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">I loved her, and sought her out from my youth, I desired to make her my spouse, and I was a lover of her beauty.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">In that she is conversant with God, she magnifieth her nobility: yea, the Lord of all things himself loved her.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فان في نسبها مجدا لانها تحيا عند الله ورب الجميع قد احبها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">In that she is conversant with God, she magnifieth her nobility: yea, the Lord of all things himself loved her.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">For she is privy to the mysteries of the knowledge of God, and a lover of his works.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فهي صاحبة اسرار علم الله والمتخيرة لاعماله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">For she is privy to the mysteries of the knowledge of God, and a lover of his works.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">If riches be a possession to be desired in this life; what is richer than wisdom, that worketh all things?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">اذا كان الغنى ملكا نفيسا في الحياة فاي شيء اغنى من الحكمة صانعة الجميع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">If riches be a possession to be desired in this life; what is richer than wisdom, that worketh all things?</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">And if prudence work; who of all that are is a more cunning workman than she?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">و ان كانت الفطنة هي التي تعمل فمن احكم منها في هندسة الاكوان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">And if prudence work; who of all that are is a more cunning workman than she?</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">And if a man love righteousness her labours are virtues: for she teacheth temperance and prudence, justice and fortitude: which are such things, as men can have nothing more profitable in their life.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">و اذا كان احد يحب البر فالفضائل هي اتعابها لانها تعلم العفة والفطنة والعدل والقوة التي لا شيء للناس في الحياة انفع منها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">And if a man love righteousness her labours are virtues: for she teacheth temperance and prudence, justice and fortitude: which are such things, as men can have nothing more profitable in their life.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">If a man desire much experience, she knoweth things of old, and conjectureth aright what is to come: she knoweth the subtilties of speeches, and can expound dark sentences: she foreseeth signs and wonders, and the events of seasons and times.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">و اذا كان احد يؤثر انواع العلم فهي تعرف القديم وتتمثل المستقبل وتفقه فنون الكلام وحل الاحاجي وتعلم الايات والعجائب قبل ان تكون وحوادث الاوقات والازمنة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">If a man desire much experience, she knoweth things of old, and conjectureth aright what is to come: she knoweth the subtilties of speeches, and can expound dark sentences: she foreseeth signs and wonders, and the events of seasons and times.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">Therefore I purposed to take her to me to live with me, knowing that she would be a counsellor of good things, and a comfort in cares and grief.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لذلك عزمت ان اتخذها قرينة لحياتي علما بانها تكون لي مشيرة بالصالحات ومفرجة لهمومي وكربي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Therefore I purposed to take her to me to live with me, knowing that she would be a counsellor of good things, and a comfort in cares and grief.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">For her sake I shall have estimation among the multitude, and honour with the elders, though I be young.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فيكون لي بها مجد عند الجموع وكرامة لدى الشيوخ على ما انا فيه من الفتاء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">For her sake I shall have estimation among the multitude, and honour with the elders, though I be young.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">I shall be found of a quick conceit in judgment, and shall be admired in the sight of great men.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">و اعد حاذقا في القضاء وعجيبا امام المقتدرين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">I shall be found of a quick conceit in judgment, and shall be admired in the sight of great men.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">When I hold my tongue, they shall bide my leisure, and when I speak, they shall give good ear unto me: if I talk much, they shall lay their hands upon their mouth.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">اذا صمت ينتظرون واذا نطقت يصغون واذا افضت في الكلام يضعون ايديهم على افواههم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">When I hold my tongue, they shall bide my leisure, and when I speak, they shall give good ear unto me: if I talk much, they shall lay their hands upon their mouth.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">Moreover by the means of her I shall obtain immortality, and leave behind me an everlasting memorial to them that come after me.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">و انال بها الخلود واخلف عند الذين بعدي ذكرا مؤبدا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Moreover by the means of her I shall obtain immortality, and leave behind me an everlasting memorial to them that come after me.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">I shall set the people in order, and the nations shall be subject unto me.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ادبر الشعوب وتخضع لي الامم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">I shall set the people in order, and the nations shall be subject unto me.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">Horrible tyrants shall be afraid, when they do but hear of me; I shall be found good among the multitude, and valiant in war.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">يسمع الملوك المرهوبون فيخافونني ويظهر في الجمع صلاحي وفي الحرب باسي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Horrible tyrants shall be afraid, when they do but hear of me; I shall be found good among the multitude, and valiant in war.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">After I am come into mine house, I will repose myself with her: for her conversation hath no bitterness; and to live with her hath no sorrow, but mirth and joy.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">و اذا دخلت بيتي سكنت اليها لانه ليس في معاشرتها مرارة ولا في الحياة معها غمة بل سرور وفرح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">After I am come into mine house, I will repose myself with her: for her conversation hath no bitterness; and to live with her hath no sorrow, but mirth and joy.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">Now when I considered these things in myself, and pondered them in my heart, how that to be allied unto wisdom is immortality;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">فلما تفكرت في نفسي بهذه وتاملت في قلبي ان في قربى الحكمة خلودا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Now when I considered these things in myself, and pondered them in my heart, how that to be allied unto wisdom is immortality;</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">And great pleasure it is to have her friendship; and in the works of her hands are infinite riches; and in the exercise of conference with her, prudence; and in talking with her, a good report; I went about seeking how to take her to me.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و في مصافاتها لذة صالحة وفي اتعاب يديها غنى لا ينقص وفي الترشح لمؤانستها فطنة وفي الاشتراك في حديثها فخرا طفقت اطوف طالبا ان اتخذها لنفسي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">And great pleasure it is to have her friendship; and in the works of her hands are infinite riches; and in the exercise of conference with her, prudence; and in talking with her, a good report; I went about seeking how to take her to me.</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">For I was a witty child, and had a good spirit.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">و قد كنت صبيا حسن الطباع ورزقت نفسا صالحة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">For I was a witty child, and had a good spirit.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">Yea rather, being good, I came into a body undefiled.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">ثم بازديادي صلاحا حصلت على جسد غير مدنس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Yea rather, being good, I came into a body undefiled.</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">Nevertheless, when I perceived that I could not otherwise obtain her, except God gave her me; and that was a point of wisdom also to know whose gift she was; I prayed unto the Lord, and besought him, and with my whole heart I said,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">و لما علمت باني لا اكون عفيفا ما لم يهبني الله العفة وقد كان من الفطنة ان اعلم ممن هذه الموهبة توجهت الى الرب وسالته من كل قلبي قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Nevertheless, when I perceived that I could not otherwise obtain her, except God gave her me; and that was a point of wisdom also to know whose gift she was; I prayed unto the Lord, and besought him, and with my whole heart I said,</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <!-- Chunk 5/10: Chapters 9-10 -->
  <chapter num="9">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">O God of my fathers, and Lord of mercy, who hast made all things with thy word,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">يا اله الاباء يا رب الرحمة يا صانع الجميع بكلمتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">O God of my fathers, and Lord of mercy, who hast made all things with thy word,</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">And ordained man through thy wisdom, that he should have dominion over the creatures which thou hast made,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">و فاطر الانسان بحكمتك لكي يسود على الخلائق التي كونتها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">And ordained man through thy wisdom, that he should have dominion over the creatures which thou hast made,</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">And order the world according to equity and righteousness, and execute judgment with an upright heart:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و يسوس العالم بالقداسة والبر ويجري الحكم باستقامة النفس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">And order the world according to equity and righteousness, and execute judgment with an upright heart:</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">Give me wisdom, that sitteth by thy throne; and reject me not from among thy children:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">هب لي الحكمة الجالسة الى عرشك ولا ترذلني من بين بنيك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Give me wisdom, that sitteth by thy throne; and reject me not from among thy children:</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">For I thy servant and son of thine handmaid am a feeble person, and of a short time, and too young for the understanding of judgment and laws.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فاني انا عبدك وابن امتك انسان ضعيف قليل البقاء وناقص الفهم في القضاء والشرائع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">For I thy servant and son of thine handmaid am a feeble person, and of a short time, and too young for the understanding of judgment and laws.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">For though a man be never so perfect among the children of men, yet if thy wisdom be not with him, he shall be nothing regarded.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">على انه ان كان في بني البشر احد كامل فما لم تكن معه الحكمة التي منك لا يحسب شيئا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">For though a man be never so perfect among the children of men, yet if thy wisdom be not with him, he shall be nothing regarded.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">Thou hast chosen me to be a king of thy people, and a judge of thy sons and daughters:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">انك قد اخترتني لشعبك ملكا ولبنيك وبناتك قاضيا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Thou hast chosen me to be a king of thy people, and a judge of thy sons and daughters:</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Thou hast commanded me to build a temple upon thy holy mount, and an altar in the city wherein thou dwellest, a resemblance of the holy tabernacle, which thou hast prepared from the beginning.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">و امرتني ان ابني هيكلا في جبل قدسك ومذبحا في مدينة سكناك على مثال المسكن المقدس الذي هياته منذ البدء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Thou hast commanded me to build a temple upon thy holy mount, and an altar in the city wherein thou dwellest, a resemblance of the holy tabernacle, which thou hast prepared from the beginning.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">And wisdom was with thee: which knoweth thy works, and was present when thou madest the world, and knew what was acceptable in thy sight, and right in thy commandments.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ان معك الحكمة العليمة باعمالك والتي كانت حاضرة اذ صنعت العالم وهي عارفة ما المرضي في عينيك والمستقيم في وصاياك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">And wisdom was with thee: which knoweth thy works, and was present when thou madest the world, and knew what was acceptable in thy sight, and right in thy commandments.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">O send her out of thy holy heavens, and from the throne of thy glory, that being present she may labour with me, that I may know what is pleasing unto thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فارسلها من السماوات المقدسة وابعثها من عرش مجدك حتى اذا حضرت تجد معي واعلم ما المرضي لديك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">O send her out of thy holy heavens, and from the throne of thy glory, that being present she may labour with me, that I may know what is pleasing unto thee.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">For she knoweth and understandeth all things, and she shall lead me soberly in my doings, and preserve me in her power.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فانها تعلم وتفهم كل شيء فتكون لي في افعالي مرشدا فطينا وبعزها تحفظني</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">For she knoweth and understandeth all things, and she shall lead me soberly in my doings, and preserve me in her power.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">So shall my works be acceptable, and then shall I judge thy people righteously, and be worthy to sit in my father's seat.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فتغدو اعمالي مقبولة واحكم لشعبك بالعدل واكون اهلا لعرش ابي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">So shall my works be acceptable, and then shall I judge thy people righteously, and be worthy to sit in my father's seat.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">For what man is he that can know the counsel of God? or who can think what the will of the Lord is?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فاي انسان يعلم مشورة الله او يفطن لما يريد الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">For what man is he that can know the counsel of God? or who can think what the will of the Lord is?</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">For the thoughts of mortal men are miserable, and our devices are but uncertain.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ان افكار البشر ذات احجام وبصائرنا غير راسخة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">For the thoughts of mortal men are miserable, and our devices are but uncertain.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">For the corruptible body presseth down the soul, and the earthy tabernacle weigheth down the mind that museth upon many things.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">اذ الجسد الفاسد يثقل النفس والمسكن الارضي يخفض العقل الكثير الهموم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">For the corruptible body presseth down the soul, and the earthy tabernacle weigheth down the mind that museth upon many things.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">And hardly do we guess aright at things that are upon earth, and with labour do we find the things that are before us: but the things that are in heaven who hath searched out?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">و نحن بالجهد نتمثل ما على الارض وبالكد ندرك ما بين ايدينا فما في السماوات من اطلع عليه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">And hardly do we guess aright at things that are upon earth, and with labour do we find the things that are before us: but the things that are in heaven who hath searched out?</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">And thy counsel who hath known, except thou give wisdom, and send thy Holy Spirit from above?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">و من علم مشورتك لو لم تؤت الحكمة وتبعث روحك القدوس من الاعالي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">And thy counsel who hath known, except thou give wisdom, and send thy Holy Spirit from above?</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">For so the ways of them which lived on the earth were reformed, and men were taught the things that are pleasing unto thee, and were saved through wisdom.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فانه كذلك قومت سبل الذين على الارض وتعلم الناس مرضاتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">For so the ways of them which lived on the earth were reformed, and men were taught the things that are pleasing unto thee, and were saved through wisdom.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <chapter num="10">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">She preserved the first formed father of the world, that was created alone, and brought him out of his fall,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">هي التي حفظت اول من جبل ابا للعالم لما خلق وحده</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">She preserved the first formed father of the world, that was created alone, and brought him out of his fall,</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">And gave him power to rule all things.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">و انقذته من زلته واتته قوة ليتسلط على الجميع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">And gave him power to rule all things.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">But when the unrighteous went away from her in his anger, he perished also in the fury wherewith he murdered his brother.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و لما ارتد عنها الظالم في غضبه هلك في حنقه الذي كان به قاتل اخيه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">But when the unrighteous went away from her in his anger, he perished also in the fury wherewith he murdered his brother.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">For whose cause the earth being drowned with the flood, wisdom again preserved it, and directed the course of the righteous in a piece of wood of small value.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و لما غمر الطوفان الارض بسببه عادت الحكمة فخلصتها بهدايتها للصديق في الة خشب حقيرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">For whose cause the earth being drowned with the flood, wisdom again preserved it, and directed the course of the righteous in a piece of wood of small value.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">Moreover, the nations in their wicked conspiracy being confounded, she found out the righteous, and preserved him blameless unto God, and kept him strong against his tender compassion toward his son.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">و هي التي عند اتفاق لفيف الامم على الشر لقيت الصديق وصانته لله بغير وصمة وحفظت احشائه صماء عن ولده</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Moreover, the nations in their wicked conspiracy being confounded, she found out the righteous, and preserved him blameless unto God, and kept him strong against his tender compassion toward his son.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">When the ungodly perished, she delivered the righteous man, who fled from the fire which fell down upon the five cities.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">و هي التي انقذت الصديق من المنافقين الهالكين فهرب من النار الهابطة على المدن الخمس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">When the ungodly perished, she delivered the righteous man, who fled from the fire which fell down upon the five cities.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">Of whose wickedness even to this day the waste land that smoketh is a testimony, and plants bearing fruit that never come to ripeness: and a standing pillar of salt is a monument of an unbelieving soul.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">و الى الان يشهد بشرهم قفر يسطع منه الدخان ونبات يثمر ثمرا لا ينضج وعمود من ملح قائم تذكارا لنفس لم تؤمن</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Of whose wickedness even to this day the waste land that smoketh is a testimony, and plants bearing fruit that never come to ripeness: and a standing pillar of salt is a monument of an unbelieving soul.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">For regarding not wisdom, they gat not only this hurt, that they knew not the things which were good; but also left behind them to the world a memorial of their foolishness: so that in the things wherein they offended they could not so much as be hid.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">و الذين اهملوا الحكمة لم ينحصر ظلمهم لانفسهم بجهلهم الصلاح ولكنهم خلفوا للناس ذكر حماقتهم بحيث لم يستطيعوا كتمانما زلوا فيه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">For regarding not wisdom, they gat not only this hurt, that they knew not the things which were good; but also left behind them to the world a memorial of their foolishness: so that in the things wherein they offended they could not so much as be hid.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">But wisdom delivered from pain those that attended upon her.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">و اما الذين خدموا الحكمة فانقذتهم من كل نصب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">But wisdom delivered from pain those that attended upon her.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">When the righteous fled from his brother's wrath she guided him in right paths, shewed him the kingdom of God, and gave him knowledge of holy things, made him rich in his travels, and multiplied the fruit of his labours.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">و هي التي قادت الصديق الهارب من غضب اخيه في سبل مستقيمة وارته ملكوت الله واتته علم القديسين وانجحته في اتعابه واكثرت ثمرات اعماله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">When the righteous fled from his brother's wrath she guided him in right paths, shewed him the kingdom of God, and gave him knowledge of holy things, made him rich in his travels, and multiplied the fruit of his labours.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">In the covetousness of such as oppressed him she stood by him, and made him rich.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">و عند طماعة المستطيلين عليه انتصبت لمعونته واغنته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">In the covetousness of such as oppressed him she stood by him, and made him rich.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">She defended him from his enemies, and kept him safe from those that lay in wait, and in a sore conflict she gave him the victory; that he might know that goodness is stronger than all.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">و وقته من اعدائه وحمته من الكامنين له واظفرته في القتال الشديد لكي يعلم ان التقوى اقدر من كل شيء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">She defended him from his enemies, and kept him safe from those that lay in wait, and in a sore conflict she gave him the victory; that he might know that goodness is stronger than all.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">When the righteous was sold, she forsook him not, but delivered him from sin: she went down with him into the pit,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">و هي التي لم تخذل الصديق المبيع بل صانته من الخطيئة ونزلت معه في الجب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">When the righteous was sold, she forsook him not, but delivered him from sin: she went down with him into the pit,</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">And left him not in bonds, till she brought him the sceptre of the kingdom, and power against those that oppressed him: as for them that had accused him, she shewed them to be liars, and gave him perpetual glory.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و في القيود لم تفارقه حتى ناولته صوالجة الملك وسلطانا على الذين قسروه وكذبت الذين عابوه واتته مجدا ابديا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">And left him not in bonds, till she brought him the sceptre of the kingdom, and power against those that oppressed him: as for them that had accused him, she shewed them to be liars, and gave him perpetual glory.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">She delivered the righteous people and blameless seed from the nation that oppressed them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">و هي التي انقذت شعبا مقدسا وزرية لا وصمة فيها من امة مضايقيهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">She delivered the righteous people and blameless seed from the nation that oppressed them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">She entered into the soul of the servant of the Lord, and withstood dreadful kings in wonders and signs;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">و حلت نفس عبد للرب وقاومت ملوكا مرهوبين بعجائب وايات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">She entered into the soul of the servant of the Lord, and withstood dreadful kings in wonders and signs;</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">Rendered to the righteous a reward of their labours, guided them in a marvellous way, and was unto them for a cover by day, and a light of stars in the night season;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">و جزت القديسين ثواب اتعابهم وقادتهم في طريق عجيب وكانت لهم ظلا في النهار وضياء نجوم في الليل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Rendered to the righteous a reward of their labours, guided them in a marvellous way, and was unto them for a cover by day, and a light of stars in the night season;</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">Brought them through the Red sea, and led them through much water:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و عبرت بهم البحر الاحمر واجازتهم المياه الغزيرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Brought them through the Red sea, and led them through much water:</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">But she drowned their enemies, and cast them up out of the bottom of the deep.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">اما اعداؤهم فاغرقتهم ثم قذفتهم من عمق الغمار على الشاطئ فسلب الصديقون المنافقين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">But she drowned their enemies, and cast them up out of the bottom of the deep.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">Therefore the righteous spoiled the ungodly, and praised thy holy name, O Lord, and magnified with one accord thine hand, that fought for them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">و رنموا لاسمك القدوس ايها الرب وحمدوا بقلب واحد يدك الناصرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Therefore the righteous spoiled the ungodly, and praised thy holy name, O Lord, and magnified with one accord thine hand, that fought for them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">For wisdom opened the mouth of the dumb, and made the tongues of them that cannot speak eloquent.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">لان الحكمة فتحت افواه البكم وجعلت السنة الاطفال تفصح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">For wisdom opened the mouth of the dumb, and made the tongues of them that cannot speak eloquent.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <!-- Chunk 6/10: Chapters 11-12 -->
  <chapter num="11">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">She prospered their works in the hand of the holy prophet.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ثم سددت مساعيهم بارشاد نبي قديس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">She prospered their works in the hand of the holy prophet.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">They went through the wilderness that was not inhabited, and pitched tents in places where there lay no way.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فساروا في برية لا ساكن بها وضربوا اخبيتهم في ارض قفرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">They went through the wilderness that was not inhabited, and pitched tents in places where there lay no way.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">They stood against their enemies, and were avenged of their adversaries.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و قاوموا محاربيهم ودافعوا اعداءهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">They stood against their enemies, and were avenged of their adversaries.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">When they were thirsty, they called upon thee, and water was given them out of the flinty rock, and their thirst was quenched out of the hard stone.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و في عطشهم دعوا اليك فاعطوا ماء من صخرة الصوان وشفاء لغليلهم من الحجر الجلمود</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">When they were thirsty, they called upon thee, and water was given them out of the flinty rock, and their thirst was quenched out of the hard stone.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">For by what things their enemies were punished, by the same they in their need were benefited.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فكان الذي عذب به اعداؤهم اذ اعوزهم ما يشربون وبنو اسرائيل متهللون بكثرته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">For by what things their enemies were punished, by the same they in their need were benefited.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">For instead of a fountain of a perpetual running river troubled with foul blood,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">هو الذي احسن به اليهم في عوزهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">For instead of a fountain of a perpetual running river troubled with foul blood,</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">For a manifest reproof of that commandment, whereby the infants were slain, thou gavest unto them abundance of water by a means which they hoped not for:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فانك بلبلت اولئك اذ بدلتهم بمعين النهر الدائم دما صديدا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">For a manifest reproof of that commandment, whereby the infants were slain, thou gavest unto them abundance of water by a means which they hoped not for:</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Declaring by that thirst then how thou hadst punished their adversaries.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">عقابا لهم على قضائهم بقتل الاطفال وهؤلاء اعطيتهم ماء غزيرا عند الياس منه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Declaring by that thirst then how thou hadst punished their adversaries.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">For when they were tried albeit but in mercy chastised, they knew how the ungodly were judged in wrath and tormented, thirsting in another manner than the just.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لكي تريهم بعطشهم هذا كيف عاقبت اضدادهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">For when they were tried albeit but in mercy chastised, they knew how the ungodly were judged in wrath and tormented, thirsting in another manner than the just.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">For these thou didst admonish and try, as a father: but the other, as a severe king, thou didst condemn and punish.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فانهم بامتحانك لهم وان كان تاديب رحمة فهموا كيف كان عذاب المنافقين المقضي عليهم بالغضب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">For these thou didst admonish and try, as a father: but the other, as a severe king, thou didst condemn and punish.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Whether they were absent or present, they were vexed alike.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لانك جربت هؤلاء كاب انذارا لهم واولئك ابتليتهم كملك قاس قضاء عليهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Whether they were absent or present, they were vexed alike.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">For a double grief came upon them, and a groaning for the remembrance of things past.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">و قد مسهم في الغيب من الضر ما مسهم في المشهد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">For a double grief came upon them, and a groaning for the remembrance of things past.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">For when they heard by their own punishments the other to be benefited, they had some feeling of the Lord.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">اذ اخذهم ضعفان من الحزن والنحيب بتذكر الضربات السالفة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">For when they heard by their own punishments the other to be benefited, they had some feeling of the Lord.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">For whom they rejected with scorn, when he was long before thrown out at the casting forth of the infants, him in the end, when they saw what came to pass, they admired.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">لانهم لما سمعوا ان ما كان لهم عقابا صار لاعدائهم احسانا شعروا بيد الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">For whom they rejected with scorn, when he was long before thrown out at the casting forth of the infants, him in the end, when they saw what came to pass, they admired.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">But for the foolish devices of their wickedness, wherewith being deceived they worshipped serpents void of reason, and vile beasts, thou didst send a multitude of unreasonable beasts upon them for vengeance;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">و الذي قضوا من قبل بطرحه في النهر واستخفوا به ورذلوه استعظموه في اخر الامر اذا كان عطش الصديقين على خلاف عطشهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">But for the foolish devices of their wickedness, wherewith being deceived they worshipped serpents void of reason, and vile beasts, thou didst send a multitude of unreasonable beasts upon them for vengeance;</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">That they might know, that wherewithal a man sinneth, by the same also shall he be punished.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">و اذ كانوا قد سفهوا في افكارهم الاثيمة وضلوا حتى عبدوا زحافات حقيرة ووحوشا لا نطق لها انتقمت منهم بان ارسلت عليهم جما من الحيوانات التي لا نطق لها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">That they might know, that wherewithal a man sinneth, by the same also shall he be punished.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">For thy Almighty hand, that made the world of matter without form, wanted not means to send among them a multitude of bears or fierce lions,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">لكي يعلموا ان ما خطئ به احد به يعاقب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">For thy Almighty hand, that made the world of matter without form, wanted not means to send among them a multitude of bears or fierce lions,</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">Or unknown wild beasts, full of rage, newly created, breathing out either a fiery vapour, or filthy scents of scattered smoke, or shooting horrible sparkles out of their eyes:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و لم يكن صعبا على يدك القادرة على كل شيء التي صنعت العالم من مادة غير مصورة ان تبعث عليهم جما من الادباب او الاسود الباسلة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Or unknown wild beasts, full of rage, newly created, breathing out either a fiery vapour, or filthy scents of scattered smoke, or shooting horrible sparkles out of their eyes:</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">Whereof not only the harm might dispatch them at once, but also the terrible sight utterly destroy them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">او من اصناف جديدة لم تعرف من الوحوش الضارية التي تنفخ نارا او تبعث دخانا قاتما او ترسل من عيونها شرارا مخيفا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Whereof not only the harm might dispatch them at once, but also the terrible sight utterly destroy them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">Yea, and without these might they have fallen down with one blast, being persecuted of vengeance, and scattered abroad through the breath of thy power: but thou hast ordered all things in measure and number and weight.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">اذا لكانت تهلكهم خوفا من منظرها فضلا عن ان تهشمهم باصابتها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Yea, and without these might they have fallen down with one blast, being persecuted of vengeance, and scattered abroad through the breath of thy power: but thou hast ordered all things in measure and number and weight.</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">For thou canst shew thy great strength at all times when thou wilt; and who may withstand the power of thine arm?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">بل قد كان نفس كافيا لاسقاطهم فيتعقبهم القضاء وروح قدرتك يذريهم لكنك رتبت كل شيء بمقدار وعدد ووزن</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">For thou canst shew thy great strength at all times when thou wilt; and who may withstand the power of thine arm?</language></verse>
    <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">For the whole world before thee is as a little grain of the balance, yea, as a drop of the morning dew that falleth down upon the earth.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">و عندك قدرة عظيمة في كل حين فمن يقاوم قوة ذراعك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">For the whole world before thee is as a little grain of the balance, yea, as a drop of the morning dew that falleth down upon the earth.</language></verse>
    <verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23">But thou hast mercy upon all; for thou canst do all things, and winkest at the sins of men, because they should amend.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">ان العالم كله امامك مثل ما ترجح به كفة الميزان وكنقطة ندى تسقط على الارض عند السحر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">But thou hast mercy upon all; for thou canst do all things, and winkest at the sins of men, because they should amend.</language></verse>
    <verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24">For thou lovest all the things that are, and abhorrest nothing which thou hast made: for never wouldest thou have made any thing, if thou hadst hated it.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">لكنك ترحم الجميع لانك قادر على كل شيء وتتغاضى عن خطايا الناس لكي يتوبوا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">For thou lovest all the things that are, and abhorrest nothing which thou hast made: for never wouldest thou have made any thing, if thou hadst hated it.</language></verse>
    <verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25">And how could any thing have endured, if it had not been thy will? or been preserved, if not called by thee?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">لانك تحب جميع الاكوان ولا تمقت شيئا مما صنعت فانك لو ابغضت شيئا لم تكونه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">And how could any thing have endured, if it had not been thy will? or been preserved, if not called by thee?</language></verse>
    <verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26">But thou sparest all: for they are thine, O Lord, thou lover of souls.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">و كيف يبقى شيء لم ترده ام كيف يحفظ ما لست انت داعيا له</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">But thou sparest all: for they are thine, O Lord, thou lover of souls.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <chapter num="12">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">For thine incorruptible Spirit is in all things.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ان في كل شيء روحك الذي لا فساد فيه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">For thine incorruptible Spirit is in all things.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">Therefore chastenest thou them by little and little that offend, and warnest them by putting them in remembrance wherein they have offended, that leaving their wickedness they may believe on thee, O Lord.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فبه توبخ الخطاة شيئا فشيئا وفيما يخطاون به تذكرهم وتنذرهم لكي يقلعوا عن الشر ويؤمنوا بك ايها الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Therefore chastenest thou them by little and little that offend, and warnest them by putting them in remembrance wherein they have offended, that leaving their wickedness they may believe on thee, O Lord.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">For it was thy will to destroy by the hands of our fathers both those old inhabitants of thy holy land,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فانك ابغضت الذين كانوا قديما سكان ارضك المقدسة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">For it was thy will to destroy by the hands of our fathers both those old inhabitants of thy holy land,</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">Whom thou hatedst for doing most odious works of witchcrafts, and wicked sacrifices;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">لاجل اعمالهم الممقوتة لديك من السحر وذبائح الفجور</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Whom thou hatedst for doing most odious works of witchcrafts, and wicked sacrifices;</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">And also those merciless murderers of children, and devourers of man's flesh, and the feasts of blood,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">اذ كانوا يقتلون اولادهم بغير رحمة وياكلون احشاء الناس ويشربون دماءهم في شعائر عبادتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">And also those merciless murderers of children, and devourers of man's flesh, and the feasts of blood,</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">With their priests out of the midst of their idolatrous crew, and the parents, that killed with their own hands souls destitute of help:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فاثرت ان تهلك بايدي ابائنا اولئك الوالدين قتلة النفوس التي لا نصرة لها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">With their priests out of the midst of their idolatrous crew, and the parents, that killed with their own hands souls destitute of help:</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">That the land, which thou esteemedst above all other, might receive a worthy colony of God's children.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">لكي تكون الارض التي هي اكرم عندك من كل ارض عامرة بابناء الله كما يليق بها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">That the land, which thou esteemedst above all other, might receive a worthy colony of God's children.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Nevertheless even those thou sparedst as men, and didst send wasps, forerunners of thine host, to destroy them by little and little.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">على انك اشفقت على اولئك ايضا لانهم بشر فبعثت بالزنابير تتقدم عسكرك وتبيدهم شيئا بعد شيء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Nevertheless even those thou sparedst as men, and didst send wasps, forerunners of thine host, to destroy them by little and little.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">Not that thou wast unable to bring the ungodly under the hand of the righteous in battle, or to destroy them at once with cruel beasts, or with one rough word:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لا لانك عجزت عن اخضاع المنافقين للصديقين بالقتال او تدميرهم بمرة بالوحوش الضارية او بامر جازم من عندك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Not that thou wast unable to bring the ungodly under the hand of the righteous in battle, or to destroy them at once with cruel beasts, or with one rough word:</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">But executing thy judgments upon them by little and little, thou gavest them place of repentance, not being ignorant that they were a naughty generation, and that their malice was bred in them, and that their cogitation would never be changed.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لكن بعقابهم شيئا فشيئا منحتهم مهلة للتوبة وان لم يخف عليك ان جيلهم شرير وان خبثهم غريزي وافكارهم لا تتغير الى الابد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">But executing thy judgments upon them by little and little, thou gavest them place of repentance, not being ignorant that they were a naughty generation, and that their malice was bred in them, and that their cogitation would never be changed.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">For it was a cursed seed from the beginning; neither didst thou for fear of any man give them pardon for those things wherein they sinned.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لانهم كانوا ذرية ملعونة منذ البدء ولم يكن عفوك عن خطاياهم خوفا من احد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">For it was a cursed seed from the beginning; neither didst thou for fear of any man give them pardon for those things wherein they sinned.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">For who shall say, What hast thou done? or who shall withstand thy judgment? or who shall accuse thee for the nations that perish, whom thou made? or who shall come to stand against thee, to be revenged for the unrighteous men?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فانه من يقول ماذا صنعت او يعترض قضاءك ومن يشكوك بهلاك الامم التي خلقتها او يقف بين يديك مخاصما عن اناس مجرمين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">For who shall say, What hast thou done? or who shall withstand thy judgment? or who shall accuse thee for the nations that perish, whom thou made? or who shall come to stand against thee, to be revenged for the unrighteous men?</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">For neither is there any God but thou that careth for all, to whom thou mightest shew that thy judgment is not unright.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">اذ ليس اله الا انت المعتني بالجميع حتى تري انك لا تقضي قضاء الظلم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">For neither is there any God but thou that careth for all, to whom thou mightest shew that thy judgment is not unright.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">Neither shall king or tyrant be able to set his face against thee for any whom thou hast punished.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و ليس لملك او سلطان ان يطالبك بالذين اهلكتهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Neither shall king or tyrant be able to set his face against thee for any whom thou hast punished.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">Forsomuch then as thou art righteous thyself, thou orderest all things righteously: thinking it not agreeable with thy power to condemn him that hath not deserved to be punished.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">و اذ انت عادل تدبر الجميع بالعدل وتحسب القضاء على من لا يستوجب العقاب منافيا لقدرتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Forsomuch then as thou art righteous thyself, thou orderest all things righteously: thinking it not agreeable with thy power to condemn him that hath not deserved to be punished.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">For thy power is the beginning of righteousness, and because thou art the Lord of all, it maketh thee to be gracious unto all.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لان قوتك هي مبدا عدلك وبما انك رب الجميع فانت تشفق على الجميع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">For thy power is the beginning of righteousness, and because thou art the Lord of all, it maketh thee to be gracious unto all.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">For when men will not believe that thou art of a full power, thou shewest thy strength, and among them that know it thou makest their boldness manifest.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">و انما تبدي قوتك للذين لا يؤمنون انك على كمال القدرة وتعاقب العلماء على جسارتهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">For when men will not believe that thou art of a full power, thou shewest thy strength, and among them that know it thou makest their boldness manifest.</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">But thou, mastering thy power, judgest with equity, and orderest us with great favour: for thou mayest use power when thou wilt.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">لكنك ايها السلطان القدير تحكم بالرفق وتدبرنا باشفاق كثير لان في يدك ان تعمل بقدرة متى شئت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">But thou, mastering thy power, judgest with equity, and orderest us with great favour: for thou mayest use power when thou wilt.</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">But by such works hast thou taught thy people that the just man should be merciful, and hast made thy children to be of a good hope that thou givest repentance for sins.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">فعلمت شعبك باعمالك هذه ان الصديق ينبغي ان يكون محبا للناس وجعلت لبنيك رجاء حسنا لانك تمنحهم في خطاياهم مهلة للتوبة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">But by such works hast thou taught thy people that the just man should be merciful, and hast made thy children to be of a good hope that thou givest repentance for sins.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">For if thou didst punish the enemies of thy children, and the condemned to death, with such deliberation, giving them time and place, whereby they might be delivered from their malice:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">لانك ان كنت عاقبت اعداء بنيك المستوجبين للموت بمثل هذا التحرز والترفق وجعلت لهم زمانا ومكانا للاقلاع عن الشر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">For if thou didst punish the enemies of thy children, and the condemned to death, with such deliberation, giving them time and place, whereby they might be delivered from their malice:</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">With how great circumspection didst thou judge thine own sons, unto whose fathers thou hast sworn, and made covenants of good promises?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">فباي اعتناء دبرت بنيك الذين واثقت اباءهم بالاقسام والعهود على مواعيدك الصالحة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">With how great circumspection didst thou judge thine own sons, unto whose fathers thou hast sworn, and made covenants of good promises?</language></verse>
    <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">Therefore, whereas thou dost chasten us, thou scourgest our enemies a thousand times more, to the intent that, when we judge, we should carefully think of thy goodness, and when we ourselves are judged, we should look for mercy.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">فتؤدبنا نحن وتجلد اعداءنا جلدا كثيرا لكي نتذكر حلمك اذا حكمنا وننتظر رحمتك اذا حكم علينا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Therefore, whereas thou dost chasten us, thou scourgest our enemies a thousand times more, to the intent that, when we judge, we should carefully think of thy goodness, and when we ourselves are judged, we should look for mercy.</language></verse>
    <verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23">Wherefore, whereas men have lived dissolutely and unrighteously, thou hast tormented them with their own abominations.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">لاجل ذلك فالمنافقون الذين عاشوا بالسفه عذبتهم بارجاسهم عينها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Wherefore, whereas men have lived dissolutely and unrighteously, thou hast tormented them with their own abominations.</language></verse>
    <verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24">For they went astray very far in the ways of error, and held them for gods, which even among the beasts of their enemies were despised, being deceived, as children of no understanding.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">فانهم في ضلالهم تجاوزوا طرق الضلال اذ اتخذوا ما يستحقره اعداؤهم من الحيوان الهة مغترين كاطفال لا يفقهون</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">For they went astray very far in the ways of error, and held them for gods, which even among the beasts of their enemies were despised, being deceived, as children of no understanding.</language></verse>
    <verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25">Therefore unto them, as to children without the use of reason, thou didst send a judgment to mock them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">لذلك بعثت عليهم عقاب اولاد لا عقل لهم للسخرية</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Therefore unto them, as to children without the use of reason, thou didst send a judgment to mock them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26">But they that would not be reformed by that correction, wherein he dallied with them, shall feel a judgment worthy of God.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">و لما لم يتعظوا بتاديب السخرية ذاقوا العقاب اللائق بالله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">But they that would not be reformed by that correction, wherein he dallied with them, shall feel a judgment worthy of God.</language></verse>
    <verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27">For, look, for what things they grudged, when they were punished, that is, for them whom they thought to be gods; [now] being punished in them, when they saw it, they acknowledged him to be the true God, whom before they denied to know: and therefore came extreme damnation upon them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">و فيما تحملوه بغيظهم وقد راوا ان ما اتخذوه الها كانوا به يعذبون عرفوا الاله الحق الذي كانوا يكفرون به ولذلك حلت بهم خاتمة العقاب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">For, look, for what things they grudged, when they were punished, that is, for them whom they thought to be gods; [now] being punished in them, when they saw it, they acknowledged him to be the true God, whom before they denied to know: and therefore came extreme damnation upon them.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <!-- Chunk 7/10: Chapters 13-14 -->
  <chapter num="13">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Surely vain are all men by nature, who are ignorant of God, and could not out of the good things that are seen know him that is: neither by considering the works did they acknowledge the workmaster;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ان جميع الذين لم يعرفوا الله هم حمقى من طبعهم لم يقدروا ان يعلموا الكائن من الخيرات المنظورة ولم يتاملوا المصنوعات حتى يعرفوا صانعها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Surely vain are all men by nature, who are ignorant of God, and could not out of the good things that are seen know him that is: neither by considering the works did they acknowledge the workmaster;</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">But deemed either fire, or wind, or the swift air, or the circle of the stars, or the violent water, or the lights of heaven, to be the gods which govern the world.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">لكنهم حسبوا النار او الريح او الهواء اللطيف او مدار النجوم او لجة المياه او نيري السماء الهة تسود العالم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">But deemed either fire, or wind, or the swift air, or the circle of the stars, or the violent water, or the lights of heaven, to be the gods which govern the world.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">With whose beauty if they being delighted took them to be gods; let them know how much better the Lord of them is: for the first author of beauty hath created them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فان كانوا انما اعتقدوا هذه الهة لانهم خلبوا بجمالها فليتعرفوا كم ربها احسن منها اذ الذي خلقها هو مبدا كل جمال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">With whose beauty if they being delighted took them to be gods; let them know how much better the Lord of them is: for the first author of beauty hath created them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">But if they were astonished at their power and virtue, let them understand by them, how much mightier he is that made them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">او لانهم دهشوا من قوتها وفعلها فليتفهموا بها كم منشئها اقوى منها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">But if they were astonished at their power and virtue, let them understand by them, how much mightier he is that made them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">For by the greatness and beauty of the creatures proportionably the maker of them is seen.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فانه بعظم جمال المبروءات يبصر فاطرها على طريق المقايسة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">For by the greatness and beauty of the creatures proportionably the maker of them is seen.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">But yet for this they are the less to be blamed: for they peradventure err, seeking God, and desirous to find him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">غير ان لهؤلاء وجها من العذر لعلهم ضلوا في طلبهم لله ورغبتهم في وجدانهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">But yet for this they are the less to be blamed: for they peradventure err, seeking God, and desirous to find him.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">For being conversant in his works they search him diligently, and believe their sight: because the things are beautiful that are seen.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">اذ هم يبحثون عنه مترددين بين مصنوعاته فيغرهم منظرها لان المنظورات ذات جمال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">For being conversant in his works they search him diligently, and believe their sight: because the things are beautiful that are seen.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Howbeit neither are they to be pardoned.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">مع ذلك ليس لهم من مغفرة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Howbeit neither are they to be pardoned.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">For if they were able to know so much, that they could aim at the world; how did they not sooner find out the Lord thereof?</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لانهم ان كانوا قد بلغوا من العلم ان استطاعوا ادراك كنه الدهر فكيف لم يكونوا اسرع ادراكا لرب الدهر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">For if they were able to know so much, that they could aim at the world; how did they not sooner find out the Lord thereof?</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">But miserable are they, and in dead things is their hope, who call them gods, which are the works of men's hands, gold and silver, to shew art in, and resemblances of beasts, or a stone good for nothing, the work of an ancient hand.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">اما الذين سموا اعمال ايدي الناس الهة الذهب والفضة وما اخترعته الصناعة وتماثيل الحيوان والحجر الحقير مما صنعته يد قديمة فهم اشقياء ورجاؤهم في الاموات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">But miserable are they, and in dead things is their hope, who call them gods, which are the works of men's hands, gold and silver, to shew art in, and resemblances of beasts, or a stone good for nothing, the work of an ancient hand.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Now a carpenter that felleth timber, after he hath sawn down a tree meet for the purpose, and taken off all the bark skilfully round about, and hath wrought it handsomely, and made a vessel thereof fit for the service of man's life;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">يقطع نجار شجرة من الغابة طوع العمل ويجردها بحذقه من قشرها كله ثم بحسن صناعته يصنعها الة تصلح لخدمة العيش</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Now a carpenter that felleth timber, after he hath sawn down a tree meet for the purpose, and taken off all the bark skilfully round about, and hath wrought it handsomely, and made a vessel thereof fit for the service of man's life;</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">And after spending the refuse of his work to dress his meat, hath filled himself;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">و يستعمل نفايتها وقودا لاعداد طعامه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">And after spending the refuse of his work to dress his meat, hath filled himself;</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">And taking the very refuse among those which served to no use, being a crooked piece of wood, and full of knots, hath carved it diligently, when he had nothing else to do, and formed it by the skill of his understanding, and fashioned it to the image of a man;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ثم ياخذ قطعة من نفايتها لا تصلح لشيء خشبة ذات اعوجاج وعقد ويعتني بنقشها في اوان فراغه ويصورها بخبرة صناعته على شكل انسان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">And taking the very refuse among those which served to no use, being a crooked piece of wood, and full of knots, hath carved it diligently, when he had nothing else to do, and formed it by the skill of his understanding, and fashioned it to the image of a man;</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">Or made it like some vile beast, laying it over with vermilion, and with paint colouring it red, and covering every spot therein;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">او يمثل بها حيوان خسيسا ويدهنها بالاسفيداج ويحمر لونها بالزنجفر ويطلي كل لطخة بها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Or made it like some vile beast, laying it over with vermilion, and with paint colouring it red, and covering every spot therein;</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">And when he had made a convenient room for it, set it in a wall, and made it fast with iron:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">و يجعل لها مقاما يليق بها ويضعها في الحائط ويوثقها بالحديد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">And when he had made a convenient room for it, set it in a wall, and made it fast with iron:</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">For he provided for it that it might not fall, knowing that it was unable to help itself; for it is an image, and hath need of help:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">و يتحفظ عليها ان لا تسقط لعلمه بانها لا تقوم بمعونة نفسها اذ هي تمثال يفتقر الى من يعينه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">For he provided for it that it might not fall, knowing that it was unable to help itself; for it is an image, and hath need of help:</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">Then maketh he prayer for his goods, for his wife and children, and is not ashamed to speak to that which hath no life.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ثم يتضرع اليها عن امواله وازواجه وبنيه ولا يخجل ان يخاطب من لا روح له</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Then maketh he prayer for his goods, for his wife and children, and is not ashamed to speak to that which hath no life.</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">For health he calleth upon that which is weak: for life prayeth to that which is dead; for aid humbly beseecheth that which hath least means to help: and for a good journey he asketh of that which cannot set a foot forward:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فيطلب العافية من السقيم ويسال الميت الحياة ويستغيث بمن هو اعجز شيء عن الاغاثة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">For health he calleth upon that which is weak: for life prayeth to that which is dead; for aid humbly beseecheth that which hath least means to help: and for a good journey he asketh of that which cannot set a foot forward:</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">And for gaining and getting, and for good success of his hands, asketh ability to do of him, that is most unable to do any thing.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">و يتوسل من اجل السفر الى من لا يستطيع المشي ويلتمس النصرة في الكسب والتجارة ونجح المساعي ممن هو اقصر موجود باعا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">And for gaining and getting, and for good success of his hands, asketh ability to do of him, that is most unable to do any thing.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <chapter num="14">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Again, one preparing himself to sail, and about to pass through the raging waves, calleth upon a piece of wood more rotten than the vessel that carrieth him.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">و اخر قبل ان يركب البحر ويسير على الامواج المعربدة يستغيث بخشب هو اقصف من المركب الذي يحمله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Again, one preparing himself to sail, and about to pass through the raging waves, calleth upon a piece of wood more rotten than the vessel that carrieth him.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">For verily desire of gain devised that, and the workman built it by his skill.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">لان المركب اخترعه حب الكسب وصنعته الحكمة المهندسة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">For verily desire of gain devised that, and the workman built it by his skill.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">But thy providence, O Father, governeth it: for thou hast made a way in the sea, and a safe path in the waves;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">لكن عنايتك ايها الاب هي التي تدبره لانك انت الذي فتحت في البحر طريقا وفي الامواج مسلكا امنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">But thy providence, O Father, governeth it: for thou hast made a way in the sea, and a safe path in the waves;</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">Shewing that thou canst save from all danger: yea, though a man went to sea without art.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و بينت انك قادر ان تخلص من كل خطر ولو ركب البحر من يجهل صناعته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Shewing that thou canst save from all danger: yea, though a man went to sea without art.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">Nevertheless thou wouldest not that the works of thy wisdom should be idle, and therefore do men commit their lives to a small piece of wood, and passing the rough sea in a weak vessel are saved.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">و انت تحب ان لا تكون اعمال حكمتك باطلة فلذلك يودع الناس انفسهم خشبا صغيرا ويقطعون اللجة في سفينة ويخلصون</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Nevertheless thou wouldest not that the works of thy wisdom should be idle, and therefore do men commit their lives to a small piece of wood, and passing the rough sea in a weak vessel are saved.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">For in the old time also, when the proud giants perished, the hope of the world governed by thy hand escaped in a weak vessel, and left to all ages a seed of generation.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">و في البدء ايضا حين هلك الجبابرة المتكبرون التجا رجاء العالم الى سفينة وارشدته يديك فابقى للدهر ذرية تتوالد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">For in the old time also, when the proud giants perished, the hope of the world governed by thy hand escaped in a weak vessel, and left to all ages a seed of generation.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">For blessed is the wood whereby righteousness cometh.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فالخشب الذي به يحصل البر هو مبارك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">For blessed is the wood whereby righteousness cometh.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">But that which is made with hands is cursed, as well it, as he that made it: he, because he made it; and it, because, being corruptible, it was called god.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">اما الخشب المصنوع صنما فملعون هو وصانعه اما هذا فلانه عمله واما ذاك فلانه مع كونه فاسدا سمي الها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">But that which is made with hands is cursed, as well it, as he that made it: he, because he made it; and it, because, being corruptible, it was called god.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">For the ungodly and his ungodliness are both alike hateful unto God.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فان الله يبغض المنافق ونفاقه على السواء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">For the ungodly and his ungodliness are both alike hateful unto God.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">For that which is made shall be punished together with him that made it.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فيصيب العقاب المصنوع والصانع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">For that which is made shall be punished together with him that made it.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Therefore even upon the idols of the Gentiles shall there be a visitation: because in the creature of God they are become an abomination, and stumblingblocks to the souls of men, and a snare to the feet of the unwise.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لذلك ستفتقد اصنام الامم ايضا لانها صارت في خلق الله رجسا ومعثرة لنفوس الناس وفخا لاقدام الجهال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Therefore even upon the idols of the Gentiles shall there be a visitation: because in the creature of God they are become an abomination, and stumblingblocks to the souls of men, and a snare to the feet of the unwise.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">For the devising of idols was the beginning of spiritual fornication, and the invention of them the corruption of life.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">لان اختراع الاصنام هو اصل الفسق ووجدانها فساد الحياة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">For the devising of idols was the beginning of spiritual fornication, and the invention of them the corruption of life.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">For neither were they from the beginning, neither shall they be for ever.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">و هي لم تكن في البدء وليست تدوم الى الابد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">For neither were they from the beginning, neither shall they be for ever.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">For by the vain glory of men they entered into the world, and therefore shall they come shortly to an end.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">لانها انما دخلت العالم بحب الناس للمجد الفارغ ولذلك قد عزم على الغائها عن قريب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">For by the vain glory of men they entered into the world, and therefore shall they come shortly to an end.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">For a father afflicted with untimely mourning, when he hath made an image of his child soon taken away, now honoured him as a god, which was then a dead man, and delivered to those that were under him ceremonies and sacrifices.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">و ذلك ان والدا قد فجع بثكل معجل فصنع تمثالا لابنه الذي خطف سريعا وجعل يعبد ذلك الانسان الميت بمنزلة اله ورسم للذين تحت يده شعائر وذبائح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">For a father afflicted with untimely mourning, when he hath made an image of his child soon taken away, now honoured him as a god, which was then a dead man, and delivered to those that were under him ceremonies and sacrifices.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">Thus in process of time an ungodly custom grown strong was kept as a law, and graven images were worshipped by the commandments of kings.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">ثم على ممر الزمان تاصلت تلك العادة الكفرية فحفظت كشريعة وباوامر الملوك عبدت المنحوتات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Thus in process of time an ungodly custom grown strong was kept as a law, and graven images were worshipped by the commandments of kings.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">Whom men could not honour in presence, because they dwelt far off, they took the counterfeit of his visage from far, and made an express image of a king whom they honoured, to the end that by this their forwardness they might flatter him that was absent, as if he were present.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">و الذين لم يستطع الناس اكرامهم بمحضرهم لبعد مقامهم صوروا هيئاتهم الغائبة وجعلوا صورة الملك المكرم نصب العيون حرصا على تملقه في الغيبة كانه حاضر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Whom men could not honour in presence, because they dwelt far off, they took the counterfeit of his visage from far, and made an express image of a king whom they honoured, to the end that by this their forwardness they might flatter him that was absent, as if he were present.</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">Also the singular diligence of the artificer did help to set forward the ignorant to more superstition.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">ثم ان حب الصناع للمباهاة كان داعية للجاهلين الى المبالغة في هذه العبادة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Also the singular diligence of the artificer did help to set forward the ignorant to more superstition.</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">For he, peradventure willing to please one in authority, forced all his skill to make the resemblance of the best fashion.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">فانهم رغبة في ارضاء الامر قد افرغوا وسعهم في الصناعة لاخراج الصورة على غاية الكمال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">For he, peradventure willing to please one in authority, forced all his skill to make the resemblance of the best fashion.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">And so the multitude, allured by the grace of the work, took him now for a god, which a little before was but honoured as a man.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">فاستميل الجمهور ببهجة ذلك المصنوع حتى ان الذي كانوا قبل قليل يكرمونه كانسان عدوه الها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">And so the multitude, allured by the grace of the work, took him now for a god, which a little before was but honoured as a man.</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">And this was an occasion to deceive the world: for men, serving either calamity or tyranny, did ascribe unto stones and stocks the incommunicable name.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">و بهذا كان اقتناص الخلق فان رزيئة بعض الناس او اقتسار الملوك استعبدهم حتى جعلوا على الحجر والخشب الاسم الذي لا يشرك فيه احد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">And this was an occasion to deceive the world: for men, serving either calamity or tyranny, did ascribe unto stones and stocks the incommunicable name.</language></verse>
    <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">Moreover this was not enough for them, that they erred in the knowledge of God; but whereas they lived in the great war of ignorance, those so great plagues called they peace.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">ثم لم يكتفوا بضلالهم في معرفة الله لكنهم غاصوا في حرب الجهل الشديدة وهم يسمون مثل هذه الشرور سلاما</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Moreover this was not enough for them, that they erred in the knowledge of God; but whereas they lived in the great war of ignorance, those so great plagues called they peace.</language></verse>
    <verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23">For whilst they slew their children in sacrifices, or used secret ceremonies, or made revellings of strange rites;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">فانهم يمارسون ذبائح من بنيهم وشعائر خفية ومادب جنون على اساليب اخر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">For whilst they slew their children in sacrifices, or used secret ceremonies, or made revellings of strange rites;</language></verse>
    <verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24">They kept neither lives nor marriages any longer undefiled: but either one slew another traiterously, or grieved him by adultery.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">لا يرعون حسن السيرة ولا طهارة الزواج فيقتل الرجل صاحبه بالاغتيال ويمضه بالفاحشة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">They kept neither lives nor marriages any longer undefiled: but either one slew another traiterously, or grieved him by adultery.</language></verse>
    <verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25">So that there reigned in all men without exception blood, manslaughter, theft, and dissimulation, corruption, unfaithfulness, tumults, perjury,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">شر متفاقم في كل موضع الدم والقتل والسرقة والمكر والفساد والخيانة والفتنة والحنث وقلق الابرار</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">So that there reigned in all men without exception blood, manslaughter, theft, and dissimulation, corruption, unfaithfulness, tumults, perjury,</language></verse>
    <verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26">Disquieting of good men, forgetfulness of good turns, defiling of souls, changing of kind, disorder in marriages, adultery, and shameless uncleanness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">و كفران النعمة وتدنس النفوس والتباس المواليد وتشوش الزواج والفسق والعهر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">Disquieting of good men, forgetfulness of good turns, defiling of souls, changing of kind, disorder in marriages, adultery, and shameless uncleanness.</language></verse>
    <verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27">For the worshipping of idols not to be named is the beginning, the cause, and the end, of all evil.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">لان عبادة الاصنام المكروهة هي علة كل شر وابتداؤه وغايته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">For the worshipping of idols not to be named is the beginning, the cause, and the end, of all evil.</language></verse>
    <verse num="28"><language id="English" verse="28">For either they are mad when they be merry, or prophesy lies, or live unjustly, or else lightly forswear themselves.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="28">فانهم اذا فرحوا جنوا او تنباوا كذبوا او عاملوا ظلموا او حالفوا اسرعوا الى الحنث</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="28">For either they are mad when they be merry, or prophesy lies, or live unjustly, or else lightly forswear themselves.</language></verse>
    <verse num="29"><language id="English" verse="29">For insomuch as their trust is in idols, which have no life; though they swear falsely, yet they look not to be hurt.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="29">و لتوكلهم على اصنام لا ارواح له لا يتوقعون اذا اقسموا بالزور ان ينالهم الخسران</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="29">For insomuch as their trust is in idols, which have no life; though they swear falsely, yet they look not to be hurt.</language></verse>
    <verse num="30"><language id="English" verse="30">Howbeit for both causes shall they be justly punished: both because they thought not well of God, giving heed unto idols, and also unjustly swore in deceit, despising holiness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="30">فهناك امران يستحقون بهما حلول اعقاب سوء اعتقادهم في الله اذ اتبعوا الاصنام وقسمهم بالظلم والمكر اذا ستخفوا بالقداسة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="30">Howbeit for both causes shall they be justly punished: both because they thought not well of God, giving heed unto idols, and also unjustly swore in deceit, despising holiness.</language></verse>
    <verse num="31"><language id="English" verse="31">For it is not the power of them by whom they swear: but it is the just vengeance of sinners, that punisheth always the offence of the ungodly.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="31">لان معصية الظالمين انما يتعقبها القضاء على الخطاة لا قدرة المقسم بهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="31">For it is not the power of them by whom they swear: but it is the just vengeance of sinners, that punisheth always the offence of the ungodly.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <!-- Chunk 8/10: Chapters 15-16 -->
  <chapter num="15">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">But thou, O God, art gracious and true, longsuffering, and in mercy ordering all things,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">و انت يا الهنا ذو صلاح وصدق طويل الاناة ومدبر الجميع بالرحمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">But thou, O God, art gracious and true, longsuffering, and in mercy ordering all things,</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">For if we sin, we are thine, knowing thy power: but we will not sin, knowing that we are counted thine.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فاذا خطئنا فنحن في يدك وقد علمنا قدرتك لكنا لا نختار الخطا لعلمنا بانا من خاصتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">For if we sin, we are thine, knowing thy power: but we will not sin, knowing that we are counted thine.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">For to know thee is perfect righteousness: yea, to know thy power is the root of immortality.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فان معرفتك هي البر الكامل والعلم بقدرتك هو اصل الحياة الدائمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">For to know thee is perfect righteousness: yea, to know thy power is the root of immortality.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">For neither did the mischievous invention of men deceive us, nor an image spotted with divers colours, the painter's fruitless labour;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">لذلك لم يغونا ما اخترعته صناعة الناس الممقوتة ولا عمل المصورين العقيم من الصور الملطخة بالالوان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">For neither did the mischievous invention of men deceive us, nor an image spotted with divers colours, the painter's fruitless labour;</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">The sight whereof enticeth fools to lust after it, and so they desire the form of a dead image, that hath no breath.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">التي في النظر اليها فضيحة للسفهاء بعشقهم صورة تمثال ميت لا روح فيه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">The sight whereof enticeth fools to lust after it, and so they desire the form of a dead image, that hath no breath.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">Both they that make them, they that desire them, and they that worship them, are lovers of evil things, and are worthy to have such things to trust upon.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لا جرم ان الذين يصنعونها والذين يعشقونها والذين يعبدونها هم كلفون بالمنكرات وهم اهل لان تكون امالهم في امثال هذه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Both they that make them, they that desire them, and they that worship them, are lovers of evil things, and are worthy to have such things to trust upon.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">For the potter, tempering soft earth, fashioneth every vessel with much labour for our service: yea, of the same clay he maketh both the vessels that serve for clean uses, and likewise also all such as serve to the contrary: but what is the use of either sort, the potter himself is the judge.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">ان الخزاف يعني بعجن الطين اللين ويصنع منه كل اناء مما نستخدمه فيصنع من الطين الواحد الانية المستخدمة في الاعمال الطاهرة والمستخدمة في عكس ذلك واما تخصيص كل اناء بواحدة من الخدمتين فانما يرجع الى حكم صانع الطين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">For the potter, tempering soft earth, fashioneth every vessel with much labour for our service: yea, of the same clay he maketh both the vessels that serve for clean uses, and likewise also all such as serve to the contrary: but what is the use of either sort, the potter himself is the judge.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">And employing his labours lewdly, he maketh a vain god of the same clay, even he which a little before was made of earth himself, and within a little while after returneth to the same, out when his life which was lent him shall be demanded.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">و بعنائه الممقوت يصنع من هذا الطين الها باطلا وهو انما ولد من الطين من حين يسير وعن قليل سيعود الى ما اخذ منه حين يطالب بدين نفسه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">And employing his labours lewdly, he maketh a vain god of the same clay, even he which a little before was made of earth himself, and within a little while after returneth to the same, out when his life which was lent him shall be demanded.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">Notwithstanding his care is, not that he shall have much labour, nor that his life is short: but striveth to excel goldsmiths and silversmiths, and endeavoureth to do like the workers in brass, and counteth it his glory to make counterfeit things.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">غير ان همه ليس بانه يتعب ولا بانه قريب الاجل لكنه يباري صاغة الذهب والفضة ويعارض النحاسين ويعتد ما يصنعه من الخسائس فخرا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Notwithstanding his care is, not that he shall have much labour, nor that his life is short: but striveth to excel goldsmiths and silversmiths, and endeavoureth to do like the workers in brass, and counteth it his glory to make counterfeit things.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">His heart is ashes, his hope is more vile than earth, and his life of less value than clay:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فقلبه رماد ورجاؤه اخس من التراب وحياته احقر من الطين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">His heart is ashes, his hope is more vile than earth, and his life of less value than clay:</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">Forasmuch as he knew not his Maker, and him that inspired into him an active soul, and breathed in a living spirit.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">لانه جهل من جبله ونفخ فيه نفسا عاملة وروحا محييا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Forasmuch as he knew not his Maker, and him that inspired into him an active soul, and breathed in a living spirit.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">But they counted our life a pastime, and our time here a market for gain: for, say they, we must be getting every way, though it be by evil means.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">بل حسب حياتنا عبثا وعمرنا موسما للاكتساب وزعم انه لا بد من الربح بكل حيلة ولو بالظلم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">But they counted our life a pastime, and our time here a market for gain: for, say they, we must be getting every way, though it be by evil means.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">For this man, that of earthly matter maketh brittle vessels and graven images, knoweth himself to offend above all others.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فانه عالم بانه اعظم جرما من الجميع لانه يصنع من طين الارض انية قصمة ومنحوتات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">For this man, that of earthly matter maketh brittle vessels and graven images, knoweth himself to offend above all others.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">And all the enemies of thy people, that hold them in subjection, are most foolish, and are more miserable than very babes.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ان جميع اعداء شعبك المتسلطين عليهم هم اجهل الناس واشقى من نفوس الاطفال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">And all the enemies of thy people, that hold them in subjection, are most foolish, and are more miserable than very babes.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">For they counted all the idols of the heathen to be gods: which neither have the use of eyes to see, nor noses to draw breath, nor ears to hear, nor fingers of hands to handle; and as for their feet, they are slow to go.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">لانهم حسبوا جميع اصنام الامم الهة تلك التي لا تبصر بعيونها ولا تنشق الهواء بانوفها ولا تسمع باذانها ولا تلمس باصابع ايديها وارجلها عاجزة عن الخطو</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">For they counted all the idols of the heathen to be gods: which neither have the use of eyes to see, nor noses to draw breath, nor ears to hear, nor fingers of hands to handle; and as for their feet, they are slow to go.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">For man made them, and he that borrowed his own spirit fashioned them: but no man can make a god like unto himself.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لانها انما عملها انسان والذي اعير روحا صنعها وليس في طاقة انسان ان يصنع الها مثله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">For man made them, and he that borrowed his own spirit fashioned them: but no man can make a god like unto himself.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">For being mortal, he worketh a dead thing with wicked hands: for he himself is better than the things which he worshippeth: whereas he lived once, but they never.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">و انما هو فان فيصنع بيديه الاثيمتين ما لا حياة فيه فهو افضل من معبوداته اذ هو قد كان حيا واما هي فلم تكن حية البتة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">For being mortal, he worketh a dead thing with wicked hands: for he himself is better than the things which he worshippeth: whereas he lived once, but they never.</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">Yea, they worshipped those beasts also that are most hateful: for being compared together, some are worse than others.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و هم يعبدون اعدى الحيوان مما هو اشد البهائم عجمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Yea, they worshipped those beasts also that are most hateful: for being compared together, some are worse than others.</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">Neither are they beautiful, so much as to be desired in respect of beasts: but they went without the praise of God and his blessing.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">و ليس فيه ما في منظر الحيوانات الاخر من الحسن الشائق اذ فاته مدح الله وبركته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Neither are they beautiful, so much as to be desired in respect of beasts: but they went without the praise of God and his blessing.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <chapter num="16">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Therefore by the like were they punished worthily, and by the multitude of beasts tormented.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">لذلك كانوا احقاء بان يعاقبوا بامثال هذه ويعذبوا بجم من الحشرات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Therefore by the like were they punished worthily, and by the multitude of beasts tormented.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">Instead of which punishment, dealing graciously with thine own people, thou preparedst for them meat of a strange taste, even quails to stir up their appetite:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">اما شعبك فبدلا من ذلك العقاب احسنت اليهم باعداد السلوى ماكلا غريب الطعم اشبعت به شهوتهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Instead of which punishment, dealing graciously with thine own people, thou preparedst for them meat of a strange taste, even quails to stir up their appetite:</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">To the end that they, desiring food, might for the ugly sight of the beasts sent among them lothe even that, which they must needs desire; but these, suffering penury for a short space, might be made partakers of a strange taste.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">حتى انه بينما كان اولئك مع جوعهم فاقدي كل شهوة للطعام من كراهة ما بعثت عليهم كان هؤلاء بعد عوز يسير يتناولون ماكلا غريب الطعم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">To the end that they, desiring food, might for the ugly sight of the beasts sent among them lothe even that, which they must needs desire; but these, suffering penury for a short space, might be made partakers of a strange taste.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">For it was requisite, that upon them exercising tyranny should come penury, which they could not avoid: but to these it should only be shewed how their enemies were tormented.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فانه كان ينبغي لاولئك المقتسرين ان تنزل بهم فاقة لا مناص منها ولهؤلاء ان يروا كيف يعذب اعداؤهم لا غير</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">For it was requisite, that upon them exercising tyranny should come penury, which they could not avoid: but to these it should only be shewed how their enemies were tormented.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">For when the horrible fierceness of beasts came upon these, and they perished with the stings of crooked serpents, thy wrath endured not for ever:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">و لما اقتحم هؤلاء حنق الوحوش الهائل واهلكهم لدغ الحيات الخبيثة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">For when the horrible fierceness of beasts came upon these, and they perished with the stings of crooked serpents, thy wrath endured not for ever:</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">But they were troubled for a small season, that they might be admonished, having a sign of salvation, to put them in remembrance of the commandment of thy law.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لم يستمر غضبك الى المنتهى بل انما اقلقوا الى حين انذارا لهم ونصبت لهم علامة للخلاص تذكرهم وصية شريعتك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">But they were troubled for a small season, that they might be admonished, having a sign of salvation, to put them in remembrance of the commandment of thy law.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">For he that turned himself toward it was not saved by the thing that he saw, but by thee, that art the Saviour of all.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فكان الملتفت اليها يخلص لا بذلك المنظور بل بك يا مخلص الجميع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">For he that turned himself toward it was not saved by the thing that he saw, but by thee, that art the Saviour of all.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">And in this thou madest thine enemies confess, that it is thou who deliverest from all evil:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">و بذلك اثبت لاعدائنا انك انت المنقذ من كل سوء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">And in this thou madest thine enemies confess, that it is thou who deliverest from all evil:</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">For them the bitings of grasshoppers and flies killed, neither was there found any remedy for their life: for they were worthy to be punished by such.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لان اولئك قتلهم لسع الجراد والذباب ولم يوجد لنفوسهم شفاء اذ هم اهل لان يعاقبوا بمثل ذلك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">For them the bitings of grasshoppers and flies killed, neither was there found any remedy for their life: for they were worthy to be punished by such.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">But thy sons not the very teeth of venomous dragons overcame: for thy mercy was ever by them, and healed them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">اما بنوك فلم تقو عليهم انياب التنانين السامة لان رحمتك اقبلت وشفتهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">But thy sons not the very teeth of venomous dragons overcame: for thy mercy was ever by them, and healed them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">For they were pricked, that they should remember thy words; and were quickly saved, that not falling into deep forgetfulness, they might be continually mindful of thy goodness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">و انما نخسوا ليتذكروا اقوالك ثم خلصوا سريعا لئلا يسقطوا في نسيان عميق فيحرموا احسانك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">For they were pricked, that they should remember thy words; and were quickly saved, that not falling into deep forgetfulness, they might be continually mindful of thy goodness.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">For it was neither herb, nor mollifying plaister, that restored them to health: but thy word, O Lord, which healeth all things.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">و ما شفاهم نبت ولا مرهم بل كلمتك يارب التي تشفي الجميع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">For it was neither herb, nor mollifying plaister, that restored them to health: but thy word, O Lord, which healeth all things.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">For thou hast power of life and death: thou leadest to the gates of hell, and bringest up again.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">لان لك سلطان الحياة والموت فتحدر الى ابواب الجحيم وتصعد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">For thou hast power of life and death: thou leadest to the gates of hell, and bringest up again.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">A man indeed killeth through his malice: and the spirit, when it is gone forth, returneth not; neither the soul received up cometh again.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">اما الانسان فيقتل بخبثه لكنه لا يعيد الروح الذي قد خرج ولا يسترجع النفس المقبوضة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">A man indeed killeth through his malice: and the spirit, when it is gone forth, returneth not; neither the soul received up cometh again.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">But it is not possible to escape thine hand.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">انه ليس احد يستطيع ان يهرب من يدك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">But it is not possible to escape thine hand.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">For the ungodly, that denied to know thee, were scourged by the strength of thine arm: with strange rains, hails, and showers, were they persecuted, that they could not avoid, and through fire were they consumed.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فانك قد جلدت بقوة ذراعك المنافقين الذين جحدوا معرفتك واطلقت في اثرهم سيولا وبردا وامطارا غريبة ونارا اكلة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">For the ungodly, that denied to know thee, were scourged by the strength of thine arm: with strange rains, hails, and showers, were they persecuted, that they could not avoid, and through fire were they consumed.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">For, which is most to be wondered at, the fire had more force in the water, that quencheth all things: for the world fighteth for the righteous.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">و اغرب شيء ان النار كانت في الماء الذي يطفئ كل شيء تزداد حدة لان عناصر العالم تقاتل عن الصديقين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">For, which is most to be wondered at, the fire had more force in the water, that quencheth all things: for the world fighteth for the righteous.</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">For sometime the flame was mitigated, that it might not burn up the beasts that were sent against the ungodly; but themselves might see and perceive that they were persecuted with the judgment of God.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و كان اللهيب تارة يسكن لئلا يحرق ما ارسل على المنافقين من الحيوان ولكي يبصروا فيعلموا ان قضاء الله على اعقابهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">For sometime the flame was mitigated, that it might not burn up the beasts that were sent against the ungodly; but themselves might see and perceive that they were persecuted with the judgment of God.</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">And at another time it burneth even in the midst of water above the power of fire, that it might destroy the fruits of an unjust land.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">و تارة يخرج عن طبع النار فيتاجج في الماء لكي يستاصل انبتة الارض الاثيمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">And at another time it burneth even in the midst of water above the power of fire, that it might destroy the fruits of an unjust land.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">Instead whereof thou feddest thine own people with angels' food, and didst send them from heaven bread prepared without their labour, able to content every man's delight, and agreeing to every taste.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">اما شعبك فبدلا من ذلك اطعمتهم طعام الملائكة وارسلت لهم من السماء خبزا معدا لا تعب فيه يتضمن كل لذة ويلائم كل ذوق</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Instead whereof thou feddest thine own people with angels' food, and didst send them from heaven bread prepared without their labour, able to content every man's delight, and agreeing to every taste.</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">For thy sustenance declared thy sweetness unto thy children, and serving to the appetite of the eater, tempered itself to every man's liking.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">لان جوهرك ابدى عذوبتك لبنيك فكان يخدم شهوة المتناول ويتحول الى ما شاء كل واحد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">For thy sustenance declared thy sweetness unto thy children, and serving to the appetite of the eater, tempered itself to every man's liking.</language></verse>
    <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">But snow and ice endured the fire, and melted not, that they might know that fire burning in the hail, and sparkling in the rain, did destroy the fruits of the enemies.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">و كان الثلج والجليد يثبتان في النار ولا يذوبان لكي يعلم كيف اكلت ثمار الاعداء نار تلتهب في البرد وتبرق في المطر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">But snow and ice endured the fire, and melted not, that they might know that fire burning in the hail, and sparkling in the rain, did destroy the fruits of the enemies.</language></verse>
    <verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23">But this again did even forget his own strength, that the righteous might be nourished.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">اما عند هؤلاء فقد تناست القوة التي لها لكي يغتذي القديسون</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">But this again did even forget his own strength, that the righteous might be nourished.</language></verse>
    <verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24">For the creature that serveth thee, who art the Maker increaseth his strength against the unrighteous for their punishment, and abateth his strength for the benefit of such as put their trust in thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">اذ الخليقة الخادمة لك انت صانعها تتشدد لتعاقب المجرمين وتتراخى لتحسن الى المتوكلين عليك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">For the creature that serveth thee, who art the Maker increaseth his strength against the unrighteous for their punishment, and abateth his strength for the benefit of such as put their trust in thee.</language></verse>
    <verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25">Therefore even then was it altered into all fashions, and was obedient to thy grace, that nourisheth all things, according to the desire of them that had need:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">لذلك كانت حينئذ تتحول الى كل شيء لتخدم نعمتك الغاذية الجميع على ما يشاء كل محتاج</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Therefore even then was it altered into all fashions, and was obedient to thy grace, that nourisheth all things, according to the desire of them that had need:</language></verse>
    <verse num="26"><language id="English" verse="26">That thy children, O Lord, whom thou lovest, might know, that it is not the growing of fruits that nourisheth man: but that it is thy word, which preserveth them that put their trust in thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="26">لكي يعلم بنوك الذين احببتهم ايها الرب ان ليس ما تخرج الارض من الثمار هو يغذو الانسان لكن كلمتك هي التي تحفظ المؤمنين بك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="26">That thy children, O Lord, whom thou lovest, might know, that it is not the growing of fruits that nourisheth man: but that it is thy word, which preserveth them that put their trust in thee.</language></verse>
    <verse num="27"><language id="English" verse="27">For that which was not destroyed of the fire, being warmed with a little sunbeam, soon melted away:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="27">اذ ما لم تكن النار تحله كانت شعاعة يسيرة من الشمس تحميه فيذوب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="27">For that which was not destroyed of the fire, being warmed with a little sunbeam, soon melted away:</language></verse>
    <verse num="28"><language id="English" verse="28">That it might be known, that we must prevent the sun to give thee thanks, and at the dayspring pray unto thee.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="28">حتى يعلم انه يجب ان نسبق الشمس الى شكرك ونحضر امامك عند شروق النور</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="28">That it might be known, that we must prevent the sun to give thee thanks, and at the dayspring pray unto thee.</language></verse>
    <verse num="29"><language id="English" verse="29">For the hope of the unthankful shall melt away as the winter's hoar frost, and shall run away as unprofitable water.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="29">لان رجاء من لا شكر له يذوب كجليد شتوي ويذهب كماء لا منفعة فيه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="29">For the hope of the unthankful shall melt away as the winter's hoar frost, and shall run away as unprofitable water.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <!-- Chunk 9/10: Chapters 17-18 -->
  <chapter num="17">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">For great are thy judgments, and cannot be expressed: therefore unnurtured souls have erred.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">ان احكامك عظيمة لا يعبر عنها ولذلك ضلت النفوس التي لا تاديب لها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">For great are thy judgments, and cannot be expressed: therefore unnurtured souls have erred.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">For when unrighteous men thought to oppress the holy nation; they being shut up in their houses, the prisoners of darkness, and fettered with the bonds of a long night, lay [there] exiled from the eternal providence.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فانه لما توهم المجرمون انهم يتسلطون على الامة القديسة اذا هم ملقون في اسر الظلمة وقيود الليل الطويل محبوسون تحت سقوفهم منفيون عن العناية الابدية</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">For when unrighteous men thought to oppress the holy nation; they being shut up in their houses, the prisoners of darkness, and fettered with the bonds of a long night, lay [there] exiled from the eternal providence.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">For while they supposed to lie hid in their secret sins, they were scattered under a dark veil of forgetfulness, being horribly astonished, and troubled with [strange] apparitions.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و اذ حسبوا انهم مستترون في خطاياهم الخفية فرق بينهم ستر النسيان المظلم وهم في رعب شديد تقلقهم الاخيلة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">For while they supposed to lie hid in their secret sins, they were scattered under a dark veil of forgetfulness, being horribly astonished, and troubled with [strange] apparitions.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">For neither might the corner that held them keep them from fear: but noises [as of waters] falling down sounded about them, and sad visions appeared unto them with heavy countenances.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و لم تكن الاكنة التي لبثوا فيها لتقيهم من الذعر فقد كانت اصوات قاصفة تدوي من حولهم واشباح مكفهرة تتراى امام وجوههم الكاسفة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">For neither might the corner that held them keep them from fear: but noises [as of waters] falling down sounded about them, and sad visions appeared unto them with heavy countenances.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">No power of the fire might give them light: neither could the bright flames of the stars endure to lighten that horrible night.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">و لم يكن في قوة النار مهما اشتدت ان تاتي بضياء ولا في بريق النجوم ان ينير ذلك الليل المدلهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">No power of the fire might give them light: neither could the bright flames of the stars endure to lighten that horrible night.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">Only there appeared unto them a fire kindled of itself, very dreadful: for being much terrified, they thought the things which they saw to be worse than the sight they saw not.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">و انما كانت تلمع لهم بغتة نيران مخيفة فيرتعدون من ذلك المنظر المبهم ويتوهمون ما يظهر لهم اهول مما هو</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Only there appeared unto them a fire kindled of itself, very dreadful: for being much terrified, they thought the things which they saw to be worse than the sight they saw not.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">As for the illusions of art magick, they were put down, and their vaunting in wisdom was reproved with disgrace.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">حينئذ بطلت صناعة السحر وشعوذته وبرز على افتخارهم بالحكمة حجة مخزية</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">As for the illusions of art magick, they were put down, and their vaunting in wisdom was reproved with disgrace.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">For they, that promised to drive away terrors and troubles from a sick soul, were sick themselves of fear, worthy to be laughed at.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">اذ الذين وعدوا بنفي الجزع والبلبال عن النفس الدنفة هؤلاء ادنفهم خوف مضحك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">For they, that promised to drive away terrors and troubles from a sick soul, were sick themselves of fear, worthy to be laughed at.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">For though no terrible thing did fear them; yet being scared with beasts that passed by, and hissing of serpents,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فانهم وان لم يصبهم شيء هائل كان مرور الوحوش وفحيح الافاعي يدحرهم فيهلكون من الخوف ويتوقون حتى الهواء الذي لا محيد عنه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">For though no terrible thing did fear them; yet being scared with beasts that passed by, and hissing of serpents,</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">They died for fear, denying that they saw the air, which could of no side be avoided.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لان الخبث ملازم للجبن فهو يقضي على نفسه بشهادته ولقلق الضمير لا يزال متخيلا الضربات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">They died for fear, denying that they saw the air, which could of no side be avoided.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">For wickedness, condemned by her own witness, is very timorous, and being pressed with conscience, always forecasteth grievous things.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فان الخوف انما هو ترك المدد الذي من العقل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">For wickedness, condemned by her own witness, is very timorous, and being pressed with conscience, always forecasteth grievous things.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">For fear is nothing else but a betraying of the succours which reason offereth.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">و انتظار المدد من الداخل اضعف ولذلك تحسب مجلبة العذاب المجهولة اشد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">For fear is nothing else but a betraying of the succours which reason offereth.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">And the expectation from within, being less, counteth the ignorance more than the cause which bringeth the torment.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فالذين ناموا تلك النومة في ذلك الليل الذي لا يطاق الوارد من اخاديد الجحيم الفظيعة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">And the expectation from within, being less, counteth the ignorance more than the cause which bringeth the torment.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">But they sleeping the same sleep that night, which was indeed intolerable, and which came upon them out of the bottoms of inevitable hell,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">كانوا تارة تقتحمهم الاخيلة وتارة تنحل قواهم من انخلاع قلوبهم لما غشيهم من مفاجاة الخوف الغير المتوقع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">But they sleeping the same sleep that night, which was indeed intolerable, and which came upon them out of the bottoms of inevitable hell,</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">Were partly vexed with monstrous apparitions, and partly fainted, their heart failing them: for a sudden fear, and not looked for, came upon them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">ثم حيثما سقط احد بقى محبوسا في سجن لا حديد فيه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Were partly vexed with monstrous apparitions, and partly fainted, their heart failing them: for a sudden fear, and not looked for, came upon them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">So then whosoever there fell down was straitly kept, shut up in a prison without iron bars,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فان كان فلاحا او راعيا او صاحب عمل من اعمال الصحراء اخذ بغتة فوقع في قسر لا انفكاك عنه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">So then whosoever there fell down was straitly kept, shut up in a prison without iron bars,</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">For whether he were husbandman, or shepherd, or a labourer in the field, he was overtaken, and endured that necessity, which could not be avoided: for they were all bound with one chain of darkness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">اذ جميعهم كانوا مقيدين بسلسلة واحدة من الظلام فدوي الريح واغاريد الطيور على الاغصان الملتفة وصوت المياه المندفعة بقوة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">For whether he were husbandman, or shepherd, or a labourer in the field, he was overtaken, and endured that necessity, which could not be avoided: for they were all bound with one chain of darkness.</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">Whether it were a whistling wind, or a melodious noise of birds among the spreading branches, or a pleasing fall of water running violently,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و قعقعة الحجارة المتدحرجة وركض الحيوانات الذي لا يرى وزئير الوحوش الضارية والصدى المتردد في بطون الجبال كل ذلك كان يذيبهم من الخوف</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Whether it were a whistling wind, or a melodious noise of birds among the spreading branches, or a pleasing fall of water running violently,</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">Or a terrible sound of stones cast down, or a running that could not be seen of skipping beasts, or a roaring voice of most savage wild beasts, or a rebounding echo from the hollow mountains; these things made them to swoon for fear.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">و بينما كان سائر العالم يضيئه نور ساطع ويتعاطى اعماله بغير مانع</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Or a terrible sound of stones cast down, or a running that could not be seen of skipping beasts, or a roaring voice of most savage wild beasts, or a rebounding echo from the hollow mountains; these things made them to swoon for fear.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">For the whole world shined with clear light, and none were hindered in their labour:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">كان اولئك منفردين في ظل ليل مدلهم مشاكل لما سيغشاهم من الظلمة لكنهم كانوا على انفسهم اثقل من الظلمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">For the whole world shined with clear light, and none were hindered in their labour:</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">Over them only was spread an heavy night, an image of that darkness which should afterward receive them: but yet were they unto themselves more grievous than the darkness.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">Over them only was spread an heavy night, an image of that darkness which should afterward receive them: but yet were they unto themselves more grievous than the darkness.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Over them only was spread an heavy night, an image of that darkness which should afterward receive them: but yet were they unto themselves more grievous than the darkness.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <chapter num="18">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">Nevertheless thy saints had a very great light, whose voice they hearing, and not seeing their shape, because they also had not suffered the same things, they counted them happy.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">اما قديسوك فكان عندهم نور عظيم وكان اولئك يسمعون اصواتهم بغير ان يبصروا اشخاصهم ويغبطونهم على انهم لا يقاسون مثل حالهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Nevertheless thy saints had a very great light, whose voice they hearing, and not seeing their shape, because they also had not suffered the same things, they counted them happy.</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">But for that they did not hurt them now, of whom they had been wronged before, they thanked them, and besought them pardon for that they had been enemies.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">و يشكرونهم على انهم لا يؤذون الذين قد ظلموهم ويستغفرونهم من معاداتهم لهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">But for that they did not hurt them now, of whom they had been wronged before, they thanked them, and besought them pardon for that they had been enemies.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">Instead whereof thou gavest them a burning pillar of fire, both to be a guide of the unknown journey, and an harmless sun to entertain them honourably.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">و بازاء ذلك جعلت لهؤلاء عمود نار دليلا في طريق لم يعرفوه شمسا لتلك الضيافة الكريمة لا اذى بها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Instead whereof thou gavest them a burning pillar of fire, both to be a guide of the unknown journey, and an harmless sun to entertain them honourably.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">For they were worthy to be deprived of light and imprisoned in darkness, who had kept thy sons shut up, by whom the uncorrupt light of the law was to be given unto the world.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">اما اولئك فكان جديرا بهم ان يفقدوا النور ويحبسوا في الظلمة لانهم حبسوا بنيك الذين بهم سيمنح الدهر نور شريعتك الغير الفاني</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">For they were worthy to be deprived of light and imprisoned in darkness, who had kept thy sons shut up, by whom the uncorrupt light of the law was to be given unto the world.</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">And when they had determined to slay the babes of the saints, one child being cast forth, and saved, to reprove them, thou tookest away the multitude of their children, and destroyedst them altogether in a mighty water.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">و لما ائتمروا ان يقتلوا اطفال القديسين وعرض واحد منهم لذلك ثم خلص عاقبتهم انت باهلاك جمهور اولادهم ثم دمرتهم جميعا في الماء الغامر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">And when they had determined to slay the babes of the saints, one child being cast forth, and saved, to reprove them, thou tookest away the multitude of their children, and destroyedst them altogether in a mighty water.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">Of that night were our fathers certified afore, that assuredly knowing unto what oaths they had given credence, they might afterwards be of good cheer.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">و تلك الليلة قد اخبر بها اباؤنا من قبل لكي تطيب نفوسهم لعلمهم اليقين ما الاقسام التي يثقون بها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Of that night were our fathers certified afore, that assuredly knowing unto what oaths they had given credence, they might afterwards be of good cheer.</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">So of thy people was accepted both the salvation of the righteous, and destruction of the enemies.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">ففاز شعبك بخلاص الصديقين وهلاك الاعداء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">So of thy people was accepted both the salvation of the righteous, and destruction of the enemies.</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">For wherewith thou didst punish our adversaries, by the same thou didst glorify us, whom thou hadst called.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فان الذي عاقبت به المقاومين هو الذي جذبتنا به اليك ومجدتنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">For wherewith thou didst punish our adversaries, by the same thou didst glorify us, whom thou hadst called.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">For the righteous children of good men did sacrifice secretly, and with one consent made a holy law, that the saints should be like partakers of the same good and evil, the fathers now singing out the songs of praise.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فان القديسين بني الصالحين كانوا يذبحون خفية ويوجبون على انفسهم شريعة الله هذه ان يشترك القديسون في السراء والضراء على السواء وكانوا يرنمون بتسابيح الاباء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">For the righteous children of good men did sacrifice secretly, and with one consent made a holy law, that the saints should be like partakers of the same good and evil, the fathers now singing out the songs of praise.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">But on the other side there sounded an ill according cry of the enemies, and a lamentable noise was carried abroad for children that were bewailed.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">و قد رفع الاعداء جلبة اصواتهم بالبكاء والنحيب على اطفالهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">But on the other side there sounded an ill according cry of the enemies, and a lamentable noise was carried abroad for children that were bewailed.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">The master and the servant were punished after one manner; and like as the king, so suffered the common person.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">و كان قضاء واحد على العبد والمولى وضربة واحدة نالت الشعب والملك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">The master and the servant were punished after one manner; and like as the king, so suffered the common person.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">So they all together had innumerable dead with one kind of death; neither were the living sufficient to bury them: for in one moment the noblest offspring of them was destroyed.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">و كان لكلهم اجمعين اموات لا يحصون قد ماتوا ميتة واحدة حتى ان الاحياء لم يكفوا لدفن الموتى اذ في لحظة ابيد نسلهم الاعز</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">So they all together had innumerable dead with one kind of death; neither were the living sufficient to bury them: for in one moment the noblest offspring of them was destroyed.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">For whereas they would not believe any thing by reason of the enchantments; upon the destruction of the firstborn, they acknowledged this people to be the sons of God.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">و بعد ان ابوا بسبب السحر ان يؤمنوا بشيء اعترفوا عند هلاك الابكار بان الشعب هو ابن لله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">For whereas they would not believe any thing by reason of the enchantments; upon the destruction of the firstborn, they acknowledged this people to be the sons of God.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">For while all things were in quiet silence, and that night was in the midst of her swift course,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و حين شمل كل شيء هدوء السكوت وانتصف مسير الليل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">For while all things were in quiet silence, and that night was in the midst of her swift course,</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">Thine Almighty word leaped down from heaven out of thy royal throne, as a fierce man of war into the midst of a land of destruction,</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">هجمت كلمتك القديرة من السماء من العروش الملكية على ارض الخراب بمنزلة مبارز عنيف</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Thine Almighty word leaped down from heaven out of thy royal throne, as a fierce man of war into the midst of a land of destruction,</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">And brought thine unfeigned commandment as a sharp sword, and standing up filled all things with death; and it touched the heaven, but it stood upon the earth.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">و سيف صارم يمضي قضاءك المحتوم فوقف وملا كل مكان قتلى وكان راسه في السماء وقدماه على الارض</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">And brought thine unfeigned commandment as a sharp sword, and standing up filled all things with death; and it touched the heaven, but it stood upon the earth.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">Then suddenly visions of horrible dreams troubled them sore, and terrors came upon them unlooked for.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">حينئذ بلبلتهم بغتة اخيلة الاحلام بلبلة شديدة وغشيتهم اهوال مفاجئة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Then suddenly visions of horrible dreams troubled them sore, and terrors came upon them unlooked for.</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">And one thrown here, and another there, half dead, shewed the cause of his death.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">و كان كل واحد عند صرعه بين حي وميت يعلن لاي سبب يموت</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">And one thrown here, and another there, half dead, shewed the cause of his death.</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">For the dreams that troubled them did foreshew this, lest they should perish, and not know why they were afflicted.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">لان الاحلام التي اقلقتهم انباتهم بذلك لئلا يهلكوا وهم يجهلون مجلبة هلاكهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">For the dreams that troubled them did foreshew this, lest they should perish, and not know why they were afflicted.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">Yea, the tasting of death touched the righteous also, and there was a destruction of the multitude in the wilderness: but the wrath endured not long.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">و الصديقون ايضا مستهم محنة الموت ووقعت الضربة على جم منهم في البرية لكن الغضب لم يلبث طويلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Yea, the tasting of death touched the righteous also, and there was a destruction of the multitude in the wilderness: but the wrath endured not long.</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">For then the blameless man made haste, and stood forth to defend them; and bringing the shield of his proper ministry, even prayer, and the propitiation of incense, set himself against the wrath, and so brought the calamity to an end, declaring that he was thy servant.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">لان رجلا لا عيب فيه بادر لحمايتهم فبرز بسلاح خدمته الذي هو الصلاة والتكفير بالبخور وقاوم الغضب وازال النازلة فتبين انه خادمك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">For then the blameless man made haste, and stood forth to defend them; and bringing the shield of his proper ministry, even prayer, and the propitiation of incense, set himself against the wrath, and so brought the calamity to an end, declaring that he was thy servant.</language></verse>
    <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">So he overcame the destroyer, not with strength of body, nor force of arms, but with a word subdued him that punished, alleging the oaths and covenants made with the fathers.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">فانتصر على الجمع لا بقوة الجسد ولا باعمال السلاح ولكنه بالكلام كف المعاقب مذكرا الاقسام والعهود للاباء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">So he overcame the destroyer, not with strength of body, nor force of arms, but with a word subdued him that punished, alleging the oaths and covenants made with the fathers.</language></verse>
    <verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23">For when the dead were now fallen down by heaps one upon another, standing between, he stayed the wrath, and parted the way to the living.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">فانه اذ كان القتلى يتساقطون جماعات وقف في الوسط فحسم السخط وقطع المسلك الى الاحياء</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">For when the dead were now fallen down by heaps one upon another, standing between, he stayed the wrath, and parted the way to the living.</language></verse>
    <verse num="24"><language id="English" verse="24">For in the long garment was the whole world, and in the four rows of the stones was the glory of the fathers graven, and thy Majesty upon the daidem.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="24">لانه كان على ثوبه السابغ العالم كله واسماء الاباء المجيدة منقوشة في اربعة اسطر من الحجارة الكريمة وعظمتك على تاج راسه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="24">For in the long garment was the whole world, and in the four rows of the stones was the glory of the fathers graven, and thy Majesty upon the daidem.</language></verse>
    <verse num="25"><language id="English" verse="25">Unto these the destroyer gave place, and was afraid of them: for it was enough that they only tasted of the wrath.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="25">فهذه خضع المهلك لها وهابها وكان مجرد اختبار الغضب قد كفى</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="25">Unto these the destroyer gave place, and was afraid of them: for it was enough that they only tasted of the wrath.</language></verse>
  </chapter>

  <!-- Chunk 10/10: Chapter 19 -->
  <chapter num="19">
    <verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1">As for the ungodly, wrath came upon them without mercy unto the end: for he knew before what they would do;</language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">اما المنافقون فاستمر عليهم الى الانقضاء غضب لا رحمة معه لانه كان يعلم من قبل ماذا سيكون من امرهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">As for the ungodly, wrath came upon them without mercy unto the end: for he knew before what they would do;</language></verse>
    <verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2">How that having given them leave to depart, and sent them hastily away, they would repent and pursue them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">وانهم بعد ترخيصهم لهم في الذهاب ومبادرتهم لاطلاقهم يندمون فيجدون في اثرهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">How that having given them leave to depart, and sent them hastily away, they would repent and pursue them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3">For whilst they were yet mourning and making lamentation at the graves of the dead, they added another foolish device, and pursued them as fugitives, whom they had intreated to be gone.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فانهم قبل ان تنقضي مناحتهم وهم منتحبون على قبور امواتهم عادوا فاتخذوا مشورة جهل اخرى وسعوا في اثار الذين حثوهم على الرحيل سعيهم وراء قوم فارين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">For whilst they were yet mourning and making lamentation at the graves of the dead, they added another foolish device, and pursued them as fugitives, whom they had intreated to be gone.</language></verse>
    <verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4">For the destiny, whereof they were worthy, drew them unto this end, and made them forget the things that had already happened, that they might fulfil the punishment which was wanting to their torments:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">و انما ساقهم الى هذا الاجل امر لا بد منه انساهم ما سبق من الحوادث لكي يستتموا ما بقي من الام عقابهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">For the destiny, whereof they were worthy, drew them unto this end, and made them forget the things that had already happened, that they might fulfil the punishment which was wanting to their torments:</language></verse>
    <verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5">And that thy people might pass a wonderful way: but they might find a strange death.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">و يعبر شعبك اعجب عبور ويموت اولئك اغرب ميتة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">And that thy people might pass a wonderful way: but they might find a strange death.</language></verse>
    <verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6">For the whole creature in his proper kind was fashioned again anew, serving the peculiar commandments that were given unto them, that thy children might be kept without hurt:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">و كانت جميع الخلائق كل واحدة في جنسها تستبدل طبعها وتخدمك بحسب ما رسم لها لكي يحفظ بنوك بغير ضر</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">For the whole creature in his proper kind was fashioned again anew, serving the peculiar commandments that were given unto them, that thy children might be kept without hurt:</language></verse>
    <verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7">As namely, a cloud shadowing the camp; and where water stood before, dry land appeared; and out of the Red sea a way without impediment; and out of the violent stream a green field:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فالغمام ظلل المحلة ومما كان قبلا يغمر بالمياه برزت ارض يابسة طريق ممهد في البحر الاحمر ومرج اخضر في قعر لجة عظيمة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">As namely, a cloud shadowing the camp; and where water stood before, dry land appeared; and out of the Red sea a way without impediment; and out of the violent stream a green field:</language></verse>
    <verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8">Wherethrough all the people went that were defended with thy hand, seeing thy marvellous strange wonders.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">هناك عبرت الامة كلها وهم في ستر يدك يرون عجائب الايات</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Wherethrough all the people went that were defended with thy hand, seeing thy marvellous strange wonders.</language></verse>
    <verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9">For they went at large like horses, and leaped like lambs, praising thee, O Lord, who hadst delivered them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">و رتعوا كالخيل ووثبوا كالحملان مسبحين لك ايها الرب مخلصهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">For they went at large like horses, and leaped like lambs, praising thee, O Lord, who hadst delivered them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10">For they were yet mindful of the things that were done while they sojourned in the strange land, how the ground brought forth flies instead of cattle, and how the river cast up a multitude of frogs instead of fishes.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">متذكرين ما وقع في غربتهم كيف اخرجت الارض الذباب بدلا من نتاج الحيوان وفاض النهر بجم من الضفادع عوض الاسماك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">For they were yet mindful of the things that were done while they sojourned in the strange land, how the ground brought forth flies instead of cattle, and how the river cast up a multitude of frogs instead of fishes.</language></verse>
    <verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11">But afterwards they saw a new generation of fowls, when, being led with their appetite, they asked delicate meats.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">و اخيرا راوا صنفا جديدا من الطير حين حثتهم شهوتهم ان يتطلبوا طعاما لذيذا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">But afterwards they saw a new generation of fowls, when, being led with their appetite, they asked delicate meats.</language></verse>
    <verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12">For quails came up unto them from the sea for their contentment.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فصعدت السلوى من البحر تسلية لهم اما الخطاة فنزل عليهم الانتقام مع ما له من العلائم القديمة التي هي شدة الصواعق وانما اصابهم ما استحقت فواحشهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">For quails came up unto them from the sea for their contentment.</language></verse>
    <verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13">And punishments came upon the sinners not without former signs by the force of thunders: for they suffered justly according to their own wickedness, insomuch as they used a more hard and hateful behaviour toward strangers.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">اذ كانت معاملتهم للاضياف اشد كراهية فان اولئك ابوا ان يقبلوا غرباء لم يعرفوهم اما هؤلاء فاستعبدوا اضيافا قد احسنوا اليهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">And punishments came upon the sinners not without former signs by the force of thunders: for they suffered justly according to their own wickedness, insomuch as they used a more hard and hateful behaviour toward strangers.</language></verse>
    <verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14">For the Sodomites did not receive those, whom they knew not when they came: but these brought friends into bondage, that had well deserved of them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">و فضلا عن ذلك فان عليهم افتقادا اخر اذ ان اولئك انما قبلوا قوما اجنبيين كرها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">For the Sodomites did not receive those, whom they knew not when they came: but these brought friends into bondage, that had well deserved of them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15">And not only so, but peradventure some respect shall be had of those, because they used strangers not friendly:</language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">اما هؤلاء فانهم قبلوا اضيافا باحتفال وفرح واشركوهم في حقوقهم ثم اساءوا اليهم بصنوف العذاب الشديد</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">And not only so, but peradventure some respect shall be had of those, because they used strangers not friendly:</language></verse>
    <verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16">But these very grievously afflicted them, whom they had received with feastings, and were already made partakers of the same laws with them.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">فضربوا بالعمى مثل اولئك الواقفين على باب الصديق الذين شملتهم ظلمة هائلة فجعل كل منهم يتلمس طالبا مدخل بابه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">But these very grievously afflicted them, whom they had received with feastings, and were already made partakers of the same laws with them.</language></verse>
    <verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17">Therefore even with blindness were these stricken, as those were at the doors of the righteous man: when, being compassed about with horrible great darkness, every one sought the passage of his own doors.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">اذ تغيرت نسب العناصر بعضها الى بعض كما يتغير في العود اسم صوت من اللحن والصوت باق وذلك بين لمن تامل تلك الحوادث</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Therefore even with blindness were these stricken, as those were at the doors of the righteous man: when, being compassed about with horrible great darkness, every one sought the passage of his own doors.</language></verse>
    <verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18">For the elements were changed in themselves by a kind of harmony, like as in a psaltery notes change the name of the tune, and yet are always sounds; which may well be perceived by the sight of the things that have been done.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فالارضيات تحولت الى مائيات والسابحات سعت على الارض</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">For the elements were changed in themselves by a kind of harmony, like as in a psaltery notes change the name of the tune, and yet are always sounds; which may well be perceived by the sight of the things that have been done.</language></verse>
    <verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19">For earthly things were turned into watery, and the things, that before swam in the water, now went upon the ground.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">و النار كانت لها قوة في الماء اشد من قوتها الغريزية والماء نسي قوته المطفئة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">For earthly things were turned into watery, and the things, that before swam in the water, now went upon the ground.</language></verse>
    <verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20">The fire had power in the water, forgetting his own virtue: and the water forgat his own quenching nature.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">و بالعكس اللهيب لم يؤذ جسم السريع الفاسد من الحيوان اذ كان يمشي فيه ولم يذب الطعام السماوي السريع الذوبان كالجليد لانك يا رب عظمت شعبك في كل شيء ومجدته ولم تهمله بل كنت مؤازرا له في كل زمان ومكان</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">The fire had power in the water, forgetting his own virtue: and the water forgat his own quenching nature.</language></verse>
    <verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21">On the other side, the flames wasted not the flesh of the corruptible living things, though they walked therein; neither melted they the icy kind of heavenly meat that was of nature apt to melt.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">On the other side, the flames wasted not the flesh of the corruptible living things, though they walked therein; neither melted they the icy kind of heavenly meat that was of nature apt to melt.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">On the other side, the flames wasted not the flesh of the corruptible living things, though they walked therein; neither melted they the icy kind of heavenly meat that was of nature apt to melt.</language></verse>
    <verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22">For in all things, O Lord, thou didst magnify thy people, and glorify them, neither didst thou lightly regard them: but didst assist them in every time and place.</language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">For in all things, O Lord, thou didst magnify thy people, and glorify them, neither didst thou lightly regard them: but didst assist them in every time and place.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">For in all things, O Lord, thou didst magnify thy people, and glorify them, neither didst thou lightly regard them: but didst assist them in every time and place.</language></verse>
  </chapter>
</book>