<book>
		<chapter num="1">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> In the eighth month of the second year of Darius, the word of the LORD came to Zechariah the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo the prophet, saying, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">في الشهر الثامن في السنة الثانية لداريوس كانت كلمة الرب الى زكريا بن برخيا بن عدّو النبي قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Dalam bulan yang kedelapan pada tahun kedua zaman Darius datanglah firman TUHAN kepada nabi Zakharia bin Berekhya bin Ido, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> "The LORD has been very angry with your fathers. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">قد غضب الرب غضبا على آبائكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">"Sangat murka TUHAN atas nenek moyangmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> "Therefore say to them, 'Thus says the LORD of hosts: "Return to Me," says the LORD of hosts, "and I will return to you," says the LORD of hosts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فقل لهم. هكذا قال رب الجنود. ارجعوا اليّ يقول رب الجنود فارجع اليكم يقول رب الجنود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Sebab itu katakanlah kepada mereka: Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Kembalilah kepada-Ku, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam, maka Akupun akan kembali kepadamu, firman TUHAN semesta alam.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> "Do not be like your fathers, to whom the former prophets preached, saying, 'Thus says the LORD of hosts: "Turn now from your evil ways and your evil deeds." ' But they did not hear nor heed Me," says the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">لا تكونوا كآبائكم الذين ناداهم الانبياء الاولون قائلين هكذا قال رب الجنود ارجعوا عن طرقكم الشريرة وعن اعمالكم الشريرة. فلم يسمعوا ولم يصغوا اليّ يقول رب الجنود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Janganlah kamu seperti nenek moyangmu yang kepadanya para nabi yang dahulu telah menyerukan, demikian: Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Berbaliklah dari tingkah lakumu yang buruk dan dari perbuatanmu yang jahat! Tetapi mereka tidak mau mendengarkan dan tidak mau menghiraukan Aku, demikianlah firman TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> "Your fathers, where [are] they? And the prophets, do they live forever? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">آباؤكم اين هم. والانبياء هل ابدا يحيون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Nenek moyangmu, di mana mereka? Dan para nabi, apakah mereka hidup untuk selama-lamanya?</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Yet surely My words and My statutes, Which I commanded My servants the prophets, Did they not overtake your fathers? "So they returned and said: 'Just as the LORD of hosts determined to do to us, According to our ways and according to our deeds, So He has dealt with us.' " ' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ولكن كلامي وفرائضي التي اوصيت بها عبيدي الانبياء أفلم تدرك آباءكم. فرجعوا وقالوا كما قصد رب الجنود ان يصنع بنا كطرقنا وكاعمالنا كذلك فعل بنا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Tetapi segala firman dan ketetapan-Ku yang telah Kuperintahkan kepada hamba-hamba-Ku, para nabi, bukankah itu telah sampai kepada nenek moyangmu? Maka bertobatlah mereka serta berkata: Sebagaimana TUHAN semesta alam bermaksud mengambil tindakan terhadap kita sesuai dengan tingkah laku kita dan perbuatan kita, demikianlah Ia mengambil tindakan terhadap kita!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> On the twenty-fourth day of the eleventh month, which is the month Shebat, in the second year of Darius, the word of the LORD came to Zechariah the son of Berechiah, the son of Iddo the prophet: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">في اليوم الرابع والعشرين من الشهر الحادي عشر. هو شهر شباط. في السنة الثانية لداريوس كانت كلمة الرب الى زكريا بن برخيا بن عدّو النبي قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Pada hari yang kedua puluh empat dari bulan yang kesebelas--itulah bulan Syebat--pada tahun yang kedua zaman Darius datanglah firman TUHAN kepada nabi Zakharia bin Berekhya bin Ido, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> I saw by night, and behold, a man riding on a red horse, and it stood among the myrtle trees in the hollow; and behind him [were] horses: red, sorrel, and white. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">رأيت في الليل واذا برجل راكب على فرس احمر وهو واقف بين الآس الذي في الظل وخلفه خيل حمر وشقر وشهب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">"Tadi malam aku mendapat suatu penglihatan: tampak seorang yang menunggang kuda merah! Dia sedang berdiri di antara pohon-pohon murad yang di dalam jurang; dan di belakangnya ada kuda-kuda yang merah, yang merah jambu dan yang putih.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Then I said, "My lord, what [are] these?" So the angel who talked with me said to me, "I will show you what they [are."] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فقلت يا سيدي ما هؤلاء. فقال لي الملاك الذي كلمني انا أريك ما هؤلاء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Maka aku bertanya: Apakah arti semuanya ini, ya tuanku? Lalu malaikat yang berbicara dengan aku itu menjawab: Aku ini akan memperlihatkan kepadamu apa arti semuanya ini!</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> And the man who stood among the myrtle trees answered and said, "These [are the ones] whom the LORD has sent to walk to and fro throughout the earth." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فاجاب الرجل الواقف بين الآس وقال هؤلاء هم الذين ارسلهم الرب للجولان في الارض.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Orang yang berdiri di antara pohon-pohon murad itu mulai berbicara, katanya: Inilah mereka semua yang diutus TUHAN untuk menjelajahi bumi!</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> So they answered the Angel of the LORD, who stood among the myrtle trees, and said, "We have walked to and fro throughout the earth, and behold, all the earth is resting quietly." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فاجابوا ملاك الرب الواقف بين الآس وقالوا قد جلنا في الارض واذا الارض كلها مستريحة وساكنة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Berbicaralah mereka kepada Malaikat TUHAN yang berdiri di antara pohon-pohon murad itu, katanya: Kami telah menjelajahi bumi, dan sesungguhnya seluruh bumi itu tenang dan aman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Then the Angel of the LORD answered and said, "O LORD of hosts, how long will You not have mercy on Jerusalem and on the cities of Judah, against which You were angry these seventy years?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فاجاب ملاك الرب وقال. يا رب الجنود الى متى انت لا ترحم اورشليم ومدن يهوذا التي غضبت عليها هذه السبعين سنة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Berbicaralah Malaikat TUHAN itu, katanya: Ya TUHAN semesta alam, berapa lama lagi Engkau tidak menyayangi Yerusalem dan kota-kota Yehuda yang telah tujuh puluh tahun lamanya Kaumurkai itu?</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> And the LORD answered the angel who talked to me, [with] good [and] comforting words. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فاجاب الرب الملاك الذي كلمني بكلام طيب وكلام تعزية.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Lalu kepada malaikat, yang berbicara dengan aku itu, TUHAN menjawab dengan kata-kata yang ramah dan yang menghiburkan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> So the angel who spoke with me said to me, "Proclaim, saying, 'Thus says the LORD of hosts: "I am zealous for Jerusalem And for Zion with great zeal. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فقال لي الملاك الذي كلمني ناد قائلا. هكذا قال رب الجنود. غرت على اورشليم وعلى صهيون غيرة عظيمة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Berkatalah kepadaku malaikat yang berbicara dengan aku itu: Serukanlah ini: Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Sangat besar usaha-Ku untuk Yerusalem dan Sion,</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> I am exceedingly angry with the nations at ease; For I was a little angry, And they helped -- [but] with evil [intent."] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">وانا مغضب بغضب عظيم على الامم المطمئنين. لاني غضبت قليلا وهم اعانوا الشر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">tetapi sangat besar murka-Ku terhadap bangsa-bangsa yang merasa dirinya aman, yang, sementara Aku murka sedikit, telah membantu menimbulkan kejahatan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> 'Therefore thus says the LORD: "I am returning to Jerusalem with mercy; My house shall be built in it," says the LORD of hosts, "And a [surveyor's] line shall be stretched out over Jerusalem." ' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لذلك هكذا قال الرب. قد رجعت الى اورشليم بالمراحم فبيتي يبنى فيها يقول رب الجنود ويمد المطمار على اورشليم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Sebab itu, beginilah firman TUHAN, Aku kembali lagi kepada Yerusalem dengan kasih sayang. Rumah-Ku akan didirikan pula di sana, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam, dan tali pengukur akan direntangkan lagi di atas Yerusalem.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> "Again proclaim, saying, 'Thus says the LORD of hosts: "My cities shall again spread out through prosperity; The LORD will again comfort Zion, And will again choose Jerusalem." ' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ناد ايضا وقل. هكذا قال رب الجنود. ان مدني تفيض بعد خيرا والرب يعزّي صهيون بعد ويختار بعد اورشليم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Serukanlah ini selanjutnya: Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Kota-kota-Ku akan berlimpah-limpah pula dengan kebajikan, dan TUHAN akan menghiburkan Sion dan akan memilih Yerusalem pula."</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> Then I raised my eyes and looked, and there [were] four horns. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">فرفعت عينيّ ونظرت واذا باربعة قرون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Aku melayangkan mataku dan melihat: tampak empat tanduk.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> And I said to the angel who talked with me, "What [are] these?" So he answered me, "These [are] the horns that have scattered Judah, Israel, and Jerusalem." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">فقلت للملاك الذي كلمني. ما هذه. فقال لي هذه هي القرون التي بددت يهوذا واسرائيل واورشليم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Lalu aku bertanya kepada malaikat yang berbicara dengan aku itu: "Apakah arti semuanya ini?" Maka ia menjawab aku: "Inilah tanduk-tanduk yang telah menyerakkan Yehuda, Israel dan Yerusalem."</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> Then the LORD showed me four craftsmen. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">فاراني الرب اربعة صنّاع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Kemudian TUHAN memperlihatkan kepadaku empat tukang besi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> And I said, "What are these coming to do?" So he said, "These [are] the horns that scattered Judah, so that no one could lift up his head; but the craftsmen are coming to terrify them, to cast out the horns of the nations that lifted up [their] horn against the land of Judah to scatter it." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">فقلت جاء هؤلاء ماذا يفعلون. فتكلم قائلا هذه هي القرون التي بددت يهوذا حتى لم يرفع انسان راسه. وقد جاء هؤلاء ليرعبوهم وليطردوا قرون الامم الرافعين قرنا على ارض يهوذا لتبديدها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Lalu aku bertanya: "Orang-orang ini datang untuk melakukan apa?" Maka ia menjawab: "Inipun adalah tanduk-tanduk yang telah menyerakkan Yehuda, sehingga tidak seorangpun berani mengangkat kepalanya. Dan semuanya ini datang untuk mengejutkan mereka, yakni untuk menghempaskan tanduk bangsa-bangsa yang telah mengangkat tanduk terhadap tanah Yehuda hendak menyerakkannya."</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="2">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Then I raised my eyes and looked, and behold, a man with a measuring line in his hand. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">فرفعت عينيّ ونظرت واذا رجل وبيده حبل قياس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Aku melayangkan mataku dan melihat: tampak seorang yang memegang tali pengukur.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> So I said, "Where are you going?" And he said to me, "To measure Jerusalem, to see what [is] its width and what [is] its length." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فقلت الى اين انت ذاهب. فقال لي لاقيس اورشليم لارى كم عرضها وكم طولها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Lalu aku bertanya: "Ke manakah engkau ini pergi?" Maka ia menjawab aku: "Ke Yerusalem, untuk mengukurnya, untuk melihat berapa lebarnya dan panjangnya."</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> And there [was] the angel who talked with me, going out; and another angel was coming out to meet him, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">واذا بالملاك الذي كلمني قد خرج وخرج ملاك آخر للقائه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Dan sementara malaikat yang berbicara dengan aku itu maju ke depan, majulah seorang malaikat lain mendekatinya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> who said to him, "Run, speak to this young man, saying: 'Jerusalem shall be inhabited [as] towns without walls, because of the multitude of men and livestock in it. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فقال له اجر وكلم هذا الغلام قائلا. كالاعراء تسكن اورشليم من كثرة الناس والبهائم فيها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">yang diberi perintah: "Berlarilah, katakanlah kepada orang muda yang di sana itu, demikian: Yerusalem akan tetap tinggal seperti padang terbuka oleh karena banyaknya manusia dan hewan di dalamnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> 'For I,' says the LORD, 'will be a wall of fire all around her, and I will be the glory in her midst.' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">وانا يقول الرب اكون لها سور نار من حولها واكون مجدا في وسطها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Dan Aku sendiri, demikianlah firman TUHAN, akan menjadi tembok berapi baginya di sekelilingnya, dan Aku akan menjadi kemuliaan di dalamnya."</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> " Up, up! Flee from the land of the north," says the LORD; "for I have spread you abroad like the four winds of heaven," says the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">يا يا اهربوا من ارض الشمال يقول الرب. فاني قد فرقتكم كرياح السماء الاربع يقول الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Ayo, ayo, larilah dari Tanah Utara, demikianlah firman TUHAN; sebab ke arah keempat mata angin Aku telah menyerakkan kamu, demikianlah firman TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> "Up, Zion! Escape, you who dwell with the daughter of Babylon." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">تنجّي يا صهيون الساكنة في بنت بابل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Ayo, luputkanlah dirimu ke Sion, hai, penduduk Babel!</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> For thus says the LORD of hosts: "He sent Me after glory, to the nations which plunder you; for he who touches you touches the apple of His eye. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">لانه هكذا قال رب الجنود. بعد المجد ارسلني الى الامم الذين سلبوكم لانه من يمسكم يمسّ حدقة عينه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Sebab beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam, yang dalam kemuliaan-Nya telah mengutus aku, mengenai bangsa-bangsa yang telah menjarah kamu--sebab siapa yang menjamah kamu, berarti menjamah biji mata-Nya--:</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> "For surely I will shake My hand against them, and they shall become spoil for their servants. Then you will know that the LORD of hosts has sent Me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">لاني هانذا احرّك يدي عليهم فيكونون سلبا لعبيدهم. فتعلمون ان رب الجنود قد ارسلني</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">"Sesungguhnya Aku akan menggerakkan tangan-Ku terhadap mereka, dan mereka akan menjadi jarahan bagi orang-orang yang tadinya takluk kepada mereka. Maka kamu akan mengetahui bahwa TUHAN semesta alam yang mengutus aku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> " Sing and rejoice, O daughter of Zion! For behold, I am coming and I will dwell in your midst," says the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">ترنمي وافرحي يا بنت صهيون لاني هانذا آتي واسكن في وسطك يقول الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Bersorak-sorailah dan bersukarialah, hai puteri Sion, sebab sesungguhnya Aku datang dan diam di tengah-tengahmu, demikianlah firman TUHAN;</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> "Many nations shall be joined to the LORD in that day, and they shall become My people. And I will dwell in your midst. Then you will know that the LORD of hosts has sent Me to you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فيتصل امم كثيرة بالرب في ذلك اليوم ويكونون لي شعبا فاسكن في وسطك فتعلمين ان رب الجنود قد ارسلني اليك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">dan banyak bangsa akan menggabungkan diri kepada TUHAN pada waktu itu dan akan menjadi umat-Ku dan Aku akan diam di tengah-tengahmu." Maka engkau akan mengetahui, bahwa TUHAN semesta alam yang mengutus aku kepadamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> "And the LORD will take possession of Judah as His inheritance in the Holy Land, and will again choose Jerusalem. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">والرب يرث يهوذا نصيبه في الارض المقدسه ويختار اورشليم بعد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Dan TUHAN akan mengambil Yehuda sebagai milik-Nya di tanah yang kudus, dan Ia akan memilih Yerusalem pula.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> "Be silent, all flesh, before the LORD, for He is aroused from His holy habitation!" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">اسكتوا يا كل البشر قدام الرب لانه قد استيقظ من مسكن قدسه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Berdiam dirilah, hai segala makhluk, di hadapan TUHAN, sebab Ia telah bangkit dari tempat kediaman-Nya yang kudus.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="3">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Then he showed me Joshua the high priest standing before the Angel of the LORD, and Satan standing at his right hand to oppose him. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وأراني يهوشع الكاهن العظيم قائما قدام ملاك الرب والشيطان قائم عن يمينه ليقاومه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Kemudian ia memperlihatkan kepadaku imam besar Yosua berdiri di hadapan Malaikat TUHAN sedang Iblis berdiri di sebelah kanannya untuk mendakwa dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> And the LORD said to Satan, "The LORD rebuke you, Satan! The LORD who has chosen Jerusalem rebuke you! [Is] this not a brand plucked from the fire?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فقال الرب للشيطان لينتهرك الرب يا شيطان. لينتهرك الرب الذي اختار اورشليم. أفليس هذا شعلة منتشلة من النار</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Lalu berkatalah Malaikat TUHAN kepada Iblis itu: "TUHAN kiranya menghardik engkau, hai Iblis! TUHAN, yang memilih Yerusalem, kiranya menghardik engkau! Bukankah dia ini puntung yang telah ditarik dari api?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Now Joshua was clothed with filthy garments, and was standing before the Angel. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">وكان يهوشع لابسا ثيابا قذرة وواقفا قدام الملاك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Adapun Yosua mengenakan pakaian yang kotor, waktu dia berdiri di hadapan Malaikat itu,</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Then He answered and spoke to those who stood before Him, saying, "Take away the filthy garments from him." And to him He said, "See, I have removed your iniquity from you, and I will clothe you with rich robes." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فاجاب وكلم الواقفين قدامه قائلا انزعوا عنه الثياب القذرة. وقال له انظر. قد اذهبت عنك اثمك والبسك ثيابا مزخرفة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">yang memberikan perintah kepada orang-orang yang melayaninya: "Tanggalkanlah pakaian yang kotor itu dari padanya." Dan kepada Yosua ia berkata: "Lihat, dengan ini aku telah menjauhkan kesalahanmu dari padamu! Aku akan mengenakan kepadamu pakaian pesta."</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> And I said, "Let them put a clean turban on his head." So they put a clean turban on his head, and they put the clothes on him. And the Angel of the LORD stood by. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فقلت ليضعوا على راسه عمامة طاهرة. فوضعوا على راسه العمامة الطاهرة والبسوه ثيابا وملاك الرب واقف.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Kemudian ia berkata: "Taruhlah serban tahir pada kepalanya!" Maka mereka menaruh serban tahir pada kepalanya dan mengenakan pakaian kepadanya, sedang Malaikat TUHAN berdiri di situ.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> Then the Angel of the LORD admonished Joshua, saying, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فاشهد ملاك الرب على يهوشع قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Lalu Malaikat TUHAN itu memberi jaminan kepada Yosua, katanya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> "Thus says the LORD of hosts: 'If you will walk in My ways, And if you will keep My command, Then you shall also judge My house, And likewise have charge of My courts; I will give you places to walk Among these who stand here. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">هكذا قال رب الجنود ان سلكت في طرقي وان حفظت شعائري فانت ايضا تدين بيتي وتحافظ ايضا على دياري واعطيك مسالك بين هؤلاء الواقفين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">"Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Apabila engkau hidup menurut jalan yang Kutunjukkan dan melakukan tugas yang Kuberikan kepadamu, maka engkau akan memerintah rumah-Ku dan mengurus pelataran-Ku, dan Aku akan mengizinkan engkau masuk ke antara mereka yang berdiri melayani di sini.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> 'Hear, O Joshua, the high priest, You and your companions who sit before you, For they are a wondrous sign; For behold, I am bringing forth My Servant the BRANCH. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فاسمع يا يهوشع الكاهن العظيم انت ورفقاؤك الجالسون امامك. لانهم رجال آية. لاني هانذا آتي بعبدي الغصن.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Dengarkanlah, hai imam besar Yosua! Engkau dan teman-temanmu yang duduk di hadapanmu--sungguh kamu merupakan suatu lambang. Sebab, sesungguhnya Aku akan mendatangkan hamba-Ku, yakni Sang Tunas.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> For behold, the stone That I have laid before Joshua: Upon the stone [are] seven eyes. Behold, I will engrave its inscription,' Says the LORD of hosts, 'And I will remove the iniquity of that land in one day. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فهوذا الحجر الذي وضعته قدام يهوشع على حجر واحد سبع اعين. هانذا ناقش نقشه يقول رب الجنود وازيل اثم تلك الارض في يوم واحد.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Sebab sesungguhnya permata yang telah Kuserahkan kepada Yosua--satu permata yang bermata tujuh--sesungguhnya Aku akan mengukirkan ukiran di atasnya, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam, dan Aku akan menghapuskan kesalahan negeri ini dalam satu hari saja.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> In that day,' says the LORD of hosts, 'Everyone will invite his neighbor Under his vine and under his fig tree.' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">في ذلك اليوم يقول رب الجنود ينادي كل انسان قريبه تحت الكرمة وتحت التينة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Pada hari itu, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam, setiap orang dari padamu akan mengundang temannya duduk di bawah pohon anggur dan di bawah pohon ara."</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="4">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Now the angel who talked with me came back and wakened me, as a man who is wakened out of his sleep. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">فرجع الملاك الذي كلمني وايقظني كرجل أوقظ من نومه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Datanglah kembali malaikat yang berbicara dengan aku itu, lalu dibangunkannyalah aku seperti seorang yang dibangunkan dari tidurnya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> And he said to me, "What do you see?" So I said, "I am looking, and there [is] a lampstand of solid gold with a bowl on top of it, and on the [stand] seven lamps with seven pipes to the seven lamps. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">وقال لي ماذا ترى. فقلت قد نظرت واذا بمنارة كلها ذهب وكوزها على راسها وسبعة سرج عليها وسبع انابيب للسرج التي على راسها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Maka berkatalah ia kepadaku: "Apa yang engkau lihat?" Jawabku: "Aku melihat: tampak sebuah kandil, dari emas seluruhnya, dan tempat minyaknya di bagian atasnya; kandil itu ada tujuh pelitanya dan ada tujuh corot pada masing-masing pelita yang ada di bagian atasnya itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> "Two olive trees [are] by it, one at the right of the bowl and the other at its left." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">وعندها زيتونتان احداهما عن يمين الكوز والاخرى عن يساره.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Dan pohon zaitun ada terukir padanya, satu di sebelah kanan tempat minyak itu dan satu di sebelah kirinya."</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> So I answered and spoke to the angel who talked with me, saying, "What [are] these, my lord?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فاجبت وقلت للملاك الذي كلمني قائلا ما هذه يا سيدي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Lalu berbicaralah aku, kataku kepada malaikat yang berbicara dengan aku itu: "Apakah arti semuanya ini, tuanku?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Then the angel who talked with me answered and said to me, "Do you not know what these are?" And I said, "No, my lord." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فاجاب الملاك الذي كلمني وقال لي أما تعلم ما هذه. فقلت لا يا سيدي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Maka berbicaralah malaikat yang berbicara dengan aku itu, katanya kepadaku: "Tidakkah engkau tahu, apa arti semuanya ini?" Jawabku: "Tidak, tuanku!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> So he answered and said to me: "This [is] the word of the LORD to Zerubbabel: 'Not by might nor by power, but by My Spirit,' Says the LORD of hosts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فاجاب وكلمني قائلا هذه كلمة الرب الى زربابل قائلا لا بالقدرة ولا بالقوة بل بروحي قال رب الجنود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Maka berbicaralah ia, katanya: "Inilah firman TUHAN kepada Zerubabel bunyinya: Bukan dengan keperkasaan dan bukan dengan kekuatan, melainkan dengan roh-Ku, firman TUHAN semesta alam.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> 'Who [are] you, O great mountain? Before Zerubbabel [you shall become] a plain! And he shall bring forth the capstone With shouts of "Grace, grace to it!" ' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">من انت ايها الجبل العظيم. امام زربابل تصير سهلا. فيخرج حجر الزاوية بين الهاتفين كرامة كرامة له</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Siapakah engkau, gunung yang besar? Di depan Zerubabel engkau menjadi tanah rata. Ia akan mengangkat batu utama, sedang orang bersorak: Bagus! Bagus sekali batu itu!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Moreover the word of the LORD came to me, saying: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">وكانت اليّ كلمة الرب قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Kemudian datanglah firman TUHAN kepadaku, demikian:</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> "The hands of Zerubbabel Have laid the foundation of this temple; His hands shall also finish [it.] Then you will know That the LORD of hosts has sent Me to you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ان يدي زربابل قد اسستها هذا البيت فيداه تتمّمانه فتعلم ان رب الجنود ارسلني اليكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">"Tangan Zerubabel telah meletakkan dasar Rumah ini, dan tangannya juga akan menyelesaikannya. Maka kamu akan mengetahui, bahwa TUHAN semesta alam yang mengutus aku kepadamu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> For who has despised the day of small things? For these seven rejoice to see The plumb line in the hand of Zerubbabel. They are the eyes of the LORD, Which scan to and fro throughout the whole earth." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لانه من ازدرى بيوم الأمور الصغيرة. فتفرح اولئك السبع ويرون الزيج بيد زربابل. انما هي اعين الرب الجائلة في الارض كلها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Sebab siapa yang memandang hina hari peristiwa-peristiwa yang kecil, mereka akan bersukaria melihat batu pilihan di tangan Zerubabel. Yang tujuh ini adalah mata TUHAN, yang menjelajah seluruh bumi."</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> Then I answered and said to him, "What [are] these two olive trees -- at the right of the lampstand and at its left?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فاجبت وقلت له ما هاتان الزيتونتان عن يمين المنارة وعن يسارها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Lalu berbicaralah aku kepadanya: "Apakah arti kedua pohon zaitun yang di sebelah kanan dan di sebelah kiri kandil ini?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> And I further answered and said to him, "What [are these] two olive branches that [drip] into the receptacles of the two gold pipes from which the golden [oil] drains?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">واجبت ثانية وقلت له ما فرعا الزيتون اللذان بجانب الانابيب من ذهب المفرغان من انفسهما الذهبيّ.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Untuk kedua kalinya berbicaralah aku kepadanya: "Apakah arti kedua dahan pohon zaitun yang di samping kedua pipa emas yang menyalurkan cairan emas dari atasnya itu?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Then he answered me and said, "Do you not know what these [are?"] And I said, "No, my lord." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فاجابني قائلا اما تعلم ما هاتان. فقلت لا يا سيدي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Ia menjawab aku: "Tidakkah engkau tahu, apa arti semuanya ini?" Jawabku: "Tidak, tuanku!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> So he said, "These [are] the two anointed ones, who stand beside the Lord of the whole earth." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">فقال هاتان هما ابنا الزيت الواقفان عند سيد الارض كلها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Lalu ia berkata: "Inilah kedua orang yang diurapi yang berdiri di dekat Tuhan seluruh bumi!"</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="5">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Then I turned and raised my eyes, and saw there a flying scroll. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">فعدت ورفعت عينيّ ونظرت واذا بدرج طائر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Aku melayangkan mataku pula, maka aku melihat: tampak sebuah gulungan kitab yang terbang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> And he said to me, "What do you see?" So I answered, "I see a flying scroll. Its length [is] twenty cubits and its width ten cubits." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">فقال لي ماذا ترى. فقلت اني ارى درجا طائرا طوله عشرون ذراعا وعرضه عشر اذرع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Berkatalah ia kepadaku: "Apa yang engkau lihat?" Jawabku: "Aku melihat sebuah gulungan kitab yang terbang; panjangnya dua puluh hasta dan lebarnya sepuluh hasta."</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Then he said to me, "This [is] the curse that goes out over the face of the whole earth: 'Every thief shall be expelled,' according [to] this side of [the scroll;] and, 'Every perjurer shall be expelled,' according [to] that side of it." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فقال لي هذه هي اللعنة الخارجة على وجه كل الارض. لان كل سارق يباد من هنا بحسبها وكل حالف يباد من هناك بحسبها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Lalu ia berkata kepadaku: "Inilah sumpah serapah yang keluar menimpa seluruh negeri; sebab menurut sumpah serapah itu setiap pencuri di sini masih bebas dari hukuman, dan setiap orang yang bersumpah palsu di sini juga masih bebas dari hukuman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> "I will send out [the curse,"] says the LORD of hosts; "It shall enter the house of the thief And the house of the one who swears falsely by My name. It shall remain in the midst of his house And consume it, with its timber and stones." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">اني اخرجها يقول رب الجنود فتدخل بيت السارق وبيت الحالف باسمي زورا وتبيت في وسط بيته وتفنيه مع خشبه وحجارته</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Aku telah menyuruhnya keluar, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam, supaya itu masuk ke dalam rumah pencuri dan ke dalam rumah orang yang bersumpah palsu demi nama-Ku, dan supaya itu bermalam di dalam rumah mereka dan memusnahkannya, baik kayunya maupun batu-batunya."</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Then the angel who talked with me came out and said to me, "Lift your eyes now, and see what this [is] that goes forth." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">ثم خرج الملاك الذي كلمني وقال لي. ارفع عينيك وانظر ما هذا الخارج.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Tampillah malaikat yang berbicara dengan aku itu, katanya kepadaku: "Cobalah layangkan matamu dan lihatlah apa yang muncul itu!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> So I asked, "What [is] it?" And he said, "It [is] a basket that is going forth." He also said, "This [is] their resemblance throughout the earth: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فقلت ما هو. فقال هذه هي الايفة الخارجة. وقال هذه عينهم في كل الارض.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Lalu tanyaku: "Apa itu?" Jawabnya: "Yang muncul itu sebuah gantang!" Lagi katanya: "Inilah kejahatan mereka di seluruh negeri!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> "Here [is] a lead disc lifted up, and this [is] a woman sitting inside the basket"; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">واذا بوزنة رصاص رفعت. وكانت امرأة جالسة في وسط الايفة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Lihat, tutup timah gantang itu telah terangkat, dan seorang perempuan duduk di dalamnya!</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> then he said, "This [is] Wickedness!" And he thrust her down into the basket, and threw the lead cover over its mouth. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فقال هذه هي الشر. فطرحها الى وسط الايفة وطرح ثقل الرصاص على فمها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Kemudian berkatalah ia: "Itulah kefasikan!" Lalu didorongnyalah perempuan itu kembali ke dalam gantang dan dibantingnyalah batu timah itu ke mulut gantang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Then I raised my eyes and looked, and there [were] two women, coming with the wind in their wings; for they had wings like the wings of a stork, and they lifted up the basket between earth and heaven. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ورفعت عينيّ ونظرت واذا بامرأتين خرجتا والريح في اجنحتهما. ولهما اجنحة كاجنحة اللقلق فرفعتا الايفة بين الارض والسماء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Lalu aku melayangkan mataku dan aku melihat: tampak tampil dua orang perempuan yang sayapnya didorong oleh angin. Adapun sayap mereka adalah sayap seperti burung ranggung. Mereka mengangkut gantang itu di antara bumi dan langit.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> So I said to the angel who talked with me, "Where are they carrying the basket?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فقلت للملاك الذي كلمني الى اين هما ذاهبتان بالايفة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Bertanyalah aku kepada malaikat yang berbicara dengan aku itu: "Ke mana mereka membawa gantang itu?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> And he said to me, "To build a house for it in the land of Shinar; when it is ready, [the basket] will be set there on its base." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فقال لي لتبنيا لها بيتا في ارض شنعار. واذا تهيّأ تقرّ هناك على قاعدتها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Jawabnya kepadaku: "Ke tanah Sinear, untuk mendirikan sebuah rumah bagi perempuan itu. Dan apabila itu selesai, maka mereka akan menempatkan dia di sana di tempat rumah itu didirikan."</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="6">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Then I turned and raised my eyes and looked, and behold, four chariots [were] coming from between two mountains, and the mountains [were] mountains of bronze. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">فعدت ورفعت عينيّ ونظرت واذا باربع مركبات خارجات من بين جبلين والجبلان جبلا نحاس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Aku melayangkan mataku pula, maka aku melihat: tampak keluar empat kereta dari antara dua gunung. Adapun gunung-gunung itu adalah gunung-gunung tembaga.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> With the first chariot [were] red horses, with the second chariot black horses, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">في المركبة الاولى خيل حمر وفي المركبة الثانية خيل دهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Kereta pertama ditarik oleh kuda merah, kereta kedua oleh kuda hitam.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> with the third chariot white horses, and with the fourth chariot dappled horses -- strong [steeds.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">وفي المركبة الثالثة خيل شهب وفي المركبة الرابعة خيل منمّرة شقر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Kereta ketiga oleh kuda putih, dan kereta keempat oleh kuda yang berbelang-belang dan berloreng-loreng.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Then I answered and said to the angel who talked with me, "What [are] these, my lord?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">فاجبت وقلت للملاك الذي كلمني ما هذه يا سيدي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Berbicaralah aku kepada malaikat yang berbicara dengan aku itu: "Apakah arti semuanya ini, tuanku?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> And the angel answered and said to me, "These [are] four spirits of heaven, who go out from [their] station before the Lord of all the earth. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فاجاب الملاك وقال لي هذه هي ارواح السماء الاربع خارجة من الوقوف لدى سيد الارض كلها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Berbicaralah malaikat itu kepadaku: "Semuanya ini keluar ke arah keempat mata angin, sesudah mereka menghadap kepada Tuhan seluruh bumi."</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> "The one with the black horses is going to the north country, the white are going after them, and the dappled are going toward the south country." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">التي فيها الخيل الدهم تخرج الى ارض الشمال والشّهب خارجة وراءها والمنمّرة تخرج نحو ارض الجنوب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Yang ditarik oleh kuda hitam itu keluar ke Tanah Utara; yang putih itu keluar ke arah barat; yang berbelang-belang itu keluar ke Tanah Selatan;</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> Then the strong [steeds] went out, eager to go, that they might walk to and fro throughout the earth. And He said, "Go, walk to and fro throughout the earth." So they walked to and fro throughout the earth. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">اما الشقر فخرجت والتمست ان تذهب لتتمشى في الارض فقال اذهبي وتمشّي في الارض. فتمشت في الارض.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">dan yang merah itu keluar, gelisah untuk pergi, hendak menjelajahi bumi. Lalu berkatalah ia: "Pergilah, jelajahilah bumi!" Maka mereka menjelajahi bumi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> And He called to me, and spoke to me, saying, "See, those who go toward the north country have given rest to My Spirit in the north country." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">فصرخ عليّ وكلمني قائلا. هوذا الخارجون الى ارض الشمال قد سكّنوا روحي في ارض الشمال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Kemudian berteriaklah ia kepadaku: "Lihat, mereka yang keluar ke Tanah Utara itu akan menenteramkan roh-Ku di Tanah Utara."</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Then the word of the LORD came to me, saying: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">وكان اليّ كلام الرب قائلا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Datanglah firman TUHAN kepadaku, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> "Receive [the gift] from the captives -- from Heldai, Tobijah, and Jedaiah, who have come from Babylon -- and go the same day and enter the house of Josiah the son of Zephaniah. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">خذ من اهل السبي من حلداي ومن طوبيا ومن يدعيا الذين جاءوا من بابل وتعال انت في ذلك اليوم وادخل الى بيت يوشيا بن صفنيا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">"Pergilah pada hari ini juga ke rumah Yosia bin Zefanya dan pungutlah persembahan dari pihak orang-orang buangan, yaitu dari Heldai, Tobia dan Yedaya, semuanya orang-orang yang sudah datang kembali dari Babel,</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> "Take the silver and gold, make an elaborate crown, and set [it] on the head of Joshua the son of Jehozadak, the high priest. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ثم خذ فضة وذهبا واعمل تيجانا وضعها على راس يهوشع بن يهوصادق الكاهن العظيم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">pungutlah perak dan emas, buatlah mahkota dan kenakanlah itu pada kepala imam besar Yosua bin Yozadak;</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> "Then speak to him, saying, 'Thus says the LORD of hosts, saying: "Behold, the Man whose name [is] the BRANCH! From His place He shall branch out, And He shall build the temple of the LORD; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">وكلمه قائلا. هكذا قال رب الجنود قائلا. هوذا الرجل الغصن اسمه ومن مكانه ينبت ويبني هيكل الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">katakanlah kepadanya: Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Inilah orang yang bernama Tunas. Ia akan bertunas dari tempatnya dan ia akan mendirikan bait TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> Yes, He shall build the temple of the LORD. He shall bear the glory, And shall sit and rule on His throne; So He shall be a priest on His throne, And the counsel of peace shall be between them both." ' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فهو يبني هيكل الرب وهو يحمل الجلال ويجلس ويتسلط على كرسيه ويكون كاهنا على كرسيه وتكون مشورة السلام بينهما كليهما.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Dialah yang akan mendirikan bait TUHAN, dan dialah yang akan mendapat keagungan dan akan duduk memerintah di atas takhtanya. Di sebelah kanannya akan ada seorang imam dan permufakatan tentang damai akan ada di antara mereka berdua.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> "Now the elaborate crown shall be for a memorial in the temple of the LORD for Helem, Tobijah, Jedaiah, and Hen the son of Zephaniah. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">وتكون التيجان لحالم ولطوبيا وليدعيا ولحين بن صفنيا تذكارا في هيكل الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Dan mahkota itu akan tetap tinggal dalam bait TUHAN sebagai tanda peringatan akan Heldai, Tobia, Yedaya dan akan Yosia bin Zefanya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> "Even those from afar shall come and build the temple of the LORD. Then you shall know that the LORD of hosts has sent Me to you. And [this] shall come to pass if you diligently obey the voice of the LORD your God." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">والبعيدون يأتون ويبنون في هيكل الرب فتعلمون ان رب الجنود ارسلني اليكم. ويكون اذا سمعتم سمعا صوت الرب الهكم****</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Orang-orang dari jauh akan datang untuk turut membangun bait TUHAN; maka kamu akan mengetahui bahwa TUHAN semesta alam yang mengutus aku kepadamu. Dan hal ini akan terjadi, apabila kamu dengan baik-baik mendengarkan suara TUHAN Allahmu."</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="7">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Now in the fourth year of King Darius it came to pass [that] the word of the LORD came to Zechariah, on the fourth day of the ninth month, Chislev, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وكان في السنة الرابعة لداريوس الملك ان كلام الرب صار الى زكريا في الرابع من الشهر التاسع في كسلو</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Pada tahun yang keempat zaman raja Darius datanglah firman TUHAN kepada Zakharia, pada tanggal empat bulan kesembilan, yakni bulan Kislew.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> when [the people] sent Sherezer, with Regem-Melech and his men, [to] the house of God, to pray before the LORD, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">لما ارسل اهل بيت ايل شراصر ورجم ملك ورجالهم ليصلّوا قدام الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Adapun penduduk Betel telah mengutus Sarezer dan Regem-Melekh serta orang-orangnya untuk melunakkan hati TUHAN,</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> [and] to ask the priests who [were] in the house of the LORD of hosts, and the prophets, saying, "Should I weep in the fifth month and fast as I have done for so many years?" </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">وليكلموا الكهنة الذين في بيت رب الجنود والانبياء قائلين أأبكي في الشهر الخامس منفصلا كما فعلت كم من السنين هذه</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">untuk menanyakan kepada para imam dari rumah TUHAN semesta alam dan kepada nabi, demikian: "Haruskah kami sekalian menangis dan berpantang dalam bulan yang kelima seperti yang telah kami lakukan bertahun-tahun lamanya?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Then the word of the LORD of hosts came to me, saying, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ثم صار اليّ كلام رب الجنود قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Maka datanglah firman TUHAN semesta alam kepadaku, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> "Say to all the people of the land, and to the priests: 'When you fasted and mourned in the fifth and seventh [months] during those seventy years, did you really fast for Me -- for Me? </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">قل لجميع شعب الارض وللكهنة قائلا. لما صمتم ونحتم في الشهر الخامس والشهر السابع وذلك هذه السبعين سنة فهل صمتم صوما لي انا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">"Katakanlah kepada seluruh rakyat negeri dan kepada para imam, demikian: Ketika kamu berpuasa dan meratap dalam bulan yang kelima dan yang ketujuh selama tujuh puluh tahun ini, adakah kamu sungguh-sungguh berpuasa untuk Aku?</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> 'When you eat and when you drink, do you not eat and drink [for yourselves?] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ولما اكلتم ولما شربتم أفما كنتم انتم الآكلين وانتم الشاربين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Dan ketika kamu makan dan ketika kamu minum, bukankah kamu makan dan minum untuk dirimu sendiri?</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> '[Should you] not [have obeyed] the words which the LORD proclaimed through the former prophets when Jerusalem and the cities around it were inhabited and prosperous, and the South and the Lowland were inhabited?' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">أليس هذا هو الكلام الذي نادى به الرب عن يد الانبياء الاولين حين كانت اورشليم معمورة ومستريحة ومدنها حولها والجنوب والسهل معمورين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Bukankah ini firman yang telah disampaikan TUHAN dengan perantaraan para nabi yang dahulu, ketika Yerusalem dengan kota-kota yang di sekelilingnya masih didiami orang dan masih sentosa dan Tanah Negeb dan Daerah Bukit masih didiami?"</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> Then the word of the LORD came to Zechariah, saying, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">وكان كلام الرب الى زكريا قائلا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Firman TUHAN datang kepada Zakharia, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> "Thus says the LORD of hosts: 'Execute true justice, Show mercy and compassion Everyone to his brother. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">هكذا قال رب الجنود قائلا. اقضوا قضاء الحق واعملوا احسانا ورحمة كل انسان مع اخيه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">"Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Laksanakanlah hukum yang benar dan tunjukkanlah kesetiaan dan kasih sayang kepada masing-masing!</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> Do not oppress the widow or the fatherless, The alien or the poor. Let none of you plan evil in his heart Against his brother.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">ولا تظلموا الارملة ولا اليتيم ولا الغريب ولا الفقير ولا يفكر احد منكم شرا على اخيه في قلبكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Janganlah menindas janda dan anak yatim, orang asing dan orang miskin, dan janganlah merancang kejahatan dalam hatimu terhadap masing-masing."</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> "But they refused to heed, shrugged their shoulders, and stopped their ears so that they could not hear. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فابوا ان يصغوا واعطوا كتفا معاندة وثقّلوا آذانهم عن السمع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Tetapi mereka tidak mau menghiraukan, dilintangkannya bahunya untuk melawan dan ditulikannya telinganya supaya jangan mendengar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> "Yes, they made their hearts like flint, refusing to hear the law and the words which the LORD of hosts had sent by His Spirit through the former prophets. Thus great wrath came from the LORD of hosts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">بل جعلوا قلبهم ماسا لئلا يسمعوا الشريعة والكلام الذي ارسله رب الجنود بروحه عن يد الانبياء الاولين فجاء غضب عظيم من عند رب الجنود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Mereka membuat hati mereka keras seperti batu amril, supaya jangan mendengar pengajaran dan firman yang disampaikan TUHAN semesta alam melalui roh-Nya dengan perantaraan para nabi yang dahulu. Oleh sebab itu datang murka yang hebat dari pada TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> "Therefore it happened, [that] just as He proclaimed and they would not hear, so they called out and I would not listen," says the LORD of hosts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فكان كما نادى هو فلم يسمعوا كذلك ينادون هم فلا اسمع قال رب الجنود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">"Seperti mereka tidak mendengarkan pada waktu dipanggil, demikianlah Aku tidak mendengarkan pada waktu mereka memanggil, firman TUHAN semesta alam.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> "But I scattered them with a whirlwind among all the nations which they had not known. Thus the land became desolate after them, so that no one passed through or returned; for they made the pleasant land desolate." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">واعصفهم الى كل الامم الذين لم يعرفوهم. فخربت الارض وراءهم لا ذاهب ولا آئب فجعلوا الارض البهجة خرابا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Oleh sebab itu Aku meniupkan mereka seperti angin badai ke antara segala bangsa yang tidak dikenal mereka, dan sesudahnya tanah itu menjadi sunyi sepi, sehingga tidak ada yang lalu lalang di sana; demikianlah mereka membuat negeri yang indah itu menjadi tempat yang sunyi sepi."</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="8">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Again the word of the LORD of hosts came, saying, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وكان كلام رب الجنود قائلا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Datanglah firman TUHAN semesta alam, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> "Thus says the LORD of hosts: 'I am zealous for Zion with great zeal; With great fervor I am zealous for her.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">هكذا قال رب الجنود. غرت على صهيون غيرة عظيمة وبسخط عظيم غرت عليها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">"Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Aku berusaha untuk Sion dengan kegiatan yang besar dan dengan kehangatan amarah yang besar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> "Thus says the LORD: 'I will return to Zion, And dwell in the midst of Jerusalem. Jerusalem shall be called the City of Truth, The Mountain of the LORD of hosts, The Holy Mountain.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">هكذا قال الرب قد رجعت الى صهيون واسكن في وسط اورشليم فتدعى اورشليم مدينة الحق وجبل رب الجنود الجبل المقدس</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Beginilah firman TUHAN: Aku akan kembali ke Sion dan akan diam di tengah-tengah Yerusalem. Yerusalem akan disebut Kota Setia, dan gunung TUHAN semesta alam akan disebut Gunung Kudus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> "Thus says the LORD of hosts: 'Old men and old women shall again sit In the streets of Jerusalem, Each one with his staff in his hand Because of great age. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">هكذا قال رب الجنود. سيجلس بعد الشيوخ والشيخات في اسواق اورشليم كل انسان منهم عصاه بيده من كثرة الايام.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Akan ada lagi kakek-kakek dan nenek-nenek duduk di jalan-jalan Yerusalem, masing-masing memegang tongkat karena lanjut usianya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> The streets of the city Shall be full of boys and girls Playing in its streets.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">وتمتلئ اسواق المدينة من الصبيان والبنات لاعبين في اسواقها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Dan jalan-jalan kota itu akan penuh dengan anak laki-laki dan anak perempuan yang bermain-main di situ.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> "Thus says the LORD of hosts: 'If it is marvelous in the eyes of the remnant of this people in these days, Will it also be marvelous in My eyes?' Says the LORD of hosts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">هكذا قال رب الجنود ان يكن ذلك عجيبا في اعين بقية هذا الشعب في هذه الايام أفيكون ايضا عجيبا في عينيّ يقول رب الجنود</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Kalau pada waktu itu sisa-sisa bangsa ini menganggap hal itu ajaib, apakah Aku akan menganggapnya ajaib? demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> "Thus says the LORD of hosts: 'Behold, I will save My people from the land of the east And from the land of the west; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">هكذا قال رب الجنود. هانذا اخلّص شعبي من ارض المشرق ومن ارض مغرب الشمس.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Sesungguhnya, Aku menyelamatkan umat-Ku dari tempat terbitnya matahari sampai kepada tempat terbenamnya,</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> I will bring them [back,] And they shall dwell in the midst of Jerusalem. They shall be My people And I will be their God, In truth and righteousness.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">وآتي بهم فيسكنون في وسط اورشليم ويكونون لي شعبا وانا اكون لهم الها بالحق والبرّ</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">dan Aku akan membawa mereka pulang, supaya mereka diam di tengah-tengah Yerusalem. Maka mereka akan menjadi umat-Ku dan Aku akan menjadi Allah mereka dalam kesetiaan dan kebenaran."</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> " Thus says the LORD of hosts: 'Let your hands be strong, You who have been hearing in these days These words by the mouth of the prophets, Who [spoke] in the day the foundation was laid For the house of the LORD of hosts, That the temple might be built. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">هكذا قال رب الجنود لتتشدد ايديكم ايها السامعون في هذه الايام هذا الكلام من افواه الانبياء الذي كان يوم أسس بيت رب الجنود لبناء الهيكل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: "Kuatkanlah hatimu, hai orang-orang yang selama ini telah mendengar firman ini, yang diucapkan para nabi, sejak dasar rumah TUHAN semesta alam diletakkan, untuk mendirikan Bait Suci itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> For before these days [There were] no wages for man nor any hire for beast; [There was] no peace from the enemy for whoever went out or came in; For I set all men, everyone, against his neighbor. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">لانه قبل هذه الايام لم تكن للانسان اجرة ولا للبهيمة اجرة ولا سلام لمن خرج او دخل من قبل الضيق واطلقت كل انسان الرجل على قريبه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Sebab sebelum waktu itu tidak ada rezeki bagi manusia, juga tidak bagi binatang; dan karena musuh tidak ada keamanan bagi orang yang keluar dan bagi orang yang masuk, lagipula Aku membuat manusia semua bertengkar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> 'But now I [will] not [treat] the remnant of this people as in the former days,' says the LORD of hosts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">اما الآن فلا اكون انا لبقية هذا الشعب كما في الايام الاولى يقول رب الجنود.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Tetapi sekarang, Aku tidak lagi seperti waktu dahulu terhadap sisa-sisa bangsa ini, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam,</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> 'For the seed [shall be] prosperous, The vine shall give its fruit, The ground shall give her increase, And the heavens shall give their dew -- I will cause the remnant of this people To possess all these. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">بل زرع السلام الكرم يعطي ثمره والارض تعطي غلتها والسموات تعطي نداها واملّك بقية هذا الشعب هذه كلها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">melainkan Aku akan menabur damai sejahtera. Maka pohon anggur akan memberi buahnya dan tanah akan memberi hasilnya dan langit akan memberi air embunnya. Aku akan memberi semuanya itu kepada sisa-sisa bangsa ini sebagai miliknya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> And it shall come to pass [That] just as you were a curse among the nations, O house of Judah and house of Israel, So I will save you, and you shall be a blessing. Do not fear, Let your hands be strong.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ويكون كما انكم كنتم لعنة بين الامم يا بيت يهوذا ويا بيت اسرائيل كذلك اخلصكم فتكونون بركة فلا تخافوا. لتتشدد ايديكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Dan kalau dahulu kamu telah menjadi kutuk di antara bangsa-bangsa, hai kaum Yehuda dan kaum Israel, maka sekarang Aku akan menyelamatkan kamu, sehingga kamu menjadi berkat. Janganlah takut, kuatkanlah hatimu!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> " For thus says the LORD of hosts: 'Just as I determined to punish you When your fathers provoked Me to wrath,' Says the LORD of hosts, 'And I would not relent, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">لانه هكذا قال رب الجنود كما اني فكرت في ان اسيء اليكم حين اغضبني آباؤكم قال رب الجنود ولم اندم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Sebab beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: "Kalau dahulu Aku telah bermaksud mendatangkan malapetaka kepada kamu, ketika nenek moyangmu membuat Aku murka, dan Aku tidak menyesal, firman TUHAN semesta alam,</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> So again in these days I am determined to do good To Jerusalem and to the house of Judah. Do not fear. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">هكذا عدت وفكرت في هذه الايام في ان احسن الى اورشليم وبيت يهوذا. لا تخافوا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">maka pada waktu ini Aku kembali bermaksud berbuat baik kepada Yerusalem dan kepada kaum Yehuda. Janganlah takut!</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> These [are] the things you shall do: Speak each man the truth to his neighbor; Give judgment in your gates for truth, justice, and peace; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">هذه هي الأمور التي تفعلونها. ليكلم كل انسان قريبه بالحق. اقضوا بالحق وقضاء السلام في ابوابكم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Inilah hal-hal yang harus kamu lakukan: Berkatalah benar seorang kepada yang lain dan laksanakanlah hukum yang benar, yang mendatangkan damai di pintu-pintu gerbangmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> Let none of you think evil in your heart against your neighbor; And do not love a false oath. For all these [are things] that I hate,' Says the LORD." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ولا يفكرنّ احد في السوء على قريبه في قلوبكم. ولا تحبوا يمين الزور. لان هذه جميعها اكرهها يقول الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Janganlah merancang kejahatan dalam hatimu seorang terhadap yang lain dan janganlah mencintai sumpah palsu. Sebab semuanya itu Kubenci, demikianlah firman TUHAN."</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> Then the word of the LORD of hosts came to me, saying, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">وكان اليّ كلام رب الجنود قائلا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Datanglah firman TUHAN semesta alam kepadaku, bunyinya:</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> "Thus says the LORD of hosts: 'The fast of the fourth [month,] The fast of the fifth, The fast of the seventh, And the fast of the tenth, Shall be joy and gladness and cheerful feasts For the house of Judah. Therefore love truth and peace.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">هكذا قال رب الجنود. ان صوم الشهر الرابع وصوم الخامس وصوم السابع وصوم العاشر يكون لبيت يهوذا ابتهاجا وفرحا واعيادا طيبة. فاحبوا الحق والسلام.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">"Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Waktu puasa dalam bulan yang keempat, dalam bulan yang kelima, dalam bulan yang ketujuh dan dalam bulan yang kesepuluh akan menjadi kegirangan dan sukacita dan menjadi waktu-waktu perayaan yang menggembirakan bagi kaum Yehuda. Maka cintailah kebenaran dan damai!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> "Thus says the LORD of hosts: 'Peoples shall yet come, Inhabitants of many cities; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">هكذا قال رب الجنود سيأتي شعوب بعد وسكان مدن كثيرة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: "Masih akan datang lagi bangsa-bangsa dan penduduk banyak kota.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> The inhabitants of one [city] shall go to another, saying, "Let us continue to go and pray before the LORD, And seek the LORD of hosts. I myself will go also." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">وسكان واحدة يسيرون الى اخرى قائلين لنذهب ذهابا لنترضى وجه الرب ونطلب رب الجنود. انا ايضا اذهب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Dan penduduk kota yang satu akan pergi kepada penduduk kota yang lain, mengatakan: Marilah kita pergi untuk melunakkan hati TUHAN dan mencari TUHAN semesta alam! Kamipun akan pergi!</language></verse>
			<verse num="22"><language id="English" verse="22"> Yes, many peoples and strong nations Shall come to seek the LORD of hosts in Jerusalem, And to pray before the LORD.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="22">فتاتي شعوب كثيرة وامم قوية ليطلبوا رب الجنود في اورشليم وليترضوا وجه الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="22">Jadi banyak bangsa dan suku-suku bangsa yang kuat akan datang mencari TUHAN semesta alam di Yerusalem dan melunakkan hati TUHAN."</language></verse>
			<verse num="23"><language id="English" verse="23"> "Thus says the LORD of hosts: 'In those days ten men from every language of the nations shall grasp the sleeve of a Jewish man, saying, "Let us go with you, for we have heard [that] God [is] with you." ' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="23">هكذا قال رب الجنود. في تلك الايام يمسك عشرة رجال من جميع ألسنة الامم يتمسكون بذيل رجل يهودي قائلين نذهب معكم لاننا سمعنا ان الله معكم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="23">Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: "Pada waktu itu sepuluh orang dari berbagai-bagai bangsa dan bahasa akan memegang kuat-kuat punca jubah seorang Yahudi dengan berkata: Kami mau pergi menyertai kamu, sebab telah kami dengar, bahwa Allah menyertai kamu!"</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="9">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> The burden of the word of the LORD Against the land of Hadrach, And Damascus its resting place (For the eyes of men And all the tribes of Israel Are on the LORD); </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وحي كلمة الرب في ارض حدراخ ودمشق محلّه. لان للرب عين الانسان وكل اسباط اسرائيل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Ucapan Ilahi. Firman TUHAN datang atas negeri Hadrakh dan berhenti di Damsyik. Sebab kepunyaan Tuhanlah kota-kota Aram serta segala suku Israel;</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Also [against] Hamath, [which] borders on it, And [against] Tyre and Sidon, though they are very wise. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">وحماة ايضا تتاخمها وصور وصيدون وان تكن حكيمة جدا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">juga Hamat yang berbatas kepadanya, pula Tirus dan Sidon, sekalipun mereka sangat bijaksana.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> For Tyre built herself a tower, Heaped up silver like the dust, And gold like the mire of the streets. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">وقد بنت صور حصنا لنفسها وكوّمت الفضة كالتراب والذهب كطين الاسواق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Tirus mendirikan tembok benteng bagi dirinya dan menimbun perak seperti debu dan emas seperti lumpur di jalan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Behold, the LORD will cast her out; He will destroy her power in the sea, And she will be devoured by fire. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">هوذا السيد يمتلكها ويضرب في البحر قوّتها وهي تؤكل بالنار.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Namun sesungguhnya, Tuhan akan membuatnya miskin dan akan melontarkan kekuatannya ke dalam laut, dan kota itu sendiri akan habis dimakan api.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Ashkelon shall see [it] and fear; Gaza also shall be very sorrowful; And Ekron, for He dried up her expectation. The king shall perish from Gaza, And Ashkelon shall not be inhabited. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">ترى اشقلون فتخاف وغزة فتتوجع جدا وعقرون. لانه يخزيها انتظارها والملك يبيد من غزة واشقلون لا تسكن.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Askelon akan melihatnya, lalu takut; juga Gaza, lalu gemetar sangat; Ekronpun, sebab harapannya sudah kandas. Dari Gaza raja akan binasa dan Askelon tidak akan didiami lagi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> "A mixed race shall settle in Ashdod, And I will cut off the pride of the Philistines. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ويسكن في اشدود زنيم واقطع كبرياء الفلسطينيين.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Di Asdod akan diam keturunan campuran, dan kebanggaan orang Filistin akan Kulenyapkan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> I will take away the blood from his mouth, And the abominations from between his teeth. But he who remains, even he [shall be] for our God, And shall be like a leader in Judah, And Ekron like a Jebusite. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">وانزع دماءه من فمه ورجسه من بين اسنانه فيبقى هو ايضا لالهنا ويكون كامير في يهوذا وعقرون كيبوسيّ.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Aku akan melenyapkan darah dari mulutnya dan kejijikan dari antara giginya, dan yang tinggal dari merekapun akan menjadi kepunyaan Allah kita. Mereka akan dianggap seperti suatu kaum di Yehuda, dan orang Ekron seperti orang Yebus.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> I will camp around My house Because of the army, Because of him who passes by and him who returns. No more shall an oppressor pass through them, For now I have seen with My eyes. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">واحلّ حول بيتي بسبب الجيش الذاهب والآئب فلا يعبر عليهم بعد جابي الجزية. فاني الآن رأيت بعينيّ</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Aku berkemah dekat rumah-Ku sebagai pengawal terhadap mereka yang lalu-lalang; tidak akan ada lagi penindas mendatanginya, sebab sekarang Aku sendiri telah mengindahkannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> " Rejoice greatly, O daughter of Zion! Shout, O daughter of Jerusalem! Behold, your King is coming to you; He [is] just and having salvation, Lowly and riding on a donkey, A colt, the foal of a donkey. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ابتهجي جدا يا ابنة صهيون اهتفي يا بنت اورشليم. هوذا ملكك يأتي اليك هو عادل ومنصور وديع وراكب على حمار وعلى جحش ابن اتان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Bersorak-soraklah dengan nyaring, hai puteri Sion, bersorak-sorailah, hai puteri Yerusalem! Lihat, rajamu datang kepadamu; ia adil dan jaya. Ia lemah lembut dan mengendarai seekor keledai, seekor keledai beban yang muda.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> I will cut off the chariot from Ephraim And the horse from Jerusalem; The battle bow shall be cut off. He shall speak peace to the nations; His dominion [shall be] 'from sea to sea, And from the River to the ends of the earth.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">واقطع المركبة من افرايم والفرس من اورشليم وتقطع قوس الحرب. ويتكلم بالسلام للامم وسلطانه من البحر الى البحر ومن النهر الى اقاصي الارض.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Ia akan melenyapkan kereta-kereta dari Efraim dan kuda-kuda dari Yerusalem; busur perang akan dilenyapkan, dan ia akan memberitakan damai kepada bangsa-bangsa. Wilayah kekuasaannya akan terbentang dari laut sampai ke laut dan dari sungai Efrat sampai ke ujung-ujung bumi.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> " As for you also, Because of the blood of your covenant, I will set your prisoners free from the waterless pit. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">وانت ايضا فاني بدم عهدك قد اطلقت اسراك من الجب الذي ليس فيه ماء.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Mengenai engkau, oleh karena darah perjanjian-Ku dengan engkau, Aku akan melepaskan orang-orang tahananmu dari lobang yang tidak berair.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Return to the stronghold, You prisoners of hope. Even today I declare [That] I will restore double to you. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">ارجعوا الى الحصن يا اسرى الرجاء. اليوم ايضا اصرّح اني ارد عليك ضعفين</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Kembalilah ke kota bentengmu, hai orang tahanan yang penuh harapan! Pada hari ini juga Aku memberitahukan: Aku akan memberi ganti kepadamu dua kali lipat!</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> For I have bent Judah, My [bow,] Fitted the bow with Ephraim, And raised up your sons, O Zion, Against your sons, O Greece, And made you like the sword of a mighty man." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">لاني أوترت يهوذا لنفسي وملأت القوس افرايم وانهضت ابناءك يا صهيون على بنيك يا ياوان وجعلتك كسيف جبّار.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Sebab Aku melentur Yehuda bagi-Ku, busur Kuisi dengan Efraim, dan Aku mengayunkan anak-anakmu, hai Sion, terhadap anak-anakmu, hai Yunani, dan Aku akan memakai engkau seperti pedang seorang pahlawan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Then the LORD will be seen over them, And His arrow will go forth like lightning. The Lord GOD will blow the trumpet, And go with whirlwinds from the south. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ويرى الرب فوقهم وسهمه يخرج كالبرق والسيد الرب ينفخ في البوق ويسير في زوابع الجنوب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">TUHAN akan menampakkan diri kepada mereka, dan anak panah-Nya akan melayang keluar seperti kilat. Dan Tuhan ALLAH akan meniup sangkakala dan akan berjalan maju dalam angin badai dari selatan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> The LORD of hosts will defend them; They shall devour and subdue with slingstones. They shall drink [and] roar as if with wine; They shall be filled [with blood] like basins, Like the corners of the altar. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">رب الجنود يحامي عنهم فياكلون ويدوسون حجارة المقلاع ويشربون ويضجون كما من الخمر ويمتلئون كالمنضح وكزوايا المذبح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">TUHAN semesta alam akan melindungi mereka, dan mereka akan menghabisi dan menginjak-injak pengumban-pengumban. Mereka akan minum darah seperti minum anggur dan menjadi penuh seperti bokor penyiraman, seperti penjuru-penjuru mezbah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> The LORD their God will save them in that day, As the flock of His people. For they [shall be like] the jewels of a crown, Lifted like a banner over His land -- </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">ويخلصهم الرب الههم في ذلك اليوم كقطيع شعبه بل كحجارة التاج مرفوعة على ارضه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">TUHAN, Allah mereka, akan menyelamatkan mereka pada hari itu; seperti kawanan domba umat-Nya itu, sungguh, mereka seperti permata-permata mahkota yang berkilap-kilap, demikianlah mereka di tanah TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> For how great is its goodness And how great its beauty! Grain shall make the young men thrive, And new wine the young women. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ما اجوده وما اجمله. الحنطة تنمي الفتيان والمسطار العذارى</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Sungguh, alangkah baiknya itu dan alangkah indahnya! Teruna bertumbuh pesat karena gandum, dan anak dara karena anggur.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="10">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Ask the LORD for rain In the time of the latter rain. The LORD will make flashing clouds; He will give them showers of rain, Grass in the field for everyone. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">اطلبوا من الرب المطر في اوان المطر المتأخر فيصنع الرب بروقا ويعطيهم مطر الوبل. لكل انسان عشبا في الحقل.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Mintalah hujan dari pada TUHAN pada akhir musim semi! Tuhanlah yang membuat awan-awan pembawa hujan deras, dan hujan lebat akan Diberikannya kepada mereka dan tumbuh-tumbuhan di padang kepada setiap orang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> For the idols speak delusion; The diviners envision lies, And tell false dreams; They comfort in vain. Therefore [the people] wend their way like sheep; They are in trouble because [there is] no shepherd. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">لان الترافيم قد تكلموا بالباطل والعرافون رأوا الكذب واخبروا باحلام كذب. يعزّون بالباطل. لذلك رحلوا كغنم. ذلوا اذ ليس راع.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Sebab apa yang dikatakan oleh terafim adalah jahat, dan yang dilihat oleh juru-juru tenung adalah dusta, dan mimpi-mimpi yang disebutkan mereka adalah hampa, serta hiburan yang diberikan mereka adalah kesia-siaan. Oleh sebab itu bangsa itu berkeliaran seperti kawanan domba dan menderita sengsara sebab tidak ada gembala.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> " My anger is kindled against the shepherds, And I will punish the goatherds. For the LORD of hosts will visit His flock, The house of Judah, And will make them as His royal horse in the battle. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">على الرعاة اشتعل غضبي فعاقبت الاعتدة. لان رب الجنود قد تعهد قطيعه بيت يهوذا وجعلهم كفرس جلاله في القتال.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">"Terhadap para gembala akan bangkit murka-Ku dan terhadap kepala-kepala kawanan kambing Aku akan mengadakan pembalasan, sebab TUHAN semesta alam memperhatikan kawanan ternak-Nya, yakni kaum Yehuda, dan membuat mereka sebagai kuda keagungan-Nya dalam pertempuran.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> From him comes the cornerstone, From him the tent peg, From him the battle bow, From him every ruler together. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">منه الزاوية منه الوتد منه قوس القتال منه يخرج كل ظالم جميعا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Dari pada mereka akan muncul batu penjuru, dari pada mereka akan muncul patok kemah, dari pada mereka akan muncul busur perang, dari pada mereka akan keluar semua penguasa bersama-sama.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> They shall be like mighty men, Who tread down [their enemies] In the mire of the streets in the battle. They shall fight because the LORD is with them, And the riders on horses shall be put to shame. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">ويكونون كالجبابرة الدائسين طين الاسواق في القتال ويحاربون لان الرب معهم والراكبون الخيل يخزون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Maka mereka akan seperti pahlawan yang menginjak-injak musuh seakan-akan itu lumpur di jalan; mereka akan berperang, sebab TUHAN menyertai mereka, dan mereka akan membuat malu orang-orang yang mengendarai kuda.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> "I will strengthen the house of Judah, And I will save the house of Joseph. I will bring them back, Because I have mercy on them. They shall be as though I had not cast them aside; For I [am] the LORD their God, And I will hear them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">واقوي بيت يهوذا واخلّص بيت يوسف وارجعهم لاني قد رحمتهم ويكونون كاني لم ارفضهم لاني انا الرب الههم فاجيبهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Aku akan membuat kuat kaum Yehuda, dan Aku menyelamatkan keturunan Yusuf. Aku akan membawa mereka kembali, sebab Aku menyayangi mereka; dan keadaan mereka seakan-akan tidak pernah ditolak oleh Aku, sebab Akulah TUHAN, Allah mereka, dan Aku akan menjawab mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> [Those of] Ephraim shall be like a mighty man, And their heart shall rejoice as if with wine. Yes, their children shall see [it] and be glad; Their heart shall rejoice in the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">ويكون افرايم كجبار ويفرح قلبهم كانه بالخمر وينظر بنوهم فيفرحون ويبتهج قلبهم بالرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Efraim akan seperti seorang pahlawan, hati mereka akan bersukacita seperti oleh anggur. Anak-anak mereka akan melihatnya, lalu bersukacita dan hati mereka bersorak-sorak karena TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> I will whistle for them and gather them, For I will redeem them; And they shall increase as they once increased. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">اصفر لهم واجمعهم لاني قد فديتهم ويكثرون كما كثروا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Aku akan bersiul memanggil mereka dan Aku akan mengumpulkan mereka, sebab Aku sudah membebaskan mereka, dan jumlah mereka menjadi banyak seperti dahulu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> "I will sow them among the peoples, And they shall remember Me in far countries; They shall live, together with their children, And they shall return. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">وازرعهم بين الشعوب فيذكرونني في الاراضي البعيدة ويحيون مع بنيهم ويرجعون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Sekalipun Aku telah menyerakkan mereka ke antara bangsa-bangsa, tetapi di tempat-tempat yang jauh mereka akan ingat kepada-Ku; mereka akan hidup bersama-sama anak-anak mereka dan mereka akan kembali.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> I will also bring them back from the land of Egypt, And gather them from Assyria. I will bring them into the land of Gilead and Lebanon, Until no [more room] is found for them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">وارجعهم من ارض مصر واجمعهم من اشور وآتي بهم الى ارض جلعاد ولبنان ولا يوجد لهم مكان.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Aku akan membawa mereka kembali dari tanah Mesir, dan dari Asyur Aku akan mengumpulkan mereka; Aku akan membawa mereka masuk ke tanah Gilead dan ke Libanon, sehingga tidak ada tempat lagi bagi mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> He shall pass through the sea with affliction, And strike the waves of the sea: All the depths of the River shall dry up. Then the pride of Assyria shall be brought down, And the scepter of Egypt shall depart. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">ويعبر في بحر الضيق ويضرب اللجج في البحر وتجف كل اعماق النهر وتخفض كبرياء اشور ويزول قضيب مصر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Mereka akan menyeberangi laut Mesir dan Ia akan memukul gelombang di laut, sehingga segala tempat yang dalam di sungai Nil menjadi kering. Kebanggaan Asyur akan diturunkan dan tongkat kerajaan Mesir akan lewat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> "So I will strengthen them in the LORD, And they shall walk up and down in His name," Says the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">واقويهم بالرب فيسلكون باسمه يقول الرب</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Aku akan menguatkan mereka, dan mereka akan bermegah di dalam nama TUHAN," demikianlah firman TUHAN.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="11">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Open your doors, O Lebanon, That fire may devour your cedars. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">افتح ابوابك يا لبنان فتأكل النار ارزك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Bukalah pintu-pintumu, hai Libanon, supaya api dapat memakan pohon-pohon arasmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> Wail, O cypress, for the cedar has fallen, Because the mighty [trees] are ruined. Wail, O oaks of Bashan, For the thick forest has come down. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">ولول يا سرو لان الارز سقط لان الاعزاء قد خربوا. ولول يا بلوط باشان لان الوعر المنيع قد هبط.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Merataplah, hai pohon sanobar, sebab sudah rebah pohon aras dan sudah dirusakkan pohon-pohon yang hebat! Merataplah, hai pohon-pohon tarbantin Basan, sebab telah rata hutan yang lebat itu!</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> [There is] the sound of wailing shepherds! For their glory is in ruins. [There is] the sound of roaring lions! For the pride of the Jordan is in ruins. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">صوت ولولة الرعاة لان فخرهم خرب. صوت زمجرة الاشبال لان كبرياء الاردن خربت.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Dengar, para gembala meratap! Sebab kemegahan mereka sudah dirusakkan. Dengar, singa-singa mengaum! Sebab sudah dirusakkan kebanggaan sungai Yordan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> Thus says the LORD my God, "Feed the flock for slaughter, </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">هكذا قال الرب الهي ارع غنم الذبح</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Beginilah firman TUHAN Allahku kepadaku: "Gembalakanlah domba-domba sembelihan itu!</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> "whose owners slaughter them and feel no guilt; those who sell them say, 'Blessed be the LORD, for I am rich'; and their shepherds do not pity them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">الذين يذبحهم مالكوهم ولا يأثمون وبائعوهم يقولون مبارك الرب قد استغنيت. ورعاتهم لا يشفقون عليهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Orang-orang yang membelinya menyembelihnya dengan tidak merasa bersalah dan orang-orang yang menjualnya berkata: Terpujilah TUHAN! Aku telah menjadi kaya! Dan orang-orang yang menggembalakannya tidak mengasihaninya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> "For I will no longer pity the inhabitants of the land," says the LORD. "But indeed I will give everyone into his neighbor's hand and into the hand of his king. They shall attack the land, and I will not deliver [them] from their hand." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">لاني لا اشفق بعد على سكان الارض يقول الرب بل هانذا مسلّم الانسان كل رجل ليد قريبه وليد ملكه فيضربون الارض ولا انقذ من يدهم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Sebab Aku tidak lagi akan mengasihani penduduk bumi, demikianlah firman TUHAN, melainkan sesungguhnya, Aku akan menyerahkan manusia masing-masing ke dalam tangan gembalanya dan ke dalam tangan rajanya; mereka ini akan menghancurkan bumi dan Aku tidak akan melepaskan seorangpun dari tangan mereka."</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> So I fed the flock for slaughter, in particular the poor of the flock. I took for myself two staffs: the one I called Beauty, and the other I called Bonds; and I fed the flock. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">فرعيت غنم الذبح. لكنهم اذل الغنم. واخذت لنفسي عصوين فسميت الواحدة نعمة وسميت الاخرى حبالا ورعيت الغنم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">Maka aku menggembalakan domba-domba sembelihan itu untuk pedagang-pedagang domba. Aku mengambil dua tongkat: yang satu kusebutkan "Kemurahan" dan yang lain kusebutkan "Ikatan"; lalu aku menggembalakan domba-domba itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> I dismissed the three shepherds in one month. My soul loathed them, and their soul also abhorred me. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">وابدت الرعاة الثلاثة في شهر واحد وضاقت نفسي بهم وكرهتني ايضا نفسهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Dalam satu bulan aku melenyapkan ketiga gembala itu. Kemudian aku tidak dapat menahan hati lagi terhadap domba-domba itu, dan merekapun merasa muak terhadap aku.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> Then I said, "I will not feed you. Let what is dying die, and what is perishing perish. Let those that are left eat each other's flesh." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">فقلت لا ارعاكم. من يمت فليمت ومن يبد فليبد والبقية فلياكل بعضها لحم بعض</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Lalu aku berkata: "Aku tidak mau lagi menggembalakan kamu; yang hendak mati, biarlah mati; yang hendak lenyap, biarlah lenyap, dan yang masih tinggal itu, biarlah masing-masing memakan daging temannya!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> And I took my staff, Beauty, and cut it in two, that I might break the covenant which I had made with all the peoples. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">فاخذت عصاي نعمة وقصفتها لانقض عهدي الذي قطعته مع كل الاسباط.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Aku mengambil tongkatku "Kemurahan", lalu mematahkannya untuk membatalkan perjanjian yang telah kuikat dengan segala bangsa.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> So it was broken on that day. Thus the poor of the flock, who were watching me, knew that it [was] the word of the LORD. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فنقض في ذلك اليوم وهكذا علم اذل الغنم المنتظرون لي انها كلمة الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Jadi dibatalkanlah perjanjian pada hari itu, maka tahulah pedagang-pedagang domba yang sedang mengamat-amati aku, bahwa itu adalah firman TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> Then I said to them, "If it is agreeable to you, give [me] my wages; and if not, refrain." So they weighed out for my wages thirty [pieces] of silver. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">فقلت لهم ان حسن في اعينكم فاعطوني اجرتي والا فامتنعوا. فوزنوا اجرتي ثلاثين من الفضة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Lalu aku berkata kepada mereka: "Jika itu kamu anggap baik, berikanlah upahku, dan jika tidak, biarkanlah!" Maka mereka membayar upahku dengan menimbang tiga puluh uang perak.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> And the LORD said to me, "Throw it to the potter" -- that princely price they set on me. So I took the thirty [pieces] of silver and threw them into the house of the LORD for the potter. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">فقال لي الرب القها الى الفخاري الثمن الكريم الذي ثمنوني به. فاخذت الثلاثين من الفضة والقيتها الى الفخاري في بيت الرب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Tetapi berfirmanlah TUHAN kepadaku: "Serahkanlah itu kepada penuang logam!" --nilai tinggi yang ditaksir mereka bagiku. Lalu aku mengambil ketiga puluh uang perak itu dan menyerahkannya kepada penuang logam di rumah TUHAN.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Then I cut in two my other staff, Bonds, that I might break the brotherhood between Judah and Israel. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ثم قصفت عصاي الاخرى حبالا لانقض الإخاء بين يهوذا واسرائيل</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Kemudian aku mematahkan tongkat yang kedua, yaitu "Ikatan", untuk meniadakan persaudaraan antara Yehuda dan Israel.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> And the LORD said to me, "Next, take for yourself the implements of a foolish shepherd. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">فقال لي الرب خذ لنفسك بعد ادوات راع احمق.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Sesudah itu berfirmanlah TUHAN kepadaku: "Ambillah sekali lagi perkakas seorang gembala yang pandir!</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> "For indeed I will raise up a shepherd in the land [who] will not care for those who are cut off, nor seek the young, nor heal those that are broken, nor feed those that still stand. But he will eat the flesh of the fat and tear their hooves in pieces. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">لاني هانذا مقيم راعيا في الارض لا يفتقد المنقطعين ولا يطلب المنساق ولا يجبر المنكسر ولا يربّي القائم ولكن ياكل لحم السمان وينزع اظلافها</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Sebab sesungguhnya, Aku akan membangkitkan di negeri ini seorang gembala yang tidak mengindahkan yang lenyap, yang tidak mencari yang hilang, yang tidak menyembuhkan yang luka, yang tidak memelihara yang sehat, melainkan memakan daging dari yang gemuk dan mencabut kuku mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> "Woe to the worthless shepherd, Who leaves the flock! A sword [shall be] against his arm And against his right eye; His arm shall completely wither, And his right eye shall be totally blinded." </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ويل للراعي الباطل التارك الغنم. السيف على ذراعه وعلى عينه اليمنى. ذراعه تيبس يبسا وعينه اليمنى تكلّ كلولا</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Celakalah gembala-Ku yang pandir, yang meninggalkan domba-domba! Biarlah pedang menimpa lengannya dan menimpa mata kanannya! Biarlah lengannya kering sekering-keringnya, dan mata kanannya menjadi pudar sepudar-pudarnya!"</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="12">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> The burden of the word of the LORD against Israel. Thus says the LORD, who stretches out the heavens, lays the foundation of the earth, and forms the spirit of man within him: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">وحي كلام الرب على اسرائيل. يقول الرب باسط السموات ومؤسس الارض وجابل روح الانسان في داخله</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Ucapan ilahi. Firman TUHAN tentang Israel: Demikianlah firman TUHAN yang membentangkan langit dan yang meletakkan dasar bumi dan yang menciptakan roh dalam diri manusia:</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> "Behold, I will make Jerusalem a cup of drunkenness to all the surrounding peoples, when they lay siege against Judah and Jerusalem. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">هانذا اجعل اورشليم كاس ترنّح لجميع الشعوب حولها وايضا على يهوذا تكون في حصار اورشليم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">"Sesungguhnya Aku membuat Yerusalem menjadi pasu yang menyebabkan segala bangsa di sekeliling menjadi pening; juga Yehuda akan mengalami kesusahan ketika Yerusalem dikepung.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> "And it shall happen in that day that I will make Jerusalem a very heavy stone for all peoples; all who would heave it away will surely be cut in pieces, though all nations of the earth are gathered against it. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">ويكون في ذلك اليوم اني اجعل اورشليم حجرا مشوالا لجميع الشعوب وكل الذين يشيلونه ينشقون شقا. ويجتمع عليها كل امم الارض.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Maka pada waktu itu Aku akan membuat Yerusalem menjadi batu untuk diangkat bagi segala bangsa. Siapa yang mengangkatnya pastilah mendapat luka parah. Segala bangsa di bumi akan berkumpul melawannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> "In that day," says the LORD, "I will strike every horse with confusion, and its rider with madness; I will open My eyes on the house of Judah, and will strike every horse of the peoples with blindness. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">في ذلك اليوم يقول الرب اضرب كل فرس بالحيرة وراكبه بالجنون. وافتح عينيّ على بيت يهوذا واضرب كل خيل الشعوب بالعمى.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Pada waktu itu, demikianlah firman TUHAN, Aku akan membuat segala kuda menjadi bingung, penunggangnya menjadi gila. Atas kaum Yehuda, Aku akan membuka mata-Ku, tetapi segala kuda bangsa akan Kubuat menjadi buta.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> "And the governors of Judah shall say in their heart, 'The inhabitants of Jerusalem [are] my strength in the LORD of hosts, their God.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">فتقول امراء يهوذا في قلبهم ان سكان اورشليم قوة لي برب الجنود الههم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Sesudah itu kaum-kaum di Yehuda akan berkata dalam hatinya: Penduduk Yerusalem mempunyai kekuatan oleh karena TUHAN semesta alam, Allah mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> "In that day I will make the governors of Judah like a firepan in the woodpile, and like a fiery torch in the sheaves; they shall devour all the surrounding peoples on the right hand and on the left, but Jerusalem shall be inhabited again in her own place -- Jerusalem. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">في ذلك اليوم اجعل امراء يهوذا كمصباح نار بين الحطب وكمشعل نار بين الحزم فياكلون كل الشعوب حولهم عن اليمين وعن اليسار فتثبت اورشليم ايضا في مكانها باورشليم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Pada waktu itu Aku akan membuat kaum-kaum di Yehuda seperti anglo berapi di tengah-tengah timbunan kayu dan seperti suluh berapi di tengah-tengah timbunan bulir gandum; api keduanya akan menjilat ke kanan dan ke kiri segala bangsa di sekeliling, tetapi Yerusalem selanjutnya akan tetap tinggal di tempatnya yang dahulu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> " The LORD will save the tents of Judah first, so that the glory of the house of David and the glory of the inhabitants of Jerusalem shall not become greater than that of Judah. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">ويخلص الرب خيام يهوذا اولا لكيلا يتعاظم افتخار بيت داود وافتخار سكان اورشليم على يهوذا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">TUHAN akan pertama-tama memberi kemenangan kepada kemah-kemah Yehuda, supaya keluarga Daud dan penduduk Yerusalem jangan terlalu bermegah-megah terhadap Yehuda.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> "In that day the LORD will defend the inhabitants of Jerusalem; the one who is feeble among them in that day shall be like David, and the house of David [shall be] like God, like the Angel of the LORD before them. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">في ذلك اليوم يستر الرب سكان اورشليم فيكون العاثر منهم في ذلك اليوم مثل داود وبيت داود مثل الله مثل ملاك الرب امامهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Pada waktu itu TUHAN akan melindungi penduduk Yerusalem, dan orang yang tersandung di antara mereka pada waktu itu akan menjadi seperti Daud, dan keluarga Daud akan menjadi seperti Allah, seperti Malaikat TUHAN, yang mengepalai mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> "It shall be in that day [that] I will seek to destroy all the nations that come against Jerusalem. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ويكون في ذلك اليوم اني التمس هلاك كل الامم الآتين على اورشليم</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Maka pada waktu itu Aku berikhtiar untuk memunahkan segala bangsa yang menyerang Yerusalem."</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> " And I will pour on the house of David and on the inhabitants of Jerusalem the Spirit of grace and supplication; then they will look on Me whom they pierced. Yes, they will mourn for Him as one mourns for [his] only [son,] and grieve for Him as one grieves for a firstborn. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">وافيض على بيت داود وعلى سكان اورشليم روح النعمة والتضرعات فينظرون اليّ الذي طعنوه وينوحون عليه كنائح على وحيد له ويكونون في مرارة عليه كمن هو في مرارة على بكره.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">"Aku akan mencurahkan roh pengasihan dan roh permohonan atas keluarga Daud dan atas penduduk Yerusalem, dan mereka akan memandang kepada dia yang telah mereka tikam, dan akan meratapi dia seperti orang meratapi anak tunggal, dan akan menangisi dia dengan pedih seperti orang menangisi anak sulung.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> "In that day there shall be a great mourning in Jerusalem, like the mourning at Hadad Rimmon in the plain of Megiddo. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">في ذلك اليوم يعظم النوح في اورشليم كنوح هدد رمون في بقعة مجدّون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Pada waktu itu ratapan di Yerusalem akan sama besarnya dengan ratapan atas Hadad-Rimon di lembah Megido.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> "And the land shall mourn, every family by itself: the family of the house of David by itself, and their wives by themselves; the family of the house of Nathan by itself, and their wives by themselves; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">وتنوح الارض عشائر عشائر على حدتها عشيرة بيت داود على حدتها ونساؤهم على حدتهنّ. عشيرة بيت ناثان على حدتها ونساؤهم على حدتهنّ‎.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Negeri itu akan meratap, setiap kaum keluarga tersendiri; kaum keluarga keturunan Daud tersendiri dan isteri mereka tersendiri; kaum keluarga keturunan Natan tersendiri dan isteri mereka tersendiri;</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> "the family of the house of Levi by itself, and their wives by themselves; the family of Shimei by itself, and their wives by themselves; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">عشيرة بيت لاوي على حدتها ونساؤهم على حدتهنّ. عشيرة شمعي على حدتها ونساؤهم على حدتهنّ.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">kaum keluarga keturunan Lewi tersendiri dan isteri mereka tersendiri; kaum keluarga Simei tersendiri dan isteri mereka tersendiri;</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> "all the families that remain, every family by itself, and their wives by themselves. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">كل العشائر الباقية عشيرة عشيرة على حدتها ونساؤهم على حدتهنّ</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">juga segala kaum keluarga yang masih tinggal, setiap kaum keluarga tersendiri dan isteri mereka tersendiri."</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="13">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> "In that day a fountain shall be opened for the house of David and for the inhabitants of Jerusalem, for sin and for uncleanness. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">في ذلك اليوم يكون ينبوع مفتوحا لبيت داود ولسكان اورشليم للخطية وللنجاسة.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">"Pada waktu itu akan terbuka suatu sumber bagi keluarga Daud dan bagi penduduk Yerusalem untuk membasuh dosa dan kecemaran.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> " It shall be in that day," says the LORD of hosts, "[that] I will cut off the names of the idols from the land, and they shall no longer be remembered. I will also cause the prophets and the unclean spirit to depart from the land. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">ويكون في ذلك اليوم يقول رب الجنود اني اقطع اسماء الاصنام من الارض فلا تذكر بعد وازيل الانبياء ايضا والروح النجس من الارض.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Maka pada waktu itu, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam, Aku akan melenyapkan nama-nama berhala dari negeri itu, sehingga orang tidak menyebutnya lagi. Juga para nabi dan roh najis akan Kusingkirkan dari negeri itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> "It shall come to pass [that] if anyone still prophesies, then his father and mother who begot him will say to him, 'You shall not live, because you have spoken lies in the name of the LORD.' And his father and mother who begot him shall thrust him through when he prophesies. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">ويكون اذا تنبأ احد بعد ان اباه وامه والديه يقولان له لا تعيش لانك تكلمت بالكذب باسم الرب. فيطعنه ابوه وامه والداه عندما يتنبأ.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Dan apabila seseorang masih tampil sebagai nabi, maka ayahnya dan ibunya, yang telah memperanakkan dia, akan berkata kepadanya: Janganlah engkau hidup lagi, sebab yang kaukatakan demi nama TUHAN itu adalah dusta! Lalu ayahnya dan ibunya, yang telah memperanakkan dia, akan menikam dia pada waktu ia bernubuat.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> " And it shall be in that day [that] every prophet will be ashamed of his vision when he prophesies; they will not wear a robe of coarse hair to deceive. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">ويكون في ذلك اليوم ان الانبياء يخزون كل واحد من رؤياه اذا تنبأ ولا يلبسون ثوب شعر لاجل الغش.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Pada waktu itu para nabi masing-masing akan mendapat malu oleh karena penglihatannya sebagai nabi, dan tidak ada lagi dari mereka yang mengenakan jubah berbulu untuk berbohong;</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> "But he will say, 'I [am] no prophet, I [am] a farmer; for a man taught me to keep cattle from my youth.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">بل يقول لست انا نبيا. انا انسان فالح الارض لان انسانا اقتناني من صباي.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">tetapi masing-masing akan berkata: Aku ini bukan seorang nabi, melainkan seorang pengusaha tanah, sebab tanah adalah harta kepunyaanku sejak kecil.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> "And [one] will say to him, 'What are these wounds between your arms?' Then he will answer, '[Those] with which I was wounded in the house of my friends.' </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">فيقول له ما هذه الجروح في يديك. فيقول هي التي جرحت بها في بيت احبائي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Dan apabila ada orang bertanya kepadanya: Bekas luka apakah yang ada pada badanmu ini?, lalu ia akan menjawab: Itulah luka yang kudapat di rumah sahabat-sahabatku!"</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> " Awake, O sword, against My Shepherd, Against the Man who is My Companion," Says the LORD of hosts. "Strike the Shepherd, And the sheep will be scattered; Then I will turn My hand against the little ones. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">استيقظ يا سيف على راعيّ وعلى رجل رفقتي يقول رب الجنود. اضرب الراعي فتتشتّت الغنم وارد يدي على الصغار.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">"Hai pedang, bangkitlah terhadap gembala-Ku, terhadap orang yang paling karib kepada-Ku!", demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam. "Bunuhlah gembala, sehingga domba-domba tercerai-berai! Aku akan mengenakan tangan-Ku terhadap yang lemah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> And it shall come to pass in all the land," Says the LORD, "[That] two-thirds in it shall be cut off [and] die, But [one-] third shall be left in it: </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ويكون في كل الارض يقول الرب ان ثلثين منها يقطعان ويموتان والثلث يبقى فيها.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Maka di seluruh negeri, demikianlah firman TUHAN, dua pertiga dari padanya akan dilenyapkan, mati binasa, tetapi sepertiga dari padanya akan tinggal hidup.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> I will bring the [one-third] through the fire, Will refine them as silver is refined, And test them as gold is tested. They will call on My name, And I will answer them. I will say, 'This [is] My people'; And each one will say, 'The LORD [is] my God.' " </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">وادخل الثلث في النار وامحصهم كمحص الفضة وامتحنهم امتحان الذهب. هو يدعو باسمي وانا اجيبه. اقول هو شعبي وهو يقول الرب الهي</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Aku akan menaruh yang sepertiga itu dalam api dan akan memurnikan mereka seperti orang memurnikan perak. Aku akan menguji mereka, seperti orang menguji emas. Mereka akan memanggil nama-Ku, dan Aku akan menjawab mereka. Aku akan berkata: Mereka adalah umat-Ku, dan mereka akan menjawab: TUHAN adalah Allahku!"</language></verse>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="14">
			<verse num="1"><language id="English" verse="1"> Behold, the day of the LORD is coming, And your spoil will be divided in your midst. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="1">هوذا يوم للرب ياتي فيقسم سلبك في وسطك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="1">Sesungguhnya, akan datang hari yang ditetapkan TUHAN, maka jarahan yang dirampas dari padamu akan dibagi-bagi di tengah-tengahmu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="2"><language id="English" verse="2"> For I will gather all the nations to battle against Jerusalem; The city shall be taken, The houses rifled, And the women ravished. Half of the city shall go into captivity, But the remnant of the people shall not be cut off from the city. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="2">واجمع كل الامم على اورشليم للمحاربة فتؤخذ المدينة وتنهب البيوت وتفضح النساء ويخرج نصف المدينة الى السبي وبقية الشعب لا تقطع من المدينة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="2">Aku akan mengumpulkan segala bangsa untuk memerangi Yerusalem; kota itu akan direbut, rumah-rumah akan dirampoki dan perempuan-perempuan akan ditiduri. Setengah dari penduduk kota itu harus pergi ke dalam pembuangan, tetapi selebihnya dari bangsa itu tidak akan dilenyapkan dari kota itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="3"><language id="English" verse="3"> Then the LORD will go forth And fight against those nations, As He fights in the day of battle. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="3">فيخرج الرب ويحارب تلك الامم كما في يوم حربه يوم القتال.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="3">Kemudian TUHAN akan maju berperang melawan bangsa-bangsa itu seperti Ia berperang pada hari pertempuran.</language></verse>
			<verse num="4"><language id="English" verse="4"> And in that day His feet will stand on the Mount of Olives, Which faces Jerusalem on the east. And the Mount of Olives shall be split in two, From east to west, [Making] a very large valley; Half of the mountain shall move toward the north And half of it toward the south. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="4">وتقف قدماه في ذلك اليوم على جبل الزيتون الذي قدام اورشليم من الشرق فينشق جبل الزيتون من وسطه نحو الشرق ونحو الغرب واديا عظيما جدا وينتقل نصف الجبل نحو الشمال ونصفه نحو الجنوب.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="4">Pada waktu itu kaki-Nya akan berjejak di bukit Zaitun yang terletak di depan Yerusalem di sebelah timur. Bukit Zaitun itu akan terbelah dua dari timur ke barat, sehingga terjadi suatu lembah yang sangat besar; setengah dari bukit itu akan bergeser ke utara dan setengah lagi ke selatan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="5"><language id="English" verse="5"> Then you shall flee [through] My mountain valley, For the mountain valley shall reach to Azal. Yes, you shall flee As you fled from the earthquake In the days of Uzziah king of Judah. Thus the LORD my God will come, [And] all the saints with You. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="5">وتهربون في جواء جبالي لان جواء الجبال يصل الى آصل وتهربون كما هربتم من الزلزلة في ايام عزّيا ملك يهوذا ويأتي الرب الهي وجميع القديسين معك</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="5">Maka tertutuplah lembah gunung-gunung-Ku, sebab lembah gunung itu akan menyentuh sisinya; dan kamu akan melarikan diri seperti kamu pernah melarikan diri oleh karena gempa bumi pada zaman Uzia, raja Yehuda. Lalu TUHAN, Allahku, akan datang, dan semua orang kudus bersama-sama Dia.</language></verse>
			<verse num="6"><language id="English" verse="6"> It shall come to pass in that day [That] there will be no light; The lights will diminish. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="6">ويكون في ذلك اليوم انه لا يكون نور. الدراريّ تنقبض.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="6">Maka pada waktu itu tidak akan ada lagi udara dingin atau keadaan beku,</language></verse>
			<verse num="7"><language id="English" verse="7"> It shall be one day Which is known to the LORD -- Neither day nor night. But at evening time it shall happen [That] it will be light. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="7">ويكون يوم واحد معروف للرب. لا نهار ولا ليل بل يحدث انه في وقت المساء يكون نور.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="7">tetapi akan ada satu hari--hari itu diketahui oleh TUHAN--dengan tidak ada pergantian siang dan malam, dan malampun menjadi siang.</language></verse>
			<verse num="8"><language id="English" verse="8"> And in that day it shall be [That] living waters shall flow from Jerusalem, Half of them toward the eastern sea And half of them toward the western sea; In both summer and winter it shall occur. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="8">ويكون في ذلك اليوم ان مياها حيّة تخرج من اورشليم نصفها الى البحر الشرقي ونصفها الى البحر الغربي. في الصيف وفي الخريف تكون.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="8">Pada waktu itu akan mengalir air kehidupan dari Yerusalem; setengahnya mengalir ke laut timur, dan setengah lagi mengalir ke laut barat; hal itu akan terus berlangsung dalam musim panas dan dalam musim dingin.</language></verse>
			<verse num="9"><language id="English" verse="9"> And the LORD shall be King over all the earth. In that day it shall be -- "The LORD [is] one," And His name one. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="9">ويكون الرب ملكا على كل الارض. في ذلك اليوم يكون الرب وحده واسمه وحده.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="9">Maka TUHAN akan menjadi Raja atas seluruh bumi; pada waktu itu TUHAN adalah satu-satunya dan nama-Nya satu-satunya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="10"><language id="English" verse="10"> All the land shall be turned into a plain from Geba to Rimmon south of Jerusalem. Jerusalem shall be raised up and inhabited in her place from Benjamin's Gate to the place of the First Gate and the Corner Gate, and [from] the Tower of Hananeel to the king's winepresses. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="10">وتتحول الارض كلها كالعربة من جبع الى رمّون جنوب اورشليم. وترتفع وتعمر في مكانها من باب بنيامين الى مكان الباب الاول الى باب الزوايا ومن برج حننئيل الى معاصر الملك.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="10">Seluruh negeri ini akan berubah menjadi seperti Araba-Yordan, dari Geba sampai ke Rimon di sebelah selatan Yerusalem. Tetapi kota itu akan menjulang tinggi dan tetap tinggal di tempatnya, dari pintu gerbang Benyamin sampai ke tempat pintu gerbang yang dahulu, yakni sampai ke pintu gerbang Sudut, dan dari menara Hananeel sampai ke tempat pemerasan anggur raja.</language></verse>
			<verse num="11"><language id="English" verse="11"> [The people] shall dwell in it; And no longer shall there be utter destruction, But Jerusalem shall be safely inhabited. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="11">فيسكنون فيها ولا يكون بعد لعن فتعمر اورشليم بالأمن</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="11">Orang akan menetap di dalamnya, sebab penumpasan tidak akan ada lagi, dan Yerusalem akan tetap aman.</language></verse>
			<verse num="12"><language id="English" verse="12"> And this shall be the plague with which the LORD will strike all the people who fought against Jerusalem: Their flesh shall dissolve while they stand on their feet, Their eyes shall dissolve in their sockets, And their tongues shall dissolve in their mouths. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="12">وهذه تكون الضربة التي يضرب بها الرب كل الشعوب الذين تجندوا على اورشليم. لحمهم يذوب وهم واقفون على اقدامهم وعيونهم تذوب في اوقابها ولسانهم يذوب في فمهم.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="12">Inilah tulah yang akan ditimpakan TUHAN kepada segala bangsa yang memerangi Yerusalem: daging mereka akan menjadi busuk, sementara mereka masih berdiri, mata mereka akan menjadi busuk dalam lekuknya dan lidah mereka akan menjadi busuk dalam mulut mereka.</language></verse>
			<verse num="13"><language id="English" verse="13"> It shall come to pass in that day [That] a great panic from the LORD will be among them. Everyone will seize the hand of his neighbor, And raise his hand against his neighbor's hand; </language><language id="Arabic" verse="13">ويكون في ذلك اليوم ان اضطرابا عظيما من الرب يحدث فيهم فيمسك الرجل بيد قريبه وتعلو يده على يد قريبه.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="13">Maka pada waktu itu akan terjadi kegemparan besar dari pada TUHAN di antara mereka, sehingga masing-masing memegang tangan temannya dan mengangkat tangannya melawan tangan temannya.</language></verse>
			<verse num="14"><language id="English" verse="14"> Judah also will fight at Jerusalem. And the wealth of all the surrounding nations Shall be gathered together: Gold, silver, and apparel in great abundance. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="14">ويهوذا ايضا تحارب اورشليم وتجمع ثروة كل الامم من حولها ذهب وفضة وملابس كثيرة جدا.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="14">Juga Yehuda akan berperang melawan Yerusalem itu; dan dikumpulkanlah harta benda segala bangsa di sekeliling, yaitu emas, perak dan pakaian dalam jumlah yang sangat besar.</language></verse>
			<verse num="15"><language id="English" verse="15"> Such also shall be the plague On the horse [and] the mule, On the camel and the donkey, And on all the cattle that will be in those camps. So [shall] this plague [be.] </language><language id="Arabic" verse="15">وكذا تكون ضربة الخيل والبغال والجمال والحمير وكل البهائم التي تكون في هذه المحالّ. كهذه الضربة</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="15">Tulah seperti itu juga akan menimpa kuda, bagal, unta, keledai dan segala hewan yang ada dalam perkemahan-perkemahan itu.</language></verse>
			<verse num="16"><language id="English" verse="16"> And it shall come to pass [that] everyone who is left of all the nations which came against Jerusalem shall go up from year to year to worship the King, the LORD of hosts, and to keep the Feast of Tabernacles. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="16">ويكون ان كل الباقي من جميع الامم الذين جاءوا على اورشليم يصعدون من سنة الى سنة ليسجدوا للملك رب الجنود وليعيّدوا عيد المظال.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="16">Maka semua orang yang tinggal dari segala bangsa yang telah menyerang Yerusalem, akan datang tahun demi tahun untuk sujud menyembah kepada Raja, TUHAN semesta alam, dan untuk merayakan hari raya Pondok Daun.</language></verse>
			<verse num="17"><language id="English" verse="17"> And it shall be [that] whichever of the families of the earth do not come up to Jerusalem to worship the King, the LORD of hosts, on them there will be no rain. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="17">ويكون ان كل من لا يصعد من قبائل الارض الى اورشليم ليسجد للملك رب الجنود لا يكون عليهم مطر.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="17">Tetapi bila mereka dari kaum-kaum di bumi tidak datang ke Yerusalem untuk sujud menyembah kepada Raja, TUHAN semesta alam, maka kepada mereka tidak akan turun hujan.</language></verse>
			<verse num="18"><language id="English" verse="18"> If the family of Egypt will not come up and enter in, they [shall have] no [rain;] they shall receive the plague with which the LORD strikes the nations who do not come up to keep the Feast of Tabernacles. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="18">وان لا تصعد ولا تات قبيلة مصر ولا مطر عليها تكن عليها الضربة التي يضرب بها الرب الامم الذين لا يصعدون ليعيّدوا عيد المظال.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="18">Dan jika kaum Mesir tidak datang dan tidak masuk menghadap, maka kepada mereka akan turun tulah yang ditimpakan TUHAN kepada bangsa-bangsa yang tidak datang untuk merayakan hari raya Pondok Daun.</language></verse>
			<verse num="19"><language id="English" verse="19"> This shall be the punishment of Egypt and the punishment of all the nations that do not come up to keep the Feast of Tabernacles. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="19">هذا يكون قصاص مصر وقصاص كل الامم الذين لا يصعدون ليعيدوا عيد المظال</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="19">Itulah hukuman dosa Mesir dan hukuman dosa segala bangsa yang tidak datang untuk merayakan hari raya Pondok Daun.</language></verse>
			<verse num="20"><language id="English" verse="20"> In that day "HOLINESS TO THE LORD" shall be [engraved] on the bells of the horses. The pots in the LORD's house shall be like the bowls before the altar. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="20">في ذلك اليوم يكون على اجراس الخيل قدس للرب والقدور في بيت الرب تكون كالمناضح امام المذبح.</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="20">Pada waktu itu akan tertulis pada kerencingan-kerencingan kuda: "Kudus bagi TUHAN!" dan kuali-kuali di rumah TUHAN akan seperti bokor-bokor penyiraman di depan mezbah.</language></verse>
			<verse num="21"><language id="English" verse="21"> Yes, every pot in Jerusalem and Judah shall be holiness to the LORD of hosts. Everyone who sacrifices shall come and take them and cook in them. In that day there shall no longer be a Canaanite in the house of the LORD of hosts. </language><language id="Arabic" verse="21">وكل قدر في اورشليم وفي يهوذا تكون قدسا لرب الجنود وكل الذابحين يأتون ويأخذون منها ويطبخون فيها. وفي ذلك اليوم لا يكون بعد كنعاني في بيت رب الجنود</language><language id="Indonesian" verse="21">Maka segala kuali di Yerusalem dan di Yehuda akan menjadi kudus bagi TUHAN semesta alam; semua orang yang mempersembahkan korban akan datang mengambilnya dan memasak di dalamnya. Dan tidak akan ada lagi pedagang di rumah TUHAN semesta alam pada waktu itu.</language></verse>
		</chapter>
	
		</book>