<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Season id="ApostlesFast ^ WatosDays ^ !EntranceOfTheLordChrist">      <Section expanded="true" antiphonePitch="2">         <Title>            <Language id="English">               Psali Watos for the Apostles' Fast            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ابصالية واطس لصوم آبائنا الرسل            </Language>         </Title>               <Comment>            <Language id="English">               The following psali is said on the Watos days of the Apostles' Fast            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تقال فى صوم آبائنا الرسل            </Language>         </Comment>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               A Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc: Pennou] n~a~l/yinoc: ] n~oum/ini n~nefe~biaik: na[oic n~io] n~a~poctoloc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Our Lord Jesus Christ: our True God: gave a sign to His servants: my lords and fathers the Apostles.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ربنا يسوع المسيح: إلهنا الحقيقي: أعطى علامة لعبيده: وساداتي الآباء الرُّسل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Bo/~yia~ niben etj/k e~bol: ouoh tefjom afmorou m~moc: af] ersisi nwou e~bol: eyrouhiwis qen pikocmoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               All the perfect help: through His strength He bound them with: He gave them authority: to preach in the world.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كل معونةٍ كاملةٍ: بقوته منطَقَهم بها: وأعطاهم سلطاناً: أن يكرزوا في العالم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ge gar n~yof afcwtp m~mwou: afmahou e~bolqen ka] niben: afouorpou afhonhen nwou: je masenwten qen mai niben.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               For He has chosen them: and filled them with all understanding: and He sent and commanded them: saying "Go to all places."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لأنَّه هو اختارهم: وملأهم من كل فهم: وأرسلهم وأمرهم: اذهبوا في كل موضع.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Dauid aftamon qen pefjwm: nefmetmeyreu af] nan: je P% efe~] n~oujom: n~n/ethisennoufi m~Pefran.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               David taught us in his book: He gave us His testimonies: that the Lord gives strength: to those who preach His name.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               علَّمنا داود في كتابه: أعطانا شهاداته: إنَّ الرَّبَّ يُعطي قوةࣾ: للمُبَشّرين بِاسمه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               ~Ere nim qen nicovoc: nierm/neut/c kalwc: nacaji n~netenmakaricmoc: na% n~io] n~a~poctoloc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Who among the wise: truly have explained: speaking of your blessedness: O my lords and fathers the Apostles.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مَن في كل الحكماء: المُفسِّرين حسناً: ينطقون بطوباويتكم: ياساداتي الآباء الرسُّل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ze ontwc afcaji qen oumeym/i: afws nwten n~je ~P[oic efjw m~moc: je n/eterhupomonin nem/i: n~h~r/i qen napiracmoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Truly He spoke in truth: the Lord promised saying: "O you who were patient with Me: in My tribulations.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               نَعم حقاً تكلَّم بالحقَّ: ووعدكم الربُّ قائلاً: أيها الذين صبِرتم معي: في تجاربي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               ?ppe a~nok ]cemni nemwten: n~oudia~y/k/ qen outajro: je tetennahemci n~ywten: n~h~r/i qen tametouro.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               "Behold I firmly establish: a covenant with you: you will sit: in My kingdom."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هأنذا أُقرِّرُ معكم: عهداً ثابتاً: بإنكم تجلسون: في ملكوتي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               ~Yronoc m~m/i eyouab: e~retene~hemci e~h~r/i e~jwou: ouoh e~retene~]hap: n~nirwmi n~te nijwou.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               "True and holy thrones: you will sit upon: and you will judge: the men of all generations."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كراسي مُقدَّسة حقيقية: تجلسون عليها: وتدينون: أجيال الأجيال.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Icjen niman~sai sa niman~hwtp: nem icjen pemhit sa v~r/c: matajro n~n/etcwtp: matacyo n~nia~ceb/c.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               From the East to the West: and from North to the South: confirm the elect: and restore the impious.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مِن المشارق إلى المغارب: ومِن الشمال إلى الجنوب: ثَبِّـــــتوا المُختارين: رُدُّوا المُنافقين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Kurioc pe Maciac: afcwtp n~nefa~poctoloc: e~te Petroc nem And~reac: Iwann/c nem Iakwboc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The Lord is the Messiah: He has chosen His apostles: who are Peter and Andrew: and John and James.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الرب ماسيا: اختار رُسلَهُ: الذين هم بطرس وأندراوس: ويوحنا ويعقوب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Loipon Vilippoc nem Matyeoc: Baryolomeoc nem Ywmac: Iakwboc n~te Alveoc: nem Cimwn pikananeoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               And Philip and Matthew: Bartholomew and Thomas: James the son of Alphaeus: and Simon the Canaanite.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأيضاً فيلبس ومَتَّى: برثولماوس وتوما: ويعقوب ابن حلفى: وسمعان القانوي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Matyiac v/etafswpi: n~t~sebiw~ n~Iouda: nem p~jwk e~bol nem p~cepi: n/etaumosi n~ca Decpota.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Matthias was chosen: instead of Judas: and was counted with the rest: who followed the Master.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               متياس الذي صار: عِـوضاً عن يهوذا: وكامل البقية: الذين تبعوا السَّيد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Nai afcotpou afhonhen nwou: n~je P,#c# Emmanou/l: je masenwten ha nie~cwou: n/etcwrem qen Picra/l.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               These Christ Immanuel: has chosen and ordered: saying "Go to the sheep: the lost ones of Israel."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هؤلاء اختارهم: المسيح عمانوئيل: وأمرهم قائلاً اذهبوا إلى خراف: إسرائيل الضالة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Xelcwlou qen oumetlamp~roc: n~te piwmc eyouab: en onomati tou Yeou Patroc: nem ~Ps/ri nem Pip~neuma eyouab.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Adorn them with the splendor: of the holy Baptism: in the Name of God the Father: the Son and the Holy Spirit.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               زيّنوهم ببهاء: المعمودية المُقدَّسة: بِاسم الله الآب: والإبن والرُّوح القُدُس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ouoh matal[o n~n/etswni: nidemwn hitou e~bol: a~rivaqri n~niiabi: qen oujom ecj/k e~bol.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               And heal the sick: cast out the demons: remedy the ill: with perfect strength.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               اِشفُوا المرضى: أَخرِجوا الشياطين: أبرِئوا الأسقام: بقوةٍ كاملةٍ.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Piersisi eym/n e~bol: qen t~ve nem hijen pikahi: n~te picwnh nem pibwl e~bol: ]nat/if nwten qen oua~mahi.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The eternal authority: in heaven and on earth: to loose and to bind: "I shall give you with power."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               السُّلطان الدائم: في السَّماء وعلى الأرض: الذي للربط والحلِّ: بعزَّةٍ أُعطيه لكم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Rek petenmasj qen outajro: n~nirwmi n~acyen/c: e~taferh~mot nwou n~je ~Pouro: eyrou]hap qen ]k~ricic.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Incline your ears in firmness: to the meek men: which the King has granted: to judge in retribution.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أميلوا سمعكم بثباتٍ: للرجال الضُّعفاءِ: الذين أنْعَمَ لهم الملكُ: أن يدينوا في القضاء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Cwtem je a~ pouq~rwou senaf: e~bol hijen p~ho m~p~kahi t/rf: ouoh noucaji auvoh m~mauatf: qen p~h/t n~te pie~p~t/rf.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Listen for their voices went out: onto the face of the whole world: and their words have reached: into the hearts of everyone.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               اسمعوا أنه قد خرج صوتهم: على وجه الأرض كلها: وكلامهم وحدِهِ بلغ: الى قلب الجميع.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Tote rwn naqici an: tenereuvomin m~mwten: ouoh penlac na,rwf an: tenerhouo~ [ici m~mwten.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Then our mouth will not weary: to praise you: and our tongue will not cease: to magnify you.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               حينئذٍ لايتعب فَمُنا: إذ نمدحكم: ولساننا لا يسكت: إذ نزيدكم رفعةً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Uc netenran nem netenerv~meui~: eum/n qen rwou n~nipictoc: eunohem m~mwou e~bolqen nimeui~: n~te pidia~boloc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Your names and your remembrances: is on the mouths of the faithful: they saved them from: the thoughts of the devil.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ها أن أسماءكم وتذكاراتكم: دائمةً في أفواه المؤمنين: تُنجِّيهم من أفكار: إبليس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               ~Viwt n~te nimetsenh/t: nai nan hiten noueu,/: hiten tekmetrefw~oun~h/t: nahmen e~bolha pivas et,/.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               O Father of compassions: have mercy through their prayers: through Your patience: save us from snares.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يا أبا الرأفات: ارحمنا بصلواتهم: وبطول أناتك: نَجِّنا من الفخ المنصوب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               &lt;w nan e~bol n~nena~nomia~: w~ piatar,/ pisa e~neh: hiten noutwbh nem noup~recbia~: icjen ]nou nem sa e~neh.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Forgive us our iniquities: O Eternal One without beginning: and through their intercessions: both now and forever.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               اغفـر لنا آثامنا: أيها الأزلي الأبدي: بطلباتهم وشفاعتهم: من الآن وإلى الأبَدِ.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               "epi n~te nene~hoou: qen tekjom a~reh e~ron: nahmen e~bolha pipethwou: qen peknah] matajron.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The rest of our days: in Your strength guard us: deliver us from evil: in Your faith confirm us.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               احفظنا بقوَّتك: بقية أيامنا: ونَجِّنا من الشرير: وفي إيمانك ثبِّتنا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               ~W Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc: eybe nekcwtp n~a~poctoloc: a~riv~meui~ m~pie~la,ictoc: ouoh opten hwn nem nekpictoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               O our Lord Jesus Christ: for Your chosen apostles: remember the poor: and count us with Your faithful.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ياربنا يسوع المسيح: من أجل رسلك المختارين: اُذكر الحقير: واحسبنا نحن أيضاً مع مؤمنيك.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>      <Season id="ApostlesFast ^ AdamDays ^ !EntranceOfTheLordChrist">      <Section expanded="true" antiphonePitch="2">         <Title>            <Language id="English">               Psali Adam for the Apostles' Fast            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أبصالية آدام لصوم أبائنا الرسل            </Language>         </Title>               <Comment>            <Language id="English">               The following psali is said on the Adam days of the Apostles' Fast            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تقال فى صوم الرسل            </Language>         </Comment>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Aiws oub/k ~P[oic: m~per,arwk e~roi: swpi n/i n~ourefrwic: ouoh mah~y/k e~roi.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               I cried to You O Lord: do not forget me: be to me a guard: and hear me.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               صرختُ اليكَ يارب: فلا تسكت عنِّــــي: كُنْ لي حارساً: وإصْغ إليَّ.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Bwrp n/i e~bolqen p~[ici: n~tekbo/~yia~: w~li n~naqici: nem naa~nomia~.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Send me Your help: from the highest: lift away my afflictions: and my iniquities.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أَرْسِلْ لي معونتك: من العلاءِ: ارفع أتعابي: وآثامي .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ge gar qen ou]ma]: ]najw n~hanlogoc: eybe na[oic n~io]: n~a~poctoloc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               For with joy: I will declare the words: concerning my lords: and fathers the Apostles.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لأِّني بمسرةٍ: أَنطق بأقـوالٍ: من أجل ساداتي: الآباء الرسل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Dauid peynanef: qen pip#n#a# e~te n~q/tf: je a~ pouq~rwou senaf: hijen p~ikahi t/rf.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               David the Beautiful: in the spirit which was in him: said "Their voices went out: to all the earth."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               داود الحسن: بالروح الذى فيه: قال خرجت أصواتهم: على الأرض كلها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               ~Ete nai ne nicen]: n~te ]oryodoxia~: etau,w m~pinah]: qen ]ekk~lycia~.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               These are the foundations: of the Orthodoxy: who established the faith: in the Church.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هؤلاءِ هم أُسس: الأرثوذكسية: الذين وضعوا الإيمان: في الكنيسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ze ontwc eybe vai: n~ywou pe e~tau[imwit nan: e~qoun e~pioujai: nai gar ne nouran.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Therefore truly: they are our guides: unto salvation: and these are their names.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               من أجل هذا: حقاً نَعَمْ هم الذين: أرشدونا إلى الخلاص: وهذه هيَ أسماؤُهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               ?ppe Petroc nem And~reac: Iwann/c nem Iakwboc: Vilippoc nem Matyeoc: nem Baryolomeoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Behold Peter and Andrew: John and James: Philip and Matthew: and Bartholomew.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بطرس وأندراوس: يوحنا ويعقوب: فيلبس ومَتَّى: وبرثولماوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ywmac nem Iakwboc: nem Cimwn piref,oh: nem Yaddeoc picovoc: qen Matyiac aumoh.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Thomas and James: and Simon the Zealot: and the wise Thaddeus: and with Matthias they were completed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               توما ويعقوب: وسمعان الغيور: وتدّاوس الحكيم: وبمتياس قد كملوا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Pim/t c~nau e~te m~mau: n~w~ni m~margarit/c: nem pikes~be c~nau: n~cwtp m~may/t/c.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Behold these twelve: are precious pearls: and the other seventy two: chosen disciples.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أولئك الاثـنا عشر: الأحجار الجوهرية: والاثنان والسبعون: تلميذاً المختارين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Kata ,wra niben: nem polic nem ]mi: aumosi n~c/ou niben: aui~ri n~hanm/ini.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               To every land: city and village: they went and continually: performed miracles.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               في كل كورةٍ: ومدينةٍ وقريةٍ: ساروا في كل حينٍ: وصنعوا آياتٍ.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Loipon qen oumeym/i: autacyo n~]oikoumen/: e~p~couen ]meym/i: eybe p~a~sai n~nis~v/ri.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               And also truly: they restored the world: to the knowledge of the Truth: because of the many wonders.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأيضاً بالحقيقة: ردُّوا المسكونة: إلى معرفة الحق: من أجل كثرة العجائب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Mwu~c/c gar afi~ni: e~bolqen oupetra n~w~ni: m~m/t c~nau m~p/g/: euqa] e~bol eubebi.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               For Moses has brought: out from a rock: twelve fountains: flowing and gushing.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لأنَّ موسى أخرج: من صخرة حجرية: اثـنتي عشرة عيناً: تنبع وتفيض.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Nafsop qen Ailim: n~je m/t c~nau m~p/g/: nem hanm/s n~cim: nem s~be m~beni.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               There was in Elim: twelve fountains: and many herbs: and seventy palm trees.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لأنه كان في إيليـم: اثـنتا عشرة عيناً: وأعشابٍ كثيرة: وسبعون نخلةً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Xulon n~]bw n~jwit: peje pip~rov/t/c: afviri e~bol afrwt: m~m/t c~nau n~k~ladoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The prophet has said: "An olive tree: has blossomed and budded: into twelve branches.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               قال النبي: إن شجرة الزيتون: أيْنَعَتْ وأنـبتـت: اثـنى عشر غصناً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Oum/i a~l/ywc: ne naiparabol/: e~jen nia~poctoloc: etau,w n~nientol/.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Truly indeed: these are parables: of the apostles: who passed on the commandments.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               حقاً بالحقيقة: إن هذه الأمثال: على الرُّسل: الذين وضعوا الوصايا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Paim/t c~nau afcotpou: n~je Pencwt/r: ouoh afouorpou: m~v~r/] n~hanvwct/r.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               These twelve were chosen: by our Savior: and He sent them everywhere: like the stars.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هؤلاء الاثـنا عشر: أختارهم مُخَلِّصنا: وأرسلهم: مثل كواكب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ran n~nivul/: aui~ri m~m/t c~nau: nem m/t c~nau m~pul/: n~te y~baki e~te m~mau.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The names of: the twelve tribes: and the twelve gates: of that city.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أسماء الأسباط: اثـنا عشر: واثـنا عشر باباً: لتلك المدينة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Comc n~ywten ]nou: je qen pie~hoou: m/t c~nau n~ounou: saucini kata e~hoou.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Look and learn now: that in a day: there are twelve hours: pass by every day.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أنظروا أنتم الآن: أن في اليوم: اثـنتي عشرة ساعةٍ: تَمُــــــــرُّ كل يومٍ.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Tote nia~bot on: m/t c~nau qen ]rompi: ouoh nenzwte on: m/t c~nau qen tou/~pi.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               And also the months: twelve in a year: and also our daily works: twelve in their count.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأيضاً اثـنى عشر: شهراً في السنة: وأمور حياتنا: اثـنا عشر في عددها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               ~Uppe naitupoc: ceercummenin nan: e~jen nia~poctoloc: e~tauhisennoufi nan.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Behold all these symbols: direct us to: the Apostles: who preached to us.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هوذا هذه الأمثلة: تدلنا: على الرُّسل: الذين بشَّرونا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               ~Vnou] pimam~vwt: hiten noueu,/: n/etauenkot: mam~ton n~nou'u,/.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               O God of Refuge: through their prayers: repose all the souls: of those who have slept.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يا الله الملجأ: بصلواتهم: نَيِّح: نفوس الراقدين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               &lt;w nan e~bol n~nennobi: nem nena~nomia~: qen tekmetmairwmi: hiten noup~recbia~.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Forgive us our sins: and our iniquities: through Your love for man: and through their intercessions.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بشفاعاتهم: اغفر لنا خطايانا: وآثامنا: بمحبتك للبشر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               "epi m~peklaoc: a~reh e~rwou ~P[oic: n/e~te nouk n~c~keuoc: w~ Pinou] n~refrwic.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The rest of Your people: guard them O Lord: those which are Your vessels: O God the Guardian.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بقية شعبك: احفظهم يارب: الآنية التي لك: أيها الإله الحارس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               ~W v/etafswpi: nem nefa~poctoloc: ,w nan e~bol n~nennobi: a~non qa peklaoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               O who was: with His apostles: forgive us our sins: we Your people.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يا مَن كان: مع رُسله: اغفر لنا خطايانا: نحن شعبك.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season></Document>