<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Anioui m~Po#c#: n~ouw~ou nem outaio: a~nioui~ m~Po#c#: n~hanhumnoc m~pi[ro.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         Present to the Lord, glory and honor, present to the Lord, praises of victory.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         قدموا للرب مجداً وكرامة قدموا للرب تسابيح الغلبة.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Bwrp naf e~p~swi m~m/ni: n~hanhi/b n~at,arof: nem hanjw m~beri: nem hanyucia n~atc~nof.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         Send up unto Him, always silent lambs, and new songs, and blood offerings.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         أرسلوا له ألي فوق دائما حملانا غير ساكتة واناشيد جديدة وذبائح غير دموية.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Ge gar afyamion: ouoh a~non an pe: aftoubon aft~cabon: n~nimwit n~te t~ve.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         For He created us, when we were nothing, He purified and taught us, the ways of heaven.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         لأنه خلقنا واذ نحن لم نكن وطهرنا وعلمنا طرق السماء.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Dauid n~c/ou niben: efjoc qen oumeym/i: w~ouniatou n~ouon niben: etsop qen pek/i.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         David says in truth, at all times, blessed are those who dwell, in Your house.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         يقول داود في كل حين بالحقيقة طوبي لجميع الساكنين في بيتك.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Eie~i~ e~qoun: sa piman~erswousi: n~te Vnou] qen oumoun: eie~swt hanswouswousi.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         I will enter, unto the altar of God, at all times, and offer oblations.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         ادخل إلي مذبح الله دائماً واذبح الذبائح.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Ze ontwc qen ous~v/ri: a~ P,#c# pimairwmi: swp e~rof m~picebi: m~v~r/] n~nirwmi.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         For truly it is wondrous, that Christ the Lover of Man, accepted circumcision, like men.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         فعجباً بالحقيقة أن المسيح محب البشر قبل الختان مثل البشر.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         ?ppe gar Loukac: afcaji qen vai: eybe maciac: ouoh afc~qai.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         For behold Luke, spoke of that, for the Messiah, and wrote and said.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         لأن لوقا تكلم بهذا من أجل ماسيا وكتب.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Yebdwmac e~tack/n: aumou] e~rof: je I/#c# pe pefran: kata p~caji m~piaggeloc.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         When the week was finished, His name was called, Jesus according, to the saying of the angel.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         ولما كمل الاسبوع دُعي اسمه يسوع كقول الملاك.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Iwc/f nem Calwm/: nem Maria tefmau: e~taujwk m~pih~me: n~e~hoou e~te m~mau.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         Joseph and Salome, and Mary His mother, when they finished, the forty days.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         يوسف وسالومي ومريم امه لما اكملوا تلك الاربعين يوماً.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Ke palin ausenwou: e~p~/i n~]p~roceu,/: eyroui~ni e~jwou: n~hancwtp n~eu,/.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         And also they went, to the house of prayers, to offer for themselves, the choice offerings.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         وأيضاً ذهبوا إلي بيت الصلاة ليقدموا عنهما تقدمات مختارة.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Loipon gar aujimi: n~Cimwn piou/b: efo~hi e~ratf efsemsi: qen tefmetou/b.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         They also have found, Simeon the priest, standing and serving, through his priesthood.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         وأيضاً وجدوا سمعان الكاهن واقفاً يخدم في كهنوته.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Mpefera~mel/c: alla af] m~pefouoi: afolf qen oui/c: e~jen nefj~voi.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         So he did not hesitate, but took the risk, and carried Him quickly, on his arms.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         فلم يتهاون. بل بادر. وحمله بسرعة علي ذراعيه.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Nafjoc je Pa[oic: ]nou ,~na,a pekbwk: je n~yok pe e~takrwic: e~roi eyrinau e~rok.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         And he said now O Lord, let your servant go, for You have kept me, to see You.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         وكان يقول الآن ياسيدي اطلق عبدك لأنك حفظتني لكي أراك.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Xapina aci~: n~je Anna ]p~rov/t/c: ]cemne n~c~himi: acero~mologit/c.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         And suddenly, Anna the prophetess, the meek woman, came and confessed.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         وبغتة جاءت حنة النبية المرأة العفيفة واعترفت.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Ouoh naccaji eyb/tf: qaten ouon niben: ouoh pilaoc t/rf: naujoust e~rof n~c/ou niben.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         And she spoke about Him, in front of everyone, for all the people, waited for Him at all times.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         وكانت تتكلم من أجله أمام الجميع واذ كان كل انسان ينتظره كل حين.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Penn/b pimairwmi: Penouro P,#c#: afswp e~rof m~picebi: eyrefjwk m~pinomoc.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         Our Master the Lover of Man, Christ our King, accepted to Himself the circumcision, to complete the Law.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         سيدنا محب البشر ملكنا المسيح قبل الختان ليكمل الناموس.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Rasi ouoh yel/l: w~ p~genoc n~nirwmi: je Emmanou/l: afw~li n~nennobi.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         Rejoice and be glad, O you sons of men, for Immanuel, has carried our sins.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         افرحوا وتهللوا ياجنس البشر لان عمانوئيل حمل خطايانا.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Ce ontwc aftajro: m~pefjinerrwmi: afjwk m~penyebio: n~h~r/i qen pefcebi.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         Yes in truth, He confirmed His Incarnation, and fulfilled our humbleness, by His circumcision.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         نعم بالحقيقة ثبت تأنسه واكمل تواضعنا بختانه.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Tote aft~cabon: e~hanmwit n~te pioujai: ouoh afcw] m~mon: kata pefnis] n~nai.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         Therefore He taught us, the ways of salvation, and He has saved us, according to His great mercy.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         حينئذ علمنا طرق الخلاص وخلصنا كعظيم رحمته.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Uioc Yeoc n~yof: qen oua~l/yia: acmici m~mof: n~je y/eyouab Maria.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         He is the Son of God, in truth and she, gave birth to Him, Saint Mary the Virgin.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         هو ابن الله بالحقيقة قد ولدته القديسة مريم.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         V/e~toufai m~mof: n~je nitaxic eth/p: afw~li m~mof: n~je Cimwn piou/b.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         He who is carried, by the invisible hosts, was carried by, Simeon the priest.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         الذي تحمله الرتب الخفية قد حمله سمعان الكاهن.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         &lt;ouab w~ P,#c#: qen tekoikonomia: ouats~]si e~roc: te tekjwm nem tekcovia.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         Holy are You O Christ, in Your precepts, and unlimited is, Your power and wisdom.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         قدوس أيها المسيح في تدبيرك وغير محدودة هي قوتك وحكمتك.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         "epi m~peklaoc: matal[o n~nouswni: nem n/e~tauenkot Po#c#: a~ripoumeui~.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         And the rest of Your people, heal their sicknesses, and those who departed, O Lord remember them.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         وسائر شعبك اشف أمراضهم والذين رقدوا يارب اذكرهم.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="Coptic">         Wcautoc pekbwk: a~nok qa pirefernobi: ]]ho e~rok: ,w n/i e~bol n~nanobi.      </Language>      <Language id="English">         Likewise I Your servant, the sinner, I entreat You, to forgive me my sins.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         كذلك انا عبدك الخاظئ أتوسل اليك أن تغفر لي خطاياي.      </Language>   </Text></Document>