<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Season id="Meshir.1">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The First Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الأول من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the first day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الأول من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Second Universal Council in the city of Constantinople</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار اجتماع المجمع المسكونى الثانى بمدينة القسطنطينية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 97 of the martyrs (381 A.D.) one hundred and fifty fathers assembled in the second universal council upon the order of Emperor Theodosius the Great, in the City of Constantinople. Pope Timothy I (22nd Patriarch) along with some bishops attended the council on behalf of the church of Alexandria. This council assembled to judge Macdonius, Patriarch of Constantinople, Sabilius and Apolinarius for their blasphemy against God the Word and the Holy Spirit.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 97 للشهداء ( 381 م ) إجتمع بمدينة القسطنطينية المجمع المسكونى الثانى حضره مائة وخمسون أسقفاً بأمر الملك ثيؤدوسيوس الكبير وحضره عن كنيسة الإسكندرية البابا تيموثاس الأول البطريرك (٢٢) ومعه بعض الأساقفة. وقد عقد هذا المجمع لمحاكمة مقدونيوس بطريرك القسطنطينية وأوسابيوس ومكدونيوس وأبوليناريوس المجدفين على الله الكلمة والروح القدس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When these heresies became widespread, the fathers of the church were concerned about the soundness of the faith of the church, and informed Emperor Theodosius about them. He ordered the assembly of this council. When the council convened Abba Timothy asked Macdonius; "What is your believe." He replied; “The Holy Spirit was created like any other creature.” Abba Timothy debated his opinion and made it clear to him its corruption and advised him to renounce his erroneous belief. When he refused, the council excommunicated and divested him of his rank.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وذلك أنه لما شاعت هذه البدع خشى الآباء على سلامة إيمان الكنيسة وأعلموا الملك بها فأمر بعقد هذا المجمع. ولما تم انعقاد المجمع سأل البابا تيموثاوس مكدونيوس عن إعتقاده فأجاب "أن الروح القدس مخلوق كسائر المخلوقات " فناقشه فى هذا الرأى وأظهر له فساد رأيه ونصحه أن يرجع عنه فلم يسمع فحرمه المجمع وأنزله عن رتبته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Then Pope Timothy asked Sabilius about his believe and he replied saying; "The Trinity has one being and one person." Abba Timothy said, "If the Trinity is one being and one person as you claimed, then the mentioning of the Trinity is groundless, and your baptism is futile, because it is in the Name of the Father, and the Son and the Holy Spirit. Then Abba Timothy advised him to renounce his erroneous belief. When he did not hearken the council excommunicated, and divested him of his rank.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم سأل أيضاً البابا تيموثاؤس أوسابيوس عن معتقده فأجابه قائلاً: " أن للثالوث ذاتاً واحدةً وأقنوماً واحداً فقال له البابا تيموثاؤس السكندرى : "إذا كان للثالوث كما زعمت ذاتاً واحدةً وأقنوماً واحداً فقد بطل ذكر الثالوث وتكون أيضاً معموديتك باطلة لأنها باسم الآب والابن والروح القدس "ثم نصحه أن يرجع عن خطئه فلم يسمع فحرمه المجمع وأنزله عن رتبته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Then Abba Timothy asked Apolinarius, "And you, what is your statement of faith?" Apolinarius replied saying; "The Incarnation of the Son was by uniting with the human flesh without the rational being, for His divinity replaced the soul and the mind of the human being." Abba Timothy replied saying, "God the Word united with our nature to save us, therefore if He only united with the animal body, then He did not save mankind but the animals. Humans will rise on the resurrection day with the rational soul with which there will be the judgment, and accordingly they will be granted the blessing or the condemnation. Therefore, the Incarnation would be futile. If that was the case, why did He call Himself the Son of Man if He did not unite with the rational speaking soul?" Pope Timothy advised him repeatedly to renounce his erroneous belief, but he did not hearken. The council excommunicated him as his other two friends.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم سأل أيضاً البابا تيموتاوس السكندرى أبوليناريوس وأنت ما هو اعتقادك. فأجابه بقوله: "إن تجسد الابن كان باتحاده مع الجسد البشرى وبدون النفس الناطقة لأن لاهوته قام مقام النفس والعقل"، فرد عليه الأنبا تيموتاوس قائلاً: "إن الله الكلمة إنما اتحد بطبيعتنا لكى يخلصنا ، فإن كان اتحاده بالجسد الحيوانى فقط فهو إذن لم يخلص البشر بل الحيوانات لأن البشر يقومون فى يوم القيامة العامة بالنفس العاقلة وبها تتم الدينونة وبها ينالون النعيم أو العذاب وعلى ذلك تكون قد بطلت منفعة التجسد ، وإذا كان هكذا فكيف يقول هو عن نفسه أنه ابن الإنسان إذا كان لم يتحد بالنفس الناطقة العاقلة". ثم نصحه كثيراً ليرجع عن بدعته فلم يسمع فحرمه المجمع.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Finally, the council excommunicated the three Macdonius, Sabilius and Apolinarius and all those who agreed with them. Then they completed the creed of faith from, "Yes we believe in the Holy Spirit, the Lord, giver of Life... to the end." They also put down many canons needed for the church then went back to their Sees in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بدعته فلم يسمع فحرمه المجمع. أخيراً قرر المجمع حرمان هؤلاء الثلاثة مكدونيوس وأوسابيوس وأبوليناريوس وكل من يقول بقولهم ثم أكملوا قانون الإيمان من أول  " نعم نؤمن بالروح القدس....إلخ " ثم وضعوا القوانين اللازمة للكنيسة. بعد ذلك رجعوا إلى كراسيهم بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of these holy fathers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات هؤلاء الآباء القديسين فلتكن معنا. آمين            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Abadion Bishop of Ansena</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس أباديون أسقف أنصنا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also of the year 20 of the martyrs (304 A.D.) was the martyrdom of St. Abadion, bishop of Ansena. He was ordained by Pope Peter the seal of martyrs, bishop for Ansena and he shepherd his flock with all sincerity.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 20 للشهداء ( 304 م ) استشهد القديس الأنبا أباديون أسقف أنصنا (هى قرية الشيخ عبادة حالياً بمركز ملوى وسُميت الشيخ عبادة نسبة للأنبا أباديون).  كان قد رسمه البابا بطرس خاتم الشهداء أسقفاً على أنصنا فرعى شعبه بكل أمانة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Diocletian incited the persecution against the Christians, Arianus the governor of Ansena was extremely violent in his persecution and was very versatile in the different ways of tormenting them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أعلن دقلديانوس الاضطهاد على المسيحيين ، وكان أريانوس والى أنصنا، عنيفاً جداً فى اضطهاده ويتفنن كثيراً فى تعذيبهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He seized the St. Abadion and took him along with him in his journey to Assiut and Akhmeem to personally witness the torment of believers that he might weaken and deny the faith but he remained steadfast in his faith. The Governor ordered to bind the Saint and he took him along. The Saint went with him rejoicing as if someone going to a feast. He ordered to crucify him, two pigeon appeared above the cross and the nails were loosened and the Saint went down safely. Finally the governor ordered to behead him and he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ألقى القبض على القديس أباديون وأخذه معه رحلته إلى أسيوط وأخميم ليشاهد عذابات المؤمنين بنفسه فيضعف وينكر الإيمان، لكنه ظل ثابتاً على ايمانه فأمر الوالى بتقييده وأخذه معه فرحاً متهللاً كمن فى وليمة فأمر بصلبه فظهرت حمامتان على الصليب وانحلت المسامير ونزل الأسقف سالماً. أخيراً أمر الوالى بقطع رأسه فنال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Consecration of the Church of St. Peter, the Seal of Martyrs in the City of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تكريس كنيسة القديس بطرس خاتم الشهداء بمدينة الإسكندرية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the consecration of the Church of St. Peter the seal of martyrs. The believers built this church west of Alexandria during the reign of Emperor Constantine the great. The church existed till shortly after the Arab conquest of Egypt.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تم تكريس كنيسة القديس بطرس خاتم الشهداء التى بناها المؤمنون بغرب الإسكندرية فى عهد الملك قسطنطين الكبير. وظلت هذه الكنيسة قائمة إلى زمان دخول العرب مصر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of this Saint be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات هذا القديس فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.2">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Second Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثانى من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the second day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثانى من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Great Saint Anba Paul, the First Hermit</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس العظيم الأنبا بولا أول السواح</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 57 of the martyrs (341 A.D.) the great saint Anba Paul, the first hermit, departed. He was born in the city of Thebes and had a brother whose name was Peter.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               في مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 57 للشهداء( 341 م ) ، تنيح القديس العظيم الأنبا بولا أول السواح. ولد بمدينة طيبة وكان له أخ اسمه بطرس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When their father departed, they divided the inheritance between them, and Peter took the greater share for Paul was still young in age.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما توفى والدهما ، شرعا في قسمة الميراث بينهما ، فأخذ بطرس النصيب الأكبر لأن بولا كان صبياً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When they did not agree with each other, they went to the governor to judge between them. On their way, they saw a funeral procession and he was told that the deceased was one of the wealthy people of the city.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وإذ لم يتفقا مضيا إلى الحاكم ليفصل بينهما. وفى الطريق وجدا جنازة ميت وعرف بولا أنها لأحد أغنياء المدينة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Paul sighed and said, "What do I have to do then with all the money of this vain world which I shall leave naked?" He said to his brother, “let us return, for I am not asking you for anything."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فتنهد القديس وقال " مالى إذن ومال هذا العالم الفانى الذى سأتركه وأنا عريان " ، ثم قال لأخيه " ارجع بنا يا أخى فلست مطالباً لك بشىء".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On their way back Paul left his brother and went on his way outside of the city. Paul found a grave where he stayed for three days praying to God to guide him to what pleases Him. His brother searched for him and when he did not find him, he was exceedingly sorry for what he had done.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى الطريق العودة غافل القديس بولا أخاه وخرج إلى خارج المدينة. فوجد قبراً أقام به ثلاثة أيام ، وهو يصلى طالباً من الله أن يرشده لعمل ما يرضيه. أما أخوه فإنه بحث عنه كثيراً ولما يجده حزن وتأسف عما فرط منه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Lord sent to St. Paul an angel who walked with him to the eastern inner wilderness. He dwelt there for seventy years, during which he did not see the face of a man. He had on a tunic made of palm tree fiber. The Lord sent him a raven every day with a half loaf of bread.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أرسل الرب ملاكاً للقديس بولا ، وسار معه إلى البرية الشرقية الداخلية ، وهناك أقام سبعين سنة لم يعاين فيها وجه إنسان. وكان يلبس ثوباً من الليف ، والرب يرسل له غراباً بنصف خبزة فى كل يوم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Lord willed to reveal his holiness and godliness, He sent an angel to St. Antony (Antonius) the great and told him, "There is a man in the inner wilderness, the world is not worthy of his footsteps. By his prayers, the Lord descends rain and dew to fall on the earth, and brings the flood water of the Nile in due time."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أراد الرب إظهار بره وقداسته ، أرسل ملاكاً للقديس العظيم الأنبا أنطونيوس وقال له: "يوجد فى البرية الداخلية إنسان لا يستحق العالم وطأة قدميه ، وبصلواته يُنزل  الرب المطر والندى على الأرض ويأتى بالنيل فى حينه".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When St. Antony heard this, he rose right away and walked a distance of one day and God guided him to the cave of St. Paul. He entered, and bowed down to each other. They sat down talking about the greatness of God. In the evening, the raven came bringing a whole loaf of bread. St. Paul said to St. Antony, "Now, I know that you are one of the servants of God. For seventy years, the Lord sent me everyday a half loaf of bread, but today, the Lord is sending your food also. Now, go and bring me back in a hurry the vestment that Emperor Constantine had given to Pope Athanasius."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فقام القديس أنطونيوس لوقته وسار مسافة يوم ، حتى أرشده الرب إلى مغارة القديس الأنبا بولا ، فدخل إليه وسجد كل منهما للآخر ، وجلسا يتحدثان بعظائم الله.  ولما صار المساء أتى الغراب ومعه خبزة كاملة. فقال القديس بولا للقديس أنطونيوس  "الآن علمت أنك من عبيد الله ، إن لى إلى اليوم سبعين سنة والرب يرسل  لى نصف خبزة كل يوم. أما اليوم فقد أرسل الرب لك طعامك. والآن أسرع وأحضر لى الحلة التى أعطاها الملك قسطنطين للبطريرك أثناسيوس".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Antony went to St. Athanasius, and brought the vestment and returned to St. Paul. On his way back, he saw the soul of St. Paul carried by the angels up to heaven. When he arrived to the cave, he found that St. Paul had departed. He clothed him in the vestment and took his fiber tunic.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فمضى القديس أنطونيوس وأحضر الحلة وعاد بها إلى القديس ، وفيما هو فى الطريق رأى نفس القديس بولا والملائكة يصعدون بها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he wanted to bury him, he wondered how to dig the grave. Two lions appeared to him and were shaking their heads. He knew that they were sent from God. He pointed to them the place of the grave and they dug the grave with their claws. He then buried the body, and went back to the Pope, told him what had happened and gave him the fiber tunic. St. Athanasius sent men to bring St. Paul's body to him but they could not find his grave.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم تحير كيف يحفر القبر وإذا بأسدين يشيران برأسيهما فعلم أنهما مرسلان من الله ، فحدد لهما مكان القبر فحفراه ، ثم وارى الجسد ، وعاد إلى البابا وأعلمه بذلك وسلمه ثوب الليف فأرسل البابا رجالاً ليحملوا الجسد لكنهم لم يتعرفوا على مكانه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Athanasius used to put on the palm fiber tunic on three times a year during the Divine Liturgy of the Lord's major feasts.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أما الثوب الليف فكان يلبسه البابا ثلاث مرات فى السنة أثناء التقديس فى الأعياد السيدية الكبرى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of the saint Anba Paul be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات القديس الأنبا بولا فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Longinus, Abbot of El-Zugag Monastery</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس لنجينوس رئيس دير الزجاج</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, the Holy Father Anba Longinus, the abbot of El-Zugag monastery, departed. He was born in Cilicia (in Asia Minor). When his mother departed he became a monk along with his father Lucianus in one of the monasteries.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تنيح القديس الأنبا لنجينوس رئيس دير الزجاج. وُلد فى كيليكية ، ولما توفيت  والدته ، ترهب فى أحد الأديرة هو ووالده لوقيانوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of the abbot of the monastery, the monks wanted St. Lucianus to become their abbot, but he did not accept. He fled from the monastery with his son Longinus and went to Syria. They dwelt there in a church and God revealed their virtues by performing many miracles on their hands. For their fear of the glory of men Longinus took the permission of his father to go to Egypt.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد نياحة رئيس الدير ، أراد الرهبان إقامة لوقيانوس رئيساً عليهم، فلم يقبل وهرب من الدير هو ابنه وأتيا إلى الشام، وأقام فى إحدى الكنائس. وقد أظهر الله فضائلهما بإجراء عدة معجزات على أيديهما ، فخافا مجد الناس، واستأذن لنجينوس أباه فى الذهاب إلى مصر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He went to the monastery of El-Zugag to the west of Alexandria. He pursued a life of godliness, piety and asceticism. After the departure of the abbot, the monks made him abbot against his will. Shortly after, his father Lucianus came, and they worked in making the canvas sails of boats, and sold them to support themselves. God performed many miracles on their hands.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقصد دير الزجاج غربى الإسكندرية. فسار فى الفضيلة والتقوى والنسك. فأقامه الرهبان رئيساً على الدير رغماً عنه. بعد قليل أتى أبوه لوقيانوس ، وكانا يعملان فى صناعة قلاع المراكب ويأكلان من عملهما.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Father Lucianus departed in peace, and shortly after, his son Longinus departed also on this day.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم تنيح الأب لوقيانوس بسلام ولحقه إبنه بعد قليل فى مثل هذا اليوم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of these two saints be with us all, and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهما فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.3">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Third Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the third day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. James, the Monk</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس يعقوب الراهب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. James, the ascetic monk, departed. This father denounced the world since his young age. He dwelt in a cave for fifteen years, during which he exerted himself with long fasting and frequent prayers and he never left the cave all that time.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تنيح القديس يعقوب الراهب. كان هذا الأب زاهداً فى العالم منذ حداثته. فسكن فى مغارة خمس عشرة سنة. وقد أجهد نفسه بالصوم والصلاة ولم يخرج من المغارة قط.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The devil was envious of him so he enticed a wicked woman who decorated herself and went to him. She tried to seduce him to commit sin with her. But he preached to her, and reminded her of the torment of the fire of hell, judgment and the eternal punishments. She repented and went back to the city thanking God Who granted her to return from the way of eternal death to the way of eternal life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فحسده الشيطان ، وأوعز إلى امرأة شريرة ، تزينت وذهبت إلية وأغرته أن يسقط فى الخطية معها. فوعظها القديس وذكرها بعذاب نار جهنم والدينونة والعقاب. فتابت على يديه وعادت إلى المدينة وهى تشكر الله الذى أنعم عليها بالرجوع من طريق الموت إلى طريق الحياة الأبدية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               God performed many miracles by his hands. When the Lord willed to relieve him from the toil of this futile world he fell ill for a short time then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أراد الرب أن يريحه من أتعاب هذا العالم الزائل ، مرض قليلاً ، ثم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Hedra, of the Rock of Banhadab</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس هدرا بحاجر بنهدب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also St. Hedra, of the Rock of Banhadab, departed. He was the first monk to settle on the rock of Banhadab for his love of the solitary life rejecting the waves of this vain world.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تنيح القديس هدرا وهو أول من ترهب بحاجر بنهدب ( فى جبل الأساس القريب من مدينة نقادة محافظة قنا ).لكثرة محبته للوحدة وليطرح عنه أمواج هذا هذا العالم الزائل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his days, there was an ascetic man who was known for his spiritual deeds and virtues whose name was Juda. This Juda because of his simplicity had disbelieved in the resurrection of the bodies. God the lover of mankind did not will for this hermit to perish so He guided him to go to St. Hedra. He told the Saint of his disbelieve. He was converted from his error by St. Hedra who exhorted and explained to him this doctrine. He told him that the Lord Jesus Christ was the first fruits of those who have fallen asleep. St. Juda believed and thanked St. Hedra for he had enlightened him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان فى زمانه رجل ناسك مشهور بالأعمال والفضائل الروحانية اسمه يهوذا ، ولعظم سذاجته لم يكن يؤمن بقيامة الأجساد. وأن الله محب البشر لم يشأ هلاك هذا الناسك ، فأرشده أن يمضى إلى القديس هدرا، وأعلم القديس هدرا بأمره. فوعظه وشرح له هذه العقيدة وأن يسوع المسيح هو باكورة الراقدين ، فآمن القديس يهوذا وشكره لأنه أنار بصيرته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Hedra became well known for his godliness and piety and the Lord wrought many miracles by his hands. Many came to him to receive his blessing and prayers. This father endured the life of the wilderness and asceticism. He became ill for a short time then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               اشتهر القديس هدرا بالفضيلة والتقوى وقد أجرى الرب على يديه معجزات كثيرة وكان الكثيرون يأتون إليه لينالوا بركته وصلواته. وقد صبر هذا الأب على حياة البرية والتقشف ، فمرض قليلاً ثم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.4">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fourth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fourth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Agabus, One of the Seventy Disciples</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس أغابوس أحد السبعين رسولاً</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Agabus, one of the seventy disciples, was martyred. They were chosen by the Lord to go before Him to preach the word of life. St. Agabus was with the twelve disciples in the upper room of Zion on the day of Pentecost.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم استشهاد القديس أغابوس أحد السبعين رسولاً الذين اختارهم الرب ليكرزوا بكلمة الحياة ( لو 10 : 1 ). كان مع الاثنى عشر رسولاً فى علية صهيون عندما حل عليهم الروح القدس ( أع 2 : 1 – 12).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               God granted him the gift of prophecy, as the Acts of the Apostles tells us, "And as we stayed many days, a certain prophet named Agabus came down from Judea. When he had come to us, he took Paul's belt, bound his own hands and feet, and said, 'Thus says the Holy Spirit, so shall the Jews at Jerusalem bind the man who owns this belt, and delivers him into the hands of the Gentiles."' (Acts 21: 10-11)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ومنحه الله نعمة النبوة فهو الذى تنبأ عن المجاعة التى حدثت بعد ذلك فى أيام كلوديوس قيصر ( أع 11 : 28 ). كما تنبأ عن بولس الرسول أن اليهود سيقيدونه متى وصل إلى أورشليم ويسلمونه إلى أيدى الأمم ( أع 21 : 10 – 11 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He also prophesied about a famine which was fulfilled during the time of Claudius Caesar.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This apostle preached the gospel to many countries converting many of the Jews and the Greeks to the faith of the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كرز هذا الرسول ببشارة الإنجيل فى بلاد كثيرة ورد كثيرين من اليهود واليونانيين إلى الإيمان بالسيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Finally the Jews of Jerusalem seized, and scourged him severely then tied a rope around his neck and dragged him outside the city where they stoned him until he delivered up his pure spirit in the hand of the Lord whom he loved. Thus he received the crown of martyrdom. A light came down from heaven to his body. When a Jewish woman saw that light she cried saying, "Truly this man was righteous." Then she shouted in a loud voice saying, "I am a Christian." They stoned her also; she departed in peace and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أخيراً قبض عليه اليهود فى أورشليم وضربوه كثيراً ثم وضعوا فى عنقه حبلاً وجروه إلى خارج المدينة حيث رجموه بالحجارة إلى أن استودع روحه الطاهرة فى يدى الرب الذى أحبه ونال إكليل الشهادة ، حينئذ ظهر نور رآه الناس متصلاً بالسماء وبجسده. ولما رأت امرأة يهودية ذلك صاحت بأعلى صوتها " إن هذا الرجل بار " وقالت " أنا مسيحية " فرجموها هى أيضاً وانتقلت بسلام ونالت إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of this apostle be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات القديس أغابوس الرسول فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.5">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fifth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fifth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Relocation of the Relics of the Forty-Nine Elders of the Wilderness of Shiheet</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار نقل أعضاء التسعة والأربعين شهيداً شيوخ برية شيهيت</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, the church celebrates the commemoration of the relocation of the relics of the forty-nine martyrs of the wilderness of Shiheet to their church in the monastery of St. Macarius.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى هذا اليوم تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار نقل أعضاء التسعة والأربعين شهيداً شيوخ برية  شيهيت.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Benjamin I, 38th Patriarch, repeated their shrouding, embalming, and re-burying them in the middle of the church. He also established this day a feast for relocating their bodies.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وذلك عندما أعاد البابا بنيامين الأول البطريرك الثامن والثلاثون تكفينهم وتحنيطهم ودفنهم فى وسط الكنيسة وثبت هذا اليوم عيداً لنقل أجسادهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The pure relics of these Saints remained in this church until it fell apart. The monks kept their bodies in one of the cells till the time when el-Moalem Ibrahim El-Gohary built for them a church in the year 1732 A.D. Their bodies still exist till present time in this church in the monastery of St. Macarius the great. The church is called the church of the elders.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد ظلت هذه الرفات الطاهرة فى هذه البيعة حتى تصدعت ، فاحتفظ الرهبان  بالأجساد فى إحدى القلالى ، إلى أن بنى لهم المعلم إبراهيم الجوهرى كنيسة خاصة بهم فى سنة 1732م.  ولازالت أجسادهم بها إلى هذا اليوم. وهى بدير القديس مكاريوس الكبير وتسمى (كنيسة الشيوخ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Agrippinus, 10th Pope of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا أغريبينوس البطريك العاشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 178 A.D., Pope Agrippinus, the 10th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This Holy Father was born in Alexandria. He was pure, saintly and feared God. He was ordained a priest for the church of Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 178 م تنيح البابا أغريبينوس البطريرك العاشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا القديس بالإسكندرية ، وكان قديساً طاهراً خائفاً من الله ، فرسموه قساً على كنيسة الإسكندرية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the blessed father Pope Celadion, the 9th Patriarch, departed, he was chosen patriarch. By the grace of God, he took over the apostolic throne, preaching the word of God, teaching the principles of the faith, and guarding the flock.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما تنيح الأب المغبوط  كلاوتيانوس البطريرك التاسع انتخبوه بطريركاً فتولى بنعمة الله الخلافة على الكرسى الرسولى. وقد كان هذا  البطريرك كارزاً ومعلماً أصول الإيمان وحارساً الرعية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He did not possess any silver or gold, except what met his basic needs. He was a contemporary of the persecution of Emperor Marcus Aurelius, during which he supported the faithful exhorting them more over he preached to the heathens and converted many of them to the faith. When he completed his good endeavor, he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولم يقتن ذهباً ولا فضة بل ما كان ضرورياً فقط. وقد عاصر إضطهاد الإمبراطور مرقس أوريليوس فكان يسند المؤمنين ويعظهم بل كان يكرز للوثنين أيضاً وضم منهم عدداً كبيراً إلى الإيمان. ولما أكمل سعيه الحسن تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Saints Anba Bishay the Founder of the Red Monastery</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس الأنبا بشاى صاحب الدير الأحمر</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also the saints Anba Bishay the founder of the red monastery, west of Souhag, departed. This Holy Father was born in the village of Absounah. In his young age, he worked in in-appropriate jobs but because of the Love of God for him, He brought upon him a sickness during which he saw a vision. In this vision he saw the places of torment. He sighed, cried and raised his eyes to heaven saying, “My Lord and God, if you heal me I will repent and worship you with all my heart.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تنيح القديس الأنبا بشاى صاحب الدير الأحمر بغرب سوهاج. وُلد هذا القديس فى قرية أبصونة ( قرية قديمة مازالت بنفس الاسم تابعة لمركز المراغة بمحافظة سوهاج ). كان فى شبابه يعمل أعمالاً لا تليق ، ولمحبة الرب جلب عليه مرضاً ورأى رؤيا نظر فيها مواضع العذاب. فتنهد وبكى ورفع عينيه إلى السماء وقال " يا سيدى وإلهى إذا شفيتنى فأنا أتوب وأعبدك من كل قلبى ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he was cured a noble thought pondered in his heart, so he started to renounce this world and forsake everything even the sheep that he tended and went up the mountain. On his way, he met Anba Pigol (Bajoul), the uncle of St. Shenoute the Archimandrite, and dwelt with him on mount Adribah. They practiced many worship and ascetic works without boredom, fasting and vigils. They suffered from the enemy many temptations but the Lord saved them from his snares.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما شفى تحرك فى قلبه الفكر الصالح وبدأ يزهد فى هذا العالم ، وترك كل شىء حتى الغنم التى كان يرعاها وصعد إلى الجبل ، فصادف القديس الأنبا بيجول خال القديس الأنبا شنودة رئيس المتوحدين ، وسكن معه فى جبل أدربية. وكانا يقومان بعبادات ونسك بلا ملل وأصوام وسهر. وقد تحملا من العدو تجارب كثيرة والرب خلصهما منها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The account of Anba Bishay became well known in all the land of Egypt. He put down many discourses and useful teachings for the monks and the laity. One time he fasted for a whole month and the deeds of people were uncovered before him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وشاع خبر الأ نبا بشاى فى كل أرض مصر ووضع مقالات كثيرة وتعاليم نافعة للرهبان والعلمانيين. ودفعة صام شهراً كاملاً. وكانت أعمال الناس مكشوفة لديه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During these days, Anba Shenouda went up to his uncle Anba Pigol and the angel of the Lord directed him to put on his nephew the Holy Eskeem. He put on him the Eskeem in the presence of Anba Bishay. The three joined together in worship and asceticism. They made for themselves dwellings in the mountain and built a church after the name of the Virgin Mary.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى تلك الأيام صعد أنبا شنودة إلى خاله الأنبا بيجول ، وأن ملاك الرب أشار عليه أن يلبسه الإسكيم. فألبسه الإسكيم بحضور أنبا بشاى ، وظل الثلاثة متفقين فى العبادة والنسك ، وصنعوا لهم مساكن فى الجبل ، وبنوا كنيسة على اسم القديسة العذراء مريم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Anba Bishay finished his good endeavor, departed in peace and the saint Anba Shenouda shrouded him. He buried him in the monastery which was named after him and known by the Red Monastery, west of Souhag. Anba Shenouda wrote down his biography and asceticism. He called him Peter for what he saw from his endurance of hardships as the rock.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل أنبا بشاى سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام ، فكفنه القديس الأنبا شنودة ، ودفنه فى الدير الذى سمى باسمه  " وهو الشهير بالدير الأحمر غربى سوهاج ". وقد كتب القديس الأنبا شنودة سيرته ونسكياته ودعاه "بطرس" لما رآه من قوة إحتماله الأتعاب مثل الصخر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Apollo, the Companion of Anba Abib</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة الأنبا أبللو رفيق القديس الأنبا أبيب من قديسى القرن الرابع الميلادى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the saint Anba Apollo who was like the angels, the companion of St. Abib departed. They were of the fourth century saints. He was born in the city of Akhmeem. He resembled his parents in piety since his young age. He practiced life of asceticism and was inclined to the solitary life. He spent his time in studying the Holy Bible, contemplating and praying.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تنيح القديس الأنبا أبوللو المتشبه بالملائكة صديق الأنبا أبيب وهما من قديسى القرن الرابع الميلادى.  ولد هذا القديس بمدينة أخميم وكان مثل أبويه تقياً منذ حداثته يمارس الحياة النسكية ميالاً لحياة الوحدة ، يقضى وقته فى دراسة الكتاب المقدس والتأمل والصلاة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He had a close friend called Abib and they were in agreement in thought and had the same monastic aspiration. Apollo went to one of the monasteries where he dwelt in seclusion in a cell practicing a life of fellowship with God. He met his friend Anba Abib from time to time and was present at the time of his departure. The Holy Father Anba Apollo departed in a good old age.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . وكان له صديق حميم يدعى أبيب فإتفقا معاً فى الفكر وتلاقت اشتياقاتهما للحياة الرهبانية. انطلق أبوللو إلى أحد الأديرة حيث سكن فى قلاية منفردة يمارس حياة الشركة مع الله. وكان يلتقى من وقت لآخر بصديقه أبيب وحضر نياحته ( نياحة الأنبا أبيب يوم 25 بابة). تنيح القديس الأنبا أبوللو فى شيخوخة صالحة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Hippolytus, Pope of Rome</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس أبوليدس بابا روما</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also marks the martyrdom of St. Hippolytus, Pope of Rome. He was a perfect and righteous man, so they choose him for the Roman See after the departure of Father Augius (Hyginus Pius). This was in the first year of the enthronement of Abba Celadion, 9th Patriarch of Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً استشهد البابا القديس أبوليدس بابا روما. كان رجلاً فاضلاً وكاملاً  فإختاروه لكرسى روما بعد الأب أجيوس ، فى أول سنة من جلوس البابا كلاوتيانوس  (جلس البابا كلاوتيانوس سنة 152 م  وتنيح سنة 166 م ). البطريرك السكندرى التاسع.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Hippolytus constantly taught his people and defended the Orthodox faith. When Claudius Caesar (Antonius) the Roman Emperor heard of him, summoned the saint and asked him to worship the idols. When he refused, he ordered to torture him. They tortured him severely then tied a heavy stone to his feet and threw him into the sea. He departed in peace and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان البابا أبوليدس مداوماً على تعليم شعبه ، ومدافعاً عن الإيمان المستقيم.فسمع به إمبراطور روما أنطونيوس قيصر فعرض عليه عبادة الأوثان ، ولما لم يرض أمر بتعذيبه. فعذبوه كثيراً ثم ربطوا فى عنقه حجراً ثقيلاً وألقوه فى البحر فتنيح بسلام ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the following day, one of the faithful found the body of the saint floating above the water, and the stone was still tied to his feet. He took him to his home, shrouded him with expensive shrouds, and buried him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ووجد جسده أحد المؤمنين طافياً على الماء والحجر مربوطاً فى رجليه. فأخذه إلى منزله وكفنه بأكفان فاخرة ودفنه. وقد            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This father left a great wealth of teachings and 38 church canons that are still in use.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كتب هذا الأب أقوالاً كثيرة نافعة وقوانين لا تزال باقية عددها ثمانية وثلاثون قانوناً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Aba-Noub, the Owner of the Golden Fan</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس أبانوب صاحب المروحة الذهب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the departure of the saint Aba-Noub (Apanoub) who is known as the Owner of the Golden Fan.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تنيح القديس أبانوب صاحب المروحة الذهب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.6">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Sixth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the sixth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Sts. Cyrus, John, the Three Virgins and Their Mother</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد القديسين أباكير ويوحنا والثلاث عذارى وأمهن</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the saints Cyrus (Abakir), John, the three virgins, and their mother were martyred in the city of Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم  استشهاد القديسين أباكير ويوحنا والثلاث عذارى وأمهن  بمدينة الإسكندرية. و            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Abakir (Cyrus) was born in Alexandria to godly parents who raised him up with a Christian upbringing. He grew loving God and the church. He learned the medical profession and became known for his knowledge, godliness and love for the poor. They accused him before the governor that he was healing the people with sorcery and magic. He ordered to arrest him in spite of his knowledge of all the services that he offered freely to the people. Cyrus fled to the eastern desert where he joined the hermits, lived among them and served them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولد أباكير فى مدينة الإسكندرية من أبوين تقيين وربياه تربية مسيحية فنشأ محباً لله وللكنيسة وتعلم مهنة الطب فاشتهر بعلمه وتقواه ومحبة الفقراء فوشوا به عند الوالى أنه يشفى الناس بالسحر والشعوذة فأمر بالقبض عليه رغم علمه بالخدمات الكثيرة التى يقدمها لكل الناس فهرب أباكير إلى الصحراء الشرقية حيث إنضم للنساك وعاش معهم وكان يخدمهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               However, John was a high ranking officer in the army of the countries in Mesopotamia. He was a pious Christian inclined to the ascetic life and worship. When he heard about Abakir (Cyrus), he left the military service, went to visit the holy places in Jerusalem, and then went to the eastern desert where St. Cyrus was. John met him, and saluted each other, and John dwelt nearby Cyrus. He took him as a teacher and they became spiritual brothers.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أما يوحنا فكان ضابطاً كبيراً فى جيش بلاد ما بين النهرين ، وكان مسيحياً تقياً يميل إلى حياة النسك والعبادة فلما سمع بخبر أباكير ، ترك الجندية وجاء وزار الأماكن المقدسة فى أورشليم ثم جاء إلى الصحراء الشرقية حيث يوجد القديس أباكير فتقابلا وسلما على بعضهما وسكن يوحنا بجوار أباكير واتخذه معلماً له فى الفضيلة وصارا كأخوين روحيين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Diocletian incited the persecution against the Christians, Alexandria became a stage for the torment and torture of the believers. The soldiers of the Governor seized a Christian woman called Athanasia (which means: the immortal) and her three virgin daughters. Theeodora (which means: the gift of God), Theopisti (which means: the faith of God) and Theodosia (which means: the glory of God). They led them bound for trial and torture to an area called Kanoub, east of Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أشعل دقلديانوس الاضطهاد ضد المسيحين، وكانت الإسكندرية مسرحاً لحالات الاضطهاد والتعذيب فأمسك جنود الوالى بسيدة مسيحية مؤمنة تدعى أثناسيا (خالدة وغير مائتة) وبناتها العذارى الثلاث ثيؤدرا (أي عطية الله) وثاؤبستى (أي إيمان الله) وثاؤذكسيا (أي مجد الله) واقتادوهن مقيدات للمحاكمة والتعذيب فى منطقة تدعى كانوب بشرق الإسكندرية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When St. Cyrus (Abakir) heard, while he was in the desert, of the arrest of Athanasia and her daughters, he had compassion for them, for he had known them from before. He was concerned that torture might weaken their faith. He decided to go down to Alexandria to stand beside them. His spiritual brother John went down with him. As they entered Alexandria they went to Kanoub to encourage Athanasia and her daughters.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               سمع القديس أباكير وهو فى الصحراء بخبر القبض على أثناسيا وبناتها وكان يعرفهن من قبل فأشفق عليهن لئلا يؤثر فيهن العذاب فيضعفن فقرر أن ينزل إلى الإسكندرية للوقوف بجانبهن ونزل معه أخوه الروحى يوحنا. وما ان دخلا إلى الإسكندرية وذهبا إلى كانوب لكى يشجعا أثناسيا وبناتها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Some wicked men informed the Governor of the arrival of Cyrus and John. He ordered to arrest, try, and torment them with severe tortures. He also ordered to behead Anastasia and her three daughters before Abakir (Cyrus) and John to frighten them. Nevertheless, they became more steadfast in their faith and longed also for receiving the crown of martyrdom. After a long series of tortures, the Governor ordered to behead them thus they received the crown of martyrdom. That was in the area called Kanoub which was called later on Abu-Kir in reference to the saint Abakir.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               حتى وشى بعض الأشرار للوالى بوصول أباكير ويوحنا ، فأمر بالقبض عليهما ومحاكمتها وتعذيبهما بعذابات شديدة. وأمر الوالى بقطع رؤوس أثناسيا وبناتها الثلاث أمام أباكير ويوحنا لكى يرعبهما ولكنهما إزدادا فى التمسك بإيمانهما وإشتاقا أن ينالا إكليل الشهادة أيضا، وبعد سلسلة من العذابات أمر الوالى بقطع رأسيهما فنالا إكليل الشهادة فى منطقة كانوب التى تسمت بعد ذلك أبوقير نسبة للقديس أباكير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Julius of Aqfahs came with his men, carried the bodies of the martyrs and buried them in a tomb nearby the church of St. Mark in Alexandria and he also wrote down the story of their strive and martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعدها جاء القديس يوليوس الأقفهصى مع غلمانه وحملوا أجساد الشهداء ودفنوهم فى مقبرة بقرب كنيسة مارمرقس بالإسكندرية وكتب أيضاً قصة جهادهم وأستشهادهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Mark (Marcus) IV, 84th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا مرقس الرابع البطريرك الرابع والثمانين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also of the year 1079 of the martyrs (1363 A.D.) Pope Mark (Marcus) IV, 84th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. He was a native of the city of Qalyub and became a monk in the Shahran monastery by the name the monk Ghabrial. He was a righteous monk, knowledgeable and godly.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 1079 للشهداء ( 1363 م ) تنيح البابا مرقس الرابع البطريرك الرابع والثمانون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. كان  هذا البطريرك من أهالى قليوب ترهب بدير شهران باسم الراهب غبريال وكان راهباً فاضلاً ذا علم وتقوى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of Pope Peter V, the bishops and the archons (lay leaders) convened and they choose this monk. He was consecrated Patriarch on the 8th of Thoout, year 1065 A.M. (1348 A.D.) by the name Pope Mark IV.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد نياحة البابا بطرس الخامس اجتمع الأساقفة والأراخنة ووقع إختيارهم على هذا الراهب وتمت رسامته بطريركاً يوم 8 توت سنة 1065 للشهداء ( 1348 م) باسم البابا مرقس الرابع.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his days a severe persecution befell the Copts, some of the churches were destroyed and the monasteries were ruined. The country faced many difficulties. The Pope was imprisoned and the Christian King of Ethiopia had to intervene to release the Pope.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد حدثت فى أيامه اضطهادات شديدة على الأقباط وهُدمت بعض الكنائس وخُربت بعض الأديرة وعم الضيق والحزن كافة البلاد، كما تعرض البابا للسجن أيضاً وتدخل ملك النوبة المسيحى لإطلاق سراح البابا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Finally after thankfully enduring the Lord willed to relieve him from the toils of this world, he delivered his pure soul in the hand of the Lord and was buried in Shahran monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأخيراً بعد صبر وشكر على التجارب التي مر بها ، أراد الرب أن يريحه من أتعاب هذا العالم فإستودع روحه الطاهرة فى يد الرب ودُفن بدير شهران.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Zanofios</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس زانوفيوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the Holy Father Anba Zanofios, departed. He was the abbot of a large community of monks in the region of el-Mara’igh, district of Akhmeem. He was known for asceticism and worship. He taught his children the monk’s virtues, worship and the fear of God. He also established a convent for the virgins, put in charge a righteous mother and sent them epistles that explained the commandments and monastic rules.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تنيح الأب القديس زانوفيوس. كان هذا القديس أباً لمجمع رهبانى كبير بناحية المرايغ ( هى مدينة المراغة حالياً بمحافظة سوهاج ) فى مقاطعة أخميم. اشتهر بالنسك والعبادة وكان يعلم أولاده الرهبان الفضيلة والعبادة ومخافة الله. كما بنى ديراً للعذارى وجعل لهن أماً رئيسة وكان هو يرسل إليهن الرسائل بها الوصايا والقوانين الرهبانية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he finished his good endeavor departed in peace and was buried in his monastery. God wrought many signs from his pure body.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام ودُفن فى ديره وأجرى الله من جسده آيات كثيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.7">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Seventh Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the seventh day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Alexandros II, 43rd Pope of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا القديس ألكسندروس البطريرك الثالث والأربعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 445 of the martyrs (729 A.D.), the Holy Father Abba Alexandros II, 43rd Pope of Alexandria, departed. He was born in the village of Bana, El Mahalla el-Kobra. He was raised on piety, godliness and love of solitary life. He became a monk in the monastery of Pateron, the monastery of the fathers, which was also known as El-Zugag monastery by the name of the monk Alexandros. He lived a life of asceticism, fasting and prayers until the fame of his virtues became well known, so the fathers ordained him a priest for the church of the monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 445 م للشهداء ( 729 م )، تنيح البابا القديس ألكسندروس البطريرك الثالث والأربعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا القديس فى قرية بنا بالمحلة الكبرى، وتربى على التقوى والفضيلة ومحبة الانفراد، ثم مضى وترهب بدير الباتيرون أى دير الآباء الذى كان معروفاً بدير الزجاج بأسم الراهب ألكسندروس. فعاش فى نسك وصوم وصلاة حتى ذاع صيت فضائله فرسمه الأباء قساً على كنيسة الدير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the apostolic throne became vacant by the departure of Pope Simeon I, they unanimously agreed to choose the monk Fr. Alexandros. They consecrated him Patriarch on the 30th of Parmoute, year 420 A.M (704 A.D.)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما خلا الكرسى البطريركى بنياحة البابا سيمون الأول، أجمعت أراء الأساقفة والشعب على اختيار الراهب القس ألكسندروس فرسموه بطريركاً يوم 30 برمودة سنة 420 للشهداء  (704م).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The early days of his pontificate were tranquil however the devil incited the war against the church. The ruler of the country mistreated the Christians and seized the Patriarch and did not release him until he collected for him three thousands Dinars. The governorship of this ruler did not last long moreover the next ruler was even worse than him. The state of the Christians deteriorated more. The fines and difficulties were repeated under the next following four rulers. Hardships were from within the church and also from the Chalcedonians. The Pope endured all these pains praying and supplicating the Lord until he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت أيامه الأولى هادئة ، غير أن الشيطان أثار الحرب على الكنيسة، فأساء الوالى معاملة المسيحيين ، وقبض على البطريرك ولم يتركه حتى جمع له ثلاثة آلاف دينار. ولم تدم رئاسة هذا الوالى  طويلاً ولكن قام بعده من هو أشر منه،  فازدادت أحوال المسيحيين سوءاً وتكررت الغرامات والمضايقات مع أربعة ولاة آخرين. وكانت المحاربات من داخل الكنيسة أيضاً ومن الخلقيدونيين كذلك. واحتمل البابا كل هذه الآلام مصلياً ومتضرعاً للرب حتى تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Theodorus (Theodore), 45th Pope of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا القديس ثيؤدورس البطريرك الخامس والأربعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 458 of the martyrs (742 A.D.) St. Theodorus (Theodor) I, 45th Pope of Alexandria, departed. This Holy Father became a monk by the name Tadros in a monastery nearby Mariot. He became a disciple under the guidance of a holy elder monk called Yoannis (John). Abba Yoannis was inspired by the Holy Spirit that his disciple Tadros would become one day a Patriarch. Abba Yoannis told the people in the church about his vision.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 458 للشهداء ( 742 م )، تنيح البابا القديس ثيؤدورس البطريرك الخامس والأربعون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ترهب هذا القديس باسم الراهب تادرس بدير قريب من مريوط وتتلمذ لراهب شيخ قديس يدعى يؤانس. وقد أوحى للأب يوأنس من الروح القدس بأن تلميذه تادرس سوف يصير يوماً ما بطريركاً، فأعلم الناس بهذا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The monk Tadros struggled in his worship and was perfect in his humility and meekness. When the apostolic throne became vacant by the departure of Pope Cosma I, the bishops and lay-leaders convened. They remembered the prophecy of Anba Yoannis so they brought the monk Fr. Tadros from the monastery against his will. They consecrated him Patriarch on the 1st day of Epep, year 446 A.M. (730 A.D.)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان الراهب تادرس مجاهداً فى عبادته  وإتضاعه ووداعته. ولما خلا الكرسى البطريركى بنياحة البابا قسما الأول ، اجتمع الأساقفة والأراخنة، وتذكروا نبوة القديس يوأنس فأرسلوا إلى الدير وأحضروا الراهب القس تادرس رغماً عنه ورسموه بطريركاً يوم أول أبيب سنة 446 للشهداء (730 م).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After his enthronement, he took interest in the pastoral care of his flock. The church during his days enjoyed a good deal of rest although he faced many hardships for he witnessed the calamities brought by the rulers. He patiently endured what he witnessed nevertheless the church continued to grow spiritually until he completed his good strive and departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما ارتقى كرسى مارمرقس اهتم بالعمل الرعوى، وحظيت الكنيسة فى أيامه بأكمل قسط من الراحة ، إلا أنه صادف متاعب عديدة لدى مشاهدته الفظائع التى أتاها الولاة. وأستمر صابراً على ما رأى وكانت الكنيسة تنمو روحياً إلى أن أكمل هذا البابا جهاده الحسن وتنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.8">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eighth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eighth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Feast of Presenting the Lord Christ to the Temple</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">عيد دخول السيد المسيح إلى الهيكل</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the church celebrates the feast of presenting the Lord Christ into the temple. It is one of the minor feasts of the Lord. On the forties day of the birth of the Lord Christ, His mother the Virgin St. Mary took Him along with St. Joseph the carpenter and went with Him to the temple, to do for him according to the custom of the law and to offer on His behalf the required sacrifice according to their ability. Because of the poverty of the Virgin and Joseph, they offered the sacrifice of the poor which was two young pigeons.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى هذا اليوم تعيد الكنيسة بعيد دخول السيد المسيح إلى الهيكل ، وهو أحد الأعياد السيدية السبعة الصغرى. ففى اليوم الأربعين لميلاد السيد المسيح أخذته أمه السيدة العذراء مريم ومعها القديس يوسف النجار وذهبا به إلى الهيكل ليصنعا له حسب عادة الناموس ولكى يقدما عنه الذبيحة المطلوبة حسب مقدرتهما ( لا 12 : 1 – 8 ). ولفقر السيدة العذراء و القديس يوسف قدما عنه  تقدمة الفقراء وهى فرخى حمام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Virgin St. Mary who conceived by the Holy Spirit and gave birth to the Savior of the world with all purity, submitted to this law to exercise the virtues of humility, obedience to the law, and for us to follow her example. And to follow her Son the Lord Jesus Christ who obeyed the law of the Old Testament with all humility before He established the law of the New Testament.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               والعذراء مريم التى حبلت بالروح القدس وولدت مخلص العالم بطهارة ونقاوة أطاعت هذه الشريعة لكى تمارس فضيلتى الاتضاع وطاعة الناموس ولكى نقتدى نحن بها وبابنها الرب يسوع المسيح الذى أطاع شريعة العهد القديم بكل اتضاع قبل أن يؤسس شريعة العهد الجديد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               And behold in the Temple there was an old priest whose name was Simeon, and this man was just and devout, waiting for the consolation of Israel, and the Holy Spirit was upon him. And when the parents brought in the Child Jesus, to do for Him according to the custom of the law, Simeon took Him up in his arms and blessed God and said: “Lord, now You are letting Your servant depart in peace … “ Then Simeon blessed them and said to Mary, “Behold this Child is destined for the fall and rising of many in Israel and for a sign which will be spoken against (which is the sign of the Cross) yes, a sword will pierce through your own soul also (the sword of grief at the crucifixion of Christ) .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان فى الهيكل في هذا الوقت كاهن شيخ قديس اسمه سمعان وكان باراً تقياً ينتظر تعزية إسرائيل والروح القدس كان عليه، وعندما دخل بالطفل يسوع أبواه ليصنعا له حسب عادة الناموس أخذه سمعان على ذراعيه وبارك الله قائلاً: الآن يا سيد تطلق عبدك بسلام.....وباركهما سمعان وقال للعذراء مريم إن هذا قد وضع لسقوط وقيام كثيرين فى إسرائيل ولعلامة تقاوم (وهى علامة الصليب) وأنت أيضا يجوز فى نفسك سيف ( سيف الحزن عند صلب المسيح ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Now there was one, Anna, a prophetess, the daughter of Phanuel, and coming in that instant she gave thanks to the Lord, and spoke of Him to all those who looked for redemption in Jerusalem. So when they had performed all things according to the law of the Lord, they returned to Galilee, to their own city, Nazareth. And the child grew and became strong in spirit, filled with wisdom; and the grace of God was upon Him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت هناك في الهيكل أيضاً نبية قديسة اسمها حنة بنت فنوئيل وقفت تسبح الله وتكلمت (تنبأت عنه) أمام الحاضرين. ولما أكملوا كل شىء حسب ناموس الرب رجعوا إلى الجليل إلى مدينتهم الناصرة.  وكان الصبى ينمو ويتقوى بالروح ممتلئاً حكمة وكانت نعمة الله عليه ( لو 2 : 22 – 28 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of our Lord Jesus Christ who laid down for us the way of salvation be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة ربنا يسوع المسيح الذى رسم لنا طريق الخلاص فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Simeon the Elder</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس سمعان الشيخ</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also St. Simeon the elder departed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تنيح القديس سمعان الشيخ.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Simeon was one of the seventy elders who translated the Old Testament from the Hebrew language to the Greek in Alexandria. That was by the order of Ptolemy Philadelphus, king of Egypt.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وهو أحد السبعين شيخاً الذين ترجموا التوراة من اللغة العبرية إلى اليونانية فى الإسكندرية بأمر ملك مصر بطليموس فلادلفوس .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Simeon was translating the verse from Isaiah the prophet (7:14), "Behold, the virgin shall conceive and bear a Son, and shall call His name Immanuel," he was afraid to translate that a virgin would conceive, because the King might mock him and accuse him of ignorance. He wanted to translate the virgin as a "young lady or damsel".            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما وصل إلى قول إشعياء النبى " هوذا العذراء تحبل وتلد ابناً وتدعو إسمه عمانوئيل " ( لو 2 : 29 – 32 )، خشى أن يكتب " العذارء " تحبل فيهزأ به الملك ويتهمه بالجهل ، فأراد ان يكتب كلمة "فتاة" بدلاً من كلمة "عذراء".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He became doubtful saying to himself it is impossibility for a virgin to conceive. God revealed to him in a vision that he would not die before he would see Immanuel born of a virgin. This was fulfilled and he lived about three hundred years until the Lord Christ was born from the Virgin Mary without a human seed but by the Holy Spirit. Simeon was well advanced in age and his sight dimmed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وداخله الشك قائلاً فى نفسه أنه لأمر ممتنع أن تلد عذراء. فألقى الله عليه سباتاً فنام، ورأى فى الرؤيا من يقوله له " إنك لن تعاين الموت حتى ترى عمانوئيل مولوداً من عذراء "، وتم ذلك، فعاش سمعان حوالى ثلاثمائة سنة حتى وُلد السيد المسيح من العذراء مريم بغير زرع بشر ، بل بحلول الروح القدس عليها. وكان بصر سمعان قد كف.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he came by the Spirit into the temple and carried the Divine Child in his hands, his sight came back, and the Holy Spirit told him, "This is the child that you have been waiting for." He blessed God and said, "You are letting Your servant depart in peace according to Your Word, for my eyes have seen Your salvation which You have prepared before the face of all peoples." (Luke 2:28-32) He blessed Joseph and Mary and prophesied for them about the future of the Child and about the pains that the Virgin would suffer and in the same day he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما أتى بالروح إلى الهيكل وحمل الطفل الإلهى على ذراعية أبصر ، وأعلمه الروح القدس أن هذا هو الذى كنت تنتظره ، فبارك الله وقال  " الآن تطلق عبدك يا سيد بسلام حسب قولك لأن عينى قد أبصرتا خلاصك الذى أعددته قدام جميع الشعوب " لو 2 : 29 – 32 )، ثم بارك القديس يوسف والعذراء مريم وتنبأ لهما عن مستقبل الطفل وعن الآلام التى ستقاسيها السيدة العذراء. وفى نفس اليوم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The prayers of this righteous man be with us all, and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.9">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Ninth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the ninth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Barsauma, the Father of the Syrian Monks</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة الأنبا برسوم أب رهبان دير السريان</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 174 of the martyrs (458 A.D.) the blessed father Anba Barsauma, the father of the Syrian monks, departed. This Holy Father was born in the city of Samosata, in Syria. A holy man prophesied about him before his birth saying to his parents, "There shall go forth from you a righteous fruit, whose fame shall spread out everywhere."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 174 للشهداء ( 458 م ) تنيح الأب المغبوط الأنبا برسوم أب رهبان دير السريان. ولد هذا القديس فى بلدة ساموساط بالشام. وقد تنبأ عنه رجل قديس قبل ولادته قائلاً لوالديه " سيخرج منكما ثمر صالح، وينتشر ذكره فى الأرض ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This prophecy was fulfilled, when Barsauma grew up, he left his parents and went to the river Euphrates where he dwelt with a holy man called Abraham. Afterwards, he lived in solitude on the mountain praying and fasting with austere asceticism. Many disciples gathered around him. The water of that place was salty, and with the prayers of the saint it became sweet. God wrought through him many miracles. A famine befell this country and God lifted it up by his prayers.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفعلاً تم هذا القول إذ أنه عندما كبر برسوم ترك أبويه وقصد نهر الفرات حيث أقام زماناً عند رجل قديس يدعى إبراهيم، ثم انفرد فى الجبل عابداً مصلياً صائماً بنسك شديد. فاجتمع حوله تلاميذ كثيرون، وكان ماء ذلك المكان مالحاً وبصلوات القديس برسوم صار حلواً. كما حدثت منه معجزات كثيرة، وحدث غلاء فى تلك البلاد فرفعه الرب بصلواته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Simeon the Stylite visited him and they blessed each other. This saint was well known for his resisting the heresy of Nestorius. He attended the Universal Council at Ephesus in the year 431 A.D. by an invitation of Emperor Theodosius the Less, who greatly honored him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد زاره القديس سمعان العمودى، وتباركا من بعضهما البعض.  إشتهر هذا الأب بمقاومته لبدعة نسطور ، وحضر مجمع أفسس سنة 431 م بدعوة من الإمبراطور ثيؤدوسيوس الصغير، الذى أكرمه كثيراً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Marcian convened the Chalcedonian council, the fathers asked the Emperor not to invite St. Barsauma to the council, for they knew of the grace that was in him. When the council agreed on the two natures of Christ, St. Barsauma resisted these heretical teachings and many hardships befell him from the Chalcedonians.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما جمع مرقيان المجمع الخلقيدونى طلب الآباء من الإمبراطور ألا يدعى برسوما إلى المجمع لعلمهم بالنعمة التى فيه وعندما قرر المجمع القول بالطبيعتين قاوم القديس برسوما هذه التعاليم الباطلة فنالته شدائد كثيرة منهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Holy Father knew the day of his departure. He gathered his disciples, blessed them and commended them to steadfast in the Orthodox faith and departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وعلم هذا القديس بيوم نياحته، فاستدعى أولاده الرهبان وباركهم وأوصاهم بالثبات على الإيمان الأرثوذكسى وتنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               At the time of his departure, a pillar of light appeared at the door of his cell. They shrouded and buried him with great honor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد ظهر وقت نياحته عمود من نور قائم على باب قلايته. فكفنوه ودفنوه بإكرام جزيل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Paul the Syrian</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد القديس بولس السريانى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 21 of the martyrs (305 A.D.) St. Paul the Syrian was martyred. His family relocated from Syria and settled in the City of Ashmunain. From working in trading his father gained a great wealth. God granted them this saint and they raised him in a true Christian upbringing, growing in godliness and loving the Lord from all his Heart.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 21 للشهداء ( 305 م ) استشهد القديس بولس السريانى. هاجرت أسرته من بلاد سوريا واستقرت فى مدينة الأشمونين ، وعمل والده فى التجارة وإقتنى أموالاً كثيرة. ورزقهما الله هذا القديس فربياه تربية حقيقة حتى نما  فى الفضيلة وأحب الرب من كل قلبه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the death of his parents, the saint prayed to God to guide him in the way that pleases Him. The Lord sent His angel in a vision and made it known to him that he will receive the crown of martyrdom. The saint rejoiced and was comforted. He distributed all his money to the poor and the needy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما توفى والده ، صلى القديس إلى الله ليرشده إلى الطريق الذى يرضيه ، فأرسل الرب ملاكه فى رؤيا وأعلمه بأنه سينال إكليل الشهادة. ففرح وتعزى ووزع كل أمواله على الفقراء والمساكين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The saint arose right away and went to the governor of Ansena (Antinoe) and confessed the Lord Christ before him. The Governor ordered him stripped naked, beaten with whips, and to place burning torches to his sides. The saint was not afraid and the governor tried again to entice him with money, but the saint told him, "My parents left me a fortune of gold and silver, and I rejected them for the sake of the love of my Lord and God Jesus Christ. So why should I look to your money now?"            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقام لوقته ومضى إلى والي أنصنا واعترف بالسيد المسيح. فأمر الوالى بأن يُعرى من ثيابه ويُضرب بالسياط وتوضع مشاعل فى جنبيه ، فلم يخف ثم حاول إغراءه بالمال فقال القديس : لقد ترك لى أبواى كثيراً من الذهب والفضة ، فلم التفت إليها حباً فى ربى وإلهى يسوع المسيح ، فكيف انظر إلى مالك الآن؟            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Governor became angry and he tormented him with different kinds of tortures. However the Lord healed and strengthened him. Later on the governor ordered him placed with venomous serpents which did not harm him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فغضب الوالى جداً وعذبه بكل أنواع العذاب وكان الرب يشفيه ويقويه. بعد ذلك أمر الوالى بأن يطلقوا عليه حيات سامة مميتة فلم تؤذه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the governor was weary of torturing him he took the saint with him to Alexandria and imprisoned him. In prison, he met his two friends the saints Esi and his sister Thecla and their soul rejoiced.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما احتار الوالى فى تعذيبه ، أخذه معه إلى الإسكندرية وأودعه السجن ، فالتقى بصديقيه القديسين ايسى وتكلا أخته فابتهجت أرواحهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Governor decided to return to Ansena, he ordered to behead St. Paul thus he received the crown of martyrdom. The faithful came, took his body, shrouded it and buried him with great honor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما عزم الوالى العودة إلى أنصنا أمر بقطع رأس القديس بولس فنال إكليل الشهادة.  فأتى بعض المؤمنين وأخذوا جسده وكفنوه ودفنوه بإكرام جزيل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Simeon</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد القديس سمعان</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also marks the martyrdom of St. Simeon.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً استشهد القديس سمعان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Euphrosyne of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديسة أفروسينا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Also on this day of the year 186 of the martyrs (470 A.D.) was the departure of St. Euphrosyne of Alexandria. This saint was born in Alexandria, an only child to godly and wealthy family. They raised her with a true Christian upbringing. She learnt from her parents the fear of God and the charity for the poor and the needy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً سنة 186 للشهداء ( 470 م ) ، تنيحت القديسة أفروسينا ، ولدت هذه القديسة بالإسكندرية وكانت أبنة وحيدة لأسرة تقية وغنية. فربياها تربية مسيحية حقيقية ، وتعلمت من والديها مخافة الله ومحبة الفقراء والمساكين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When she was eighteen years old, she left her home, wearing the attire of men and went to one of the monasteries. The abbot of the monastery accepted her and put her up in a solitary cell. She devoted herself to fasting, prayers and austere asceticism which changed her appearance.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما بلغت الثامنة عشر ، تركت بيتها وتزيت بزى الرجال ، وذهبت إلى أحد أديرة الرهبان فقبلها رئيس الدير وأسكنها قلاية منفردة ، عكفت على الصوم والعبادة والنسك الزائد حتى تبدلت هيئتها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Her father visited the monastery often asking the monks to pray for him for the Lord to grant him peace and comfort for his heart. Euphrosyne recognized him but he did not know her, however she received and encouraged him. He found consolation from the words of grace that she spoke to him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان والدها يتردد على الدير ليطلب من الرهبان أن يصلوا عنه ليعطيه الرب سلاماً وتعزية قلبية. وعرفته أفروسينا وكانت تقابله وتشجعه أما هو فلم يعرفها. وصار يتردد على الدير كثيراً إذ كان يجد راحة من كلمات النعمة التى كانت تكلمه بها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Euphrosyne became ill and she knew the day of her departure. When her father came to the monastery, she revealed her identity to him and told him that she was about to depart. He embraced her crying however she encouraged and consoled him then she departed between his arms.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مرضت أفروسينا وعرفت بيوم انتقالها ، فلما حضر والدها إلى الدير عرفته بنفسها وبأنها ستنتقل. فقبلها باكياً ، فشجعته وعزته ، ثم تنيحت بين يديه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was very much moved and agreed with his wife to forsake the vanity of the world. He sold all his possessions and distributed the money to the churches and the poor. His wife joined one of the convents and he dwelt in the cell of his daughter in the monastery for ten years then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . أما هو فتأثر جداً واتفق مع زوجته على الزهد فى الدنيا. فباع أملاكه ووزع ثمنها على الكنائس والفقراء ودخلت إمراته أحد الراهبات ، أما هو فسكن فى قلاية ابنته عشر سنوات ثم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of St. Euphrosyne be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . بركة صلوات القديسة أفروسينا فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.10">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Tenth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم العاشر من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the tenth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم العاشر من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Philo, Bishop of the Persians</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس فيلو أسقف فارس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day St. Philo, bishop of the Persians, was martyred by the hand of the Persian Emperor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم إستشهد القديس فيلو أسقف فارس على يد ملك الفرس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He tried to force him to worship fire and to kneel to the sun that the Persian Emperor worshiped. When St. Philo refused to obey the orders of the emperor and stood fast in his faith in the Lord Christ, the emperor tormented him with different kinds of tortures. Finally he ordered to behead him with the sword thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الذى حاول معه لكى يجبره على عبادة النار ويسجد للشمس التى كان يتعبد لها. ولما لم يطع أوامر الملك. أمر الملك بقطع رأسه بحد السيف فنال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Justus, the Son of Emperor Numerian</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس يسطس إبن الملك نوماريوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, St. Justus, the son of Emperor Numerian, was martyred. He was a prince and a high ranking army commander. When he returned victoriously from the war against the Persians, he found that his father had died; Diocletian had married his sister and became emperor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً استشهد القديس يسطس ابن الملك نوماريوس. كان أميراً وقائداً كبيراً فى الجيش. وبعد أن عاد من الحرب مع الفرس منتصراً وجد أن أباه قد مات وتزوج دقلديانوس بأخته وصار ملكاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the nobles of the empire met together to enthrone Justus emperor, he refused, for he preferred the heavenly kingdom over the earthly. After a while Diocletian abandoned the faith of the Lord Christ and worshiped the idols. When Justus objected to what Diocletian had done, he seized him, his wife Theoclea and his son Abali and sent them to Alexandria to be tortured there away from their country and their people.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما اجتمع كبار رجال الدولة لتنصيب يسطس إمبراطوراً رفض مفضلاً المملكة السمائية على الأرضية. وبعد مدة إرتد دقلديانوس عن الأيمان بالسيد المسيح وعبد الأوثان. ولما اعترض يسطس قبض عليه دقلديانوس هو وزوجته ثاؤكليا وابنه أبالى وأرسلهم إلى الإسكندرية لتعذيبهم بعيداً عن بلدهم وشعبهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When they arrived to Alexandria, the governor tried to persuade them to worship the idols. They refused declaring their steadfastness in their faith in the Lord Christ. He sent St. Justus to Antinoe (Ansena ), Abali, his son, to Basta and Theoclea to Sa el-Hagar. The rulers tortured them then beheaded the three saints, and they received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما وصلوا أرسل يسطس إلى أنصنا (وهى الآن قرية الشيخ عبادة شرق ملوى ) ، وأبالى إلى بسطة ( مدينة قديمة كانت بالقرب من الزقازيق الحالية) ، وثاؤكليا إلى صا الحجر ( مدينة فرعونية قديمة تقع الآن فى محافظة الشرقية) ، فعذبهم الولاة هناك ثم قطعوا رؤوسهم فنالوا أكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Isidore of Pelusium</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس إيسوذوروس الفرمى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 166 of the martyrs (450 A.D.) the great saint, ascetic and scholar Anba Isidore of Pelusium (El-Farama), departed. He was born in Alexandria in the year 370 A.D. to a large family. He was related to the saints Pope Theophilus, the 23rd patriarchs of Alexandria and Pope Cyril I, the 24th Patriarch. His parents raised him up with a Christian upbringing and taught him the church subjects.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 166 للشهداء ( 450 م ) تنيح القديس العظيم العالم الناسك الأنبا إيسوذوروس الفرمى.  ولد هذا القديس فى الإسكندرية سنة 370م من عائلةً كبيرة ، وكان قريباً للقديسين ثاوفيلس بابا الإسكندرية الثالث والعشرين وكيرلس البابا الرابع والعشرين. رباه أبواه تربية مسيحية وعلماه العلوم الكنسية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he grew he learnt the Greek language and its literature which he excelled in and surpassed many. He became a scholar in many subjects, Philosophy, History and Logic however he was a humble ascetic.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما كبر تعلم اللغة اليونانية وآدابها فأتقنها وبرع فيها وصار عالماً فى كل العلوم والفلسفات والتاريخ والمنطق ، ومع ذلك كان ناسكاً متواضعاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He fled away from the glory of the world and became a monk in one of the monasteries in the region of el-Farama. Then he moved to the region of Pelusium to live there a life of solitude and asceticism. His monastic conduct was purely evangelical inclined to simplicity caring for the inward adornment of the soul with virtues.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هرب من مجد العالم وترهب فى أحد الأديرة بمنطقة الفرما ( مدينة فى سيناء على ساحل البحر الأبيض المتوسط شرقى بور سعيد بحوالى 25 كيلو متراً ) ، لذلك دعى إيسوذوروس الفرمى ، ثم انتقل إلى منطقة البلوزيوم ( مدينة ساحلية فى سيناء شرقى بور سعيد ) ليعيش هناك حياة الوحدة والنسك، وكان منهجه الرهبانى إنجيلياً صرفاً ، يميل إلى البساطة والاهتمام بزينة النفس الداخلية بالفضائل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was interested in his seclusion to interpret the Holy Scriptures. He commented on many books of the Old and New Testaments. He also wrote powerful epistles to many of the emperors, patriarchs, bishops and monks. These epistles estimated to be about two thousands. The gifts of the Holy Spirit were abundantly clear in his writings. When he reached a good old age departed in peace and went to the Lord whom he loved.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . اهتم فى خلوته بتفسير الكتاب المقدس ففسر  الكثير من أسفار العهدين القديم والجديد ، كما كتب رسائل قوية لكثير من الملوك والبطاركة والأسقافة والرهبان قُدرت بنحو ألفى رسالة ، وكانت مواهب الروح القدس تتدفق منه بغزارة. ولما وصل إلى شيخوخة حسنة تنيح بسلام ومضى إلى الرب الذى أحبه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماُ آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.11">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eleventh Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الحادى عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eleventh day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الحادى عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Yoannis XIII (John), 94th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا القديس يوأنس الثالث عشر البطر يرك الرابع والتسعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 1240 of the martyrs (1524 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Yoannis XIII (John), the 94th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This saint was born in the city of Sedfa. He was a godly man, charitable to the poor and the needy. He became a monk in the monastery of the Virgin St. Mary, el-Moharraq. He lived a pious monastic life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 1240 م للشهداء ( 1524 م ) تنيح البابا القديس يوأنس الثالث عشر البطريرك الرابع والتسعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا القديس ببلدة صدفا ( إحدى مراكز محافظة أسيوط حالياً ) كان رجلاً فاضلاً محسناً على الفقراء والمساكين ، ترهب بدير القديسة العذراء المحرق وسار سيرة رهبانية فاضلة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of Pope Yoannis XII, the bishops and the lay leaders of the people unanimously agreed to choose the monk John el-Moharraqy (John el-Masry, the Egyptian) to be ordained patriarch. He was consecrated on the 15th day of Meshir, year 1200 of the martyrs (1484 A.D.). He shepherded the flock of God with the best of care.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد نياحة البابا يوأنس الثانى عشر أجمع الأساقفة وأراخنة الشعب على اختيار الراهب يوحنا المحرقى ( يوحنا المصرى) لرسامته بطريركاً فرسموه يوم 15 أمشير سنة 1200 للشهداء 14840 م.  فرعى رعية الله أحسن رعاية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his days there was a Coptic episcopate on the island of Cyprus and also was the return of the relics of the great martyr St. Philopateer Mercurius (Abu-Saifain) to his church in Old Cairo .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان فى عهده توجد أسقفية قبطية فى جزيرة قبرص وفى عهده أيضاً تم إحضار جسد الشهيد العظيم مرقوريوس أبى سيفين إلى كنيسته بمصر القديمة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Yoannis remained on the apostolic throne struggling to improve the standing of his church for forty years accomplished in them many renovations, improvements and wrote many spiritual books.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               واستمر البابا يوأنس على الكرسى المرقسى مجاهداً فى سبيل إعلاء قدر كنيسته مدة 40 سنة أتم فيها الكثير من الإصلاح والتجديد وكتب العديد من المؤلفات الروحية النافعة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Then he departed in peace and was buried in the church of the Virgin Mary in Haret Zuweila which was the Papal residence at that time.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم تنيح بسلام ودُفن بكنيسة القديسة العذراء مريم بحارة زويلة التى كانت مقراً للبطريركية في ذلك الوقت.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Fabianus (Fabrianus), Pope of Rome</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد القديس فابيانوس بابا روما</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, St. Fabianus, Pope of Rome, was martyred. This father was a righteous scholar. He was ordained bishop for the City of Rome. He taught his people and guided them in the way of Christian perfection.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً إستشهد القديس فابيانوس بابا روما. كان هذا الأب عالماً صالحاً فأقاموه أسقفاً على روما فأخذ يعلم شعبه ويقوده فى طريق الكمال.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Decius incited persecution against the Christians, many were martyred at his hands. The Emperor was informed that St. Fabianus was confirming the Christians in their faith which hindered worshipping the idols. He brought Fabianus to Ephesus and commanded him to raise incense to the idols but he refused. The Emperor tormented him with many severe tortures for a long time. Finally he ordered to behead him with the sword thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أثار الإمبراطور ديسيوس الاضطهاد على المسيحين واستشهد كثيرون على يديه بلغه أن القديس فابيانوس يثبت المسيحيين على إيمانهم ويعطل عبادة الأوثان. فاستحضره بأفسس وطلب منه أن يبخر للأصنام فلم يقبل فعذبه بعذابات شديدة مدة طويلة. وأخيراً أمر بقطع رأسه بحد السيف فنال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Fabianus stayed on the apostolic throne for twelve year.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بعد أن أقام على الكرسى 12 سنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.12">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twelfth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثانى عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twelfth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثانى عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Honorable Archangel Michael</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار رئيس الملائكة الجليل ميخائيل</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the church celebrates, the monthly commemoration of the honorable Michael the Archangel, the intercessor of mankind.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى هذا اليوم تعيد الكنيسة بالتذكار الشهرى لرئيس الملائكة الجليل ميخائيل والشفيع فى جنس البشر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               His holy intercession be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               شفاعته المقدسة فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Gelasius, the Ascetic</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس جلاسيوس الناسك</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Also on this day, St. Gelasius, the ascetic, departed. This Holy Father was born to Christian parents, who brought him up with a Christian upbringing. They taught him the church subjects, and he was ordained a deacon.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تنيح القديس جلاسيوس الناسك. ولد هذا القديس من أبوين مسيحيين فربياه تربية مسيحية وعلماه علوم الكنيسة فرُسم شماساً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He became a monk in the wilderness of Shiheet. The angel of the Lord guided him to a place in the inner wilderness where some monks who desired the solitary life gathered around him. St. Gelasius became a teacher and guide for them. He worked in transcribing the Holy Scriptures.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم ترهب فى برية شيهيت وأرشده ملاك الرب إلى مكان داخل البرية فأجتمع حوله بعض الرهبان من محبى الوحدة فصار لهم معلماً ومرشداً. وكان يعمل بنسخ الكتب المقدسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He loved everyone and forgiving those who trespassed against him. He reached a high degree of holiness to the extent that he raised a dead man.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان محباً للجميع يغفر ويسامح لكل من يسىء إليه ، فوصل إلى درجة عالية من القداسة حتى أنه أقام ميتاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               His life was a good example for everyone. After a long struggle in the monastic life, asceticism, worship and guiding the brethren, he departed in peace and gained the eternal rest.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد جهاد طويل فى الرهبنة والنسك والعبادة وإرشاد الإخوة حيث كانت حياته قدوة حسنة للجميع تنيح بسلام ونال الراحة الأبدية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.13">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Thirteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the thirteenth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Sergius of Atripe, His Father, Mother, Sister, and Many Others with Them</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس سرجيوس الأتريبى وأبيه وأمه وأخته وكثيرين معهم</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Sergius, his father, mother, sister and many others with them were martyred. This saint was born in the City of Atripe to pious parents who raised him with Christian principles.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم إستشهد القديس سرجيوس وأبوه وأمه وأخته وكثيرون معهم. ولد القديس سرجيوس فى مدينة أتريب من أبوين تقيين فربياه على الآداب المسيحية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he was 20 years old, he thought about the vanity of the world and the eternal happiness, so he rose and went to Cyprian, the governor. He professed his faith in the Lord Christ before him. The governor commanded to torture and then imprisoned him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما بلغ عمره عشرين سنة ، فكر فى زوال العالم والسعادة الآبدية ، فقام ومضى إلى الوالى كبريانوس واعترف أمامه بالسيد المسيح.  فأمر الوالى بتعذيبه وسجنه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               At night he saw in a vision the habitations of the righteous, his soul was comforted, and the Lord healed him from his wounds.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى الليل أبصر فى رؤيا مساكن الأبرار فتعزت نفسه وشفاه الرب من أوجاعه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Ohios, the captain of the soldiers, took charge of torturing St. Sergius. He ordered to skin him and to rub his wounds with salt and vinegar, then crush him with the pressing wheel (Hinbazeen), to pull his nails out and to place him on an iron bed over a blazing fire. However the Lord strengthened and healed him. When Ohios, the commander, was weary of torturing him he ordered to behead him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تولى أوهيوس الإسفهسلار تعذيب القديس ، فأمر بسلخ جلده وتدليكه بخل وملح ، ثم عصره بالهنبازين وقلع أظافره ، ووضعه على سرير حديد تحته نار موقدة ، وكان الرب في كل هذه العذابات يقويه ويشفيه. ولما ضجر أوهيوس الإسفهسلار أمر بقطع رأسه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               At that time his father, mother, sister and many others with them came. When they saw him tied up with the bridle of a horse dragging him to the place of execution, they protested the soldiers for their extreme cruelty. The captain ordered to behead them all and they all received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأثناء ذلك حضر أبوه وأمه وأخته وكثيرون معهم فلما رأوه مشدوداً بلجام كالخيل إلى موضوع الإستشهاد ، احتجوا على الجند لقساوتهم فأمر القائد بقطع رؤوسهم جميعاً فنالوا أكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Timothy III, the 32nd Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس تيموثاؤس الثالث البطريرك الثانى والثلاثين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 252 of the martyrs (536 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Timothy III, the 32nd Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This saint was born in the city of Alexandria. He studied the church subjects and excelled in them. He was ordained a priest for the church of St. Mark in Alexandria. The fame of his holiness, knowledge, and steadfastness in the Orthodox faith became well known.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 252 للشهداء ( 536 م ) ، تنيح  القديس تيموثاؤس الثالث البطريرك الثانى والثلاثين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا القديس بمدينة الإسكندرية ودرس علوم الكنيسة ونبغ فيها ، فأقاموه قساً على كنيسة مارمرقس بالإسكندرية، فذاع صيت قداسته وعلمه وتمسكه بالإيمان الأرثودكسى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the apostolic throne became vacant after the departure of Pope Dioscorus II, the bishops, priests, and lay leaders (Archons) convened and prayed entreating God to guide them to whomever worthy of this rank. The Holy Spirit inspired them to choose the priest Timothy. He was consecrated Patriarch on the first day of Hathor, year 235 of the martyrs (518 A.D.).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما خلا الكرسى بنياحة البابا ديوسقورس الثانى ، اجتمع الآباء الأساقفة والكهنة والأراخنة وصلوا طالبين إرشاد الرب فى من يصلح لهذه الرتبة ، فألهمهم الروح القدس أن يختاروا القس تيموتاوس ، فرسموه بطريركاً يوم أول هاتور سنة 235 للشهداء ( 518 م ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He followed the same manner of his predecessors by sending a fellowship epistle to his brothers the bishops of the East. They all replied declaring their joy for the perpetuity of peace and love between them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فسار على منوال سلفائه بأن أرسل رسالة الشركة إلى إخوته أساقفة الشرق ، فردوا عليه جميعاً معلنين اغتباطهم بدوام السلام والألفة بينهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This father suffered many hardships for preserving the Orthodox faith. Emperor Justin I was an advocate of the Chalcedonian council and called for a council to excommunicate St. Severus, Patriarch of Antioch. Pope Timothy refused to attend this council consequently the emperor ordered to exile him. When the faithful opposed the execution of his order he killed a large number of them. They arrested Pope Timothy and he was exiled for three years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد نالت هذا الأب شدائد كثيرة بسبب محافظته على الإيمان المستقيم ، وذلك أن الإمبراطور يوستنيانوس الأول كان مناصراً لمجمع خلقيدونية ودعا مجمعاً لحرم القديس ساويرس بطريرك أنطاكية فرفض البابا تيموثاس حضور هذا المجمع ، فأمر الإمبراطور بنفيه. ولما عارض المؤمنون فى تنفيذ الأمر قتل منهم عدد كبير وأستطاع الجنود تنفيذ الأمر والقبض على البابا البطريرك حيث نُفى ثلاث سنوات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the return of Pope Timothy from exile they continued to pursuit him and St. Severus from town to town and from a monastery to another. Where ever they went, they commended the people to steadfast in the Orthodox faith. Finally they took refuge in a monastery away from the reach of the soldiers. They wrote epistles to their people to comfort their hearts and to strengthen their resolve.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد أن عاد البابا البطريرك من منفاه ظل مُطارداً هو والقديس ساويرس الأنطاكى من بلد إلى بلد ومن دير لآخر. وكانا حيثما حلا يثُبتان الشعب على التمسك بالإيمان الأرثوذكسى ويزيدانه حماسة. وأخيراً تمكنا من الالتجاء إلى دير بعيد عن عيون الجنود، واخذا فى كتابة الرسائل لشعبيهما لتعزية القلوب وتقوية العزائم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Timothy persevered on teaching his flock with the written word directing the affairs of the church in the middle of all these hardships. He persisted in his continuous spiritual struggle until he departed to the place of perpetual peace after he had been on the apostolic throne for about 17 years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد داوم الأنبا تيموثاؤس على تعليم شعبه بالرسائل، وكان يُدير دفة الكنيسة وسط كل العواصف، وظل فى جهاده الروحى المتواصل إلى أن انتقل إلى مكان السلام الدائم. وقد أمضى على السدة المرقسية نحو سبع عشرة سنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.14">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fourteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fourteenth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Severus, Patriarch of Antioch</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس ساويرس بطريرك أنطاكية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the Holy Father St. Severus, Patriarch of Antioch, departed. This saint was born in the year 175 of the martyrs (459 A.D.) in the city of Sozopolis in Asia Minor. His parents raised him up with a Christian upbringing and taught him the religious and secular subjects. After he finished his studies of Philosophy in Alexandria he went to Beirut to study law and he excelled and everyone expected for him a great future.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تنيح القديس ساويرس بطريرك أنطاكية. ولد هذا القديس سنة 175 للشهداء ( 459 م) فى مدينة سوزوبوليس بآسيا الصغرى ( تذكر بعض المصادر الأخرى أنه ولد فى أثينا). رباه والداه تربية مسيحية وعلماه العلوم الدينية والدنيوية، وبعد أن أكمل دراساته فى العلوم الفلسفية بالإسكندرية أنطلق إلى بيروت ليدرس العلوم القانونية ، فأظهر نبوغاً فائقاً فتوقع له الجميع مستقبلاً عظيماً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Severus grew in spiritual life and an ascetic prophesied about him that he would be Patriarch of Antioch, teacher of Orthodoxy and its defender. Later on he became a monk in the monastery of St. Romanus and the fame of his virtues and knowledge became well known.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ونما ساويرس فى الحياة الروحية وتنبأ عنه احد النساك أنه سيصير بطريركاً لأنطاكية ومعلماً للأرثوذكسية ومدافعاً عنها. بعد ذلك ترهب فى دير القديس رومانوس وذاع صيت فضائله وعلمه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Patriar.ch of Antioch departed, the bishops and the people had a consensus to ordain him the Patriarch of the city in the year 512 A.D. The universal church was illuminated by his teachings.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما تنيح بطريرك أنطاكية أختاره الأساقفة والشعب وأقاموه بطريركاً على أنطاكية سنة 512 م ، فاستضاءت الكنيسة بتعاليمه التى ذاعت فى كل المسكونة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Justin I, who was Chalcedonian in faith, reigned, he called upon this Holy Father and gave him great honors to persuade him to adopt his faith. When he stood firm in his Orthodox faith, the Emperor became angry and ordered to kill him. Theodora, the emperor's wife who was Orthodox in faith, knew about what the Emperor was about to do, so she told the saint to flee to Egypt.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما ملك يوستنيانوس وكان على عقيدة مجمع خلقيدونية فاستدعى هذا الأب وأكرمه كثيراً لكى يوافقه على رأيه ولما تمسك بعقيدته الأرثوذكسية غضب الملك فخرج سراً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Severus escaped to the land of Egypt and that was during the papacy of Pope Timothy III. He wandered around between monasteries and the Egyptian cities in simple monk attire confirming the believers in the Orthodox faith. That made the emperor to incite a severe persecution against the Coptic Church for accepting St. Severus who was fleeing from his face.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وجاء إلى مصر وكان ذلك فى عهد البابا تيموثاوس الثالث وظل يطوف فى الأديرة والبلاد المصرية فى زى راهب بسيط يثبت المؤمنين على الإيمان المستقيم، مما دعى الملك أن يثير اضطهاداً شديداً على الكنيسة القبطية التى قبلت القديس ساويرس الهارب من وجهه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He dwelt in the later part of his life in the city of Sakha at a righteous Archon called Doretheos. God performed many miracles by his hands. He departed in the city of Sakha, and his body was relocated later on to the monastery of El-Zugag nearby Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد أقام فى أواخر حياته فى مدينة سخا عند رجل أرخن فاضل يدعى دوروثيئوس ، وقد أجرى الله على يديه آيات كثيرة وتنيح بمدينة سخا ونقل جسده إلى دير الزجاج.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. James (Jacob), 50th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا القديس يعقوب البطريرك الخمسين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 546 of the martyrs (830 A.D.), the Holy Father Pope James (Jacob), 50th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. He was born in the city of Nabaroh. His parents raised him up with a Christian upbringing and taught him the church subjects. When he grew, became a monk in the monastery of St. Macarius in the wilderness of Shiheet. He lived a godly monastic life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 546 للشهداء ( 830 م ) تنيح البابا القديس يعقوب البطريرك الخمسين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا القديس فى بلدة نبروه ( قرية بمركز طلخا محافظة الدقهلية حالياً)، فرباه أبواه تربية مسيحية وعلماه العلوم الكنسية ، ولما كبر ترهب بدير القديس مكاريوس ببرية شيهيت فسار سيرة رهبانية فاضلة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Mark II departed, they choose him by a consensus for the patriarchate. He was consecrated in the year 819 A.D. He renovated the churches and populated the monasteries. God granted him the working of miracles and signs as raising a child from the dead in the city of Nabaroh.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تنيح البابا مرقس الثانى انتخبوه بطريركاُ ورسموه سنة 819 م ، فجدد الكنائس وعمر الأديرة وقد وهبه الله عمل الآيات والعجائب منها أنه أقام طفلاً من الموت فى نبروه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he finished his good endeavor, he departed in peace after sitting on the apostolic throne for 10 years and 9 month.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام بعد أن جلس على الكرسى المرقسى عشرة سنين وتسعة أشهر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.15">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fifteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fifteenth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Paphnoute, the Monk</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس بفنوتيوس الراهب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the ascetic monk St. Paphnoute departed. This Holy Father became a monk in one of the monasteries of Upper Egypt. He lived a holy life to the point that they looked to him more as an angel than a human. He enjoyed much the company of the blessed spirits of the saints as he had a great favor before God in his prayers. He attracted many to the monastic life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تنيح القديس بفنوتيوس الراهب. ترهب هذا القديس فى أحد أديرة الصعيد وعاش حياة مقدسة حتى أنهم كانوا ينظرون إليه كملاك أكثر منه كإنسان، وكان يسعد كثيراً بملازمة الأرواح الطوباوية ، كما كانت له دالة عظيمة فى صلواته لدى الله، وقد جذب الكثيرين إلى طريق الرهبنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The grace of God moved him to travel to the inner wilderness to meet the fathers the anchorites and record their biographies. He rose up and walked many days in the wilderness and suffered many hardships on his way. The angel of the Lord appeared to him often to encourage and strengthen him until he finally reached where the fathers the anchorites dwelled. He saw many of them among those well known were Anba Timothy and Anba Nofer (Onnuphrius). He was the one to shroud Anba Nofer and bury him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               حركته نعمة الله للدخول إلى البرية لينظر الآباء السواح ويتعرف على سيرة حياتهم. فقام ومشى فى البرية أياماً كثيرة ولاقى متاعب جمة فى الطريق. وكان يظهر له ملاك الرب يشدده ويقويه، حتى وصل أخيراً إلى أماكن الآباء السواح ورأى كثيرين منهم أشهرهم الأنبا تيموثاوس السائح والأنبا نوفير الذى كفنه القديس بفنوتيوس ودفنه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He longed for the life of the anchorites and desired to remain there but the saint Anba Nofer told him that this was not the will of God for him. But he had to return to his monastery and to inform the brethren of what he saw and heard for the benefit of the monks and those seeking the path of righteousness. Consequently after the departure of Anba Nofer the palm tree that he fed on its fruits fell down and the spring of water dried up and the cave that he lived in collapsed so St. Paphnoute returned sorrowful.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               إستهوته حياة السياحة فأراد البقاء هناك ولكن القديس أنبا نوفير أعلمه أن ليست هذه مشيئة الله بالنسبة له، ولكن عليه أن يرجع إلى بريته ويخبر الإخوة بما رآه وسمعه لينتفع الرهبان وسالكي طريق الفضيلة. وفعلاً بعد نياحة أبى نوفير سقطت النخلة التى كان يقتات منها وجفت عين الماء وانهارت المغارة، فرجع القديس بفنوتيوس حزيناً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He persevered in the life of asceticism and worship and finally the angel of the Lord appeared to him and called upon him to depart to the eternal habitations. The brethren gathered around him and listened to many useful sayings from him then delivered up his pure soul.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وثابر القديس على حياة النسك والصلاة ، وأخيراً ظهر له ملاك الرب ودعاه للانطلاق إلى المظال الأبدية، فاجتمع حوله الإخوة وسمعوا منه أقوالاً نافعة، ثم فاضت روحه الطاهرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayer be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the Righteous Zechariah the Prophet the Son of Berechiah, the Son of Iddo</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد الصديق زكريا النبى بن براخيا بن عدو</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the righteous prophet Zechariah the Son of Berechiah, the Son of Iddo, one of the twelve Minor Prophets, was martyred. He was from the tribe of Levi, and was born in the land of Gilead. His father’s name was Berechiah who died young so the prophet was named after his grandfather Iddo.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى مثل هذا اليوم، استشهد الصديق زكريا النبى ابن براشيا بن عدو أحد الاثنى عشر نبياً الصغار، ولد هذا النبى فى أرض جلعاد، من سبط لاوى، اسم أبيه براشيا الذى مات شاباً، فسمى النبى باسم جده عدو.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was exiled to the land of the Chaldeans. In exile, he prophesied in the 8th month, in the second year of the reign of King Darius about the year 520 B.C. After the king had allowed the men of Judah to return to Jerusalem. The prophet’s message was centered on strengthening the frail determination of the people to behave with the spirit of godliness and rebuild the temple.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               سبى إلى أرض الكلدانيين وتنبأ هناك فى الشهر الثامن من السنة الثانية لملك داريوس نحو سنة 520 ق. م. بعد ان سمح الملك لرجال يهوذا بالعودة إلى اورشليم، فكانت رسالته تتركز على تشجيع عزائم الشعب الضعيفة ليسلكوا بروح التقوى ويعيدوا بناء الهيكل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He then uncovered the glorious future of Jesus Christ who emanated hope in them after the destruction of Jerusalem and the cities of Judah during the period of exile which lasted 70 years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم كشف المستقبل المجيد فى المسيح يسوع الذى يبعث فيهم الرجاء ، بعد خراب أورشليم ومدن يهوذا أثناء فترة السبى التى دامت سبعين عاماً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He also prophesied about the incarnation of the Word in the midst of Zion. He prophesied also about His triumphant entrance into Jerusalem , selling Him with thirty pieces of silver , the piercing of His hands and feet , the darkness during His crucifixion , piercing Him with the spear , the scattering of the disciples , and His sending of the Holy Spirit .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كما تنبأ عن تجسد الكلمة فى وسط صهيون ( زكريا 2 : 10) ، ودخوله أورشليم منتصراً ( زكريا 9 : 9) ، وبيعه بثلاثين من الفضة ( زكريا 11 : 12) ، وثقب يديه ( زكريا 13 : 6 ) ، وحدوث الظلمة ( زكريا 14 : 6) ، وطعنه بالحربة ( زكريا 12 : 10 ) ، وتشتت التلاميذ ( زكريا 13 : 7)، وإرسال الروح القدس ( زكريا 14 : 8 – 11).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Jews became angry from the admonishing of this prophet they conspired against him and slew him between the temple and the altar. As the Savior had told the scribes and the Pharisees, “that on you may come all the righteous bloodshed on the earth, from the blood of righteous Abel to the blood of Zechariah, son of Berechiah, whom you murdered between the temple and the altar .”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما اغتاظ اليهود من توبيخ هذا النبى تحالفوا عليه وقتلوه بين الهيكل والمذبح ، وبذلك يكون هو المقصود بقول المخلص للكتبة والفريسيين " لكى يأتى عليكم كل دم زكى سفك على الأرض من دم هابيل الصديق إلى دم زكريا بن براشيا الذى قتلتموه بين الهيكل والمذبح " ( مت 23 : 35 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات هذا النبى فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Anba Begoul (Pigol) the Priest</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد القديس أبا بيجول القس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also of the year 21 of the martyrs (305 A.D.) marks the martyrdom of St. Begoul (Pigol) the priest. This saint was born in Upper Egypt and for his piety and good conduct they ordained him a presbyter. His emphasis was on exhorting the people, teaching them, and confirming them in the faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 21 للشهداء ( 305 م )، استشهد القديس أبا بجول القس. ولد هذا القديس بصعيد مصر ، ولتقواه وسيرته الصالحة رسموه قساً، فاهتم بوعظ الشعب وتعليمه وتثبيته على الإيمان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he heard about the torment of the Christians, he went to Alexandria where he met his name ‘sake the saint Anba Begoul the soldier during his torture. They seized and handed him to the prefect Closianus who tortured then imprisoned him. When Armanius became the governor of Alexandria they brought St. Begoul the priest before him. He confessed the Lord Christ with conviction.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما سمع عن تعذيب المسيحيين مضى إلى الإسكندرية، وهناك التقى بسميه القديس أبا بجول الجندى أثناء تعذيبه، فقبضوا عليه وسلموه للوالى كلوسيانوس، فعذبه وأودعه السجن. ولما استلم أرمانيوس الولاية على الإسكندرية ، أوقفوا القديس أمامه ، فاعترف بالسيد المسيح وأظهر ثباتاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Henceforth, the governor ordered to scourge and severely tortures him which he endured with peace and serenity. The Lord performed some miracles by his hands which the governor attributed to witchcraft and told him, “O teacher of magic, why not abandon your witchcraft and worship the gods? For the One that you rely on cannot save you from my hands this time.” Armanius the governor ordered to crush him with the Hinbazeen and then placed him on an iron bed under which hot fire and finally ordered to behead him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               عندئذ أمر الوالى أن يُجلد ويعذب بشدة، فاحتمل ذلك بكل بهدوء وسكينة، وقد أجرى الله على يديه بعض المعجزات ، فنسبها الوالى للسحر وقال له " يا معلم السحرة أما تترك سحرك وتسجد للآلهه لأن الذى أنت متكل عليه لن يقدر ان يخلصك هذه المرة ". فأمر أرمانيوس الوالى أن يُعصر بالهنبازين ويوضع على سرير حديد تحته نار ، وأخيراً أمر بقطع رأسه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The saint said: “Now my joy has been completed and fulfilled my priesthood, for I have served the Lord for forty years for the sake of this hour.” The sword’s man came forward and beheads him thus he received the crown of martyrdom. A church after his name still exists in the village of Talah west of the city of el-Menia .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فقال القديس " الآن قد كمل فرحى وأتممت كهنوتى ، فلى اليوم أربعون سنة أخدم الرب لأجل هذه الساعة ". فتقدم السياف وقطع رأسه ونال إكليل الشهادة، ومازالت توجد كنيسة باسمه بقرية تلة غربى مدينة المنيا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Consecration of the First Church Dedicated for the Forty Martyrs of Sebaste</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تكريس أول كنيسة للأربعين شهيداً الذين استشهدوا فى سبسطية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the church celebrates the commemoration of the consecration of the church of the forty martyrs who were martyred in Sebaste by the hands of Emperor Licinius. It was the first church that had been built after their names where their bodies were located in Sebaste. St. Basil the Great consecrated it. He also wrote their biographies and established a great feast day for them on this day.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار تكريس بيعة الأربعين شهيداً الذين استشهدوا فى سبسطية على يد ليكينيوس قيصر. وهى أول كنيسة بُنيت على اسمهم وبها أجسادهم بسبسطية، وقام بتكريسها القدديس باسيليوس الكبير وثبت لهم عيداً عظيماً فى مثل هذا اليوم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.16">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Sixteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the sixteenth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Elizabeth, Mother of St. John the Baptist</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديسة أليصابات أم القديس يوحنا المعمدان</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the upright St. Elizabeth, mother of St. John the Baptist and the wife of Zacharias the priest, departed. This holy woman was born in Jerusalem to a righteous father called Matthan (Matthew) from the tribe of Levi and from the house of Aaron the priest. Her mother was a pious woman called Sofia.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تنيحت القديسة البارة أليصابات أم القديس يوحنا المعمدان وزوجة زكريا الكاهن. ولدت القديسة بأورشليم من أب بار اسمه متثات ( متى ) من سبط لاوى من نسل هارون وأم تقية اسمها صوفية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               There was a familial relation between her and the holy Virgin St. Mary for their mothers were related. The Holy Scriptures testified about her and her husband that: "They were both righteous before God, walking in all the commandments and ordinances of the Lord blameless ."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت بينها وبين القديسة العذراء مريم صلة قرابة من جهة والدتيهما. ويشهد الإنجيل المقدس عنها وعن زوجها أنهما كانا كلاهما " بارين أمام الله وسالكين فى جميع وصايا الرب وأحكامه بلا لوم" ( لو 1 : 6 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Elizabeth was barren; she and her husband constantly prayed and entreated God to give them an offspring. They persevered in supplicating God for many years until they became well advanced in age. God was slow in answering their prayers for a divine providence till the time that was appointed by God for the incarnation of the Lord Christ the Son of God the Logos. For St. John the Baptist, son of Zacharias and Elizabeth was the angel to prepare the way before Him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كانت أليصابات عاقراً وكانت تداوم مع زوجها على الصلاة والطلبة أمام الله لكى يرزقهما نسلاً وظلا على ذلك سنين طويلة حتى تقدما فى السن، وقد تباطأ الله عن إجابة طلبتهما لحكمة إلهية حتى يكمل الوقت المحدد من قبل الله لتجسد السيد المسيح إبن الله الكلمة ليكون يوحنا المعمدان ابن زكريا وأليصابات هو الملاك الذى يُهيىء الطريق قدامه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the fullness of time God sent His angel Gabriel to Zacharias to announce him with the conception of Elizabeth with John and the angel told him what would become of this saint. Elizabeth rejoiced along with her neighbors and relatives.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما جاء ملء الزمان أرسل الله ملاكه جبرائيل إلى زكريا فبشره بحبل أليصابات بيوحنا وأعلمه بما سيكون من أمر هذا القديس ففرحت أليصابات وفرح الجميع لها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Virgin St. Mary visited her to congratulate and serve her during her pregnancy in her old age. When she entered the house of Zacharias and greeted Elizabeth. And it happened, when Elizabeth heard the greeting of Mary that the babe leaped in her womb, and Elizabeth was filled with the Holy Spirit. Then she spoke out with a loud voice and said, “Blessed are you among women, and blessed is the fruit of your womb! But why is granted to me, that the mother of my Lord should come to me? For indeed as soon as the voice of your greeting sounded in my ears, the babe leaped in my womb for joy. Blessed is she who believed, for there will be a fulfillment of those things which were told her from the Lord. And Mary remained with her about three months, and returned to her house.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وزارتها العذراء مريم لتهنئها وتخدمها أثناء حبلها فى شيخوختها " فلما دخلت البيت وسلمت على أليصابات، فلما سمعت أليصابات سلام مريم إرتكض ( سجد ) الجنين بإبتهاج فى بطنها وامتلأت أليصابات من الروح القدس وصرخت بصوت عظيم وقالت مباركة أنت فى النساء ومباركة هى ثمرة بطنك، فمن أين لى هذا تاتى أم ربى إلَى، فهوذا حين صار صوت سلامك فى أذنى ارتكض الجنين بابتهاج فى بطنى فطوبى للتى آمنت أن يتم ما قيل لها من قبل الرب. فمكثت مريم عندها نحو ثلاثة أشهر ثم رجعت إلى بيتها " ( لو2 : 39 – 56 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Elizabeth full time came for her to be delivered and she brought forth a son. When her neighbors and relatives heard how the Lord had shown great mercy to her they rejoiced with her. The child was called John as was called by the angel.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تم زمانها لتلد ولدت ابناً وسمع جيرانها وأقرباؤها أن الرب عظم رحمته لها ففرحوا معها وسمى الطفل يوحنا كما تُسمى من الملاك.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Elizabeth completed her days, she departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكملت أيامها تنيحت بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Michael III, the 92nd Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا القديس ميخائيل الثالث البطريرك الثانى والتسعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1194 of the martyrs (1478 A.D.) Pope Michael III, the 92nd Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This Holy Father was born in Samalut, el-Minya governorate to Christian parents who taught him the Christian subjects. He longed for the monastic life, became a monk in one of the monasteries and lived a godly life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 1194 للشهداء ( 1478 م )، تنيح البابا القديس ميخائيل الثالث البطريرك الثانى والتسعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا القديس فى سمالوط بمحافظة المنيا من أبوين مسيحيين علماه العلوم المسيحية، فاشتاق إلى السيرة الرهبانية وترهب بأحد الأديرة، وسار سيرة فاضلة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of Pope Gabriel VI, the bishops and lay leaders (Archons) unanimously agreed to choose this monk for the patriarchate. He was consecrated on the 13th of Meshir, year 1193 of the martyrs (1477 A.D.). He did not last long on the apostolic throne but only one year and three days then departed in peace. He was buried with great honor in the church of the Virgin, Babylon el-Darag in Old Cairo.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد نياحة البابا غبريال السادس اجتمع الأساقفة والأرخنة وأتفقوا على إختيار هذا الراهب للبطريركية ورسموه فى 13 أمشير 1193 للشهداء ( 1477 م )، ولم يستمر على الكرسى المرقسى سوى سنة واحدة وثلاثة أيام فقط ثم تنيح بسلام ودُفن بإكرام جزيل فى كنيسة العذراء في بابلون الدرج بمصر القديمة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Hegumen Michael (Mikhael) el-Behairy, el Muharraqy</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس القمص ميخائيل البحيرى المحرقى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also of the year 1639 of the martyrs (1923 A.D.) marks the departure of the Hegumen Michael (Mikhael) el-Behairy, el Muharraqy. He was the disciple of the great saint Anba Abraam bishop of el-Fayyum and el-Giza.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 1639 للشهداء ( 1923 م ) تنيح القديس القمص ميخائيل البحيرى المحرقى وهو تلميذ القديس العظيم الأنبا أبرآم أسقف الفيوم والجيزة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Holy Father was born in the year 1847 A.D.in the city of Eshneen el-Nasarah. His parents were pious Christians who raised him in a true Christian upbringing that yielded a blessed fruit. He was called el-Behairy in reference to the name of his family (el-Beharrwah) for they were originally from el-Beheira governorate.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولد هذا القديس سنة 1847 م ببلدة اشنين النصارى ( قرية بمركز مغاغة محافظة المنيا)، من أبوين تقين ربياه تربية مسيحية حقيقية أثمرت ثمراً مباركاً وُسمى البحيرى نسبة إلى اسم عائلته ( البحاروة) لأن أصل العائلة من محافظة البحيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he was twelve years old, his father became seriously ill and was dying. His mother had compassion on him from seeing his father dead and the people crying and mourning over him, so she sent him to the house of a relative. While he was on the roof, he saw the spirit of his father ascending to heaven surrounded by luminous angels praising and singing hymns. He immediately recognized it and shouted saying; “My father … my father.” One of the angels told him ask and pray that your end would be like him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث وهو فى سن الثانية عشرة من عمره أن مرض والده مرض الموت، فاشفقت والدته عليه من أن ينظروالده ميتاً والناس يبكون عليه فأرسلته إلى بيت أحد الأقارب وبينما هو على سطح راى روح والده صاعدة إلى السماء وحولها ملائكة نورانيون يسبحون ويرنمون فعرفها فى الحال ونادى قائلاً " يا أبى..يا أبى " فقال له أحد الملائكة اطلب لكى تكون آخرتك كآخرته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During this period, he met a monk from el-Muharraq monastery whose name was the Hegumen Tawadros who always talked to him about the nobility of monasticism and the angelic life of the monks. Accordingly he passionately loved virginity and the monastic life which he practiced at home. Later on he went to el-Muharraq monastery and joined it during the time of the Hegumen Bolos el-Dalagawy el-Muharraqy who became later on the great saint Anba Abraam.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تعرف فى هذه الفترة على  راهب من دير المحرق اسمه القمص تاوضروس الذى كان يحدثه باستمرار عن سمو الرهبنة وحياة الرهبان الملائكية، فعشق البتولية والرهبنة وأخذ يتدرب عليها. بعد ذلك توجه إلى دير المحرق والتحق به فى عهد القمص بولس الدلجاوى المحرقى الذى أصبح بعد ذلك القديس العظيم الأنبا أبرآم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He remained in the monastery for a period as a novice and when the abbot of the monastery and the monks saw his meekness and obedience, he was ordained a monk by the name monk Michael (Mikhael). They handed him to a holy old monk called Hegumen Saleeb el-Owlwany to show him the path to the monastic life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ظل فى الدير مدة تحت الاختبار ولما رأى رئيس الدير والرهبان وداعته وطاعته تمت سيامته راهباً باسم الراهب ميخائيل وسلموه إلى شيخ قديس يدعى القمص صليب العلوانى ليعلمه طريق الرهبنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The monk Mikhael grew in piety and asceticism, and everyone loved him. He was ordained a priest in the year 1874 A.D. then Hegumen. Later on he became a father of confession and spiritual guide to all the monks of the monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               نما الراهب ميخائيل فى الفضيلة والنسك فأحبه الجميع ورسموه قساً سنة 1874 م ثم قمصاً وصار بعد ذلك أب اعتراف ومرشداً روحياً لجميع رهبان الدير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               God granted him the gift of healing the infirm, many sought his prayers and God was glorified through his healing hands. This saint became well known for the virtue of giving and compassion to the needy as his teacher the great saint Anba Abraam. He offered them from the little he had with love and contentment. In the later part of his life he lost his vision however he thanked God and persisted on praying.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأعطاه الله نعمة شفاء الأمراض فقصده كثيرون فكان الله يتمجد على يديه بشفائهم. واشتهر هذا القديس بفضيلة العطاء والرحمة على المساكين مثل معلمه القديس العظيم الأنبا أبرآم فكان يقدم لهم من القليل الذى عنده عن حب ورضى.   حدث فى آخر حياته فقد بصره ولكنه كان يشكر الله ويداوم على الصلاة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After a life full of righteous deeds, holiness, asceticism, compassion, purity and after he practiced and taught by his sayings and deeds, he reposed in the Lord. His age was 76 years old, twenty years in the world and 56 years in the monastery spent in hard monastic struggle elevated him to the rank of the saints.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد حياة حافلة بأعمال البر والقداسة والزهد والرحمة والعفة. وبعد أن عمل وعلم بأقواله وأفعاله رقد في الرب وكان عمره وقتئذ ٧٦ سنة قضى منها ٢٠ سنة في العالم و ٥٦ سنة في جهاد رهباني شاق رفعه الي مصاف القديسين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               At the time of his departure, one of the Ethiopian older monks, residing in the monastery, saw his pure spirit ascending to heaven accompanied by angels while singing and praising God. In the feast of his repose, year 1707 of the martyrs (1991 A.D.) and during the papacy of Pope Shenouda III, the 117th Patriarch of Alexandria, his relics was uncovered with great veneration in the presence of 14 bishops. His body was placed in a special shrine in the monastery for the Christ loving people to receive his blessings.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وعند نياحته رأى أحد الشيوخ الرهبان الأحباش المقيمين بالدير روحه الطاهرة صاعدة إلى السماء تصاحبها الملائكة الأطهار وهم يرتلون ويسبحون الله.  وفى عيد نياحته سنة 1707 للشهداء ( 1991 م ) وفى حبرية قداسة البابا شنودة الثالث البطريرك 117، تم إخراج رفات القديس بكرامة عظيمة وبحضور أربعة عشر أسقفاً، وتم وضعه فى مقصورة خاصة بالدير ليتبارك منه الشعب المحب للمسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.17">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Seventeenth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the seventeenth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Mina the Monk</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس مينا الراهب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day St. Mina the monk was martyred. This saint was born in Akhmim to Christian parents. His father worked in farming. His parents raised him in a true Christian upbringing. Since his youth, his heart was inclined to renounce the world. When he grew, became a monk in one of the monasteries of Akhmim.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم استشهد القديس مينا الراهب. ولد هذا القديس بإحدى بلاد أخميم من أبوين مسيحيين وكانت مهنة والده هي الفلاحة.رباه والداه تربية مسيحية حقيقية، ومنذ حداثته مال قلبه إلى زهد العالم فلما كبر ترهب بأحد أديرة أخميم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               For a period of time, he dwelt there in asceticism and worship. Then he went to el-Ashmunain and resided there in a monastery and did not leave it for 16 years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأقام مدة فى النسك والعبادة ثم انتقل إلى بلاد الأشمونين وأقام هناك فى دير لم يغادره لمدة ست عشر سنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Arabs ruled the country, the saint heard that they resisted and denied the doctrine of the divine incarnation. He took permission from the abbot of the monastery and went to el-Ashmunain. He came before the Arab captain of the soldiers and debated that with him. The saint explained to the captain the validity of his faith and the necessity of the incarnation of the Word of God for the salvation of the world. The son-ship of the Son is not through parental procreation but a son-ship of a special kind as the light proceeds from the Sun.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما دخل العرب مصر وسمع أنهم يقاومون عقيدة التجسد الإلهى، نزل إلى الأشمونين وتقدم إلى قائد الجند وتناقشا فى هذا الأمر وبين للقائد صحة إيمانه بضرورة تجسد الله الكلمة لخلاص العالم وأن بنوية الابن ليست عن طريق التناسل، لكنها بنوة من نوع خاص مثل ولادة النور من قرص الشمس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The captain became enraged and ordered his soldiers to cut the saint into pieces and to throw him into the river thus he received the crown of martyrdom. The believers gathered the pieces of his pure body, shrouded and buried it with great honor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فغضب القائد وأمر جنوده فقطعوه إرباً إرباً وألقوه فى النهر، فنال إكليل الشهادة وجمع المؤمنون أجزاء جسده الطاهرة وكنفوه ودفنوه بإكرام جزيل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Consecration of the Church of St. Castor of Bardanouha</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تكريس كنيسة القديس قسطور البردنوهى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the Consecration of the Church of the martyr St. Castor of Bardanouha. This saint was martyred in Alexandria and when his body arrived to his hometown Bardanouha, all the people went out to receive him. They carried his body with great veneration to his house. After the end of the persecution, they changed his home to a church after his name and was consecrated on this day. Until present time there is a church in Bardanouha after his name.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تم تكريس كنيسة القديس قسطور البردنوهى الذى أُستشهد بالإسكندرية وعند وصول جسده إلى بلده بردنوها ( قرية بمركز بنى مزار محافظة المنيا) خرج الشعب كله لاستقباله فحملوا جسده بإكرام عظيم إلى بيته. وبعد انتهاء الاضطهاد حولوا بيته إلى كنيسة على اسمه وكرسوها فى مثل هذا اليوم ، ومازالت حتى الآن توجد فى بردنوها كنيسة باسمه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.18">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eighteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eighteenth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Malatius the Confessor, Patriarch of Antioch</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس ملاتيوس المُعترف بطريرك أنطاكية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 381 A.D., St. Malatius the Confessor, Patriarch of Antioch, departed. He was consecrated a bishop for Sebaste in the year 357 A.D. He left it because of the rudeness and harshness of its people and lived in solitude nearby the City of Halab in Syria. In the year 360 A.D., he was chosen a patriarch for Antioch.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 318 م تنيح القديس ملاتيوس المُعترف بطريرك أنطاكية. رُسم أسقفاً على سبسطية سنة 357 م ، ولقساوة شعبها تركها وإنفرد قرب مدينة حلب بالشام، وفى سنة 360 م انتخبوه بطريركاً على أنطاكية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was firm in resisting the Arians. When Emperor Constantius, who was Arian, heard that, he exiled him in the same year of his enthronement. The bishops, priests and people convened and wrote to the Emperor asking for the return of their Patriarch.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فظل يقاوم الأريوسيين ، فلما سمع الملك قسطنديون وكان أريوسياً، نفاه عن كرسيه فى نفس سنة تنصيبه. فاجتمع الأساقفة والكهنة والشعب وكتبوا إلى الملك يطلبون رجوع بطريركهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Emperor responded to their request and brought St. Malatius back in the year 362 A.D., he did not cease resisting the Arians. He persisted in teaching the people the true Orthodox faith according to the faith of the council of Nicea. Therefore the emperor exiled him again. In exile, all the exiled Orthodox faithful gathered around him, encouraging and supporting each other. He sent to his flock pastoral epistles to confirm them in the Orthodox faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">                فاستجاب لمطلبهم وأعاده إليهم سنة 362 م، ولكنه بعد رجوعه لم يكف عن مقاومة الأريوسيين معلماً الشعب الإيمان الأرثودكسى السليم حسب أيمان مجمع نيقية، فنفاه الملك مرة ثانية. وفى نفس المنفى اجتمع إليه كل المنفيين من الأرثوذكس يشجعون بعضهم بعضاً وكان يرسل إلى شعبه رسائل رعوية يثبتهم بها على الإيمان الأرثودكسى النيقوي المستقيم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He remained in exile for many years then returned to Antioch in the year 378 A.D. He attended the universal Council of Constantinople in the year 381 A.D. When he finished his good endeavor departed in peace. St. John Chrysostom (Golden Mouthed) praised St. Malatius declaring his greatness and stature for what he suffered from exile and humiliation for the sake of the Orthodox faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أقام فى المنفى سنين كثيرة ثم عاد إلى أنطاكية سنة 378 م ، وشهد مجمع القسطنطينية المسكونى سنة 381 م ثم تنيح بسلام ، وقد مدحه القديس يوحنا ذهبى الفم مبيناً عظمة مقداره وإحتماله الآلام من أجل الثبات على العقيدة والإيمان المستقيم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Consecration of the Church of St. Paul the Simple</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the consecration of the church of St. Paul the simple, one of the disciples of the great saint Anba Antonius, father of all monks. Paul (Bolos) was a simple farmer from the city of Atfeeh. He got married when he was advanced in age to a young girl.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day he went home and caught his wife in the act. He left the house and went to the saint Anba Antonius to be a monk under his guidance and become his pupil. Anba Antonius tried to dissuade him from his determination for his old age and the difficulties of the path of monasticism. When he saw his firm determination, he tested him with difficult examinations and hard tests that he successfully passed them all.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he saw his perseverance, he accepted him. He commended him to establish for himself a cell nearby him. He lived close to him as            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               an obedient disciple in spite of his old age. Because of his simplicity, asceticism and his struggle, God granted him the gift of casting out evil spirits and revealing the thoughts of men.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.19">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Nineteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the nineteenth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع عشر من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Relocation of the Relics of St. Martianus the Monk to Antioch</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار نقل أعضاء القديس مرتيانوس الراهب إلى أنطاكية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the church commemorates the relocation of the relics of St. Martianus the monk from Athens to Antioch. He was a monk in Antioch and before the end of his life he went to Athens and departed there.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار نقل أعضاء القديس مرتيانوس الراهب إلى إنطاكية. كان راهباً فى أنطاكية وفى نهاية حياته ذهب إلى أثينا وتنيح هنا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When St. Demetrius was enthroned Patriarch of Antioch, he took on the endeavor of relocating the relics of St. Martianus to Antioch. He sent priests to Athens who carried the pure body with great veneration to Antioch. He placed the body in a sarcophagus for the people to receive his blessings.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما جلس القديس ديمتريوس بطريركاً على أنطاكية اهتم بنقل جسد القديس مرتيانوس إلى أنطاكية، فأرسل كهنة إلى أثينا وحملوا الجسد الطاهر إلى أنطاكية بإكرام وتبجيل عظيمين حيث وضعه البطريرك فى تابوت ليتبارك منه الشعب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.20">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twentieth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم العشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twentieth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم العشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Peter II, 21st Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا القديس بطرس الثانى البطريرك الحادى والعشرين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 95 of the martyrs (379 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Peter II, 21st Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This saint was born in Alexandria and was the successor of St. Athanasius the apostolic who was his teacher.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم سنة 95  للشهداء ( 379 م ) تنيح البابا القديس بطرس الثانى البطريرك الحادى والعشرين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا القديس فى مدينة الإسكندرية وتتلمذ على البابا أتناسيوس الرسولى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He followed his teacher in his holiness and was refined with his knowledge. When his teacher saw his advancement in godliness, he ordained him a priest and later on ordained him a bishop. Pope Athanasius sent him to Syria to join St Basil the great in resisting some of the heresies that spread there.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فتمثل بقداسته وتهذب بعلمه ولما رأى معلمه نموه فى الفضيلة رسمه قساً وبعد ذلك رسمه أسقفاً وأرسله إلى سوريا للاشتراك مع القديس باسيليوس الكبير فى مقاومة بعض البدع التى انتشرت هناك.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Athanasius felt that his departure drew near, he commended that his disciple Anba Peter succeed him. After the departure of Pope Athanasius, they consecrated him Patriarch in the year 373 A.D. for what he portrayed from godliness and knowledge.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما شعر البابا أتناسيوس بقرب نياحته أوصى أن يخلفه تلميذه الأنبا بطرس، ولما تنيح البابا أتناسيوس الرسولى أقاموا الأنبا بطرس بطريركاً سنة 373 م نظراً لما اتصف به من الفضيلة والعلم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He struggled against the Arians as he learned from his teacher Pope Athanasius. He suffered many hardships from the Arians, who tried many times, to slay him. He had to disappear for two years for the Arians appointed an illegitimate patriarch; nevertheless the people did not accept him. They brought back their father Pope Peter to his throne and he resumed his resistance against the Arians.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وجاهد ضد الأريوسيين كما تعلم من معلمه القديس أتناسيوس.  وقد قاسى شدائد كثيرة من الأريوسيين الذين حاولوا قتله مراراً كثيرة. إختفى لمدة سنين فأقام الأريوسيون بطريركاً غير شرعى غير أن الشعب لم يقبله وأعادوا أباهم البابا بطرس إلى كرسيه فعاود مقاومته للأريوسيين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he finished his good endeavor, the Lord willed to repose him from the toil of this world, departed in peace and went to the heavenly church of the first born.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح أراد الرب أن يريحه من أتعاب هذا العالم فتنيح بسلام ومضى إلى كنيسة الأبكار السمائية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the Saints, Basil, Theodore and Timothy in Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسين باسليوس وثاؤدروس وتيموتاوس بالإسكندرية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the saints Basil, Theodore and Timothy, were martyred in the City of Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً أستشهد القديسون باسليوس وثاؤدوروس وتيموتاوس بمدينة الإسكندرية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Septimius Severus incited the persecution against the Christians many were martyred at his hands in all parts of Egypt. He imprisoned many so the prisons became churches for they heard from them voices of prayers and praises.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وذلك عندما أثار الإمبراطور سبتموس ساويرس الاضطهاد على المسيحيين وأستشهد كثيرون على يديه فى كل بلاد مصر وسجن كثيرين فتحولت السجون إلى كنائس تُسمع فيها أصوات التسبيح والصلوات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               These three saints came forward and declared their faith in the Lord Christ and received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فتقدم هؤلاء الثلاثة القديسون وأعلنوا إيمانهم بالسيد المسيح ونالوا أكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.21">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-First Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الحادى والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-first day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الحادى والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Virgin St. Mary, the Theotokos</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار القديسة العذراء مريم والدة الإله</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The church celebrates on this day the monthly commemoration of the pure Lady St. Mary the Virgin, the Mother of God through whom was the salvation of Adam and his offspring.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تعيد الكنيسة اليوم بالعيد الشهرى لوالدة الإله القديسة مريم العذراء التى منها كان الخلاص لآدم وذريته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Her holy intercession be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة شفاعتها المقدسة فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Onesimus, the Disciple of the Apostle St. Paul</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس أنسيموس تلميذ القديس بولس الرسول</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also St. Onesimus , the disciple of the apostle St. Paul, was martyred. He was a slave owned by St. Philemon who was from the prominent Christians of Colosse.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى مثل هذا اليوم استشهد أنسيموس تلميذ القديس بولس الرسول. وترجمة اسمه تعنى (نافع). وقد كان عبداً للقديس فليمون الذى كان من المسيحيين البارزين فى كولوسى. (هو تلميذ القديس بولس الرسول ، وقد أقامه الآباء الرسل أسقفاً على كولوسى)            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The devil enticed Onesimus’ heart, led him to steal money from his master and fled to Rome. There he heard about the apostle St. Paul. He believed, repented and was baptized at his hands. He served with him as a deacon then sent him back to Colosse. He sent with him an epistle to St. Philemon asking him to accept Onesimus no longer as a slave but as a beloved brother. St. Tychicus accompanied him on this journey. After he received the forgiveness of his master, he returned to Rome.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أغرى الشيطان قلب أنسيموس ، فسرق أموالاً  من سيده فليمون وهرب إلى روما. وهناك سمع عن القديس بولس الرسول ، فتاب واعتمد على يديه. ثم خدم معه شماساً. وأرسله القديس بولس ثانية إلى كولوسى ومعه رسالة إلى القديس فليمون يطلب منه فيها أن يقبل أنسيموس لا كعبد بل كأخ، وكان مرافقاً له فى هذه الرحلة القديس تيخيكس (كولوسى 4 : 9). وبعد أن نال السماح من سيده عاد إلى روما.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               According to tradition, St. Onesimus later on became the bishop of Berea. After the martyrdom of St. Paul and by the order of the emperor they seized St. Onesimus and exiled him to one of the islands where he taught and baptized its people. When the ruler of the island heard that, he scourged him and ordered to break his legs so he departed and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ويقول التقليد أن القديس أنسيموس أصبح فيما بعد أسقفاً على بيريه ، وبعد استشهاد القديس بولس الرسول ، قُبض على القديس أنسيموس بأمر الإمبراطور ونُفى إلى إحد الجزائر وهناك صار يعلم ويعمد الناس، فلما سمع حاكم الجزيرة بذلك ضربه وأمر بكسر ساقيه، فتنيح ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Gabriel I, 57th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا القديس غبريال الأول البطريرك السابع والخمسين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 636 of the martyrs (920 A.D.) the saintly father Pope Gabriel I, the 57th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. He was born in the village of el-Mayah. He became a monk in the monastery of St. Macarius the great. He loved solitary life and wept much while praying, asking the Lord to save him from the snares of the devil.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 636 للشهداء ( 920 م ) تنيح البابا القديس غبريال الأول البطريرك السابع والخمسين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية.   ولد هذا القديس بقرية الميه (الماى: تابعة لشبين الكوم – محافظة المنوفية)، وترهب بدير القديس مكاريوس الكبير، وكان محباً للانفراد كثير البكاء، طالباً من الله أن ينجيه من مكائد الشيطان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the fame of his virtues became well known, he was chosen patriarch. He was enthroned on the 21st of Pashons, year 625 of the martyrs (909 A.D.) He cared a great deal for the church affairs, and the patriarchal duties did not prevent him from his worship and asceticism.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما ذاع صيته وفضله ، اختاروه بطريركاً ورُسم يوم 21 بشنس 625 للشهداء ( 909 م). فأخذ يهتم بشئون الكنيسة، ولم تعطله مهام البطريركية عن عبادته ونسكه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He spent most of his days in the wilderness and he fought against the flesh and the devil by increasing fasting, watching, prayers and humility. He persevered in this manner of worship, struggling and preaching for 11 years, then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان يقضى أغلب الأيام فى البرية، وكان يجاهد ضد الجسد والشيطان بالإكثار من الصوم والسهر والصلاة والتواضع. وظل على هذه الحال عابداً ومجاهداً وواعظاً إحدى عشرة سنة ثم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Zacharias, Bishop of Sakha</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس زخارياس أسقف سخا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also marks the departure of St. Zacharias, Bishop of Sakha. He was the son of a scribe called John who left his position and was chosen for the priesthood. He raised his son Zacharias on the Orthodox faith, studying the church and secular subjects.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفية أيضاً تنيح القديس زخارياس أسقف سخا ، هذا القديس كان ابناً لكاتب يدعى يوحنا ، ترك وظيفته وأُختير قساً ، فربى ابنه زخارياس على الإيمان المستقيم مع العلوم الكنسية والأدبية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he grew up, the Muslim ruler (El-Wazeer) appointed him a scribe in his cabinet. Afterward he agreed with a friend called Ptolemy who was the prefect of the town of Sakha, to leave their work, go to the wilderness to become monks. That coincided with the coming of a monk from the monastery of St. John Colobos (the Short), so they decided to go with him to his monastery. When the ruler (El-Wazeer) knew that, he prevented them. However they left in secret, walking to the wilderness, without knowing their way. They met on their way, by the will of God, a monk who took them to the monastery of St. John (Yehness). When their friends knew that, they took a letter from the Governor to bring them back, but the Lord dispersed their counsel.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما كبر عينه الوزير كاتباً بديوانه . وبعد ذلك اتفق مع صديق له اسمه أبلاطس كان والياً على سخا، أن يتركا عملهما ويذهبا إلى البرية للرهبنة. واتفق حضور أحد رهبان دير القديس يحنس القصير فعزما على أن يذهبا معه إلى ديره، فعلم الوالى بذلك ومنعهما. فخرجا خفية وسارا إلى البرية دون أن يعرفا الطريق، فقابلهما أحد الرهبان وصحبهما إلى دير القديس يحنس، فلما علم أصدقاؤهما أخذوا من الوالى كتاباً ليرجعوهما، فبدد الرب مشورتهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               As for Zacharias and his friend, they put on the garb of the monks and exerted themselves in much worship. That was during the time of the saints Abba Gawargah (George) and Abba Abraham who were the best guides for them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أما زخارياس وصديقه فلبسا الثوب الرهبانى وأجهدا نفسيهما فى عبادات كثيرة. وكان ذلك فى أيام القديسيين أبرآم وجاورجى ( من قديسى برية شيهيت فى القرن السابع الميلادى )، اللذين كانا خير مرشد لهما.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Bishop of Sakha departed, the people wrote to the father, the Patriarch, asking to consecrate the monk Zacharias a bishop for them. He brought him and ordained him against his will.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تنيح أسقف سخا، كتب الشعب إلى البابا البطريرك يطلبون رسامة الراهب زخارياس أسقفاً عليهم، فاستحضره ورسمه أسقفاً رغماً عنه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This father directed his interest to visiting his flock, exhorting and teaching them. He wrote many commentaries, exhortations, sermons and discourses. He remained on his throne for 30 years, and then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فاهتم هذا الأب بافتقاد شعبه ووعظه وتعليمه، كما وضع مقالات وميامر كثيرة، وأقام على الكرسى ثلاثين عاماً، ثم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.22">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Second Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثاني والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-second day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثاني والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Maruta (Marouta) the Bishop</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس ماروتا أسقف ميافرقين (من بلاد ما بين النهرين شمالى نصيبين)</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day St. Maruta, the bishop of Mia-Farkain, from the countries between the two rivers (Mesopotamia), departed. St. Maruta was a knowledgeable and righteous man.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               – فى مثل هذا اليوم تنيح القديس ماروتا أسقف ميافرقين من بلاد ما بين النهرين. كان ماروتا فاضلاً عالماً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Emperor Theodosius, the great, sent him to Shapur, king of Persia, to negotiate with him the conditions of the truce that they wanted both to sign. King Shapur welcomed him and housed him in a royal palace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أوفده الملك ثاؤدوسيوس الكبير إلى سابور ملك الفرس لمفاوضته فى أمر الهدنة التى كانا يرغبان فى توقيعها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When St. Maruta knew that the king had an infirm daughter, he asked to bring her to him. He prayed over her and she was healed and the King exceedingly rejoiced. When Maruta found favor in the sight of the king, he asked the King to give him the relics of the saints who were martyred in Persia. The saint collected the relics for which he built a church and a great wall around it. Later on, a city was built inside the wall, which was named Maruta.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما وصل إلى هناك علم أن للملك ابنة مريضة فطلب إحضارها إليه وصلى عليها فشُفيت ففرح الملك بذلك، فلما وجد ماروتا نعمة فى عينى الملك طلب منه أجساد القديسين الذين استشهدوا فى بلاد فارس فجمع الأجساد وبنى لها كنيسة وسوراً كبيراً حولها وفيما بعد بُنيت مدينة داخل هذا السور سُميت باسم ( ماروتا).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the saint had finished his good strife departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد أن أكمل جهاده الحسن تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.23">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Third Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-third day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Eusebius, Son of Basilides the Vizier</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس أوسابيوس ابن القديس واسيليدس الوزير</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 19 of the martyrs (303 A.D.), St. Eusebius, son of Basilides the vizier, was martyred.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 19 للشهداء 303م إستشهد القديس أوسابيوس ابن القديس واسيليدس الوزير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint was one of the great generals of the Roman army who fought in the war against the Persians. During the war, Diocletian abandoned the faith of the Lord Christ and worshiped the idols. When Eusebius returned after the end of the war and knew that, he agreed with his relatives, Abadir, Yustus, Ekladius, and Theodore (Tadros) to confess their faith in the Lord Christ before him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . كان هذا القديس أحد ضباط الجيش الذى يحارب ضد الفرس. وأثناء الحرب ارتد دقلديانوس عن الإيمان بالسيد المسيح وعبد الأوثان، ولما رجع أوسابيوس بعد الحرب علم بذلك فاتفق هو وأقاربه يسطس وإقلاديوس وأبادير وتادرس على أن يعترفوا أمامه بالسيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the emperor proposed for them to worship his idols, they all refused. The emperor exiled Eusebius to Egypt to be tortured there. He sent him to the governor of Qift (Coptos), who inflicted upon him many tortures; with the Hinbazeen, dismembered him and by beating him severely. However the angel of the Lord healed, strengthened and comforted him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما عرض عليهم الملك عبادة الأوثان، رفضوا، فقام الملك بنفى أوسابيوس إلى مصر لتعذيبه هناك، حيث قام الوالى بتعذيبه بالهنبازين وتقطيع الأعضاء والضرب الشديد، وكان ملاك الرب يشفيه ويقويه ويعزيه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He saw in the vision of the night, paradise, the mansions of the saints, and the place that had been prepared personally for him and his soul was consoled.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم راى فى رؤيا الليل الفردوس والأماكن المعدة للقديسين والمكان المعد له هو شخصياً فتعزت نفسها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Later on, the Governor ordered to burn him in a fiery furnace prepared for him outside the City of Ahnas (Hnes). The angel of the Lord came down and put out the fire and took St. Eusebius out safely. Finally, the Governor ordered to behead him and he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بعد ذلك أمر الوالى بإحراقه فى أتون نار أقامه له خارج مدينة اهناس ( هي مدينة اهناسيا الحالية وهى مدينة بمحافظة بنى سويف )، فخرج ملاك الرب وأطفأ اللهيب وأخرج القديس سالماً. أخيراً أمر الوالى بقطع رأسه فنال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.24">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Fourth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-fourth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Agapetus the Bishop</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس أغابيطوس الأسقف</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 52 of the martyrs (336 A.D.) St. Agapetus, bishop of Synnada, Phrygia, departed. He was born in Cappadocia to Christian parents. His parents raised him up on godliness and piety. When he grew, he served the hermits and learned from them, worship and asceticism.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 52 للشهداء ( 336 م )، تنيح القديس أغابيطوس الأسقف سينادا فى فريجية. وُلد القديس أغابيطوس فى بلاد الكبادوك من والدين مسيحيين فربياه على البر والتقوى، ولما كبر كان يخدم النساك ويتعلم منهم العبادة والتقشف.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               That was during the time of the infidel emperor Diocletian. Agapetus went to one of the monasteries where he became a monk. When Licinius the governor heard of him, he brought him by force and enlisted him a soldier in the army. This did not prevent him from continuing in his ascetic life and worship rather he greatly increased in his godliness.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان ذلك فى أيام دقلديانوس الجاحد. فلما سمع الوالى بالقديس أغابيطوس إستحضره كرهاً وعينه جندياً فى الجيش ، فلم يمنعه هذا من استمراره فى النسك والعبادة بل ازداد فى الفضيلة .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Shortly after, Diocletian perished and Constantine the great reigned. When he knew his account, he released him and the saint returned to the place of his asceticism and worship.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما مات دقلديانوس وملك الإمبراطور قسطنطين الكبير وعرف قصته أطلق سراحه فرجع إلى مكان نسكه وعبادته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The bishop of Synnada heard about him. He brought him and appointed him as his assistant then ordained him a priest. The saint was greatly dedicated in serving the people. When the bishop of Synnada departed, the people choose him as his successor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               سمع به أسقف سينادا فاستدعاه وجعله معاوناً له ورسمه قساً فأخذ يتفانى فى خدمة الشعب، ولما تنيح أسقف سينادا اختاره الشعب خلفاُ له.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He manifested a fiery zeal in shepherding and serving the souls. He persevered in exhorting and teaching his flock. He also took great interest for caring for the poor and needy. The Lord performed by his hands many splendid signs. When he completed his good endeavor, he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فأظهر غيرة نارية فى الرعاية وخدمة النفوس ودأب على الوعظ والتعليم، كما اهتم بالفقراء والمساكين، فأجرى الله على يديه آيات باهرة. ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Timothy and St. Matthias</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديسين تيموتاوس بمدينة غزة ومتياس بمدينة قوص</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the martyrdom of St. Timothy of Gaza, and St. Matthias of the City of Quos.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً استشهد القديسان تيموتاوس من غزة ومتياس من قوص.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.25">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Fifth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-fifth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Sts. Philemon, Apphia, and their Son Archippus</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديسين فليمون وأبفية وأرخبس ابنهما</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 65 A.D. Sts. Philemon, his wife Apphia, and their son Archippus were martyred. They were native of Colosse capital of Phrygia in Asia Minor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 65 م استشهد القديسون فليمون وزوجته ابفية وابنهما أرخبس. هؤلاء كانوا من أهل فريجية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They believed in the Lord Christ at the hands of the apostle St. Paul. They participated with him in the missionary ministry.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وآمنوا بالسيد المسيح على يد القديس بولس الرسول عندما كان يُكرز هناك.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Our teacher St. Paul sent an epistle to St. Philemon included the apostolic greetings to all his family members and the love of the apostle to his friend Philemon. The apostle appealed to him to accept Onesimus, the thief and fugitive slave after he had repented at the hands of St. Paul. Philemon received the epistle with joy and accepted his slave Onesimus as a brother and not as a slave as the apostle Paul commended.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد أرسل القديس بولس برسالة إلى رب الأسرة القديس فليمون، تضمنت السلام الرسولى لكل أفراد الأسرة ( فليمون: 1 – 3 )، ومحبة الرسول لصديقه (فليمون: 4 – 7 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The fathers the apostles consecrated him bishop for Colosse. After he had served his people with righteousness and purity the heathen seized him and his family. They scourged him severely then placed them in a pit and stoned them until they delivered their spirits in the hand of Christ whom they loved and served, thus they received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أثار نيرون الاضطهاد على المسيحيين بسبب حريق روما، هجم الوثنيون بعد الاحتفال بعيد الآلهة ديانا، على الكنيسة بفريجية وقت الصلاة، فقبضوا على القديس فليمون وأسرته، وجلدوهم بعنف ثم وضعوهم فى حفرة ورجموهم، فنالوا أكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Quona, in the City of Rome</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس قونا بمدينة روما. ( أو الشماس قزماس بروما )</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also St. Quona was martyred in the City of Rome. He was born to Christian parents who raised him with a spiritual ecclesiastical upbringing.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً استشهد القديس قونا بمدينة روما.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he grew his parents wed him against his will. When he was alone with his bride, he put the light that was in the room off then he lit it again. He asked his bride what is better the light or the darkness? She replied the light is better. Then he started to talk to her about the Lord Christ the light of the world. The words of grace touched her heart and they lived with each other as brother and sister in complete celibacy.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They devoted themselves to fasting, prayer and serving. He guided many from his city to the faith of Christ. The Lord also granted him the gift of performing miracles and casting evil spirits out.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When a heathen governor ruled, he pursued the Christians and tortured them. He seized Quona and scourged him until his flesh was torn. When he saw the steadfastness of his faith, he beheaded him with the sword, and so he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Mina, in the City of Quos</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس مينا بمدينة قوص</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also marks the Martyrdom of St. Mina, in the City of Quos.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً استشهد القديس مينا بمدينة قوص.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Abu-Fana in Mount Delga</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس أبو فانا بجبل دلجا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Also on this day was the departure of St. Abu-Fana in mount Delga during the reign of Emperor Theodosius the great.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً تنيح الأب القديس أبو فانا فى أيام الإمبراطور ثيؤدوسيوس الكبير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint was born to pious Christian parents who raised him in the fear of God and keeping His commandments. He grew loving the solitary life, contemplation and being merciful to the poor and the needy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولد هذا القديس من أبوين مسيحيين تقيين، ربياه فى مخافة الله وحفظ وصاياه. فنشأ محباً لحياة الخلوة والتأمل والرحمة بالفقراء والمساكين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He became a monk in his youth in one of the monasteries of el-Ashmunain. He practiced the acetic life along with manual work. He sold the work of his hands, ate with a portion of it and contributed the rest to the poor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               .ترهب فى شبابه فى أحد أديرة الأشمونين، وتدرب على الحياة النسكية مع العمل اليدوى، فكان يبيع عمل يديه حيث يأكل بجزء منه ويتصدق بالباقى للفقراء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He increased in his worship, asceticism and his love for the brethren. He longed for the solitary life to spend a greater time with the Lord Christ. He took the permission of the abbot of the monastery and dwelt in a cave in the western desert west of the village of Abu-Sair. God granted him a spring of water to drink from.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وإزداد فى العبادة والنسك ومحبة الإخوة ، ثم اشتاق أن ينفرد ليجد فرصة أكبر مع ربه ومسيحه، فاستأذن رئيس الدير وانطلق وسكن فى مغارة فى الصحراء الغربية غرب قرية " أبو صير " وقد وهبه الله ينبوع ماء ليشرب منه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The saint fasted daily till evening during summer and two days at a time in the winter along with many prayers and prostrations until his skin cleaved to his bones and looked like burnt wood.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان القديس يصوم يومياً حتى المساء فى الصيف، وفى الشتاء كان يصوم يومين يومين مع صلوات كثيرة وميطانيات حتى لصق جلده بعظمه، وصار كخشبة محروقة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In spite of his love for solitary life, he did not shut his heart toward his brothers. His dwelling became a spiritual shinning center. All the monks came to receive his guidance. The Lord also granted him the gift of performing miracles and signs.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ورغم محبته للوحدة لكنه لم يغلق قلبه عن إخوته، فتحول مسكنه إلى مركز إشعاع روحى، فكان الرهبان يأتون ليأخذوا منه الإرشاد، كما وهبه الله أن يعمل المعجزات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the hour of his departure drew near, the angel of the Lord informed him that he would depart from this world. He asked the priest of the area to bring the Holy Mysteries to him. He partook of Them standing on his feet which were swollen from standing often. He bid his brothers farewell, blessed them while asking for their prayers, then delivered his pure spirit. The fathers shrouded, and buried him with great honor. A monastery was built after his name nearby in the village of Bani-Khaled. The monastery of Abu-Fana is still located in the wilderness west of the city of Mallawy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لما قربت ساعة نياحته، أعلمه ملاك الرب بأنه سينتقل من هذا العالم فطلب من الأب كاهن المنطقة أن يناوله من الأسرار المقدسة، فتناول منها واقفاً على قدميه اللتين تورمتا من كثرة الوقوف وودع الإخوة وباركهم طالباً صلواتهم عنه. ثم فاضت روحه الطاهرة. فكفنه الآباء ودفنوه بإكرام عظيم. وقد بُنى دير على اسمه بجوار قرية بنى خالد (ما زال دير أبو فانا موجوداً فى الصحراء غربى مدينة ملوى) .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.26">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Sixth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-sixth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Righteous Hosea, the Prophet</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة الصديق هوشع النبى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, the great prophet Hosea, one of the twelve minor prophets of Israel, departed. He was born in the mountain of Ephraim, the son of Beeri. He prophesied during the days of Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz and Hezekiah, kings of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam, the son of Joash, King of Israel. (Hosea 1:1) He was also contemporary to the prophets Isaiah, Amos and Micah. He prophesied for seventy years. This prophet was also contemporary to the Assyrian exile of Israel in the year 722 B.C.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تنيح النبى العظيم هوشع أحد الاثنى عشر نبياً الصغار. ولد فى جبل إفرايم، من أب يدعى بائيرى. عاصر الملوك عزيا ويوثام وآحاز وحزقيا ملوك يهوذا ، ويربعام بن يوآش ملك إسرائيل ( هوشع ١ : 1). وكذلك إشعياء وعاموس وميخا الأنبياء وقد مارس العمل النبوى حوالى سبعين عاماً.وقد عاصر هذا النبى سبى إسرائيل بواسطة آشور سنة 722 ق. م.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He mentioned in his prophecy some strange and marvelous things. He rebuked the children of Israel for their sins and trespasses, and warned them about the evil things that would befall on them because of their crimes. He promised them if they returned to God repenting, that these evil things would be removed from them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وذكر فى نبوته أشياء غريبة وعجيبة وبكتَ بنى إسرائيل على زلاتهم وأنذرهم بالشرور التى تحل بهم عقاباً لهم على جرائمهم ووعدهم بزوال هذه المصائب عنهم إذا رجعوا إلى الرب إلههم بالتوبة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He also prophesied about the passion of our Savior, His resurrection and the salvation of Mankind.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كما تنبأ عن آلام المخلص وقيامته وخلاص بنى البشر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He said, "He has torn, but He will heal us; He has stricken, but He will bind us up. After two days He will revive us; on the third day He will raise us up, that we may live in his sight." (Hosea 6:1-2)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فقال: "ضرب فيجبرنا، يحيينا بعد يومين وفى الثالث يقيمنا فنحيا أمامه" (هوشع 6 : 1 ، 2 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He prophesied about the end of the sting of death and the dominion of hell by saying, "I will ransom them from the power of the grave, I will redeem them from death, 0 Death, I will be your plagues! 0 Grave, I will be your destruction." (Hosea 13:14)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتنبأ عن إبطال سطوة الموت وكسر شوكة الجحيم بقوله: " أين شوكتك يا موت، أين غلبتك يا هاوية " (هوشع 13 : 14 ). وقد عاصر هذا النبى سبى إسرائيل بواسطة آشور سنة 722 ق. م.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He departed in a good old age.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتنيح بشيخوخة صالحة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Zadok and the 128 who were with Him</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد القيس صادوق والمائة والثمانية والعشرين الذين معه</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the saints Zadok and the 128 men with him were martyred in Persia. Behram, King of Persia, brought them before him and proposed for them to worship the sun. St. Zadok replied saying; "I do not worship except God, the Creator of the sun and the universe." The King asked, "Does the sun have a god?" The saint replied, "Yes, and He is the Lord Christ, our God."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً استشهد القديسون صادوق والمائة والثمانية والعشرون رجلاً الذين معه. وذلك أن بهرام ملك الفرس أحضرهم أمامه وعرض عليهم أن يسجدوا للشمس. فأجابه القديس صادوق بقوله: " إننى لا أسجد إلا لله خالق الشمس  وكل الكون ". فقال له الملك: " وهل لهذه الشمس إله؟ " ، فأجابه القديس: " نعم، وهو السيد المسيح إلهنا ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Behram ordered to behead him. When the executioner came forward to cut his head, a great light appeared; all those who were present saw it and cried out saying, "We are all Christians." The King ordered to slay them all and they received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فأمر الملك بقطع رأسه. وعندما تقدم السياف ليقطع رأسه ظهر نور عظيم رآه الحاضرون فصاحوا: " نحن جميعاً مسيحيون ". فأمر الملك بقطع أعناقهم جميعاً، ونالوا أكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the Two Bishops, Tyranius and Silvanus and the Priest Zinopius and Their Companions in the city of Tyre</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد الأسقفين تيرانيوس وسلوانس والكاهن زينوبيوس ورفاقهم فى مدينة صور</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Also on this day of the year 20 of the martyrs (304 A.D.) the two bishops, Tyranius and Silvanus and the priest Zinopius and their companions, were martyred, in the city of Tyre.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 20 للشهداء ( 304 م ) استشهد الأسقفان تيرانيوس وسلوانس والكاهن زينوبيوس ورفاقهم فى مدينة صور.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Captain Vitorius ordered to torment them with many tortures. They tore their flesh by scourging, and then cast them to wild vicious beasts which did not harm them by divine providence. They tormented them again with severe tortures by fire and iron thus they received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وذلك أن القائد فيتوريوس أمر بتعذيبهم بعذابات كثيرة، فمزقوا أجسادهم بالجلد، ثم طرحوهم للوحوش الضارية فلم تؤذهم بقوة إلهية، ثم عذبوهم عذابات قاسية بالنار والحديد. فنالوا أكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.27">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Seventh Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-seventh day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Eustathius, Patriarch of Antioch</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس أوسطاسيوس بطريرك أنطاكية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 53 of the martyrs (337 A.D.), St. Eustathius, Patriarch of Antioch, departed. He was born in Pamphylia in the middle of the third century. He was well known for his godliness and knowledge. When the patriarch of Antioch departed they chose Eustathius as his successor in the year 324 A.D.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               – فى مثل هذا  اليوم من سنة 53 للشهداء ( 337 م ) تنيح القديس أوسطاسيوس بطريرك أنطاكية. ولد هذا القديس فى بمفيلية فى أواسط القرن الثالث واشتهر بالفضيلة والعلم ، ولما تنيح بطريرك أنطاكية أُنتخب أوسطاسيوس خلفاً له سنة 324 م.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               His fame became well known for his virtues and profuse knowledge. He attended the Council of Nicea to judge Arius and he defended the decisions of the Council.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد ذاعت شهرته بسبب فضائله وعلمه الغزير. وحضر مجمع نيقية لمحاكمة أريوس ودافع عن قراراته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the Council, the Arian bishops devised many plots to remove him from his position. They enticed and bribed an adulterous woman with much money to accuse St. Eustathius, the Patriarch that he was the father of her child. They convened a council and judged to excommunicate him from his Episcopal rank. They informed Emperor Constantine who believed their unfounded judgment. He deposed and banished St. Eustathius to Thrace where the saint remained until his departure.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد المجمع ثار عليه الأساقفة الأريوسيون فدبروا له مكائد كثيرة لإبعاده عن كرسيه ومنها أنهم أغروا امراة زانية بمال كثير حتى تقول أنه أنجب منها ابناً. فجمعوا مجمعاً حكموا فيه بقطعه من رتبته وأبلغوا فسطنطين الملك بذلك فصدق قولهم ونفاه إلى ثراكى (مكان بالقرب من مدينة فيلبى).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the people knew the decision of the emperor, they revolted for they were confident of his innocence. However the meek patriarch appeased then and he accepted the decision peacefully. When he arrived to his exile, he persevered in praying, contemplation and writing many useful spiritual books and sent many epistles against the Arians until he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أحس الشعب بقرار الملك ثار ثورة عارمة وكادت تحدث فتنة بسبب ثقتهم فى براءته ولكن البطريرك الوديع قام بتهدئتهم ونفذ قرار النفى بهدوء ولما وصل إلى منفاه عكف على الصلاة والتأمل ووضع الكتب الروحية النافعة وكتب رسائل ضد الأريوسيين حتى تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Lord God willed to manifest his innocence and to reveal the truth. The woman became seriously ill and she knew that was because of her false accusation against the saint. She came to the church and confessed before the people of the city of the innocence of that saint. She pointed to the Arian bishops who urged her to do that. Those Arian bishops who were responsible for the exile of the patriarch, the Lord took revenge against them and allowed them to taste the bitterness of banishment as a punishment for their wickedness.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               إلا إن الله أراد إظهار براءته وإظهار الحقيقة فمرضت المرأة مرضاً شديداً علمت أنه بسبب اتهامها ظلماً للقديس ، فحضرت إلى الكنيسة وأقرت أمام كل الشعب ببراءة القديس وأن الأساقفة الأريوسيون هم الذين دفعوها إلى ذلك. أما الأساقفة الأريوسيون الذين تسببوا فى نفى البطريرك فقد انتقم منهم الله فأذاقهم مرارة النفى عقاباً على شرهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن  معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Perpetua and her Companions</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد القديسة بِرْبِتْوَا ومَنْ معها</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 203 A.D. St. Perpetua and her companions of women and men were martyred during the reign of Emperor Septimius Severus.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً من سنة 203م استشهدت القديسة بِرْبِتْوَا ومعها عدد من النساء والرجال، وذلك في عصر الإمبراطور سبتميوس ساويرس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint was born in the year 181 A.D., in Carthage, North Africa, modern-day Tunisia. She was a well-educated young lady from an illustrious wealthy family. She was married to a noble man and had a young child. They apprehended her when she was 22 years old along with some men and women right after receiving the sacrament of Holy Baptism and became Christians.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وُلِدَت هذه القديسة سنة 181م بقرطاجنة بشمال إفريقيا وهي تونس حالياً. كانت مثقفة ومن أسرة عريقة غنية. تزوجت من رجل شريف ورُزقت منه بطفل. تم القبض عليها وعمرها 22 سنة مع بعض الرجال والنساء بعد أن نالوا سر المعمودية المقدس وصاروا مسيحيين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They were imprisoned to deny Christ, however God granted Perpetua, visions and revelations, subsequently she comforted and confirmed the others in faith. They sentenced them to deny Christ but they were steadfast in their faith, therefore they started to torture them severely.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أودعوهم السجن حتى ينكروا المسيح، ولكن الله وهب بربتوا بعض الرؤى والإعلانات فكانت تعزي وتثبِّت الآخرين. حاكموهم لكي ينكروا المسيح ولما تمسَّكوا بإيمانهم بدأوا يعذبونهم بالعذابات الشديدة،            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They threw St. Perpetua before a wild cow which struck her fiercely, tore her cloth and threw her on the ground. The Saint supported herself and tried to bring together the torn parts of her dress to cover her body. Therefore in her death she was not any less concerned about her chastity than in her life. This was an indication for the devotion of the early Christians to chastity and their perseverance on it. When she saw her family crying and screaming in the Coliseum, she told them; “be firm in the faith, love one another, and do not be grieved or frightened because of our passion.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فألقوا بالقديسة بربتوا لبقرة وحشية. نطحتها البقرة بقوة فمزقت ثيابها وألقتها على الأرض، فتساندت القديسة وحاولت أن تضم أطراف الرداء الممزق لتستر نفسها، فكانت في موتها لا تقل اهتماماً بعفتها عن حياتها. وهذا دليل على محبة المسيحيين الأوائل للعفة وتمسكهم بها، ولما رأت أسرتها تصرخ في ميدان المصارعة قالت لهم: اثبتوا في الإيمان وأحبوا بعضكم بعضاً ولا تجزعوا من آلامنا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After a series of tortures the governor ordered them beheaded and they accepted the sentence with joy. They were beheaded with the sword one after the other and they all received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد سلسلة من العذابات أمر الوالي بقطع رؤوسهم فقبلوا الحكم بفرح، فقطعوا رؤوسهم بالسيف واحداً تلو الآخر ونالوا جميعهم أكاليل الاستشهاد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.28">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Eighth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-eighth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Relocation of the Relics of the Martyr St. Theodore (Tadros), the Oriental (el-Mishreke)</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نقل أعضاء القديس تاوضروس ( تادرس) المشرقى الشهيد</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the relics of the martyr St. Theodore (Tadros) the oriental (el-Mishreke) were relocated. The martyrdom of the saint was by burning in the city of Amasia the capital of the region of Pontus in Asia Minor in the year 306 A.D. After the state of the empire settled, the Edict of Milan was proclaimed by Emperor Constantine that established religious freedom for Christians, the Divine providence willed to relocate the relics of this great martyr to the city of Nyssa where a church was built after his name. Many miracles and signs were manifested from his pure relics.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تم نقل أعضاء القديس تاوضروس ( تادرس ) المشرقى الشهيد. وذلك أنه بعد ان إستشهد القديس بالموت حرقاً ، فى مدينة أماسيا  عاصمة إقليم البنطس بآسيا الصغرى سنة 306 م. وبعد ان استقرت الأحوال وصدر منشور الإمبراطور قسطنطين الذى بموجبه أُعطيت الحرية الدينية للمسيحيين ، شاءت العناية الإلهية أن ينقل جسد هذا الشهيد العظيم إلى مدينة نيصص، حيث بُنيت له كنيسة باسمه، وظهرت من جسده عجائب وآيات كثيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.29">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Ninth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-ninth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع والعشرون من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Polycarp, Bishop of Smyrna</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس بوليكاربوس أسقف سميرنا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 167 A.D., St. Polycarp, Bishop of Smyrna (known as Izmir), was martyred. He was a contemporary of St. John the Evangelist and his disciple. He was the one about whom the Lord Christ said in the book of revelation, "And to the angel of the church in Smyrna write, 'These things says the First and the Last, Who was dead, and came to life: I know your works, tribulations and poverty, but you are rich; and I know the blasphemy of those who say they are Jews and are not, but are a synagogue of Satan. Do not fear any of those things which you are about to suffer. Indeed, the devil is about to throw some of you into prison, that you may be tested, and you will have tribulation ten days. Be faithful until death, and I will give you the crown of life."' (Revelation 2:8-10)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 167 م استشهد القديس بوليكاربوس أسقف سميرنا الشهيرة بأزمير ، وقد تتلمذ على يد القديس يوحنا الإنجيلى وهو الذى يعنيه الرب يسوع فى سفر الرؤيا بقوله " أكتب إلى ملاك كنيسة سميرنا. هذا بقوله الأول والآخر الذى كان ميتاً فعاش أنا أعرف أعمالك وضيقتك وفقرك. مع إنك غنى. وتجديف القائلين أنهم يهود وليسوا يهوداً بل هم مجمع الشيطان. لا تخف البته مما أنت عتيد أن تتألم به. هوذا إبليس مزمع أن يلقى بعضاً منكم فى السجن لكى تجربوا ويكون لكم ضيق عشرة أيام. كن أميناً إلى الموت فسأعطيك إكليل الحياة  "  (رؤ 2 : 8 – 10).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Ignatius, patriarch of Antioch, on his way to Rome for martyrdom, he passed by the city of Smyrna. St. Polycarp went out to meet the saint and he embraced him and kissed his fetters.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيما كان القديس أغناطيوس بطريرك أنطاكية ذاهباً إلى روما للاستشهاد مر على مدينة سميرنا فخرج القديس بوليكاربوس لملاقاته وعانقه وقبل قيوده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Polycarp went to Rome in the year 157 A.D. to settle a dispute between Rome and the churches of the East, in regard of the date of the honorable feast of Resurrection. He resolved the dispute with the pope of Rome in regard of this subject then returned to his See.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وعندما وقع الخلاف بين كنيسة روما وكنائس الشرق بخصوص موعد عيد القيامة المجيد ذهب القديس إلى روما سنة 157 م، واتفق مع بابا روما بخصوص هذا الامر، ثم عاد إلى مقر كرسيه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He carried his pastoral duties with ambition and divine zeal. He wrote many articles and discourses about the Virginal birth, death, hell, and eternal torment. He also wrote about the virgin St. Mary and the economy of salvation. He attracted many souls to the faith of the Lord Christ with his life-giving teachings.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وباشر أعماله الرعوية بكل همه وغيرة مقدسة. ووضع مقالات كثيرة وميامر عديدة عن الميلاد البتولى والموت والجحيم والعذاب، كما كتب عن القديسة العذراء مريم وعن تدبيرات الخلاص. وبذلك جذب نفوساً كثيرة بتعاليمه النافعة إلى الإيمان بالسيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Marcus Aurelius incited persecutions against the Christians, he arrested St. Polycarp and tried with him to deny Christ. Polycarp replied, "I have served my Lord Christ for 86 years and He never harmed me so how can I blaspheme against my King Who saved me?"            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أثار الإمبراطور مرقس أوريليوس الاضطهاد على المسيحيين، قبض على القديس بوليكاربوس وحاول معه لكى ينكر المسيح، فأجاب بوليكاربوس " ستة وثمانون سنة أخدمه ولم يسبب لى ضرراً فكيف أجدف على ملكى الذى خلصنى".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Emperor said, "If you do not fear the wild beasts, I will make the fire consume you if you do not forsake your faith." St. Polycarp said, "You threatened me with fire that burns for a while, then burns out, for you do not know the everlasting fire of judgment and the eternal punishment that are awaiting the wicked. Now why are you lingering? Do whatever you want."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أجاب الإمبراطور : إن كانت الوحوش لا تخيفك فسأجعل النيران تلتهمك إلا إذا رجعت عن إيمانك. أجابه القديس: إنك تهددنى بالنار التي تشتعل ساعة ثم تنطفىء لأنك لا تعرف نار الدينونة العتيدة والقصاص الأبدى الُمعد للأشرار.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The emperor started to severely torture him, and then he ordered to place him in the middle of fire which did not harm him. Finally he ordered to stab him with a spear. His blood flew profusely and put the fire off and he delivered his pure spirit and received the crown of life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               حينئذ بدأ الإمبراطور يعذبه بعذابات عديدة، ثم أمر بوضعه فى النار فلم تؤذه، أخيراً أمر بطعنه بالحربة فتدفق دمه وأطفأ النار وفاضت روحه الطاهرة ونال إكليل الحياة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The believers took his pure body, shrouded and prayed over him as fitting then buried him with great honor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأخذ المؤمنون جسده الطاهر وكفنوه وصلوا عليه كما يليق ثم دفنوه بإكرام جزيل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Meshir.30">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Thirtieth Day of the Blessed Month of Meshir</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثلاثون من شهر أمشير المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the thirtieth day of the blessed month of Meshir. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثلاثون من شهر أمشير المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Appearance of the Head of St. John the Baptist</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">وجود رأس القديس يوحنا المعمدان</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day we celebrate the appearance of the head of St. John the Baptist, in Homs, Syria. St. John appeared to Abba Martianus, Bishop of Homs, in a vision and guided him to the where about of the head. He found it and celebrated its appearance with a great veneration.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تم العثور على رأس يوحنا المعمدان فى حمص الشام، وذلك أن القديس يوحنا المعمدان ظهر لأنبا مرتيانوس أسقف حمص فى رؤيا وأرشده إلى موضع الرأس فأخذها واحتفل بها بإكرام جزيل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The story of the journey of the head of St. John the Baptist started when Herod cut off his holy head because of his marriage to Herodias. (Matt. 14:3-12) It was said that after the feast, he regretted the beheading of St. John so he hid the holy head in his house.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقصة رحلة رأس يوحنا المعمدان بدأت عندما قطع هيرودس رأسه المقدس بسبب زواجه من هيروديا ( مت 14 : 3 – 12 ).  ثم أخفى الرأس المقدس فى منزله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The place of the hidden head was unknown for a long time until two Christian men from Homs came to Jerusalem during the holy fast (Lent) to receive the blessings of the holy places. Night fell on them while passing by Herod’s palace, so they spent the night nearby. St. John appeared to one of them and told him about his name, informed him about the place of his head and ordered him to take it to his house. When they woke up, they dug in the place that the Saint specified for them. They found the holy head in a pottery vessel. When they opened it a sweet aroma came out of it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وظلت مجهولة زماناً طويلاً حتى أتى رجلان مسيحيان من أهل حمص إلى أورشليم فى الصوم الكبير للتبرك من الأماكن المقدسة، وأمسى عليهما الوقت بالقرب من بيت هيرودس، فناما فظهر القديس يوحنا لأحدهما وأعلمه باسمه وعرفه بموضع رأسه وأمره أن يحمله معه إلى منزله، فلما استيقظا من نومها حفرا فى الموضع الذى  أعلمهما به القديس، فوجدوا الرأس المقدس داخل وعاء فخارى. ولما فتحاه صعدت منه رائحة طيبة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The man who saw the vision took it to his house. He lit a lamp in front of it. After the departure of this man the head was handed down from one person to another in the city of Homs. Until St. John appeared to Abba Martianus, Bishop of Homs, in the later part of the fourth century, and guided him to the place of the head. He found the head, took it and celebrated for it a great feast.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأخذ الرجل الذى رأى الرؤيا الرأس معه إلى منزله، ووضع أمامه قنديلاً، وبعد وفاة هذا الرجل انتقل الرأس من مكان إلى آخر داخل مدينة حمص إلى أن ظهر القديس يوحنا لأنبا مرتيانوس أسقف حمص فى أواخر القرن الرابع وأرشده إلى موضع الرأس فأخذها واحتفل بها احتفالاً عظيماً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of St. John the Baptist be with all. Amen            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة القديس يوحنا المعمدان فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Kyrollos VI, the 116th Pope of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا كيرلس السادس البطريرك المئة والسادس عشر من بطاركة الإسكندرية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1687 of the martyrs (March 9, 1971 A.D.), the holy and righteous father Abba Kyrillos the Sixth, the 116th Pope of Alexandria, departed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               في مثل هذا اليوم أيضاً من سنة 1687 للشهداء (9 مارس 1971م) تنيح الأب القديس البار البابا كيرلس السادس، البطريرك المئة والسادس عشر من بطاركة الإسكندرية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was born in the city of Damanhour to godly and righteous parents. His name was Azer Yousef Atta. The Hegumen Tadros El-Baramousy, an elder monk used to frequently visit them, he foretold his monastic life. When he grew he practiced the monastic life at home persevering in studying the Holy Books, church subjects, its rituals and hymns. In July 1927 he went to the monastery of el-Baramous where he became a monk by the name Mina el-Baramousy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولد هذا القديس في مدينة دمنهور لأبوين تقيين بارين، وكان اسمه عازر يوسف عطا. وكان القمص تادرس البراموسي، وهو راهب شيخ، معتاداً أن يزور تلك الأسرة وكان قد تنبأ مسبقاً برهبنته. عندما كبر عازر، كان يمارس الحياة الرهبانية في منزله، كما كان مثابراً على قراءة الكتاب المقدس والمواضيع الكنسية والطقوس والألحان. وفي يوليو من سنة 1927 ذهب إلى دير البراموس حيث ترهبن باسم مينا البراموسي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On July 18, 1931 he was ordained a priest. He joined the seminary at Helwan. When he heard that Pope Youannis (113th Patriarch) intended to ordain him a bishop, he fled to Upper Egypt and stayed in St. Shenouda monastery in Souhag. He returned later on and met the Patriarch who agreed to his request of solitary life and assigned a pious monk Hegumen Abdel Messih al-Baramousy to be his spiritual guide. Then he lived in a cave, one hour walking distance from the monastery. He only came to the monastery Saturday night to take care of the elder monks, attend vespers and the Sunday liturgy to partake of the Holy Mysteries.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفي 18يوم  يوليو من سنة 1931، رُسم قسيساً، ثم التحق بالكلية الإكليريكية بحلوان. وعندما سمع أن البابا يوأنس (البطريرك المئة والثالث عشر) كان ينوي أن يرسمه أسقفاً، هرب إلى الصعيد ومكث في دير الأنبا شنودة في سوهاج. ثم عاد فيما بعد والتقى بالبطريرك الذي وافق على طلبه بالتوحد وعيّن الراهب التقي القمص عبد المسيح البراموسي ليكون مرشده الروحي. ثم بعد ذلك، عاش القديس في مغارة تبعد عن الدير ساعة واحدة مشياً على الأقدام. كان يأتي إلى الدير يوم السبت مساءً فقط ليعتني بالرهبان الشيوخ، ويحضر صلاة العشية وقداس يوم الأحد لكي يتناول من الأسرار المقدسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Early in 1936 he lived in a deserted mill on the Mokattam mount in Old Cairo, where he diligently held a daily liturgy. In 1941 he was assigned to be the abbot of Anba Samuel the Confessor monastery in Qalamoun Mount. He renovated the monastery, the church and built new cells for the monks. The church was consecrated by the late Bishop Anba Athanasius of Beni Sweif who gave him the rank of Hegumen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لقد عاش القديس في سنة 1936 في طاحونة مهجورة على جبل المقطم في مصر القديمة حيث كان قد دأب على أن يصلي قداساً كل يوم. وفي سنة 1941، عُين رئيساً لدير الأنبا صموئيل المعترف في صحراء القلمون فقام بتجديد الدير والكنيسة وبنى قلالي جديدة للرهبان. و وقد تم تدشين الكنيسة بيد المتنيح الأنبا أثناسيوس أسقف بني سويف الذي منحه رتبة القمصية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In 1947 he returned to Old Cairo where he built a church after the name of St. Mina. In that church several pious monks became his disciples, many of them later on became bishops of the church. Because of his perpetual prayers and strong faith, he healed the sick, cast out evil spirits and solved many problems for his visitors.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفي سنة 1947، عاد القديس إلى مصر القديمة حيث بنى كنيسة على اسم القديس مارمينا. كان العديد من الرهبان الأتقياء قد تتلمذوا على يديه في تلك الكنيسة كما سيم العديد منهم فيما بعد أساقفة في الكنيسة. لقد كان بسبب صلواته الدائمة وإيمانه القوي يشفي المرضى، ويخرج الأرواح الشريرة، ويحل العديد من مشاكل زائريه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Yousab II departed and after the long process of nominations, the elections were concluded and an altar lot was drawn the anchorite Hegumen Mina el-Baramousy was chosen to be the 116th Pope of Alexandria. His consecration took place on Sunday May 10, 1959 as Pope Cyril VI. In June 28, 1959 H.H. consecrated a Patriarch Catholicos for the Ethiopian church to strengthen the ties between the sister churches.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وعندما تنيح البابا يوساب الثاني وبعد عملية مطولة من الترشيحات، تم عمل القرعة الهيكلية التي وقعت على القمص مينا البراموسي ليكون البطريرك المئة والسادس عشر من بطاركة الإسكندرية. وتمت رسامته بطريركاً يوم الأحد 10 مايو سنة 1959 باسم البابا كيرلس السادس. وفي يوم 28 يونيو من سنة 1959، قام قداسته برسامة بطريرك للكنيسة الأثيوبية لكي يقوي الروابط بين الكنائس الشقيقة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In November 1959 Pope Kyrollos put the foundation stone of the monastery of the martyr Mari Mina the wonder worker in the wilderness of Mariot and relocated his pure relics to it. In 1967 Pope Kyrollos compounded the holy Myron which was a historical occasion since this was only done 26 times in the history of the Coptic Church. In April 2nd, 1968 the immaculate Mother of God St. Mary was transfigured on the domes of her church in Zeitoun. In June 1968 Pope Kyrollos received the relics of St. Mark after sojourning away from Egypt for close to eleven centuries. He laid it to rest in a reliquary specially built under the altar of the great cathedral of St. Mark which Pope Kyrollos built in the area of Anba Roweis, el-Abbasyah. This Cathedral was inaugurated in a magnificent celebration attended by the then president Naser and the late Emperor HaileSilasi and delegates from churches all over the world.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               في نوفمبر 1959، وضع البابا كيرلس حجر الأساس لدير مارمينا العجايبي في صحراء مريوط ونقل رفاته الطاهر إليه. وفي سنة 1967، قام بطبخ الميرون. لقد كان ذلك حدثاً تاريخياً حيث أن الميرون كان قد طُبخ في الكنيسة القبطية 26 مرة فقط على مدار تاريخها. وفي يوم 2 أبريل 1968، ظهرت والدة الإله السيدة العذراء على قباب كنيستها في الزيتون. وفي يونيو 1968، جلب البابا كيرلس رفات القديس مارمرقس التي بقيت خارج مصر لما يقرب من إحدى عشر قرناً من الزمان. لقد وضع هذه الرفات لتستقر في مزار بُـني خصيصاً تحت مذبح الكاتدرائية العظمى للقديس مارمرقس التي بناها البابا في منطقة الأنبا رويس بالعباسية. كانت هذه الكاتدرائية قد تم افتتاحها في احتفال مهيب حضره الرئيس جمال عبد الناصر والامبراطور الراحل هيلاسلاسي ومندوبون عن الكنائس من العالم كله.             </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Kyrollos never forgot that he is the poor monk Mina the anchorite. His food was very simple. Many days he would subsist on a meal of dry bread, salt and cumin after the late divine Liturgies which concluded in the evening. He was diligent in singing midnight praise daily. His daily liturgy was serene and profound.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لم ينسَ البابا كيرلس قط أنه الراهب الفقير مينا المتوحد. فكان طعامه بسيطاً جداً حيث كان في أيام كثيرة يأكل وجبة واحدة من الخبز الجاف، والملح، والكمون بعد أن يصلي القداسات في وقت متأخر من المساء. كما كان حريصاً على إقامة تسبحة نصف الليل يومياً. وكان قداسه اليومي هادئاً وعميقاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               God has accorded this pure father the gift of working great miracles even after his departure.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هذا وقد منح الله هذا الأب الطاهر موهبة صنع المعجزات حتى بعد نياحته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When God wanted to give him rest from the afflictions of this present age, he had a brief illness, and on the day of his departure he received a number of his children, he raised the cross and said “May the Lord arrange your affairs” then he delivered his pure soul into the hands of God whom he served and loved. On November 25, 1972 his pure relics were relocated to the monastery of St. Mina at Mariot according to his hand written will. On the day of the relocation of his relics heaven honored him for the sky thundered and rain came down in such a way that had never been seen before.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وعندما أراد الله أن يريحه من أتعاب هذا الدهر، مرض مرضاً قصيراً وفي يوم نياحته استقبل العديد من أبنائه ورفع الصليب وقال: "الرب يدبر أموركم" ثم أسلم روحه الطاهرة بيد الله الذي خدمه وأحبه. وفي يوم 25 نوفمبر من سنة 1972، تم نقل رفاته الطاهرة إلى دير مارمينا بصحراء مريوط بحسب الوصية التي كتبها بخط يده. وفي يوم نقل رفاته إلى الدير، كرمته السماء ببروق وأمطار غزيرة لم تحدث بهذه الطريقة من قبل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of this Holy Father be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">                 بركة صلوات هذا الأب القديس تكون معنا جميعاً ولإلهنا المجد الدائم إلى الأبد. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season></Document>