<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Season id="Paope.1">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The First Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الاول من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the first day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الاول من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Saint Anastasia</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديسة أنسطاسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 250 A.D., St. Anastasia was martyred. This saint was a native of Rome, and a daughter of Christian parents. They raised her well and taught her Christian manners. When she grew up, her parents wanted her to get married, but she refused.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة250م إستشهدت القديسة أنسطاسية. كانت هذه القديسة من أهل مدينة روما. وقد ولدت لأبوين مسيحيين ?ربياها أحسن تربية وأدباها بالآداب المسيحية. ولما كبرت أراد والدها أن يزوجها ?لم توا?قه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               She instead chose the pure monastic life because she longed for the heavenly glories. She joined one of the convents of the virgins in Rome. She subdued her body with piety and asceticism.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بل إختارت السيرة الرهبانية الطاهرة لإشتياقها الي الأمجاد السماوية.  ?دخلت إحدى بيوت العذارى بروما وأتعبت جسدها بالنسك والتقش?.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               It came to pass that one of the convents, nearby the convent of St. Anastasia, was celebrating a feast. The abbess took St. Anastasia, with some of the virgins, and went to join in celebrating that feast. On their way, St. Anastasia saw the soldiers of Emperor Decius torturing some Christians and dragging them. Her heart became inflamed with divine zeal and she shouted at them saying, "O you hard-hearted men is that what you do to those whom God created in His own form and image and for whom He gave Himself up?"            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . وإت?ق أن أحد بيوت العذارى القريبة منها كانت تحت?ل بأحد الأعياد ?أخذتها الرئيسة مع بعض العذارى ومضين للإشتراك ?ي ذلك العيد. ?رأت ?ي الطريق جنود ديسيوس الملك يعذبون بعض المسيحيين ?إلتهب قلبها بالغيرة المسيحية وصاحت بهم قائلة : "ياقساة القلوب أهكذا ت?علون بمن خلقهم الله علي صورته ومثاله وبذل ذاته عنهم ؟"            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One of the soldiers seized her and brought her to the Governor who asked her saying "Is it true that you are a Christian, worshipping Him who was crucified?" She confessed her faith in the Lord Christ and did not deny it. He inflicted her with severe tortures, and when she did not give up her faith, he finally commanded her beheaded. She said a fervent prayer, then she bowed her head and the swordsman beheaded her and she received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?قبض عليها أحد الجنود وقدمها للوالي الذي سألها قائلا: "هل أنت? مسيحية تعبدين المصلوب ؟ " ?إعتر?ت بالسيد المسيح ولم تنكر. ?عذبها عذاباً شديداً بعذابات مختل?ة وأخيراً أمر بقطع رأسها ?صلت صلاة حارة ثم أحنت رأسها ?ضرب السيا? عنقها ?نالت إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها ?لتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.2">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Second Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثانى من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the second day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثانى من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Coming of Saint Severus, Patriarch of Antioch, to Egypt</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار مجئ القديس ساويرس بطريرك أنطاكية الي مصر</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 234 of the martyrs (518 A.D.), St. Severus, Patriarch of Antioch, came to Egypt. That was during the reign of Emperor Justinian. This Emperor opposed the Orthodox belief, following that of the council of Chalcedon. However Queen Theodora, his wife, was an Orthodox and she loved St. Severus because of his many Christian virtues and his steadfast in the true Orthodox faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 234 للشهداء (518م) أتى القديس ساويرس بطريرك إنطاكية إلي مصر ?ي عهد الإمبراطور يوستنيان. وكان هذا الإمبراطور يتبع عقيدة مجمع خلقيدونية أما زوجته ثيودورة ?كانت أرثوذكسية محبة للقديس ساويرس بسبب ?ضائله العديدة وتمسكه بالإيمان الأرثوذكسي القويم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Emperor called him one day and many discussions took place regarding the Orthodox faith, but the Emperor would not turn away from his erroneous belief. The Emperor issued his orders to slay St. Severus. Queen Theodora besought the saint to escape to save himself but he refused saying, "I am ready to die holding the Orthodox faith." However, as the Queen and the God loving brethren insisted, he left to Egypt.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث أن دعاه الإمبراطور وحدثت بينهما مناقشات كثيرة بخصوص الإيمان الأرثوذكسي السليم ?كان القديس ساويرس ثابتاً على الإيمان الأرثوذكسي القويم ?أصدر الملك أمره بقتل القديس ساويرس. ?أوعزت إليه الملكة ثيودورة أن يهرب وينجو بن?سه ?خرج وقصد ديار مصر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Emperor sought St. Severus and did not find him, he sent soldiers after him. But God hid St. Severus from the soldiers and they did not see him although he was close to them. When he came to Egypt, he went disguised from place to place and from monastery to monastery, and God made many signs and wonders through his hands.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما طلبه الملك ولم يجده أرسل خل?ه جنوداً. ولكن الله أخ?اه عنهم ولما وصل إلي مصر كان يجول متنكراً من مكان إلي مكان ومن دير إلي دير آخر. وكان الله ي?جري علي يديه آيات كثيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day, he went to the desert of Scetis (Wadi-El Natroun), and he entered the church in a uniform of a stranger monk during the Divine Liturgy and a great miracle took place at that time. The priest had placed the bread (Kourban) on the altar, covered it with the Prospheron and continued in his prayers. After the prayer of Reconciliation the priest lifted up the Prospheron (altar covering), and he did not find the Kourban (Lamb) in the paten. So, the priest was disturbed and wept. He turned towards the worshippers saying, "O my brethren, I did not find El-Kourban in the paten, and I know not whether this thing has happened because of my sin or because of your sins." All the people wept; and straightaway, the angel of the Lord appeared to the priest and told him, "This has happened not because of your sin or because of the sins of the worshippers but because you offered El-Kourban in the presence of the father the Patriarch.? The priest replied, "And where is he, O my Lord?" The angel pointed toward St. Severus. St. Severus was standing in a corner of the church. The priest came to Abba Severus, who commanded him to continue the liturgy after they brought him to the altar with great honor. When the priest had gone up to the altar he found the offering on the paten as before. They all praised God and glorified His Holy Name. St. Severus remained in Egypt for about twenty years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث ان دخل ?ي إحدي المرات متنكراً إلي الكنيسة بدير ?ى برية شهيت ?ي زى راهب غريب. ودخل الكنيسة ?ي وقت القداس الإلهي وبعد أن وضع الكاهن القربان علي المذبح وغطاه بالإبروس?ارين وإستمر ?ي الصلاة. ولما ر?ع الإبروس?ارين لبدء القداس ?لم يجد قربانة الحمل ?ي الصينية. ?إضطرب الكاهن جداً وإلت?ت إلي المصلين قائلا: " إني لا أجد القربانة ?ي الصينية ولست أدري إن كان هذا من أجل خطيتي أو خطيتكم ?بكى الم?صلون جميعهم جداً. وللوقت ظهر ملاك الرب وقال للكاهن: " ليس هذا لأجل خطيتك ولا خطية الم?صَََلين بل لأنك ر?عت القربان ?ي حضور الآب البطريرك ?قال له الكاهن: " وأين هو يا سيدي ؟ " ?أشار له الملاك وكان القديس ساويرس واق?اً بإحدي زوايا الكنَيسة. ?أدخلوه إلي الهيكل بكرامة عظيمة وأمر الكاهن أن يكمْل القداس ?لما صعد الكاهن إلي المذبح وجد القربانة ?ي مكانها ?مجدوا الله. وقد ظل هذا القديس ?ي مصر نحو عشرين سنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته تكون معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.3">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Third Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the third day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Siemon II, 51st Pope of the See of St. Mark</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا سيمون الثاني البطريرك الحادي والخمسون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 547 of the martyrs (831 A.D.), Abba Siemon II, 51st Pope of the See of St. Mark, departed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 547 للشهداء ( 831 م ) تنيح البابا سيمون الثاني البطريرك الحادي والخمسون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This father was born in Alexandria, to Orthodox Christian parents, of the nobles of the city. They raised him on the Orthodox principals and taught him the church subjects. He chose for himself the monastic life, so he went to the desert of Scetis. He became a monk in the cell of his predecessor Abba Jacob, the 50th Patriarch. He became his disciple for many years during which he exhausted his body by strenuous ascetic life, and many worships.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولد هذا الآب بمدينة الإسكندرية من أبوين مسيحيين من أكابر المدينة ?ربياه علي المبادئ المسيحية القويمة وأدباه بعلوم الكنيسة. ولما كبر إختار لن?سه سيرة الرهبنة ?قصد برية شيهيت وترهب ?ي قلاية سل?ه البابا يعقوب البطريرك الخمسين وتتلمذ علي يديه عدة سنوات ، أضني ?يها جسده بالنسك والعبادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Abba Marcus (Mark) II became a Patriarch, he requested St. Siemon from his spiritual father Abba Jacob for what was known of his good reputation, his sound judgment and knowledge. He stayed with Abba Marcus until Pope Marcus departure.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما صار الأنبا مرقس الثاني بطريركاً طلبه أبوه يعقوب لما له من العلم والسيرة الصالحة والتدبير الحسن ?مكث عنده إلي أن تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Abba Jacob, his spiritual father, became patriarch, he kept Abba Siemon with him and he benefitted from him often. When Abba Jacob departed, the bishops, priests, and elders unanimously agreed to choose this father to be patriarch for what they had seen of him, as to righteousness and true Faith. They consecrated him a Patriarch on the 21st day of Amshir, year 546 of the martyrs (830 A.D.). He perused an angelic life, which was well-pleasing to the Lord. And, as God wished to repose him from the toils of this world, he did not stay on the throne but for only seven and a half months and departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما صار أبوه الروحاني الأنبا يعقوب بطريركاً جعله عنده وكان ينت?ع به كثيراً. ولما تنيح الأنبا يعقوب أجمع الأساق?ة والكهنة والأراخنة علي إختيار هذا الآب ليكون بطريركاً. لما رأوه ?يه مدة إقامته عند سل?يه من التقوي والإيمان الصحيح.  ?رسموه بطريركاً يوم 21 أمشير سنة 546 للشهداء (830 م ) ?سار سيرة ملائكية مرضية لله. وشاء الرب أن يريحه من أتعاب هذا العالم ?لم يقم علي الكرسي سوى سبعة أشهر ونص? وبعدها تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلاته تكون معنا أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Sts. Ursus and Victor of the Theban Legion</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديسين أورسوس وبقطر من ال?رقة الطيبية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 19 of the martyrs (303 A.D.), Sts. Ursus and Victor of the Theban Legion, were martyred.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً من سنة 19 للشهداء (303 م) إستشهد القديسان إورسوس وبقطر من ال?رقة الطيبية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               These two saints were born in the city of Thebes (Luxor). They joined the Theban Legion which had been called from Thebes in Egypt by the order of Emperor Diocletian to assist Emperor Maximian in defeating the revolts of the tribes in Western Europe. The unit of the two saints Ursus and victor was stationed near the city of Solothurn in Switzerland.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولد هذان القديسان بمدينة طيبة وإنضما الي ال?رقة الطيبية التي سا?رت لإخماد ثورات القبائل ?ي غرب أوروبا بأمر من الامبراطور دقلديانوس لمساعدة الامبراطور مكسيميانوس.  وحدث أن عسكرت كتيبة القديسين اورسوس وبقطر قرب مدينة سولوتورن بسويسرا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The members of the Legion refused to follow the orders of the Emperor to offer sacrifices to the gods. Maximian ordered to slay every tenth soldier to force the rest of the Legion to obey his orders. When he saw the steadfastness of everyone in the Christian faith, he ordered to torture and slay all the members of the Legion.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما ر?ض جميع أ?راد ال?رقة إطاعة أوامر الأمبراطور بتقديم الذبائح للالهة ?أمر مكسيميانوس بقتل عشرة أ?راد من ال?رقة لأرهاب البقية. ولما وجد تمسَّك الجميع بالايمان المسيحي أمر بتعذيب وقتل جميع ا?راد ال?رقة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He brought the two saints Ursus and Victor before the governor of Solothurn who tortured them severely for their steadfast in the Christian faith. The Lord performed many miracles during their torture. The iron chains that they were bound with became loose and when they threw them into the fire during their torture, it was extinguished and they were not burned.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأحضر القديسان أورسوس وبقطر أمام والي سولوتورن الذى عذبهما عذاباً شديداً لانهما تمسكا بالايمان المسيحي.  وقد أجري الرب الكثير من المعجزات أثناء تعذيبهما ، منها أن السلاسل الحديدية التى رب?طا بها إن?كت وعندما ألقوهما ?ي النار أثناء تعذيبهما حدث أن النار إنط?ات ولم يحترقا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Many of those who witnessed the tortures believed in the Lord Christ and declared their faith before the governor. He became enraged and ordered to behead them. Nevertheless, after their martyrdom the two stood up and carried their heads on their hands and walked for a distance then kneeled down and reposed in the Lord. Their bodies shined with a brilliant light, and many believed and declared their Christianity.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما آمن كثير من المشاهدين بالسيد المسيح وأعلنوا إيمانهم امام الوالى أغتاظ الوالي جداً وأمر بقطع رأسيهما ?حمل كل منهما رأسه وسارا بها مسا?ة ثم ركعا ورقدا ?ي الرب. ولقد لمعت أجسداهم بنور وهَّاج ?أمن عدد كبير وأعلنوا مسيحيتهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The two saints were buried with great honor in the place of their martyrdom. A church after the name of the apostle St. Peter was built in the place of their martyrdom where they placed the bodies of the two saints.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ود?ن القديسان باكرام عظيم ?ي مكان إستشهادهما حيث إقيمت كنيسة باسم القديس بطرس الرسول. و?ي القرن العاشر إقيمت بمدينة سولوتورن كنيسة كبيرة باسم القديس أورسوس ونقل إليها ر?اته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The body of St. Victor was relocated in the beginning of the sixth century to the city of Geneva where a church was built after his name. In the tenth century a cathedral was built on the name of St. Ursus in the city of Solothurn where they placed his holy relics.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أما جسد القديس بقطر ?نقل ?ي بداية القرن السادس الي مدينة جني? حيث إقيمت كنيسة باسمه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهما ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Empress Theodora</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحةالقديسة ثاؤدورا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Also on this day of the year 263 of the martyrs (547 A.D.) Empress Theodora, the wife of Emperor Justinian, departed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً من سنة 263 للشهداء ( 547 م ) تنيحت القديسة ثيودورة الملكة زوجة الامبراطور يوستنيان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Her father’s name was Acacius, one of the men of Emperor Justinian. He raised her well and reared her with the Christian manners. Because of her dazzling beauty, Emperor Justinian married her and her gifts and talents were revealed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان أبوها يدعي أكاكيوس من رجال الامبراطور يوستنيان ?رباها تربية حسنة وأدباها بالاداب المسيحية. ونظراً لجمالها الباهر ?قد تزوجها الملك يوستنيان ?ظهرت مواهبها الكثيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The people loved and obeyed her for her great role in the social reforms, building churches and hospitals. She was firm in her Orthodox faith in spite that her husband was Chalcedonian.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?أحبها الشعب وأطاعها بسبب دورها الكبير ?ي الإصلاحات الاجتماعية وبناء الكنائس والمستش?يات. وكانت متمسكة بأورثوذكسيتها. رغم أن زوجها كان خلقدونياً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               She revered St. Severus, patriarch of Antioch, for his Orthodox faith. She assisted him to escape to Egypt when her husband wanted to slay him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لذلك كانت توقر القديس ساويرس بطريرك أنطاكية بسبب معتقده الأرثوذكسي القويم وقد ساعدته علي الهروب الي مصر حينما أراد زوجها أن يقتله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               She supported and assisted the Syrian and the Egyptian (Coptic) churches. The church had experienced a tremendous growth during her time and when she finished her good endeavor, departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كما كانت تساند الكنيسة المصرية والسريانية. هذا وقد نمت الكنيسة ?ي عهدها نمواً عظيماً ولما أكملت سعيها الصالح تنيحت بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها تكون معنا.آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. John El-Ashruby, the Soldier</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس يوحنا الج?ندي الأشروبي</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, the great St. John el-Ashruby the soldier was martyred. He was born in a village called Ashruba , district of El-Bahnasa. His parents were rich, pious Christians. His father’s name was Theodor and his mother’s name was Sophia.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً أستشهد القديس العظيم يوحنا الج?ندي الأشروبي. ومن أمره أنه و?لد ?ي قرية أشروبة بولاية البهنسا (مازالت القرية تحت?ظ بن?س هذا الإسم) من والدين مسيحيين غنيين وتقيين. وكان والده ي?دعى تأودورس ووالدته ت?دعى صو?ية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               For a long time they did not have any children and they prayed by day and night for God to give them a good offspring. One day the angel of the Lord appeared to Theodor and told him that he will beget a child like a precious jewel (Gawharah). Later on they had a child they called him John and they used to call him El-Gawhary (Jewel) as the angel called him. When John El-Gawhary grew he joined the army and advanced in the ranks until he became a centurion. He was distinguished by courage, bravery and wisdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ظلا الأبوين بلا نسل مدة طويلة وكانا يصليان الليل والنهار لي?رزقهما الله نسلاً صالحاً. وذات يوم ظهر ملاك الرب لتأودورس والد القديس وقال له: ستنجب ط?لاً مثل الجوهر الثمين. وبعد هذه النبوة أنجبا ط?لاً وأسمياه يوحنا وكانوا يدعونه بأسم جوهرى كما ت?سمي من الملاك. ولما كبر يوحنا الجوهري ألتحق بالجندية وأتص? بالشجاعة والقوة والحكمة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Diocletian renounced the Christian faith and worshipped the idols many of the rulers followed him including Kelkianus, governor of El-Bahnasa. When he received the orders of the emperor to worship the idols and to offer incense for them, Kelkianus summoned John the soldier to offer incense to the idols. But when he found him in a visit to Alexandria, he sent to Armanius the governor of Alexandria to seize John and order him to worship and raise incense to the idols and if he refused to torture him severely.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتدرج ?ي الجندية حتى أصبح قائد مئة.  ولما أرتد الإمبراطور دقلديانوس عن المسيحية وعبد الأوثان تبعه جمع كثير من الولاة ومنهم قلقيانوس والي البهنسا. ولما وصلت أوامر الإمبراطور بعبادة الأوثان والتبخير لها أرسل قلقيانوس لأحضار يوحنا الج?ندي ليبخر للأصنام ، ?وجده ?ي الأسكندرية ?أرسل الي والي الأسكندرية يطلب من القبض على يوحنا الج?ندي ويأمره بعبادة الأوثان والتبخير لها وإن ر?ض ي?عذبه بأشنع العذابات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When John came before Armanius, he confessed the Lord Christ as his God and Savior. The governor became enraged and ordered to torture him. They squeezed him with the Hinbazeen, placed him on a red hot iron bed, placed fiery hot nails on his body, placed him in boiling tar, and finally they pulled out his nails and rubbed its place with vinegar and lime to torment him. He endured all tortures with patience and thanksgiving. The Lord strengthened and restored him to health without pain. Many miracles were manifested during his torture as the healing of Armanius himself from muteness which he suffered from when he blasphemed against the Lord Christ. When Armanius was weary of torturing him, he sent him back to Kelkianus, governor of El-Bahnasa, under heavy security. He also tortured him with dreadful and consecutive tortures and John endured patiently and with thanksgiving and the Lord healed and comforted him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما وق? يوحنا أمام الوالي أعتر? بالسيد المسيح رباً و ألهاً ?غضب الوالي وأصدر أوامره بتعذيبه. ?عصروه بالهنبازين ووضعوه على سرير حديدي م?حمي بالنار ووضعوا مسامير م?حماة بالنار على جسده. ثم وضعوه ?ي القار المغلي وخلعوا أظا?ره ووضعوا مكانها الخل والجير لتؤلمه أكثر وأكثر. و?ي جميع هذه العذابات كان الرب يقويه ويقيمه سليم م?عا?ي من كل ألم. وحدثت معجزات كثيرة أثناء تعذيبه منها ش?اء أرمانيوس الوالي من الخرس لما جد? على السيد المسيح. ولما تعب أرمانيوس الوالي من تعذيبه أرجعه بحراسة مشددة الي قلقيانوس والي البهنسا الذي عذبه أيضاً بسلسلة طويلة من العذابات وهو يحتمل بصبر وشكر والرب يش?يه ويعزيه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Finally the Governor ordered to behead him with the sword, thus he received the crown of martyrdom. Diogenius, who followed him from Alexandria, and one of the disciples of St. Julius of Aqfahs (El-Akfehasi), shrouded him with expensive shrouds and buried him with great veneration. He also wrote his biography as a memorial and benefit for the coming generations. The blessing of his prayers be with us all and Glory be to our God, forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أخيراً أمر الوالي بقطع رأسه بحد السي? ?نال أكليل الشهادة. وقام ديوجانيوس الذي حضر معه من الأسكندرية وهو أحد تلاميذ يوليوس الأق?هصي بتك?ينه بأك?ان غالية الثمن ود?نه بأكرام جزيل وكتب سيرته المباركة لمن?عة الأجيال. بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.4">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fourth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fourth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Bacchus, the Friend of St. Sergius</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس واخس ر?يق القديس سرجيوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Bacchus, the friend of St. Sergius, was martyred.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم إستشهد القديس واخس ر?يق القديس سرجيوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               These two saints were officers in the army of Maximianus Caesar and they believed in the Lord Christ. When Emperor Maximianus knew that, he seized them, and stripped them from their military ranks. He sent them to Antiochus, King of Syria, who imprisoned St. Sergius.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان القديسان ضابطين ?ي جيش ماكسيميانوس قيصر وقد آمنا بالسيد المسيح. ?لما علم الامبراطور بخبرهما قبض عليهما وجردهما من رتبتهما العسكرية ثم أرسلهما الي أنطيوخس والي سورية ?سجن القديس سرجيوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               However, he ordered to slay St. Bacchus. They beheaded the Saint, his body was made heavier by attaching stones to it, then cast it into the River Euphrates.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أما القديس واخس ?أمر بذبحه ?ذبحوه وطرحوه ?ي نهر ال?رات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Lord protected the body and the waves brought it to the shore near the dwelling of some ascetic holy men. The angel of the Lord appeared to two of them and commanded them to go and carry away the pure body.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعناية الله قذ?ته الأمواج الى الشاطئ بالقرب من مساكن بعض النساك ثم ظهر ملاك الرب الي إثنين منهم وأمرهما بحمل الجسد الطاهر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When they came to where the body was, they found a large eagle and a lion protecting it. The beasts were guarding the body without harming it, although they were beasts of prey, for they had been commanded by divine providence to protect the body.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?لما أتيا وجدا الجسد كما وبجواره عقْاب (نسر كبير) وأسد يحرسانه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The two holy men glorified God who takes care of His saints. They carried the body with great honor, singing hymns until they came to their cave where they buried it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?مجدا الله الذي يعتنى بقديسيه. ثم حملا الجسد بإكرام جزيل حتي أوصلاه مغارتهما ود?ناه هناك.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا  ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.5">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fifth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fifth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Paul, Patriarch of Constantinople</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد القديس بولس بطريرك القسطنطينية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 68 of the martyrs (351 A.D.), St. Paul, Patriarch of Constantinople, was martyred.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 68 للشهداء (351 م) أستشهد القديس بولس بطريرك القسطنطينية            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint was born in Thessalonica in the later part of the third century. Since his young age he became a disciple of Abba Alexandros, Patriarch of Constantinople. After the departure of St. Alexandros in the year 336 A.D., St. Paul was consecrated patriarch of Constantinople after him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولد هذا القديس بتسالونيكى ?ى أواخر القرن الثالث الميلادى. ومنذ نياحة القديس ألكسندروس سنة 336م أرتقى القديس بولس كرسى القسطنطينية بعده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he sat on the patriarchal throne, he vigorously resisted the Arians who deny the divinity of the Lord Christ, until he purged the country from them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?قاوم بشدة الأريوسيين الذين ينكرون لاهوت السيد المسيح ، حتى طهر البلاد منهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Constantine, the Great, departed, his three sons reigned after him as follow: Constantius reigned over Constantinople, Constans reigned over Rome and Constantine II reigned over France, Britannia and Hispania.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما ملك قسطنديوس ابن قسطنطين على بلاد الشرق وكان أريوسياً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Constantius held the same belief as Arius. When Constantius reigned over the countries of the East, he asked St. Paul to refrain from resisting the Arians but the Patriarch refused. The Emperor became angry and exiled him many times from his See.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               طلب إلى هذا البطريرك ان يك? عن مقاومة الأريوسيين ?ر?ض، ?غضب الملك و ن?اه عدة مرات عن كرسيه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               However, he finally exiled St. Paul to the country of Armenia. He asked one of the followers of Arius to catch up with St. Paul there and slay him. He went to him at night and strangled him, thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ى آخر مرة ن?اه إلى بلاد أرمينيا. ثم أوعز إلى أحد الأريوسيين بقتله ?دخل عليه ليلاً و خنقه. ?نال إكليل الشهادة .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا امين .            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Anba Peter, Bishop of El-Bahnasa</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة الأنبا بطرس أسق? البهنسا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, Anba Peter bishop of El-Bahnasa, departed. He became a monk in the monastery of Anba Shenouda the archimandrite, in mount Adribah, west of Souhag.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و ?يه ايضاً تنيح الأنبا بطرس أسق? البهنسا. ومن أمره أنه ترهب ?ى دير الأنبا شنودة رئيس المتوحدين بجبل أدريبه غرب سوهاج.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He devoted himself to study and search the Holy Scriptures and church books. He became a brilliant scholar especially in the rituals of the church and its hymnology. He was consecrated bishop of El-Bahnasa for the period between 1186 to 1220 A.D. In that time, El-Bahnasa was a great city and a capital of a province since the Pharaonic and Roman times. It was also a large parish that included many churches, monasteries and convents in the western desert nearby the city.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وهناك ت?رغ للدرس والبحث ?ى الكتاب المقدس وكتب الكنيسة حتى صار عالماً بارعاً خصوصاً ?ى طقوس الكنيسة و ألحانها.  ر?سم أسق?اً للبهنسا ?ى المدة من ( 1186 – 1220 م ) وكانت البهنسا ?ي ذلك الوقت مدينة عظيمة وعاصمة أحدى الولايات منذ العصور ال?رعونية و الرومانية. و كانت إيبارشية كبيرة بها الكثير من الكنائس والأديرة الخاصة بالرهبان وأديرة اخرى للراهبات بالصحراء الغربية المجاورة للمدينة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Bishop Peter had many publications in church rituals:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولهذا الاسق? مؤل?ات طقسية كثيرة أهمها :            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               First: The readings and hymns of the Holy Pascha:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أولاً:  قراءات و ألحان البصخة المقدسة:            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The believers in ancient times read the whole Holy Bible in the church during Passion wWeek which took a long time. When Pope Gabriel II, (1131-1145 A.D.), the 70th Pope, known as Ebn-Turayk, was enthroned he made some changes. He was an employee of the government before his enthronement and knew how occupied are the people and their lack of vacation times to be able to attend the long services during Passion Week. With the assistance of some monks from St. Macarius monastery in the wilderness of Scetis, he organized, arranged and wrote down the rubrics of the readings of the Holy Pascha. He divided the daily service to five Morning Hours and five Evening Hours. He chose from the two testaments what was suitable for every hour of the hours of the Pascha so the believers can follow the readings as much as their circumstances allowed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?قد كان المؤمنون ?ى العصور القديمة يقرأون الكتاب المقدس كله ?ى الكنيسة أثناء أسبوع الالام ، و كان ذلك يستغرق وقتاً طويلاً .  ولما جلس البابا غبريال الثانى البابا السبعون ، المعرو? بإبن تريك على السدة المرقسية ?ى المدة من 1131 – 1145 م. وكان هذا الآب قبل بطريركته موظ?اً عاماً ?ى الدولة ، و يعر? انشغال الناس وعدم وجود أجازات ?ى إسبوع الألآم للمسيحيين مما يضيع على الناس ?رص الاستمتاع بقراءات إسبوع الألآم الكثيرة. ?قام بمعاونة بعض رهبان دير القديس مكاريوس ببرية شيهيت بتنظيم وتدوين طقس قراءات البصخة ?قسمها الي خمس ساعات نهارية وخمس ساعات مسائية وأختار من العهدين ما يناسب كل ساعة من ساعات البصخة حتى يستطيع المؤمنون متابعة القراءات حسبما تسمح به ظرو?هم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Anba Peter was consecrated a bishop for El-Bahnasa:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما جلس الأنبا بطرس أسق?اً على أيبارشية البهنسا:            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               (1) He recognized that the lectionary of the hours of the Passion Week were not well-arranged. Some hours had many prophecies while others had few, so he decided to re-arrange them. He gathered from the Old Testament including the Deutero-canonical books what was appropriate for each hour from prophecies and psalms. Likewise from the New Testament what was appropriate for each hour from the Gospels.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وجد أن قراءات سواعى أسبوع الالآم غير متناسقة ، ?توجد ساعات ?يها نبوات كثيرة و أخرى نبوات قليلة. ?قام بتنسيقها ?جمع من العهد القديم بما ?يه الأس?ار المحذو?ة ما يناسب كل ساعة من النبوات و المزامير ومن العهد الجديد ما يناسب كل ساعة من الاناجيل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               (2) He made the hourly readings more uniform in length.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وجعل السواعى متناسقة و متقاربة ?ى قراءاتها            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               (3) He published all these changes in the Katameros (Lectionary) of the Holy Pascha which the Church still uses today.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ووضع كل هذا ?ى كتاب قطمارس البصخة الذى ما زالت الكنيسة تستخدمه حتى الان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               (4) He arranged for the readings to contain two sermons from the sayings of the fathers daily, one for the morning and another for the evening prayers. Nine of theses sermons were written by the saint Abba Shenouda the archimandrite alone. This serves as a testimony for his loyalty and love of Anba Shenouda in whose monastery he became a monk.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كما وضع لكل يوم عظتين من أقوال الآباء واحدة للصباح وواحدة للمساء. منها تسع عظات للقديس الأنبا شنودة وحده مما يدل على ولائه وحبه للقديس الانبا شنودة الذى ترهب ?ى ديره.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               (5) Anba Peter also arranged for each of the four Gospels to be read in its entirety during the Passion Week: the gospel of St. Matthew to be read Tuesday morning, the gospel of St. Mark to be read Wednesday morning, the gospel of St. Luke to be read Thursday morning after raising the morning incense and the gospel of St. John to be read Saturday evening before the liturgy of the Holy Resurrection.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كذلك رتب قراءات الأناجيل الأربعة كاملة ?ى أسبوع الالام : ?يقرأ انجيل متى ?ى صباح الثلاثاء وانجيل مرقس صباح الاربعاء و انجيل لوقا صباح الخميس بعد ر?ع بخور باكر ، وانجيل يوحنا مساء السبت قبل صلوات عيد القيامة المجيد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               (6) He also arranged the reading of the whole book of Psalms, the one hundred fifty one psalms, in the evening of Good Friday after the Burial Procession and the Hymn of Golgotha.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كذلك رتب قراءة المائة وواحد وخمسين مزموراً أى س?ر المزامير كله مساء الجمعة الكبيرة بعد عمل الد?نة و لحن غولغوثا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               (7) He compiled and edited the commentaries of the prophecies and the gospels of Passion Week in a book of commentaries that is still used till present time.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               قام بتجميع و تنقيح ت?اسير نبوات وأناجيل أسبوع الالام ?ى كتاب يحمل الاسم ما زال يستخدم حتى الان و تم طبعه عدة طبعات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               (8) He composed tunes for many of the prayers and readings especially the paschal psalms which are sung in the Adribic (mourning) tune. This tune is attributed to the monks of mount Adribah where the monastery of Anba Shenouda the Archimandrite is, west of Souhag.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               قام بتلحين الكثير من الصلوات و القراءات خصوصاً مزامير البصخة باللحن الادريبى (الحزاينى) المنسوب الى رهبان جبل أدريبة حيث دير الأنبا شنودة غربى سوهاج.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               (9) He also introduced “The Royal Tune? or “El-Lahn El-Shamy? to some of the Paschal psalms as “Pekethronos? (Your throne, O God…) and “Av-chinon? (His words were softer than oil …). He acquired it from Mount Shamah west of Luxor where the City of the Dead located in the Valley of the Kings and Queens and also where the monastery of the martyr St. Tawadros located west of Luxor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كذلك قام بإدخال اللحن الشامى ?ى بعض مزامير البصخة مثل مزمور  " بيك اثرونوس " و مزمور " ا?تشنون " نقله من جبل شامة غرب الاقصر حيث مدينة الموتى ?ى وادى الملوك و الملكات وحيث يوجد الان دير الشهيد تاوضروس المحارب غرب الاقصر .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Second: The rites of the “Lakkan? of the feast of our fathers the Apostles (5th of Epep):            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثانياً : طقس لقان عيد الاباء الرسل 5يوم أبيب:            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In its introduction it says “A Canon was composed by our father Anba Peter, bishop of the city of El-Bahnasa, is read over the Lakkan font of the fifth of Epep, the feast of the Apostles, our father Peter and our teacher Paul?.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقيل ?ى مقدمته " قانون وضعه أبونا الأنبا بطرس اسق? مدينة البهنسا يقرأ على اللقان ?ى الخامس من أبيب عيد أبوينا الرسولين ابينا بطرس ومعلمنا بولس .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Third: The rites of consecrating new Baptisteries:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثالثاً : طقس تكريس المعموديات الجديدة:            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               It is the ritual of consecrating the new Baptistery that is used till now. In a manuscript that document the ritual of consecrating the baptistery, it said; “the rubrics were put down by the holy father Anba Peter, bishop of el-Bahnasa for consecrating the new Baptistery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و هو طقس تدشين المعمودية المستعمل حتى الان وورد ?ى مخطوطة تحوى طقس تكريس المعمودية النص التالى " ترتيب وضعه أبونا القديس انبا بطرس أسق? البهنسا من أجل تكريز المعمودية الجديدة " .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               It is worth to mention that whatever this honorable bishop put down from rituals, the church approved and established immediately, is an indication that the church had put him in an honorable position for his rich knowledge, wisdom and spirituality.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ومن الجدير بالذكر ان كل ما كان يقوم به هذا الاسق? الجليل من ترتيبات طقسية كانت تأخذ به الكنيسة و تقره ?وراً مما يدل على ان الكنيسة كانت تضعه ?ى مكانة مرموقة لكثرة علمه وحكمته وروحانيته .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the days of his service were completed he departed in peace and went to his eternal home to rest.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما كملت ايام خدمته تنيح بسلام ومضى الى بيته الابدى ليستريح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا و لربنا المجد دائماً ابدياً. آمين .            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.6">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Sixth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the sixth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Righteous Hannah, Mother of Samuel, the Prophet</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة الصديقة حنة.  ام صموئيل النبي</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the church celebrates the commemoration of the departure of the righteous Hannah, the mother of Samuel the Prophet.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار نياحة القديسة حنة أم صموئيل النبي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This just woman was of the tribe of Levi. Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, married her. He also had another wife whose name was Peninnah.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كانت هذه البارة من سبط لاوي وتزوجت ألقانة بن يروحام وكان لأقانة زوجة أخري إسمها ?ننة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Hannah was barren, and Peninnah was always reviling her because she had no children. This man went up from his city yearly to worship and sacrifice to the Lord of hosts in Shiloh where the tabernacle of meeting was.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت حنة عاقراً ?كانت ضرتها ?ننة تعيرها كثيراً لعدم النسل. وكان هذا الرجل يصعد كل سنة ليذبح للرب ?ي شيلوه حيث توجد خيمة الاجتماع.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               And whenever the time came for Elkanah to make an offering, he would give portions to Peninnah his wife and to all her sons and daughters. But to Hannah he would give a double portion, for he loved her. And her rival, Peninnah, was jealous of her and provoked her, therefore Hannah wept and did not eat.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما ذبح ألقانة الذبيحة أعطي لأمراته ?ننة ولجميع بنيها وبناتها أنصبة وأما حنة ?أعطاها نصيب أثنين لأنه كان يحبها ?غارت منها ?ننة وأغاظتها ?بكت ولم تأكل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Elkanah, her husband, said to her, "Why do you weep? Why do you not eat? And why is your heart grieved? Am I not better to you than ten sons?" (1 Samuel 1:8) Hannah did not accept any consolation.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?قال لها زوجها: "لماذا تبكين ولا تأكلين أما أنا خير لك من عشرة بنين؟" (صموئيل الاول1:1-8) ?لم تقبل حنة عزاء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               She went up to the house of the Lord and Eli the priest was sitting on the seat by the doorpost. She prayed to the Lord and wept in anguish. Then she made a vow, and said, "O Lord of hosts if you will give your maid-servant a male child, then I will give him to the Lord all the days of his life, and no razor shall come upon his head." (1 Samuel 1:11) Eli the priest was watching her as she stood silently, for she was praying in her heart.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               صعدت إلي بيت الرب وكان عالى الكاهن جالساً علي الكرسي عند الباب ?صلت الي الرب وبكت ونذرت نذراً للرب إذا اعطاها نسلاً وقالت: إذا أعطيتني زرع بشر ?اني أعطيه لك كل حياته ولا يعل رأسه موسي " (1 صم :1 :11 ) ولما رأها عالي الكاهن واق?ة ساكتة لانها كانت تصلي بقلبها ?قط.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Eli thought that she was drunk and he rebuked her saying, “How long will you be drunk? Put your wine away from you!? And Hannah answered and said; "No, my lord, I am a woman of sorrowful spirit, I have drunk neither wine nor intoxicating drink, but have poured out my soul before the Lord." Then Eli answered and said, "Go in peace, and the God of Israel grant your petition." (I Samuel 1:17) She believed his words went her way and ate, and her face was no longer sad.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ظنها سكري ?إنتهرها قائلا: " إنزعي خمرك عنك" ?أجابت حنة وقالت: "لا يا سيدي أنا أمراة حزينة الروح ولم أشرب خمراً ولا مسكراً بل أسكب ن?سي أمام الرب من كثرة كربتى" ?قال لها عالي: " أذهبي بسلام واله إسرائيل يعطيك سؤل قلبك" ?أمنت ومضت ?ي طريقها وأكلت ولم يكن وجهها بعد حزيناً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Then she conceived and brought forth a son, and she called him Samuel, which is a Hebrew name means, "God has heard." When she weaned him, she took him to the house of the Lord, as she had vowed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم حبلت وولدت إبناً ودعت أسمه صموئيل وهو إسم عبراني معناه "الله سمع" ولما ?طمته أصعدته الي بيت الرب و?اء لنذرها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               She brought the child to Eli the priest, and she said, "I am the woman who stood by you here praying to the Lord. For this child I prayed, and the Lord has granted me my petition which I asked of Him. Therefore I also have lent him to the Lord; as long as he lives he shall be lent to the Lord." (I Samuel 1:26-28) Then she praised God in a profound prayer which is recorded in the 2nd chapter of the book of 1st Samuel. She lived after this a life well-pleasing to God. And the Lord visited Hannah, so that she conceived and bore three sons and two daughters (I Samuel 2:21). After she had completed her good endeavor, she departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقدمته إلي عالي الكاهن قائلة : "أنا المراة التي وق?ت تصلي الي الرب لأجل هذا الصبي ?أعطاني الرب سؤل قلبي وها إنا أقدمه للرب ليكون خادماً له ?ي بيته الي الأبد. ثم سبحت الرب بتسبحة عميقة مذكورة ?ي الإصحاح الثاني من س?ر صموئيل الأول وعاشت بعد ذلك وولدت ثلاثة بنين وبنتين (1صم 2 : 21) ولما أكملت سعيها الصالح تنيحت بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائما أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.7">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Seventh Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the seventh day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Paul of Tammoh</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس الأنبا بولا الطموهي</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 134 of the martyrs (418 A.D.), the great saint Abba Paul (Paula) of Tammoh (El-Tammohi), departed. This saint was born in the city of Tammoh (Thmoui). Since his young age he was inclined to worship in seclusion. He went to Ansena Mountain; there he lived with his disciple Ezekiel.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 134 للشهداء (418 م ) تنيح القديس العظيم الأنبا بولا الطموهى. وقد ولد هذا القديس ببلدة طموه (إحدي قرى محا?ظة الجيزة) .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               For his great love to the Lord Christ, he exhausted his body with austere asceticism, fasting, and many prayers in a way that exceeds human endurance. For this, the Lord Christ appeared to him and said; “Enough struggle my beloved Paul.? St. Paul humbly answered Him, “Let me exhaust my body, O My Master for Your name’s sake, as You exhausted Yourself for mankind, and You are the true God who gave Himself up for us the unworthy sinners.? So, the Lord consoled him and strengthened him, then ascended to heaven.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ومن عظم محبته للمسيح أضني جسده بكثرة النسك والأصوام حتي ظهر له السيد المسيح قائلاً: "ك?اك تعباً ياحبيبي بولا " ?قال له ?ي إتضاع: "دعنى ياسيدي أتعب جسدي من أجلك كما تعبت أنت من أجل جنس البشر وأنت الاله الحقيقي قد متْ عنا نحن الخطاة غير المستحقين". ?عزاه الرب وقواه ثم صعد الي السماء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Our righteous father St. Bishoy went to Mount Ansena, after the first raid of the Berbers on the wilderness of Scetis in the year 407 A.D. The saint Abba Paula received him with joy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما مضي البار الأنبا بيشوي الي جبل أنصنا بعد غارة البربر الأولي علي برية شيهيت سنة 407م، وإستقبله القديس بولا ب?رح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The angel of the Lord had appeared to Abba Paula and told him, "Your body will be with that of Anba Bishoy." The promise of the angel was fulfilled; Anba Bishoy departed on the 7th of Abib, year 133 of the martyrs (417 A.D.) and was buried there. Three month later, Abba Paula departed, and his body was placed beside the body of Anba Bishoy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لأن ملاك الرب كان قد ظهر له وقال له: "أن جسدك سيكون مع جسد الأنبا بيشوى". وقد تم قول الملاك بعد ذلك إذ تنيح الانبا بيشوي ?ي 7 أبيب 133 للشهداء (417م) ود?ن جسده هناك وبعده بثلاثة شهور تنيح القديس الأنبا بولا ووضعوا جسده بجوار جسد الأنبا بيشوي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the papacy of Pope Yousab (Joseph) I, in the period between 830 A.D. and 849 A.D., he wished to relocate the body of Anba Bishoy to his monastery in the wilderness of Scetis to be among his children the monks. Those who were in charge of this task, placed the body of St. Bishoy on a boat, however, the boat would not move.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي زمان بطريركية البابا يوساب الأول ?ي ال?ترة من سنة 830 م الي سنة 849م أراد هذا البابا نقل جسد الأنبا بيشوى الي ديره بشيهيت ليكون بين أولاده. ولما قام المكل?ون بهذه المهمة بوضع جسد الأنبا بيشوي ?ي الس?ينة تعطلت عن المسير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               There was a righteous old monk called Armia (Jeremiah) who told them, “The boat will not move with the body of Anba Bishoy alone, because there was a covenant between the two saints, Anba Bishoy and Anba Paul with a divine providence that they will not be separated during their sojourn days on earth and also after their repose.? They went back and carried the body of Anba Paul (Paula) and placed it on the boat beside the body of his friend Anba Bishoy. The boat sailed peacefully and they praised God and venerated these two great saints.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان هناك شيخ قديس ي?دعي أرميا أخبرهم ان المركب لن تستطيع المسير بجسد الأنبا بيشوي وحده ، لانه كان يوجد عهد بين القديسين الأنبا بيشوى والأنبا بولا من ق?بل الله أن يظلا معاً وغير م?ترقين ?ي أيام غربتهما علي الارض وبعد نياحتهما أيضاً.  ?رجعوا وحملوا جسد الأنبا بولا أيضاً ووضعوه ?ي الس?ينة بجوار جسد صديقه الانبا بيشوى  ، ?سارت الس?ينة بسلام ?سبحوا الله ومجدوا القديسين العظيمين الأنبا بولا وصديقه الانبا بيشوى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When they arrived with them to the monastery of Anba Bishoy in the wilderness of Shiheet, Scetis, they placed the bodies in one case (reliquary) and placed it in the church of St. Bishoy. Their bodies are still together in a splendid richly decorated shrine. Some miracles and healings are manifested from their bodies till now.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما وصلوا بهما الي دير الأنبا بيشوى ببرية شيهيت وضعوهما ?ي صندوق واحد مع بعضهما داخل كنيسة الانبا بيشوي. ومازالا يرقدان معا حتى اليوم داخل مقصورة جميلة تظهر منها بعض المعجزات والاش?ية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائما أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.8">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eighth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eighth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Matra</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس مطرا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Matra the elder was martyred. He was a pious Christian from the city of Alexandria. When the infidel emperor Decius reigned, he ordered the persecution of the Christians in every place of the Empire.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم أستشهد القديس مطرا الشيخ. وقد كان مسيحياً تقياً بمدينة الإسكندرية ?لما ملَك ديسيوس المنا?ق أمر بإضطهاد المسيحيين ?ي كل مكان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When his edict reached the city of Alexandria, they seized this saint, brought him before the governor and he confessed the Lord Christ. The Governor commanded him to worship the idols and promised him with splendid promises, which he refused. Then he threatened and intimidated him with severe punishment.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما وصلت أوامره الي مدينة الأسكندرية قبضوا علي هذا القديس وأحضروه أمام الوالي ?أعتر? بالسيد المسيح. ?أمره الوالي بالسجود للأصنام ووعده بوعود عظيمة ?لم يقبل منه. ثم هدده وتوعده بالعقاب الشديد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Matra did not change his conviction, but instead he shouted saying, "I worship and kneel only to the Lord Christ, the creator of heaven and earth. How can I forsake Him and worship idols made of stones and wood that does not hear or see?!?"            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?لم يتراجع أيضاً عن رأيه بل قال للوالي : "أنا أعبد وأسجد للسيد المسيح خالق السماء والارض ?كي? أتركه وأسجد للاصنام المصنوعة من الحجارة والخشب التي لا تسمع ولا تبصر ؟! "            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Governor became enraged and ordered him beaten. He was severely beaten and then hanged up by his arms. Later on, they imprisoned him for few days in a repugnantly smelling dark prison. Afterwards, they took him out of prison, beaten him again and wounded him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?غضب الوالي  جداً وأمر بضربه ?ضربوه وعلقوه من ذراعيه ثم حبسوه أياماً ?ي حبس مظلم كريه الرائحة وبعد ذلك أخرجوه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Finally, when the governor saw him steadfast in his faith in the Lord Christ, to Him is the glory, he ordered to behead St. Matra outside the city, so he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما رأه الوالي ثابتاً علي إيمانه بالسيد المسيح له المجد أمر بقطع رأسه خارج المدينة ?نال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the Saints Abba Hor, Tosia (Susanna) and their Children</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديسين أباهور وطوسيا واولادهما</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also is the commemoration of the martyrdom of Sts. Abba Hor, Tosia and their children.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي مثل هذا اليوم تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار استشهاد القديسين أباهور وطوسيا وأولادهما.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها ?لتكن معنا . آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Abba Agathon, the Hermit</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس الانبا اغاثون المتوحد</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also, the church celebrates the commemoration of the departure of Saint Agathon, the hermit.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي مثل هذا اليوم أيضاً تع?يد الكنيسة بتذكار نياحة القديس أغاثون المتوحد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He became a disciple of Abba Poemen in the wilderness of Scetis during the fourth century. When his teacher departed, he followed the instructions of St. Arsenius. He left the wilderness after the first raid of the Berbers on Scetis in the year 410 A.D. and lived on Torah mount .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وهو كان قد تتلمذ علي القديس بيمن ببرية شيهيت ?ي القرن الرابع وبعد نياحة معلمه سلك بإرشاد القديس أرسانيوس وقد ترك القديس البرية بعد هجوم البربر الأول عام 410 م وعاش بجبل طره (جنوب القاهرة).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He strived to fulfill the Divine commandments. He was simple in his clothing and he led a pious ascetic life. He only owned an iron knife to split the fronds (palm leaves) and braid baskets. It was said about him that he was full of sweetness, gentleness and enthusiasm. He was able with his wisdom and renouncing the world, to gather around him many monks. He loved the virtue of giving and serving the sojourners.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان حريصا علي إتمام الوصايا الالهية كما كان بسيطاً ?ي ملبسه وزاهدا ?ي معيشته ?لم يملك سوي حديدة صغيرة لشق الخوص وعمل السلاسل. وقيل عنه أنه كان مملوءاً لط?اً ونشاطاً ولحكمته الروحية ألت? حوله العديد من الرهبان. كما كان محباً ل?ضيلة العطاء وخدمة الغرباء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One time he found a sick man lying on the side of the road so he carried him to a hostel, cared for and provided for his care for four month. After the man was healed St Agathon went to the desert saying to himself, “I wish that I can find a leprous man to give him my body and he gave me his body.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ذات مرة وجد إنساناً مطروحاً عليلاً ?حمله إلى بيت وأقام يخدمه و ين?ق عليه مدة أربعة شهور. وبعد أن ش?ي أنطلق الي البرية قائلا لن?سه: كنت أشاء لو وجدت رجلا مجذوماً ياخذ جسدى ويعطيني جسده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He used to say, “I never went to sleep and I was angry at someone.? He also has a famous saying, “If a man of wrath to raise the dead, he would not be accepted by God.? The paradise of the fathers records for him many useful sayings.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كما كان يقول: "ما رقدت وأنا غاضب من إنسان وله عبارته الشهيرة" وأيضاً قال: "وإن اقام الغضوب أمواتاً ?ما هو مقبول عند الله"  وكان له أيضاً اقوال كثيرة نا?عة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When his departure drew near, he spent three days in a deep contemplation and he said to those who were around him, ?I am occupied at this hour by meeting Christ? then departed in peace. His face was shining and smiling as he was meeting his beloved friend that he longed for.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وعند إقتراب إنطلاق روحه الطاهرة إلي السماء مكث ثلاثة ايام ?ي تأمل عميق. ولما رقد قال لمن حوله إصنعوا محبة ?اني مشغول ?ي تلك الساعة بلقاء المسيح. ثم تنيح بسلام وأبصروا وجه منيراً مبتسماً كمن يستقبل حبيبه المشتاق إليه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائما أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.9">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Ninth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the ninth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Omanious (Eumenes), the Seventh Patriarch of the See of St. Mark</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا أومانيوس البطريرك السابع من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 141 A.D., the pure and chaste saint, Anba Omanious (Eumenes) the seventh patriarch of the See of St. Mark, departed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 141 م تنيح القديس البكر الطاهر أومانيوس البطريرك السابع من بطاركة الكرازة  المرقسية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint was born in the city of Alexandria and he was raised in Christian upbringing. He was known for his knowledge and moral excellence so Pope Ebrimous (Primus), the fifth Patriarch, ordained him a deacon then St. Yostus (Justus), the sixth patriarch, ordained him a priest. He also appointed him the dean of the Theological School of Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?لد هذا القديس ?ي مدينة الاسكندرية وتربي تربية مسيحية وأشتهر بالعلم وال?ضيلة ?رسمه البابا إبريموس (البطريرك الخامس) شماساً ثم رسمه القديس يسطس (البطريرك السادس) قساً وأسند إليه رئاسة مدرسة الاسكندرية اللاهوتية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Yustus departed, they unanimously agreed to appoint this father a Patriarch. He was consecrated and enthroned in the year 129 A.D. Pope Omanious consecrated many bishops for many parishes in the land of Egypt, Nubia and the five western cities (Pentapolis). He also ordained a great number of priests to shepherd the faithful and to teach them the Christian faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تنيح البابا يسطس أت?قت الاراء علي تقديمه بطريركاً ?تمت سيامته ?ي سنة 129م وقام بسيامة أساق?ة كثيرين وأرسلهم الي مراكزهم بالبلاد المصرية والنوبة والخمس مدن الغربية كما قام بسيامة عدداً كبيراً من الكهنة لرعاية المؤمنين وتعليمهم الإيمان المسيحي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Omanious persevered in bringing back the strayed sinners. He explained to the pagans plainly the Divinity of our Lord Jesus Christ. He also explained to the heretics that the Lord Christ is one in His divine essence. He remained on the patriarchal throne for eleven years and three months and departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أما القديس اومانيوس ?قد كان مداوماً علي رد الضالين من الخطاة ومبيناً للوثنين بايضاح الوهية السيد المسيح وللهراطقة وحدانية جوهر لاهوت السيد المسيح وأقام علي الكرسي المرقسي إحدي عشرة سنة وثلاثة أشهر ثم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا امين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of St. Simon (Simeon), the Bishop</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار القديس سمعان الإسق?</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the church celebrates the commemoration of St. Simon, the Bishop.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي مثل هذا اليوم تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار القديس سمعان الاسق?.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً ابدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.10">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Tenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم العاشر من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the tenth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم العاشر من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Sergius, the Friend of St. Bacchus</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد القديس سرجيوس ر?يق واخس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Sergius, the friend of St. Bacchus, was martyred, which was during the reign of Emperor Maximianus (284 – 312 A.D.).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم و?ي عهد الملك مكسيميانوس (284 – 312م) أستشهد القديس سرجيوس ر?يق القديس واخس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               These two saints were high ranking officers, advanced in the court of Emperor Maximianus, and were very close to him. This Emperor was heathen and these two saints did not agree with his infidelity.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد كان هذان القديسان من الضباط المتقدمين ?ي بلاط الملك مكسيميانوس وكانا من المقربين لديه. وكان هذا الملك وثنياً ولم يوا?قه هذان القديسان علي ك?ره.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Emperor was enraged and he sent them to Antiochus, King of Syria, to torture them and if they did not forsake their faith to slay them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?غضب عليهما  وارسلهما الي أنطيوخس والي سورية ليعذبهما. ولكن القديسان لم يرجعا عن إيمانهما المسيحي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Antiochus inflicted St. Bacchus with severe tortures and, when he did not dissuade him from his Christianity, he ordered his men to behead him. They cast his body into the River Euphrates , and he also ordered to imprison St. Sergius.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?عذب الوالي أنطيوخس القديس واخس عذاباً شديداً ثم أمر بذبحه والقائه ?ي النهر كما أمر بحبس القديس سرجيوس ?ي السجن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Sergius was grieved for his friend Bacchus until he saw him in his sleep in a beautiful palace, shining brightly and rested; so his soul was exceedingly comforted.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبقي سرجيوس حزيناً علي صديقه ?رأي ?ي نومه أخاه واخس منيراً ساطعاً ومستريحاً ?تعزت ن?سه كثيراً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Later on, the Governor commanded to drive nails into St. Sergius' feet, and to send him to Al-Rasafa tied to the tails of the horses; and his blood flowed down on the road.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد ذلك أمر الوالي أن يسمر سرجيوس بالمسامير الطويلة ?ي رجليه ?سمروه وأرسلوه الي الرصا?ة إحدي مدن الشام مربوطاً ?ي زيول الخيل وكان دمه يقطر علي الارض .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On their way, they met a virgin damsel, who gave them water to drink. When she saw the sorrowful condition the saint was in, she felt sad for him and encouraged him. The saint told her, "Come, follow me to the city of Al-Rasafa to take my body," and she followed him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي الطريق قابلتهم ?تاة ?أستقوا منها ماء ولما رأت هذا القديس ?ي هذه الحالة السيئة حزنت عليه وأخذت تشجعه ?قال لها: " الحقي بي ?ي الرصا?ة لتأخذي جسدي" ?تبعتهم الي هناك.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Governor of Al-Rasafa was a friend of St. Sergius, and the Governor tried to convince him to change his mind to save his life. When St. Sergius did not accept his advice, he ordered his head cut off, so he received the crown of martyrdom. That virgin came and received the blood which flowed from his holy neck and kept it in a clip of wool.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحاول والي الرصا?ة إقناعه بالعدول عن رأيه ح?ظاً لحياته ، ولما ر?ض أمر بقطع رأسه ونال إكليل الشهادة. ?تقدمت تلك ال?تاة وأخذت الدم الذى خرج من عنقه المقدس وجعلته ?ي جزة الصو?.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               However, the holy body was kept until the end of the days of persecution when they built a great cathedral for him at Al-Rasafa. The church was consecrated by 15 bishops. They laid his holy body in a coffin (sarcophagus) made of marble. Those who were present witnessed that fragrant oil flew from his body that healed incurable illnesses.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . أما جسده المقدس ?قد ح??ظ الي إنقضاء زمن الاضطهاد ، حيث بنوا له كنيسة عظيمة ?ي الرصا?ة قام بتكريسها خمسة عشر أسق?اً ووضعوا الجسد المقدس ?ي تابوت من الرخام وكان ينبع منه دهن طيب يش?ي الامراض المستعصية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In Old Cairo, there is a famous church after the name of St. Sergius which is called the church of Abu-Serga. The church is one of the oldest antiquated churches in Egypt.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتوجد بمصر القديمة كنيسة شهيرة باسم القديس سرجيوس يطلقون عليها كنيسة "أبوسرجة" وهي من أقدم الكنائس الاثرية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Under the church sanctuary, you find the grotto of the Holy Family where they stayed for a period of time during their flight to Egypt.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ويوجد تحت هيكلها مغارة العائلة المقدسة حيث أقامت ?يها العائلة المقدسة مدة من الزمان أثناء هروبها الي مصر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of St. Sergius be with us all and Glory be to our God, forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلاة القديس سرجيوس ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً ابدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.11">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eleventh Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الحادي عشر من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eleventh day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الحادي عشر من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. James, Patriarch of Antioch</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة الأنبا يعقوب بطريرك انطاكية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, the Holy Father Abba James, Patriarch of Antioch, departed. Great tribulations befell this father. He was exiled for defending the Orthodox faith. After he remained in exile for a period of time, the people of the city gathered and brought him back. Then the Arians exiled him again and he stayed in exile for seven more years, and then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم تنيح الآب القديس الأنبا يعقوب بطريرك أنطاكية. وقد لاقي هذا الأب شدائد كثيرة ون?ي من أجل الإيمان الأرثوذكسي. و?ي المرة الأخيرة ن?اه الأريوسيون ومكث ?ي المن?ي سبع سنين ثم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Pelagia, the Penitent</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديسة بيلاجية التائبة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, of the year 176 of the martyrs (460 A.D.), St. Pelagia, the penitent, departed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً من سنة 176 للشهداء ( 460 م ) تنيحت القديسة بيلاجية التائبة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This righteous woman was born in the city of Antioch to pagan parents. Besides a corrupt faith, she had a corrupt manner of life also.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولدت هذه القديسة بمدينة إنطاكية من إبوين وثنيين وكانت قد إقتنت مع نجاسة المعتقد نجاسة السيرة أيضاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Once, she met a holy bishop, whose name was Nonnius, of Edessa, who preached and instructed her. She believed in the Lord Christ through him, and confessed to him everything that she had done. He encouraged her not to despair but to repent with a true determination. He baptized her and then received the Holy mysteries. The grace illuminated her heart and she led a penitent life with a firm heart and a pure determination. She exhausted her body with strenuous worship, and asceticism.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت تعيش ?ي إماكن ال?جور وجمعت من ذلك مبالغ طائلة.  وقابلها مرة أسق? قديس يدعي نونيوس ?وعظها بكلام كثير ?أمنت علي يديه بالسيد المسيح وإعتر?ت له بجميع ماصنعت ?عمدها وناولها من الأسرار المقدسة ، ?إستنارت بالنعمة وتقدمت ?ي حياة التوبة بنية خالصة وأتعبت جسدها بالنسك والعبادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Then she dressed herself in the garb of men and went to Jerusalem where she met St. Alexandros, Patriarch of Jerusalem. She narrated to him her story. He sent her to one of the monasteries nearby Jerusalem. She dwelt there for 40 years worshipping with many prayers and fasts. She was known as the monk Pelagius. Then she lived a solitary life in a cave on Mount of Olives for three years and then departed in peace. No one discovered that she was a woman until it was revealed after her death and they buried her with great veneration.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم تزيت بزي الرجال وذهبت الي أورشليم. وتقابلت مع القديس الكسندروس بطريرك أورشليم وعر?ته بقصتها ?أرسلها الي أحد أديرة الرهبان القريبة من أورشليم ?مكثت ?يه نحو أربعين سنة عابدة بأصوام وصلوات وعر?ت بإسم الراهب بيلاجيوس ثم عاشت ?ي حياة الوحدة داخل مغارة مدة ثلاث سنوات ثم تنيحت بسلام. ولم يكتش? أحد انها إمرأة الا بعد نياحتها ود?نوها بإكرام جزيل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً ابدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.12">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twelfth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثانى عشر من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twelfth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثانى عشر من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Honorable Archangel Michael</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار رئيس الملائكة الجليل ميخائيل</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the twelfth day of each Coptic month the church celebrates, the commemoration of the honorable Michael the Archangel, the head of the Heavenly Hosts. He stands at all times before the throne of the Divine Majesty interceding on behalf of the human race.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تعيد الكنيسة ?ي هذا اليوم من كل شهر قبطى بتذكار رئيس الملائكة الجليل ميخائيل رئيس الأجناد السماوية القائم كل حين أمام كرسي العظمة الالهية يش?ع ?ي جنس البشر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his holy intercession be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة ش?اعته المقدسة ?لتكن معنا .أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Matthew the Evangelist</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس متي الانجيلي البشير</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, of the year 70 A.D., St. Matthew the Evangelist, was martyred. He was one of the Twelve Disciples and his name was Levi. The name Matthew came from the Hebrew word “Mattathia? which means the gift of God.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة70 م إستشهد القديس متي الإنجيلي أحد الاثني عشر رسولاً وكلمة "متي"  من الكلمة العبرية "متاثيا" أى عطية الله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint was born in Cana of Galilee. He had another name which is “Levi? the son of Alphaeus from the tribe of Levi. He was a tax collector in Capernaum for the benefit of the Roman Occupier. This job was hated by the Jews.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولد هذا القديس ?ي قانا الجليل وكان له إسم آخر هو "لاوى" بن حل?ى من سبط لاوى. وكان يعمل عشاراً أى جابياً للضرائب ?ي ك?ر ناحوم لحساب المستعمر الروماني وكانت هذه الوظي?ة مكروهة لليهود.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Lord Chris saw him sitting at the tax office in Capernaum called him for the apostolic ministry (Mat. 9:9). After his calling, he made for the Lord Christ and His disciples a great feast and he invited all his fellow tax collectors to hear the words of grace and life to believe through them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما رآه السيد المسيح جالساً عند مكان الجباية ?ى ك?ر ناحوم دعاه للخدمة الرسولية (مت 9 : 9). وبعد دعوته صنع وليمة عظيمة للرب وتلاميذه دعا ?يها زملاؤه العشارين ليسمعوا كلمات النعمة والحياة ليؤمنوا بها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He became a disciple for the Lord Christ during His earthly ministry. After the ascension of the Lord and the coming down of the Holy Spirit on him along with the disciples, he preached in the land of Palestine, Tyre and Sidon.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و القديس متى تتلمذ للسيد المسيح مدة خدمته علي الارض. وبعد الصعود وحلول الروح القدس عليه مع التلاميذ كرز ?ي بلاد ?لسطين وصور وصيدا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Saint wrote his Gospel around the year 60 A.D. in Hebrew (Aramaic) to declare to the Jews that Jesus Christ is the awaited Savior, the Messiah. In whom all the prophecies of the Old Testament were fulfilled, and for this reason he quoted many of the verses of the Old Testament that spoke about the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كتب هذا القديس إنجيله بالعبرية (الأرامية) لليهود حوالي عام 60 م ليعلن لهم أن الرب يسوع المسيح هو المسيا المخلص المنتظر الذي ?يه تحققت جميع نبوات العهد القديم ، لذلك إقتبس الكثير من آيات العهد القديم التى تتحدث عن السيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Matthew preached later on in the Arabian countries, Yemen and the southern region of the Arabian peninsula. From there he traveled to Ethiopia. There, he preached the good news of the Gospel and through him the king of Ethiopia’s daughter, Ephigenia believed. She vowed herself to a life of virginity and many of the daughters of the noble families followed her.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كرز القديس متى بعد ذلك ?ي بلاد العرب واليمن وجنوبي الجزيرة العربية ومنها سا?ر الي الحبشة حيث كرز هناك ببشارة الإنجيل. وهناك آمنت علي يديه أ?جانيا إبنة ملك الحبشة ونذرت ن?سها للبتولية وإقت?ي إثرها كثيرات من بنات العظماء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the death of the King of Ethiopia, his brother took over the kingdom by force. He wanted to marry St. Ephigenia to establish his kingdom, but she refused. The king summoned St. Matthew the apostle and asked him to convince her with this marriage. Nevertheless, he did not do that but instead he encouraged her on her vow and decision. The king was filled with rage and wanted to slay the saint.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد موت الملك أغتصب أخوه المملكة وأراد أن يتزوج أ?جانيا لكي يثبَّت مملكته ?ر?ضت.   ?إستدعي متي الرسول وطلب منه إقناعها بهذا الزواج ?لم ي?عل بل ثبتها علي عزمها ونذرها ?غضب الملك وأراد قتله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day while St. Matthew was praying the Divine Liturgy the soldiers of the king took him by surprise and beat him severely until they killed him. Thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبينما هو يصلى القداس الالهى ذات يوم ?اجأه جنود الملك بالضرب حتي قتلوه ?نال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The believers took his pure body and buried him with great honor and many churches were built after his name.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأخذ المؤمنون جسده الطاهر ود?نوه بإحترام جزيل وبنيت على إسمه كنائس كثيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. امين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Abba Demetrius I, the Vinedresser, 12th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا القديس ديمتريوس الكرام البطريرك الثانى عشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 230 A.D., the pure and celibate father, Anba Demetrius I, the 12th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضا من سنة 230 م تنيح الاب البتول الطاهر الأنبا ديمتريوس الأول البطريرك الثاني عشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint was born in the city of Ahnasia . He was an illiterate farmer, and was married. He lived with his wife for 47 years in complete celibacy with all purity and chastity.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?لد هذا القديس بأهناسيا المدينة (مدينة أثرية وهي إحدي مراكز محا?ظة بنى سوي?) وكان ?لاحاً أمياً متزوجاً وقد عاش مع أمراته ?ي بتولية كاملة و?ي ع?ة ونقاوة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the departure of St. Yulianus (Julian), the 11th Pope, drew near, the angel of the Lord appeared to St. Yulianus in a vision and told him about who would succeed him. He gave him a sign saying, "Tomorrow a man shall come to you having a cluster of grapes, he is the one to succeed you.? When he woke up from his sleep, he told those who were around him about this vision.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما قربت نياحة القديس يوليانوس البابا الحادى عشر ظهر له ملاك الرب ?ي رؤيا وأعلمه بمن سيكون بعده وأعطاه علامة بقوله: "غدا سيأتيك رجل ومعه عنقود عنب هو الذي سيخل?ك" ولما إنتبه البطريرك من نومه أخبر من حوله بهذه الرؤيا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               So it happened on the next day that St. Demetrius found a ripened cluster of grapes that was out of season. He carried it to St. Yulianus, to receive his blessing. The father, the Patriarch, took him by his hand and told those who were present, "This is your Patriarch who will be after me." Then he prayed over him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي الغد دخل القديس ديمتريوس الي البابا البطريرك ومعه عنقود عنب نضج ?ي غير أوانه ليقدمه للبابا لينال بركته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They held him and kept him in the patriarchal residence until Pope Yulianus, departed in peace, whereupon they finished the prayers of ordination and enthroned him as patriarch. He was filled with the heavenly grace, and the Lord enlightened his mind and he learned reading and writing. He studied the church books and their interpretations. Words of grace flew from his mouth when he preached the people.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?أمسكوه رغماً عنه وأبقوه ?ي الدار البطريركية الي ان تنيح البابا يوليانوس بسلام.  ?اقاموا القديس ديمتريوس بطريركاً وأكملوا الصلوات عليه ?أمتلئ من النعمة الالهية وتعلم كل علوم البيعة. وكان يعظ الشعب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He established the reckoning of the Epacts, by which the dates of fasting and feasts were determined on a fixed basis and in a very accurate manner. He appended the Holy Fast to the Passion Week.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وهو الذى وضع قواعد حساب الأبقطي الذي به تستخرج مواعيد الاصوام والأعياد بنظام ?ي غاية الدقة.  كذلك هوالذي ضم صوم الأربعين المقدسة الي صوم أسبوع الالام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Demetrius wrote in this respect to the Patriarchs of Jerusalem; of Antioch; of Rome and to others. They all approved, and followed it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكتب بذلك الي بطاركة أورشليم وروما وانطاكية ?إستحسنوه وعملوا به.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               God was with Anba Demetrius because of his purity and chastity. God granted him the gift of knowing who was worthy of partaking of the Holy Mysteries from those who were not worthy. He admonished the sinners urging them to repent.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان الله مع هذا الأب لبتوليته وأعطاه حكمة حتي أنه كان يميز من يستحق التناول ومن لا يستحق وكان يبكت الخطاة ويحثهم علي التوبة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Because he rebuked the sinners often, and urged them on repentance, some of them murmured saying, "This man is married, and how can he rebuke us?" The Lord Almighty wished to reveal to them the virtue of his celibacy, so the angel of the Lord came to him at night and told him, "O Demetrius, do not seek only your salvation and let others be in a web of doubt and perdition. You must reveal the mystery which is between yourself and your wife to the people so that you might remove the doubt from them."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?تذمر بعضهم وقالوا عليه: " هذا رجل متزوج ?كي? يبكتنا؟".  ?أراد الله إظهار بتوليته ?أتاه ملاك الرب قائلا:" لا تطلب خلاصك وحدك وتترك غيرك ?ي شبكة الشك والهلاك. يجب ان تكش? السر الذى بينك وبين زوجتك للشعب حتي يزول عنهم الشك" .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the following morning, after he had celebrated the Divine Liturgy, he ordered the people not to leave the church. He took red-hot coal and placed it in his wife's shawl and his pallium, then they went around in the church and their clothes did not burn. The people were amazed at this miracle. He then told them that he and his wife did not know each other as married people till that day. The doubt was removed from the people and they realized the purity of this father and his chastity.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي الصباح صلي القداس الالهي وبعد الصلاة أمر الشعب بعدم الخروج من الكنيسة ، ونادى على زوجته من بين النساء. ثم أخذ جمراً ووضع بعضا منه ?ي إزار زوجته وبعض آخر ?ي بلينته (أى الشملة الخاصة بالخدمة الكهنوتية) وطا?ا معا ?ي الكنيسة ?لم تحترق ثيابهما ?تعجب الشعب من هذه المعجزة ثم عر?هم أنه وزوجته لم يعر?ا بعضهما معر?ة الزواج الي اليوم وتيقنوا من بتولية هذا الأب وطهارته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the days of his papacy, he did not stop teaching and confirming the believers in the Orthodox Faith. He grown old and reached the age of 105 years, then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وظل هذا القديس يعلم شعبه ويثبتهم علي الايمان المستقيم حتي شاخ وبلغ من العمر مئة وخمس سنين وتنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessings of his prayers be with us all and Glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً ابدياً. أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.13">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Thirteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث عشرمن شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the thirteenth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث عشرمن شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Saint Zacharias, the Monk</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس زكريا الراهب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Zacharias the monk, departed. His father's name was Cyrion. He was married, but he longed for the monastic life. He revealed to his wife his desire and she agreed to his wish. Cyrion had a son, called Zacharias and a daughter. He left them with their mother and went to the desert of Scetis and became a monk under the guidance of a holy old man.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم تنيح القديس المجاهد زكريا الراهب. كان أبوه يدعي قاريون ولكنه إشتاق الي الرهبنة ?كاش? زوجته عن ?كره ?ي الرهبنة ?وا?قته علي ذلك. وكان له إبن وإبنة تركهما مع والدتهما وذهب إلي برية شيهيت حيث ترهب عند شيخ قديس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Shortly after, a great famine befell the country, the wife took the two children and went to him in the desert and handed him the children. But Cyrion told her, “You take the girl and leave the boy with me." She took her daughter and went back. Cyrion took his son Zacharias and brought him to the elders of the monastery who prayed over him and prophesied that he would become a virtuous monk.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد قليل حدث غلاء شديد ?ي البلاد ?اخذت إمراته ط?ليها وذهبت اليه ?ي البرية لتسلمه الط?لين أما هو ?قال لها خذي أنت البنت وإتركي لي الولد ?اخذت البنت وإنصر?ت.  أما هو ?قد أخذ الط?ل وأتي به الى شيوخ الدير ?صلوا عليه وتنباؤا عنه بانه سيكون راهباً ?اضلاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Zacharias was brought up well in the desert, and advanced in every virtue. Because of his fair look, there were many murmurs in the desert as they said, "How is it, a boy like that dwells in the desert among the monks?" When Zacharias heard that, he went to lake El-Natroun (which was very salty) without telling anyone. He took off his apparel, plunged his body into the lake, and remained in it for many hours. The color of his body became black and he looked like a leper. Then he went forth from the water, put on his apparel and came to his father who did not recognize him until he had stared at him closely. When he asked him about what had changed his appearance, he told him what he had done.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتربى زكريا ?ي البرية تربية صالحة وتقدم ?ي ال?ضائل. ولكن حدث تذمر بسبب جمال صورته وكانوا يقولون: " كي? يكون صبي مثل هذا ?ي البرية بين الرهبان؟" ولما سمع زكريا هذا الكلام ذهب الي بحيرة النطرون وخلع ثيابه ونزل ?يها وإنغمس ?يها عدة ساعات ?تحول لون جسده الي السواد وصار كالمجزوم. ثم صعد من الماء ولبس ثيابه وأتي الي أبيه ?لم يعر?ه الا بعد أن ت?رس ?يه جيداً ?لما ساله عن الذي غير منظره أعلمه بما عمل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On Sunday, he went with his father to the church to attend the Divine Liturgy and partake of the Holy Mysteries. The Lord revealed to St. Isidore, the priest of Scete, what St. Zacharias had done. He marveled and said to the monks, "Zacharias received the mysteries last Sunday as a man, but now he has become an angel."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما كان يوم الأحد مضي مع أبيه الي الكنيسة لحضور القداس والتناول من الأسرار المقدسة ?كش? الله للقديس إيسوذوروس قس الاسقيط ما صنعه القديس زكريا ?تعجب وقال لمجمع الرهبان : "إن زكريا قد تناول ?ي الأحد الماضي كإنسان أما الأن ?قد صار ملاكاً ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint advanced in many virtues, especially the virtue of humility that his father said about him, "I have labored greatly in the spiritual fight, but I have never attained the extent of my son Zacharias."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ونما هذا القديس ?ي جميع ال?ضائل خاصةً ?ي ?ضيلة الإتضاع حتي قال أبوه عنه: " إني تحملت تعباً كثيراً ?ي الجهاد ولكني لم أصل الي رتبة أبني زكريا ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Zacharias lived an ascetic life and strove exceedingly hard for 45 years then he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأقام القديس زكريا مجاهداً وناسكاً ?ي البرية خمسة وأربعين سنة ثم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً ابدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.14">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fourteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع عشر من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fourteenth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع عشر من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Philip, One of the Seven Deacons</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس ?يلبس أحد الشمامسة السبعة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Philip, one of the Seven Deacons, departed. This saint was born in Caesarea, Palestine. The Lord Jesus Christ chose him to be one of the 70 Disciples and sent them forth to preach and heal the sick . The Apostles chose him as one of the Seven Deacons appointed to serve .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم تنيح القديس ?يلبس أحد رؤساء الشمامسة الذين إختارهم الرسل. ولد هذا القديس ?ي قيصرية ?لسطين وقد عينه الرب يسوع من ضمن السبعين رسولاً الذين أرسلهم ليكرزوا ويش?وا المرضي (لوقا ١٠ : 1) ثم إختاره الرسل ضمن السبعة شمامسة الذين اقاموهم للخدمة ( أع 6 : 5).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint preached in the cities of Samaria and baptized its people. He also was the one to baptize Simon the magician who perished when he tried to buy the gift of the Holy Spirit with money.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بشر هذا القديس ?ي مدن السامرة وعمد أهلها وهو الذي عمَّد سيمون الساحر الذى هلك لما قصد أن يقتني موهبة الروح القدس بالمال.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day the angel of the Lord spoke to Philip saying, "Arise and go toward the south along the road which goes down from Jerusalem to Gaza." He rose and went and behold a man of Ethiopia, a eunuch of great authority under Candace, the Queen of the Ethiopians. As he was returning and sitting in his chariot, he was reading Isaiah the prophet. Then the spirit said to Philip, "Go near and join this chariot." So Philip ran to him, and heard him reading the prophet Isaiah and said, "Do you understand what you are reading?"            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وذات يوم أمر الملاك القديس ?يلبس ان يذهب من اورشليم ?ي طريق غزة ?وجد الخصّي الحبشي وزير كنداكة عند عودته من اورشليم راكباً مركبته وهو يقرأ ?ي س?ر أشعياء النبي "مثل شاه سيق الي الذبح ومثل خرو? صامت أمام الذي يجزه هكذا لم ي?تح ?اه " (أشعياء 53 : 7) . ?قال الروح القدس ل?يلبس تقدم ورا?ق هذه المركبة ?بادر ?يلبس وجلس معه ?ي المركبة وسأله " ألعلك ت?هم ما تقرا ؟"            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               And he said, "How can I, unless someone guides me?" And he asked Philip to come up and sit with him. The place in the scripture which he read was this, "He was led as a sheep to the slaughter. And as a lamb before its shearer is silent. So He opened not his mouth."            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               So the eunuch answered Philip and said, "I ask you, of whom does the prophet say this, of himself or of some other man?" Then Philip opened his mouth, and beginning at this scripture, preached Jesus to him. Now as they went down the road, they came to some water. And the eunuch said, "See, here is water; what hinders me from being baptized?" Then Philip said, if you believe with all your heart, you may." And he answered and said, "I believe that Jesus Christ is the Son of God."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يما هما سائران اقبلا علي ماء ?قال الخصي هوذا ماء ماذا يمنع ان أعتمد؟ ?قال له ?يلبس أن كنت تؤمن من كل قلبك يجوز. ?قال أنا اؤمن أن يسوع هو إبن الله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               So he commanded the chariot to stand still. And both Philip and the eunuch went down into the water, and he baptized him. Now when they came up out of the water, the Spirit of the Lord caught Philip away, so that the eunuch saw him no more; and he went on his way rejoicing.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?أمر ان تق? المركبة ?نزلا كلاهما إلي الماء ?يلبس والخصي ?عمده. ولما صعدا من الماء خط? روح الرب ?يلبس ?لم يبصره الخصي ?ذهب ?ي طريقه ?رحاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               But Philip was found at Azotus and passing through he preached in all the cities, till he came to Caesarea .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأما ?يلبس ?و?جد ?ي أشدود (أحدي مدن ?لسطين الخمسة الكبري تبعد عن غزة   24 ميل إلي الشمال). وبينما هو مجتاز كان يبشر ?ي جميع المدن حتي جاء الي قيصرية ( أع 8 :36-40) مدينة كبيرة علي شاطئ البحر الابيض المتوسط مسقط رأس ?يليبس المبشر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He went around the countries of Asia and preached the life living Gospel there and the Lord supported his ministry with many miracles. He was married and had four daughters who prophesied and preached the word of God with him. He brought many of the Jews, the Samaritans and others to the faith. When he finished his good endeavor, he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               طا? القديس ?يليبس بلاد آسيا وكرز ?يها بالبشارة المحيية وكان الرب يعضده ويؤيد خدمته بالأيات التابعة وكان متزوجاً وله أربع بنات يتنبآن ( اع 21 : 8 -9 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً ابدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.15">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fifteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس عشر من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fifteenth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس عشر من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Saint Panteleimon, the Physician</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد بندلائيمون الطبيب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 21 of the martyrs (305 A.D.), St. Panteleimon, the physician, was martyred. This saint was born in the city of Nicomedia. His father “Eustorgius? worshipped idols but his mother “Eubula? was a Christian.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 21 للشهداء ( 305 م) أستشهد القديس بندلائيمون الطبيب.  و?لد هذا القديس ?ي مدينة نيقوميدية كان أبوه (أوستورجيوس ) وثنياً وأمه (أوبالا) مسيحية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Panteleimon had been educated as a physician. He excelled in his profession and his fame spread, so Emperor Maximian made him his private physician. He appreciated him for his success in his work, intelligence and his gentle demeanor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد علماه صناعة الطب ?نبغ ?يها وذاع صيته ?جعله الملك مكسيميانوس طبيبه الخاص وكان يحبه من أجل نجاحه ?ي العمل ولط? أخلاقه وذكائه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Panteleimon met a priest whose name was Hermolaus who taught him the facts of the Christian faith and baptized him. He reached a high level of the virtuous life. God wrought great wonders by his hands.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتقابل بندلائيمون مع قسّ يدعى هومولاوس ?علمّه حقائق الإيمان المسيحي ثم عمّده. ?جاهد ?ي ال?ضيلة وإرتقي ?ي سلم درجاتها وأجري الله علي يديه آيات عظيمة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Once, a blind man came to him to be treated by his medicine. He made the sign of the Cross over his eyes in the Name of the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit and his eyes were healed immediately. When the Emperor heard the news of this account, he had the blind man brought to him and asked him about how his eyes were healed. He told him; St. Panteleimon healed him by making the sign of the cross over his eyes.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               منها أن إنسان أعمي قصده ليداويه ?رشم عليه علامة الصليب ?برئت عيناه ?ي الحال.  ولما علم الملك بالخبر إستحضر ذلك الرجل وسأله عن كي?ية ش?اء عينيه ?أعلمه أن القديس بندلائمون ش?اه برشم علامة الصليب على عيناه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Emperor had St. Panteleimon the physician brought to him and asked him about his belief. He confessed that he was a Christian. The Emperor gently rebuked him, how could he accept a faith different than that of the Emperor? The emperor brought him closer to him and bestowed riches and many honors on him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?استحضر الملك بندلائيمون الطبيب وسأله عن معتقده ?أقر إنه مسيحي وعاتبه بلط? كي? يقبل إيماناً غير إيمان الملك وقد قربه اليه وأعطاه غني وكرامات كثيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Panteleimon answered politely and courageously that he cannot renounce his Christ. The Emperor threatened to inflict upon him different kinds of tortures, but the saint was not moved. He started to torture him sometimes by beating and by flogging and often times by casting him into the sea or into the fire. The Lord Christ appeared to him to strengthen and comfort him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?أجابه بأدب وشجاعة إنه لايستطيع أن يجحد مسيحه. وعند ذلك هدده الملك بأنواع العذاب ?لم يتزعزع إيمانه. ?بدأ ?ي تعذيبه تارة بالضرب والجلد وأخري بالرمى ?ي البحر والنار ?كان السيد المسيح يظهر له ويقويه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Later on, the Emperor ordered to behead him. After the saint had prayed a fervent prayer the soldiers cut off his head and thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم أمر الملك بقطع رأسه ?صلي القديس صلاة حارة وقطع الجند رأسه ?نال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               .  بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً ابدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.16">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Sixteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس عشر من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the sixteenth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس عشر من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Agathon, 39th Pope of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة الانبا اغاثون البطريرك التاسع والثلاثين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 397 of the martyrs (681 A.D.), Pope Agathon, the 39th Pope of Alexandria, departed. He was from a noble family in Marriot. When he grew up, he became a disciple to Pope Benjamin, the 38th Pope.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 379 للشهداء ( 681 م ) تنيح البابا أغاثون البطريرك التاسع والثلاثون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. وكان من عائلة شري?ة بمريوط ?لما كبر صار تلميذاً للبابا بنيامين البطريرك الثامن والثلاثين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Anba Benjamin ordained him a priest for one of the churches of Alexandria. When the Pope disappeared for a period of time from the face of his Chalcedonian persecutors he left Agathon to preach to the believers and to establish them in the Orthodox faith. Agathon went around disguised wearing a carpenter's apparel, and carrying carpenter’s tools performing his pastoral duties and celebrating the divine mysteries in secret. He kept doing this till the return of Pope Benjamin from his hiding to the papal See, so he appointed Fr. Agathon as his private secretary.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد رسمه كاهناً علي إحدي كنائس الإسكندرية - ولما إخت?ي البابا بنيامين زمناً من وجه مضطهديه الخلقيدونين ترك الاب أغاثون يواظب علي وعظ المؤمنين وتثبيتهم علي الإيمان المستقيم ?كان يطو? متخ?ياً ?ي زى نجار يحمل أدوات النجارة ويمارس أعمال الكهنوت الرعوية ويقيم الأسرار الإلهية خ?ية. وظل هكذا حتى عاد البابا بنيامين الى مقر كرسيه ?إتخذه سكرتيراً خاصا له.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Benjamin departed, this saint was chosen to the honorable Patriarchal rank. He was consecrated on the 14th of Tobe, year 387 of the martyrs (662 A.D.). He faced great tribulations for the sake of keeping the Orthodox faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تنيح البابا بنيامين ال 38 إختير هذا القديس لرتبة البطريركية الجليلة ?رسموه  يوم 14 طوبة سنة 387 للشهداء (662م).  وقد لقي شدائد كثيرة من أجل الإيمان المستقيم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               For example, a man whose name was Theodorus, of the Chalcedonian faith, went to El-Khalifa in Damascus and gave him much money and took from him a decree to appoint him the Governor of Alexandria, El-Behira and Marriot. When he became in charge of this position, he afflicted Anba Agathon with many hardships and severely persecuted him. He levied high taxes on the Pope. He put forth an order that any man who might find the Patriarch should slay him. Anba Agathon detained himself in his cell until God destroyed that evil Governor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               من ذلك ان إنساناً يدعي ثيؤدوروس خلقيدوني المذهب ذهب إلي الخلي?ة بدمشق وقدم له أموالا وأخذ منه أمرا بتعينه والياً علي الإسكندرية والبحيرة ومريوط. ?لما تولى هذا المنصب إضطهد الأنبا أغاثون إضطهاداً شديداً وكان يطلب منه جزية كبيرة وأصدر أمراً بأن أى إنسان يجد البطريرك ?ليقتله. ?حبس الانبا اغاثون ن?سه ?ي قلايته الى ان أهلك الله هذا الوالي الشرير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the days of this Pope, the building of St. Macarius' church in his monastery in the wilderness of Scetis was completed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي زمن هذا البابا كملت عمارة كنيسة القديس مكاريوس بديره ببرية شيهيت.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One night the angel of the Lord appeared to him and told him about a holy monk from the monastery of St. Macarius whose name was John and ordered to bring him to assist him in preaching and teaching the people. The angel told him also that he would be Patriarch after him. Anba Agathon brought him and entrusted to him the administration of the churches, and teaching the believers. When he completed his good endeavor departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ى إحدى الأيام ظهر له ملاك الرب وأعلمه عن راهب قديس بدير القديس مكاريوس إسمه يوحنا وأمره بأن يستحضره ليساعده ?ي وعظ الشعب وتعليمه وأخبره بأنه سيصير بطريركاً بعده ?إستحضره وسلم إليه أمور الكنائس وتعليم الشعب ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا امين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Sts. Carpus, Apollo and Peter</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار القديسين كاربوس وأبولوس وبطرس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also is the commemoration of the saints Carpus, Apollos and Peter. They were disciples of the Holy Father Anba Isaiah of Scetis.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي مثل هذا اليوم تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار القديسين كاربوس وأبولوس وبطرس. وهؤلاء كانوا من تلاميذ القديس الأنبا أشعياء الأسقيطي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.17">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Seventeenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع عشر من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the seventeenth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع عشر من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Dioscorus II, 31st Pope of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا ديسقورس الثاني البطريرك الحادي والثلاثين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, of the year 235 of the martyrs (518 A.D.), Pope Dioscorus II, the 31st Pope of Alexandria, departed. He was born in Alexandria and he was taught and reared with all the Christian demeanors. He was gentle in his disposition and righteous in his deeds.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 235 للشهداء ( 518 م ) تنيح البابا ديسقورس الثاني البطريرك الحادي والثلاثون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. وقد ولد بالإسكندرية وتعلم وتهذب بكل الآداب المسيحية وكان وديعاً ?ي أخلاقه ?اضلاً ?ي اعماله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of his predecessor, Pope Youannes (John) II, the 30th Patriarch, the fathers of the church convened and choose him Patriarch on the 3rd of Baounah (Paone), year 232 of the martyrs (516 A.D.).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد نياحة البابا يوأنس الثانى البطريرك الثلاثين. إجتمع آباء الكنيسة وإختاروه بطريركا يوم 3 بؤونة سنة 232 للشهداء (516 م).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he was enthroned to the See of St. Mark, he wrote a catholic epistle to Anba Severus, Patriarch of Antioch. This epistle expressed the principals of the Orthodox doctrines. Anba Severus replied with a congratulatory message that Pope Dioscorus received with joy. He commanded that the message be read to all the people.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما إرتقي السدّة المرقسية كتب رسالة جامعة للأنبا ساويرس بطريرك إنطاكية ضمنَها مبادئ العقيدة الأرثوزكسية ?رد عليها برسالة تهنئة قبلها البابا ديوسقوروس ب?رح وأمر بتلاوتها علي الشعب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his days a dissension took place in Alexandria that angered Emperor Anastasius. The people was terrified from the punitive measures and pleaded to the Pope to intercede on their behalf to the Emperor. He was successful in his mission and the Emperor declared his pardon for them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد حدثت ?ي أيامه ?تنة ?ي الإسكندرية أغضبت الإمبراطور أناسطاسيوس ?خا? الناس سوء العاقبة وترجوا من البابا أن يش?ع ?يهم لدى الإمبراطور ?نجح ?ي مهمته وأعلن الإمبراطور ص?حه عنهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This father stayed on the throne of St. Mark for three years during which he preached and taught continually, and urged the priests in every city to shepherd and guard their flocks. He departed leaving his flock grieving and crying for a spiritual shepherd like him who departed to the heavenly glory that fast.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وجلس هذا الآب علي الكرسي حوالي ثلاث سنوات مداوماً علي التعليم والوعظْ وتنبيه الكهنة على حراسة الرعية ثم تنيح تاركاً شعبه يبكيه ويتألم من أن راعياً روحياً مثله إنتقل إلي عالم المجد بهذه السرعة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.18">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eighteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن عشر من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eighteenth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن عشر من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Honorable Father Saint Theophilus, 23rd Pope of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا القديس ثاؤ?يلس البطريرك الثالث والعشرين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 128 of the martyrs (412 A.D.), the Holy Father Pope Theophilus, the 23rd Pope of Alexandria, departed. Theophilus is a Greek word means “the Lover of God.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 128 للشهداء ( 412 م ) تنيح القديس البابا ثاؤ?يلس البطريرك الثالث والعشرون من بطاركة الكرسي المرقسي وكلمة "ثاؤ?يلس" كلمة يونانية معناها ( محب الله ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint was born in the city of Manf from pious, and rich Christian parents. His two parents passed away while he and his sister were still young. They were raised by an Ethiopian caregiver. She took them to Alexandria and there she took them to the church. When St. Athanasius saw her with the two children, he inquired about her story and she told him all about the children. He took the children from her and put them under his care. When they grew up a little, he put the girl in a house associated with the church till the day of her wedding to a man from El-Mahala El-Koubra. There she gave birth to a son called Kyrollos (Cyril) who became the Pillar of Faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولد هذا القديس بمدينة من?  (مدينة مصرية قديمة ورد ذكرها ?ي الكتاب المقدس بإسم نو? (أشعياء 19 : 13) وسميت ?ي العصر اليوناني والروماني مم?يس – وتسمي الان ميت رهينة – إحدي المدن الأثرية القديمة بمحا?ظة الجيزة) من أبوين مسيحيين غنيين تقيين مات والداه وهو صغير وتركاه هو وأخته ?تولت تربيتهما مربية حبشّية الجنس. وحدث أن ذهبت هذه المربية بهما إلي الإسكندرية وهناك دخلت بهما الكنيسة ?لما رآها القديس أثناسيوس مع الط?لين سألها عن خبرها ?قصت عليه قصتهما ?أخذ منها الط?لين ووضعهما تحت رعايته. ولما كبرا قليلاً وضع ال?تاة ?ي بيت تابع للكنيسة الي يوم زواجها برجل من بلدة المحلة الكبري و?يها ولدت كيرلس الذي صار عمود الدين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Theophilus became the disciple of St. Athanasius the Apostolic. He grew to be a pious scholar, so the pope appointed him a private secretary, and then promoted him to the priesthood.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               اما القديس ثاؤ?يلس ?إتخذه البابا أثناسيوس تلميذا له ?نما عالماً تقيا ?جعله سكرتيراً خاصاً له ثم رقاه الي درجة الكهنوت.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He continued to serve in the churches of Alexandria till the departure of Pope Timothy I, the 22nd patriarch. St. Theophilus was unanimously chosen to the patriarchate on the 23rd of Misra (Mesore), year 101 of the martyrs (385 A.D.) for what the people saw from good conduct and his zeal for the Orthodox faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وظل يخدم ?ي كنائس الإسكندرية إلي نياحة البابا تيموثاوس البطريرك الثاني والعشرين. ?إنتخب القديس ثاؤ?يلس بطريركياً بالإجماع ?ي 23 مسري 101 للشهداء ( 358 م ) لما رآه ?يه الشعب من حسن السيرة وعظم الغيرة علي العقيدة الأرثوذكسية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was in the place of confidence for the Orthodox Emperor Theodosius who ordered the spread of the Christian faith. He regarded Christianity the official religion of the Roman Empire.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد كان موضع ثقة الإمبراطور ثيئودوسيوس الأورثوذكسي الذي أمر بتعميم الديانة المسيحية وإعتبارها الديانة الرسمية للإمبراطورية الرومانية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Theophilus paid great attention to building churches and transformed some abandoned pagan temples to churches. He tore down the famous pagan temple of Serapion in Alexandria and built a church after the names of St. John the Baptist and Elisha the prophet. He relocated their relics to it, fulfilling the wishes of his teacher St. Athanasius the Apostolic.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أهتم البابا ثاؤ?يلس ببناء الكنائس وحول بعض المعابد الوثنية المهجورة إلي كنائس. كما هدٌم معبد سيرابيوم الوثني الشهير بالإسكندرية وبني كنيسة علي إسم القديسين يوحنا المعمدان وإليشع النبي ونقل جسديهما إليها متمماًرغبةً معلمه القديس البابا أثناسيوس الرسولي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Theophilus was knowledgeable of the church books with an expert understanding of their interpretation. He wrote many discourses and spiritual sayings urging on Love, charity and mercy, He warned the people about receiving the Divine Mysteries without true repentance and being prepared. He wrote also concerning the Resurrection and the punishment which is prepared for the unrepentant sinners and many other useful teachings.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان البابا ثاؤ?يلس عالماً بكتب البيعة خبيراً بت?اسيرها ووضع ميامر عديدة وأقوالا روحية حث ?يها علي المحبة والرحمة وحذر من التقرب من الأسرار الإلهية بغير إستعداد وتوبة حقيقية كما كتب عن القيامة والعذاب المّعد للخطاة غير التائبين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Theophilus went to Constantinople, during his papacy, twice. The first time was in the year 394 A.D. to attend one of the councils. The second time in the year 398 A.D. to attend the consecration of St. John Chrysostom Patriarch of the See of Constantinople.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وذهب البابا ثاؤ?يلس إلي القسطنطينية مرتين ?ي حياته الأولي سنة 394 م لحضور أحد المجامع والثانية سنة 398م لحضور سيامة القديس يوحنا ذهبي ال?م بطريركاً علي كرسي القسطنطينية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Theophilus loved the wilderness and its monks. He often visited the desert fathers to consult with them in all humility, to have dialogue with them, and to ask them to remember him in their prayers. When this great Pope finished his good fight departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان البابا ثاؤ?يلس يحب البرية والرهبان ?كان يكثر من الزيارات لأباء البرية يسالهم بإتضاع ويتحاور معهم ويطلب منهم أن يذكروه ?ي صلواتهم ولما أكمل هذا البابا العظيم جهاده الحسن تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً ابدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.19">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Nineteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع عشر من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the nineteenth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع عشر من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Sts. Theophilus and His Wife in Fayyum</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">استشهاد القديس ثاؤ?يلس وزوجته</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Theophilus and his wife in the city of El-Fayyum, were martyred, during the days of Emperor Diocletian the infidel. Some people brought accusation against them before the Governor of being Christians. The Governor brought them and questioned them about their faith. They confessed their faith in the Lord Christ, with all courage. He commanded to throw them in a deep pit and to stone them to death. They did so and they received the crown of martyrdom, and were buried in this pit under the stones.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم إستشهد القديس ثاؤ?يلس وزوجته بمدينة ال?يوم ?ي أيام دقلديانوس الملك الكا?ر. وذلك ان بعض الناس وشوا بهما عند الوالي إنهما مسيحيان ?أستحضرهما الوالي وسألهما عن معتقدهما ?إعتر?ا بإيمانهما بالسيد المسيح بكل شجاعة ?أمر الوالي أن يلقيا ?ي ح?رة عميقة ثم يرجما حتى الموت. ?تم ذلك ونالا إكاليل الشهادة ود?نا ?ى تلك الح?رة تحت الحجارة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Assembly of a Council in Antioch against Paul of Samosata</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">عقد مجمع بإنطاكية لمحاكمة بولس الساموساطى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 262 A.D. a Holy Council assembled in Antioch to judge Paul of Samosata, patriarch of Antioch. He was a native of Samosata , and was consecrated Patriarch of Antioch.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ى هذا اليوم أيضا من سنة 262 م عقد مجمع مقدس بإنطاكية لمحاكمة بولس الساموساطى بطريرك أنطاكية. كان من أهل ساموساط – مدينة صغيرة ?ي بلاد ما بين النهرين – ثم ر?سمَ بطريركاً علي إنطاكية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Satan sowed in his mind the belief that the Lord Christ was an ordinary man whom God had created to redeem the human race. Christ started by being born of the Virgin Mary and that the Divinity did not unite with Jesus but joined Him by the will only. He believed that God is one person, so he did not believe in the Son or the Holy Spirit.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد غرس الشيطان ?ي عقله الإعتقاد بأن السيد المسيح إنسان عادى خلقه الله ليخلص به البشر وإنه إبتدأ بولادته من العذراء مريم وإن اللاهوت لم يتحد به بل صحبه بالمشيئة. وإن الله أقنوم واحد ولم يكن يؤمن بالإبن ولا بالروح القدس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Because of him, a council assembled in the city of Antioch during the papacy of Pope Dionysius, the 14th Pope of Alexandria. He was invited to attend the council, but because of his old age and poor health, he was unable to attend. So he wrote a letter to explain that the Lord Christ is the Word of God, and His Son, and is equal to Him in essence, in divinity and in eternity. The Holy Trinity is Three Persons by character, in one God-head. One Person of the Trinity is the Son incarnate and became, in Hypostatic Union, a perfect man. Abba Dionysius affirmed these doctrines using many quotations from the Old and the New Testaments and he sent this letter with two priests of the church scholars.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?إجتمع بسببه هذا المجمع بإنطاكية ?ى أيام بطريركية البابا ديونسيوس البطريرك الرابع عشر للكرازة المرقسية، الذي دعي لحضور المجمع ولكن لم يتمكن لضع? صحته ?كتب رسالة أوضح ?يها بأن السيد المسيح كلمة الله وإبنه وأنه مساوله ?ي الجوهر و?ي الألوهية والأزلية. وإن الثالوث القدوس ثلاثة أقانيم ?ي خواصها لاهوت واحد ?ي طبيعتها وأن الإقنوم الثانى الذى هو الإبن تجسد وصار إنساناً كاملاً وإستشهد على ذلك بشهادات كثيرة من العهدين القديم والجديد ثم أرسل الرسالة مع كاهنين من علماء الكنيسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In Antioch, thirteen bishops and the two Coptic priests assembled in that council. They brought Paul before the council and asked him about the heresy that he was teaching. He declared it to them and did not deny anything. They debated the issue with him and read to him the letter of Pope Dionysius and made him listen to what the Apostle Paul said about the Lord Christ the Word of God that He is, "The brightness of His glory. And the express image of His person." (Hebrews 1:3) They lengthily debated him but he did not accept their words, and he would not turn away from his erroneous opinion. They excommunicated him, and all those who believed in his teachings, and they exiled him from his Seat.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وهناك ?ي أنطاكية إجتمع ثلاثة عشر أسق?ا? والكاهنان المصريان وحضر بولس المذكور أمام المجمع ?سألوه عن معتقده ?أقر به ولم ينكر. ?قرأوا عليه رسالة البابا ديونسيوس وأسمعوه قول الرسول بولس عن السيد المسيح كلمة الله إنه بهاء مجده ورسم إقنومه ( عب 1 : 3). وناقشوه كثيراً ?لم يرجع عن ضلاله ?حرموه وقطعوا كل من يقول بقوله ون?وه عن كرسيه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The fathers assembled in this council put forth beneficial Canons for the church, which are still in the hands of the believers till this day.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ووضع هؤلاء الأباء المجتمعين قوانين نا?عة للكنيسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.20">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twentieth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم العشرون من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twentieth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم العشرون من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Great St. John Colobos (the Short)</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس يوحنا القصير</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, of the year 125 of the martyrs (409 A.D.) the great saint, Anba John (Yoannis) Colobos (the Short, the Little, the Dwarf), departed. He was born in the year 339 A.D. in the city of Thebes (Luxor). His parents were righteous and God-fearing, rich in faith and good deeds.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 125 للشهداء ( 409 م ) تنيح القديس العظيم أنبا يحنس القصير .  و?لد هذا القديس سنة 339 م بمدينة طيبة – مدينة الاقصر حالياً – من أبوين تقيين يخا?ان الله ولم يكونا غنيين بأموال هذا العالم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he was 18 years old, the grace of God moved him to go to the wilderness of Scete (the Natroun Valley) longing to the monastic life. There he came upon a tried and holy old man whose name was Anba Pemwah (Amoi).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?لما بلغ الثامنة عشر حركته نعمة الله ان يمضي إلي برية شيهيت مشتاقاً الي الحياة الرهبانية. ?تقابل مع راهب شيخ قديس هو الأنبا بموا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               John knelt before Anba Pemwah and asked him to allow him to stay with him. The old man answered, trying him, "My son, you cannot stay with us for this is a very hard desert and those who dwell in it eat from the work of their hands, besides observing many fasts, prayers, and sleeping on the floor and many other forms of asceticism.? He enumerated for him the difficulties of monasticism but Yoannis was firm in his intention and told him, "Do not send me away, for God's sake, because I came to be in your obedience and prayers. If you accept me, I believe that God will make your heart well-pleased with me and God will help me with your prayers."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?سجد له وسأله أن يسمح بإقامته عنده. ?أراد الشيخ أن يجربه ?أخذ يعدد له متاعب الرهبنة ?كان يزداد تمسكاً ويقول: "لا تردنى يا أبي من أجل الله لأنى أتيت لأكون تحت طاعتك ، وإذا قبلتنى ?إن الله سيساعدني بصلواتك".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Abba Pemwah asked the Lord Christ to reveal to him the reality of this young man. The angel of the Lord appeared to him and said, "Accept this brother, for he shall become a chosen vessel." Anba Pemwah accepted him, shaved the hair of his head, and dressed him with the monastic garb. Saint John started his monastic life with great asceticism and splendid works.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وسأل الأنبا بموا السيد المسيح أن يكش? له أمر القديس يوحنا ?ظهر له ملاك الرب قائلا: " إقبل هذا الأخ لأنه سيكون إناء مختاراً ". ?قبله الأنبا بموا وقص شعر رأسه وألبسه ثياب الرهبنة ?إبتدأ بنسك عظيم وأعمال ?اضلة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day Anba Pemwah wanted to test St. John, so he expelled him out from his cell saying, "I cannot live with you." Anba John stayed out by the door of St. Pemwah’s cell for seven days. Every day Anba Pemwah went out and smote him with a palm branch and Anba John bowed down, in extreme humility, before him saying, "I have sinned O my father." On the seventh day, the old man went out to go to the church and he saw an angel with a crown placing it on the head of Anba John. Since that day, Anba Pemwah loved him and accepted to live with him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأراد مرة الأنبا بموا أن يجرب تلميذه يوحنا ?طرده من عنده. ?أقام سبعة أيام خارج الباب و?ى كل يوم كان الأنبا بموا يخرج ويضربه. أما هو ?كان يعمل له مطانية ويقول ?ي تواضع شديد : "أخطات يا أبي". و?ي اليوم السابع خرج الشيخ قاصداً الكنيسة ?رأى ملاكاً يضع إكليلاً علي رأس الأنبا يحنس ?أحبه وقبل سكناه معه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day Anba Pemwah wanted to test his obedience, so he gave him a piece of dry wood (walking-stick) and said to him, "Take this wood, plant and water it." St. John obeyed and went on watering it daily though the source of water was very far. After three years, that piece of wood sprouted out and grew into a fruitful tree. Anba Pemwah took some of that fruit and went around to the elder monks saying, "Take, and eat from the fruit of obedience." This tree still exists in its place in his monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأراد مرة أن يختبر طاعته ?أعطاه عوداً يابساً وأمره أن يغرسه ويسقيه. ?أطاعه القديس وصار يسقي العود ?ي كل يوم وكان الماء بعيداً جداً. وبعد ثلاث سنوات نما العود وصار شجرة مثمرة ?أخذ الأنبا بموا من ثمرها وأعطى الشيوخ قائلا: خذوا كلوا من ثمرة الطاعة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Abba Pemwah fell sick for 12 years during which Anba John served him diligently. When Abba Pemwah was about to depart, he held the hand of Anba John (Yoannis) and handed him to the elder fathers saying, "Take and keep him, for he is an angel, not a man." He commanded Anba John to stay in the place where he had planted the tree of obedience then Anba Pemwah departed in peace. Anba John dwelt beside the tree where he established a large monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما مرض الأنبا بموا كان هذا القديس يخدمه مدة إثنى عشرة سنة وعند نياحته أمسك بيده وسلمه للأباء الشيوخ قائلا: " إحت?ظوا بهذا ?إنه ملاك وليس انساناً " . وأوصاه أن يسكن ?ي المكان الذي غرس ?يه شجرة الطاعة ثم تنيح الأنبا بموا بسلام. أما الأنبا يحنس ?سكن بجوار الشجرة ، وبني بجوارها ديراً عظيماً .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               It happened when Pope Theophilus was ordaining Anba John, Hegumen and abbot, a voice from heaven was heard saying, "Axios, Axios, Axios? (That is to say he is worthy).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أراد البابا ثاؤ?يلس أن يرسمه قمصاً سمع صوتا من السماء يقول: " مستحق مستحق مستحق ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When this saint consecrated the offering, he was able to know those who were worthy to partake of it and those who were not worthy. Anba John was an extremely humble person.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان هذا الاب عندما يقدس الأسرار يعر? من يستحق التناول ومن لا يستحق وأيضاً كان ?ي غاية الإتضاع.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Later on, the Berbers attacked the desert of Scete in the year 407 A.D., so Anba John (Yoannis) left the wilderness. He went to Mt. Qulzum , in the eastern wilderness near by the city of Suez, and dwelt in a cave there. God arranged for him a man of faith to serve him. He brought to him all his needs once a week.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما هجم البربرعلي البرية سنة 407 م ترك الأنبا يحنس القصير البرية وإنطلق إلي جبل القلزم ?ي البرية الشرقية قرب مدينة السويس ، وسكن ?ي مغارة هناك ورتب الله رجلا مؤمناً ليخدمه ?كان يأتى بحاجاته مرة كل إسبوع.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he completed his good endeavor, he departed in peace in his cave in Mt. Qulzum. Later on his disciples relocated his body to the wilderness of Shiheet. The Lord wrought many miracles through his holy body. His body is located at present time in a reliquary in the shrine of the three saints Abba Macarii in the monastery of Anba Macarius the Great in the wilderness of Shiheet.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل سعيه الحسن تنيح بسلام ?ي مغارته بجبل القلزم. وبعد ذلك حمله أولاده إلي برية شيهيت يوجد جسده الان ?ي أنبوبة خاصة داخل مقصورة الثلاث مقارات بدير الأنبا مكاريوس الكبير ببرية شيهيت – وقد أجري الله من جسده المقدس معجزات كثيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.21">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-First Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الحادي والعشرين من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-first day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الحادي والعشرين من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Theotokos, the Virgin St. Mary</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">التذكار الشهري لوالدة الإله القديسة مريم</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the church celebrates the monthly commemoration of the Theotokos, the holy Virgin St. Mary.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تعيد الكنيسة ?ي هذا اليوم بالتذكار الشهري لوالدة الإله القديسة العذراء مريم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Her intercession be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة ش?اعتها ?لتكن معنا أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Joel the Prophet</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة يوئيل النبي</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also, the church celebrates the commemoration of the departure of the great Prophet Joel, the son of Pethuel, from the tribe of Reuben. Joel is a Hebrew name means “Jehovah is God.? He is one of the twelve Minor Prophets.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي هذا اليوم أيضاً تحت?ل الكنيسة بتذكار نياحة النبي العظيم يوئيل بن ?نوئيل – وهو من سبط رأوبين – وكلمة "يوئيل" إسم عبري معناه " يهوه هو الله". وهو إحدي الإثني عشر نبياً الصغار.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He prophesied in the days of Asa the son of Abia the son of Jeroboam King of Judah. He lived before the time of Isaiah the prophet. He prophesied in the kingdom of Judah and Amos prophesied in the kingdom of Israel at the same time.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتنبأ ?ي زمان أسا بن أبيا ملك يهوذا وعاش قبل زمان أشعياء. كان هو يتنبأ ?ي مملكة يهوذا وعاموس يتنبأ ?ي مملكة إسرائيل ?ي وقت واحد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He included in his prophesy an incitement for the people to offer a true repentance so the Lord would left up from them the afflictions, the tribulations and to multiply for them the wealth and the spiritual and materialistic blessings.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد ضمن نبوته تشجيعاً للشعب علي تقديم توبة صادقة لكي ير?ع الرب عنهم النكبات والتجارب ويكثر لهم الخيرات والبركات الروحية والمادية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He prophesied also about the coming of the Holy Spirit, the comforter upon the holy Apostles on the day of Pentecost . He prophesied about the preaching of the Gospel starting from Jerusalem , and also about the place of the final judgment at the second coming of the Lord Christ .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كما تنبأ عن حلول الروح القدس علي التلاميذ يوم الخمسين (يوئيل 2 : 28-32). وعن بداية البشارة بالانجيل من أورشليم ( يوئيل 3 : 18).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he finished his good course, departed in peace in a good old age, and was buried in his field in Jerusalem.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام بشيخوخة صالحة ود?ن ?ي حقله بأورشليم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Relocation of the Body of Lazarus, the Beloved of the Lord</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نقل جسد لعازر حبيب الرب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the church celebrates the commemoration of the relocation of the body of Lazarus, the beloved of the Lord, whom He raised from the dead.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي هذا اليوم أيضاً تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار نقل جسد لعازر حبيب الرب ،الذى أقامه من بين الأموات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Lazarus was ordained a bishop for Cyprus. The two apostles Paul and Barnabas had laid their hands on him to shepherd the people of this island.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد ر?سم أسق?اً على قبرص حيث وضع عليه الرسولان بولس وبرنابا اليد لرعاية شعب هذه الجزيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He departed in the year 76 A.D. and his pure body was buried in Kition which is the old Kittim , and in present time is called Larnaca located on the eastern shores of the island of Cyprus.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد تنيح سنة 76 م ود?ن جسده الطاهر ?ي كتيون. وهى كتيم القديمة ( تك 10 : 4) وتسمي حاليا لارنكا علي الساحل الشرقي لجزيرة قبرص.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Leo VI (886 - 912 A.D.) heard about the presence of the body of St. Lazarus on the island of Cyprus, he sent some priests who brought him to Constantinople in a marble sarcophagus. Then he built a church for him and placed the pure body in it with great honor and veneration. Later on the body was relocated to Marseille, France where it settled in a church there till present time.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما سمع الملك ليون السادس (886 – 912م) بوجود جسد القديس لعازر ?ي جزيرة قبرص أرسل بعض الكهنة ?أحضروه الي القسطنطينية داخل تابوت من رخام. ثم بنيت له كنيسة ووٌضع الجسد الطاهر ?يها بإكرام وإحترام جزيل . ولكن بعد هذا ن?قل الجسد الي مارسيليا ب?رنسا حيث إستقر ?ي كنيسة هناك إلي هذا اليوم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               His holy blessing be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركته المقدسة تكون معنا. أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Anba Roweis, (St. Freig, Ava Tegi)</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس الأنبا رويس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1121 of the martyrs (1405 A.D.) the great St. Freig, who is known as Anba Roweis, departed. He was a contemporary of the saint Pope Mettaos (Matthew) I. This saint was from a small village called Miniet-Yamin, El-Gharbiah Governorate. His father's name was Isaac and his mother's name was Sarah. When he was born, they called him Freig. As poor farmers he had a harsh upbringing. At times he helped his father in farming and other times he sold salt carried on a small camel. He called the camel "Roweis" (i.e. small head). Because of his humility and honesty the people loved him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً من سنة 1121 للشهداء ( 1405 م )، تنيح القديس العظيم الأنبا ?ريج الشهير بالأنبا رويس. هذا القديس كان معاصراً للقديس الأنبا متاؤس الأول. نشأ هذا القديس ?ي قرية صغيرة بمحا?ظ الغربية تسمى "منيه بيمين" وكان أسم أبيه إسحق وأمه المباركة سارة. ?ربياه تربية خشنة ك?لاحين ?قراء. وكان أحياناً يساعد والده ?ي ال?لاحة، و أحياناً أخري يبيع الملح علي جمل صغير وأحبه الناس بسبب تواضعه وأمانته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he was twenty years old he went to Cairo then to Upper Egypt. He changed his name from Freig to Roweis after the name of his small camel as a mean of humility and self-denial.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما بلغ سن العشرين سا?ر الي القاهرة  ومنها الي الوجه القبلي حيث غير إسمه من ?ريج إلي رويس – تصغير كلمة رأس – علي اسم جمله الصغير. إمعانا ?ي الإتضاع وإنكار الذات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He moved from one place to another not having a house or shelter or any belongings. He was a man of few words, many fasts and vigils. He ate very little of simple food. He partook of the holy mysteries diligently with a wholly prepared heart and in fear and trembling. He always said; ?No one is worthy to partake of these Holy Mysteries except the one that his entrails are pure as those of our pure lady St. Mary that were worthy to carry the Lord Christ.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان يتنقل من مكان لآخر، ولم يكن له بيت أو مأوي ولا قنية. وكان قليل الكلام كثير الصوم والسهر لا ياكل الا قليلاً من الاطعمة البسيطة. مواظباً علي التناول من الاسرار المقدسة بإستعداد قلبي كامل وبخو? ورعدة.  وكان يقول: " انه لا يستحق التناول من هذه الاسرار، الإ إذا كان جو?ه طاهراً نقياً كأحشاء سيدتنا الطاهرة مريم التي إستحقت أن تحمل السيد المسيح ?ي أحشائها ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He saw the glory of God coming upon the Holy Mysteries on the altar. Anba Roweis had reached an eminent degree of spirituality that he was able to move from one place to another for he has reached the level of an anchorite (hermit). God had granted him the gift of knowing hidden secrets, so the church gave him the title “Theophanius?, that is to say “who God appear to.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان يري مجد الله حالا علي الأسرار المقدسة علي المذبح. وقد وصل الأنبا رويس الي درجة روحية سامية. ?كان ينتقل من مكان لأخر اذ وصل إلي درجة السياحة. ووهبه الله معر?ة الأسرار الخ?ية وأعطته الكنيسة لقب (ثيؤ?انيوس) أى من يظهر له الله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Some evil men, thru the envy of the devil, one time plotted against him, so they delivered him to prince Sodon after they have painfully beaten him. The prince asked him for the reason why they had seized him? When he did not answer, the prince ordered to beat him till they tore his flesh and his blood flew on the ground. Then he ordered to parade him in the streets ridiculing him and striking him along with one of his disciples. What they have received from torturing on that day could not be described; finally they imprisoned them. He raised his eyes to heaven and thankfully prayed to God.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتأمر عليه الأشرار ذات مرة بحسد الشيطان ?سلموه إلي الأمير سودون بعد أن ضربوه ضرباً مبرحاً. ولما سأله الأمير عن سبب القبض عليه لم يتكلم ?أمر الأمير بضربه حتي تهرأ جسده وسال دمه. وأمر أن يطو?وا به ?ي الشوارع، ?طا?وا يستهزئون به وكانوا يضربونه ومعه أحد تلاميذه. ?نالا من التعذيب ?ى ذلك اليوم ما لا يوص? وأدخلوهما السجن. ?ر?ع عينيه وصلي الي الله شاكراً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Mettaos came and released him and his disciple from prison and took him to treat his wounds. He stayed with him for a period of time until he was healed. The Pope asked him to remain with him in the papal residence but he refused and resumed his wondering as his custom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?حضر البابا متاؤس وأخرجه هو وتلميذه من السجن، وأخذه عنده ليعالجه من جراحاته ?مكث عنده زماناً حتي ش?ي. وطلب منه البابا أن يبقي معه ?ي الدار البطريركية ?لم يوا?ق وواصل تنقلاته كعادته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Anba Roweis was merciful and compassionate to the widows, and the orphans. He treated every one gently and kindly. God granted him the gift of prophesy and he foretold many things to come.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان الأنبا رويس كثير الرحمة والش?قة علي الأرامل والأيتام ويعامل الكل بلط? وإش?اق. وأعطاه الله موهبة النبوة ?اخبر بأمور آتية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the later part of the life of this saint, he became severely ill and was bedridden for nine years in the house of one of his disciples called Michael the builder. During his illness he was consoled, patient, and thankful to the Lord.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي أواخر حياة هذا القديس مرض مرضاً شديداً ?رقد تسع سنوات كاملة ?ي بيت أحد تلاميذه ويدعى ميخائيل البنا، وكان ?ي مرضه متعزياً صابراً شاكراً الرب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the time of his departure drew near, the Virgin St. Mary, whom he loved much, came to encourage and comfort him. He signed himself with the sign of the cross, and delivered his pure spirit in the hand of the Lord. His body was buried in Dair El-Khandaq which was re-named later on after his name.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما قربت ساعة نياحته جاءت إليه القديسة العذراء مريم، التى كان يحبها كثيراً لتشجعه وتعزيه، ورشم ذاته بعلامة الصليب و?اضت روحه الطاهرة بيد الرب. ود?ن جسده بدير الخندق* الذى تسمى بعد ذلك بإسمه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً.  آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.22">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Second Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثانى والعشرين من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-second day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثانى والعشرين من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Saint Luke the Evangelist</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس لوقا الانجيلى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 67 -68 A.D., during the reign of the tyrant Emperor Nero, the great St. Luke the Evangelist, was martyred. The Saint was born in Antioch from pagan parents. They raised, brought up, and educated him as a physician. He was an eloquent speaker, writer, and painter. He lived a celibate life. He was chosen by the Lord as one of the 70 disciples .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               1- ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة ( 67 – 68 م ) ?ي عهد نيرون الطاغية إستشهد القديس العظيم لوقا الإنجيلى. ولد القديس ?ي إنطاكية من أبوين وثنيين اللذان ريباه وهذباه وعلماه مهنة الطب وكان ?صيحاً وكاتباً  ورساماً وعاش بتولاً غير متزوج. إختاره الرب يسوع المسيح من جملة السبعين رسولاً ( لو10 : 1).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He accompanied the apostle Paul in his second missionary journey from Troas to Philippi , and on his third journey from Philippi to Jerusalem . He also accompanied St. Paul in Rome during his imprisonment . St. Paul loved him much and called him, “Luke the beloved physician who is working with me.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ورا?ق القديس بولس الرسول – ?ى رحلته التبشيرية الثانية من ترواس إلي ?يلبي (اع 16 : 10 – 17)، و?ى رحلته الثالثة من ?يلبي إلي أورشليم (20 : 5 – الخ ، 21 : 1 – 18)، كما كان مرا?قاً له ?ي روما عند الأسّر . وأحبه القديس بولس كثيراً ودعاه الطبيب الحبيب (كولوسي 4 : 14) ، والعامل معه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He wrote his Gospel between the years 60 – 63 A. D., in the Greek language for the Gentiles. He portrayed the Lord Christ as a Savior for all humanity Who is fulfilling the yearning of every heart. He demonstrated Christ as human in His full humanity, and He resembled us in everything, except for sin alone. He depicted Him in his entire gospel as the lover of sinners, the healers of the sick, the comfort of the fainthearted and the shepherd of the lost sheep. The symbol of his gospel is the image of Ox for he wrote about the sacrifices and the atonement sacrifice of the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كتب إنجيله بين عامي 60 -  63 م باللغة اليونانية للأممين. و?يه يقدم السيد المسيح كمخلص لجميع البشر ومتمم إشتياقات كل قلب. وي?ظهر المسيح الإنسان ?ي ملء بشريته وإنه مثلنا ?ي كل شئ ماخلا الخطية وحدها ، ويصٌوره ?ي كل البشارة بأنه محب الخطاة ، شا?ي المرضى ومعزي منكسري القلوب وراعي الخرو? الضال. وي?رمز لإنجيله بشكل ثور لأنه تكلم عن الذبائح وذبيحة السيد المسيح الك?ارية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He also wrote the Acts of the Apostles as a continuation for his Gospel between the years 63 – 64 A.D. during his stay with the apostle Paul in his first imprisonment in Rome. He dedicated it to the same person, as he dedicated the gospel, to “the most excellent Theophilus.? In all probability this person was a noble personality in the city of Alexandria. He included in it the account of establishing the early church among the Jews in Jerusalem through the ministry of our teacher the apostle St. Peter and among the Gentiles by the ministry of our teacher the apostle St. Paul.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكتب كذلك س?ر أعمال الرسل كتكملة لإنجيله بين عاميٌ 63 – 64م وكمعلومة عامة ترمز الكنيسة لإنجيل متى بوجه أنسان لأنه تكلم عن أنساب المسيح ، ولإنجيل مرقس بوجه الأسد لأنه يقدم المسيح القوي صانع العجائب ولإنجيل لوقا بشكل الثور لأنه يتكلم عن الذبائح ولإنجيل يوحنا بوجه النسر لأنه يتكلم عن لاهوت السيد المسيح ويحلق ?ي الالهيات. وكتب هذا القديس س?ر أعمال الرسل أثناء إقامته مع الرسول بولس أثناء سجنه الأول ?ى روما، ووجٌهه الي ن?س الشخص الذي وجٌه اليه الإنجيل وهو (العزيز ثاؤ?يلس) ويرجٌح أن هذا الشخص كان من كبار الشخصيات ?ي مدينة الإسكندرية. وضٌمنه أخبار تأسيس الكنيسة الأولي بين اليهود ?ي أورشليم بواسطة خدمة معلمنا القديس بطرس وبين الأمم بواسطة خدمة معلمنا القديس بولس الرسول.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Some sources indicate that St. Luke had preached the Gospel in Dalmatia, France and Italy. He was martyred by the orders of Nero, and he was 84 years old, and thus he received the crown of martyrdom. They placed his pure body in a hair sack and cast it into the sea. With the providence of God, the waves thrown the holy body to an island and was found by a believer who took the body, shrouded it with costly shrouds and buried it with great honor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتقول بعض المصادر أن معلمنا القديس لوقا الطبيب قد بشر بالإنجيل ?ي دلماطية و?رنسا وإيطاليا. وإس?تشهد علي يد نيرون وكان عمره أربع وثمانين سنة ونال إكليل الشهادة ووضع جسده الطاهر ?ي كيس شعر وأ?لقي ?ي البحر وبتدبير الله قذ?ته الأمواج إلى جزيرة ، ?وجد الجسد المقدس  رجل مؤمن ?أخذه وك?نه بأك?ان حسنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               His body was relocated to Constantinople during the reign of Emperor Constantius, year 357 A.D., along with the relics of St. Andrew. Later on was relocated again to Italy in the year 1177 A.D.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ونقل الجسد ?ي عهد الملك قسطنطينوس سنة 357 م إلي القسطنطينية مع ر?ات القديس أندراوس، ثم ًنًقل بعد ذلك إلي إيطاليا 1177 م .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً.  آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.23">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Third Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-third day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Dionysius, Bishop of Corinth</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس ديوناسيوس أسق?  كورنثوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Dionysius, bishop of Corinth, in Greece, was martyred, during the days of Diocletian and Maximianus (284 – 312 A.D.). He endured many severe tortures for the sake of his faith in the Lord Christ, to Whom is the Glory, and for refusing to offer incense to the idols. When they saw his perseverance and were weary of torturing him, they cut off his holy head with the sword, thus he received the crown of eternal glory.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم أستشهد القديس ديوناسيوس أسق? كورنثوس ببلاد اليونان ?ي عهد دقلديانوس ومكسيميانوس ( 284 – 312 م )، وقد ع?ذب هذا الشهيد بعذابات شديدة ?ي سبيل الإيمان بالمسيح له المجد ور?ض التبخير للأوثان. وبعد أن رأوا إصراره وتعبوا من تعذيبه قطعوا رأسه المقدسة بحد السي? ?نال إكليل المجد الأبدى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Yousab, 52nd Pope of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا يوساب الأول البطريرك الثانى والخمسين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 566 of the martyrs (849 A.D.), Anba Yousab I (Joseph), the 52nd Pope of Alexandria, departed. He was the only child of his parents, who were from the city Menuf, El-Menofia governorate. When his parents departed and he was still young, a certain rich family raised him up. When he grew up he longed for the monastic life, so he went to the patriarch Pope Marcus II, and revealed to him his desire. The Pope rejoiced and sent him to the monastery of St. Macarius in the wilderness of Shiheet and became a monk under the guidance of a holy old man.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً من سنة 566 للشهداء ( 849 م ) تنيح البابا يوساب الأول البطريرك الثانى والخمسون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. كان ابناً وحيداً لأبويه ?ي مدينة منو? بمحا?ظة المنو?ية ، ومات أبواه وهو ط?ل ?أهتم بتربيته رجل غنى ، عاش عنده سعيداً. ولما كبر إشتاق إلي الحياة الرهبانية ?ذهب الي الأب البطريرك البابا مرقس الثاني وأطلعه علي رغبته، ??رح به وأرسله إلي دير القديس مكاريوس ببرية شيهيت وترهب عند شيخ قديس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The monk Yousab lived a life of asceticism and piety. Pope Marcus II ordained him a priest and served with him in the patriarchate a period of time, then returned to the wilderness.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ظل الراهب يوساب يعيش جياة الزهد والنسك والتقش?، ورسمه البابا مرقس الثانى قساً وخدم معه ?ي البطريركية مدة من الزمان ثم عاد إلى البرية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of Anba Simon II, the 51st Patriarch, the bishops and the people asked of God to make known to them whom He chose. The Lord guided them to this father. They sent a delegation to the wilderness to bring him. On their way they prayed to God saying, "We beseech Thee, O Lord; if You have chosen this father for this honor, let the sign be that we find his door open upon our arrival." When they arrived they found his door open, for he was bidding farewell to some visiting monks. When he was about to close his door, he saw them coming, so he received them with joy and welcomed them to his cell. When they entered, they seized him and told him, "Axios" (i.e. he is worthy).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد نياحة البابا سيمون الثاني البطريرك الحادي والخمسون، طلب الأساق?ة والشعب إلي الله ان ي?عرٌ?هم من يختاره ?أرشدهم إلى هذا الأب. ?أرسلوا و?داً إلي البرية لإحضاره، و?ي الطريق صلوا قائلين: " نسألك يارب ان كنت إخترت هذا الأب لهذه الرتبة ?لتكن علامة ذلك أننا عند وصولنا نجد بابه م?توحاً. ?لما وصلوا وجدوا بابه م?توحاً حيث كان يودع بعض زائريه من الرهبان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They took him to Alexandria where they placed their hands over him consecrating him patriarch on the 21st day of Hathor, year 548 of the martyrs (831 A.D.).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?أمسكوه وأخذوه إلي الإسكندرية ووضعوا عليه اليد بطريركاً يوم 21 هاتور سنة 548 للشهداء (831 م ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He took a great interest for building the churches and teaching the people. However, Satan became envious and brought much sorrow upon him. The bishops of Tinnis and Miser (Cairo) had brought many hardships upon their congregations. They appealed to the patriarch for help. Anba Yousab asked the two bishops often to be merciful to their flocks, but they would not accept his behest. He exerted a great effort to reconcile between them, but it was in vain. The Pope convened a council and excommunicated them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?إهتم ببناء الكنائس وتعليم الشعب، ?حسده الشيطان وسبب له أحزاناً كثيرة منها أن أسق? مصر وأسق? تانيس أتعبا شعبهما جداً ?أستغاثوا بالبابا ?نصح هذين الأسق?ين أن يتر?قا بالشعب ، ولما لم يلتزما بنصيحته عقد مجمعاً وقطعهما.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When they were excommunicated, unfortunately these two bishops went to the Governor in Cairo and brought false accusations against Anba Yousab. The Governor sent his brother, with some soldiers to bring the Patriarch to him. When they came to the Patriarch, the Governor's brother drew his sword to kill him. But the Lord thrust aside his hand and the sword struck a pillar and was broken. The Prince became furiously angry, so he drew his dagger and drove it with all his might into the side of this father. The dagger did not do any harm to the Patriarch other than cutting his apparel.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وللأس? ذهب هذين الأسق?ين إلي الوالي ول?قا تهماً كاذبة علي الأب البطريرك ، ?أرسل الوالي أخاه مع بعض الجنود لإحضار البطريرك ?جرد سي?ه لقتل البطريرك ?جائت الضربة ?ي العمود ?إنكسر السي? ، ?غضب الأمير وأخذ سكيناً وضربه بها ?لم تقطع سوي ثيابه ?قط.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Prince realized that the Patriarch had divine grace and heavenly protection so he brought him with respect to his brother and told him about what had happened. The Governor also respected and feared him. The Governor asked the Patriarch about the accusations that were made against him. The Patriarch proved to him the falsehoods of these accusations and informed him about the truth of these two complaining bishops. The Governor was convinced and honored the Patriarch and wrote for him a decree that no one should disobey him in any ordination or removal of any bishops or in any other work concerning the church.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . ?تحقق الأمير أن ?ي البطريرك نعمة إلهية تح?ظه. ?أخذه باحترام جزيل إلي أخيه الوالي وأعلمه بما جري، ?أحترمه الوالى جداً وخا?ه ، ثم إست?سر منه عن التهم الموجٌهة إليه ?أثبت له عدم صحتها وأعلمه بأمر الأسق?ين الشاكيين.  تقبل الوالى كلامه وأكرمه وكتب له ?رمان لئلا يعارضه أحد ?ي رسامة أو عزل ولا ?ي أى عمل يعمله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Lord wrought many miracles by his hands. He continually preached to the sinners and admonished the disobedient, establishing the people in the Orthodox faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد أظهر الله على يديه عجائب كثيرة، وظل مداوماً علي تعليم الشعب وتثبيته على الإيمان المستقيم وتوبيخ المخال?ين للعقيدة الأرثوذكسية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After having sat on the throne of St. Mark for 18 years, he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد أقام على الكرسي المرقسي نحوثمانية عشر عاماً  ثم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً.  آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.24">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Fourth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-fourth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Great Father Abba Hilarion, the Monk</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة إيلاريون الكبير الراهب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 87 of the martyrs (371 A.D.) the great Saint Anba Hilarion, departed. This saint was born at Tabatha, south of Gaza, Palestine in the year 292 A.D., to pagan parents. They taught him the Greek literature and culture. He went to the city of Alexandria to pursue his education.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 188 للشهداء ( 472 م ) تنيح القديس العظيم الأنبا إيلاريون الكبير. و?لد هذا القديس ?ي بلدة طابا جنوب غزة ?ي سنة 392 م من أبوين وثنيين علماه الآداب اليونانية، ثم قصد مدينة الإسكندرية لإتمام علومه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The divine grace moved him in the city of Alexandria to learn also the Christian doctrines and books. Abba Hilarion was convinced and believed in the Lord Christ, and received the holy baptism.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وهناك ?ي الإسكندرية حركته النعمة الإلهية ليدرس العلوم المسيحية ?اقتنع بها وأعتنقها ونال سر المعمودية المقدسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Hilarion adored prayers, worship, and asceticism. When he heard about St. Anthony the Great (251 – 356 A.D.), he went to him and became his disciple.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان إيلاريون محبا للصلاة والعبادة والنسك، ?لما سمع عن القديس أنطونيوس الكبير ذهب اليه وتتلمذ علي يديه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After a while, he went back to Palestine for he was informed that his parents had died. He distributed his wealth among the poor and needy. He built a little hut (cell) where he led a life of worship and asceticism. Many came to him seeking his prayers and guidance.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد مدة من الزمن رجع إيلاريون الي بلاد  ?لسطين إذ بلغه انتقال والديه، ?وزع أمواله علي ال?قراء والمساكين. وبنى قلاية وعاش ?يها عابداً ناسكاً وكان كثيرون يأتون إليه طالبين إرشاده وصلواته وإرشاده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Many disciples gathered around him, so he built a monastery for them and became a father and councilor for the monks. St Hilarion is considered to be the founder of monasticism in Palestine. Many came to him to take his advice and to receive the blessing of his prayers.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكثر عدد الرهبان حوله ، ?بنى لهم ديراً وصار لهم اباً ومرشداً ويعتبر هو بحق مؤسس الرهبنة ?ي ?لسطين ، وكان كثير من الشعب يأتون اليه ويسترشدون به وينالون بركة صلواته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the later part of his life he went to the island of Cyprus where he lived in seclusion in a cell for five years. There he was visited by St. Epiphanius, and St. Hilarion prophesied for him that he would be the bishop of Cyprus and the prophecy was fulfilled in the following years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي أواخر حياته مضي إلى مدينة قبرص وعاش هناك ?ي قلاية من?ردة حوالي خمس سنوات. وزاره هناك القديس إبي?انيوس، ?تنبأ له إنه سيصير أسق?اً على قبرص وقد تمت نبوته ?ي السنوات التالية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The days of this father were 80 years he spent most of it in worship and asceticism, and then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما بلغ هذا الأب القديس ثمانين سنة من عمره قضي معظمها ?ي النسك والعبادة تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. John Chrysostom (of the Golden Mouth) praised him in some of his articles and St. Basil the great mentioned him in some of his homilies.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ومدحه القديس يوحنا ذهبي ال?م وذكره القديس باسيليوس الكبير ?ي عظاته النسكية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the Sts. Paul, Longinus and Deenah (Zena)</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديسين بولس ولنجينوس ودينة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also is the commemoration of the martyrdom of Sts. Paul, Longinus and Deenah (Zena).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضآ تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار إستشهاد القديسين بولس ولنجينوس ودينة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً.  آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.25">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Fifth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-fifth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Saint Abib, the Friend of St. Apollo</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس أبيب صديق القديس أبوللو</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, the saint Abba Abib, departed. He was the friend of the saint Abba Apollo, who was like the angels. They were of the fourth century saints.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ى مثل هذا اليوم تنيح القديس الأنبا أبيب صديق القديس الأنبا أبوللو المت?شبه بالملائكة. وهما من قديسي القرن الرابع الميلادي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Abib was pious since his young age, practicing the ascetic life, sleeping on the ground, and inclined to the solitary life. He spent most of his time in studying the Holy Bible, contemplating and praying.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان أبيب تقياً منذ حداثته يمارس الحياة النسكية وينام على الأرض، ميالاً لحياة الوحدة والتأمل والصلاة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               His father admonished him and advised him not to dedicate all his life for worship and to study so he can acquire a good position in the society as his brothers. He accepted the admonishing calmly and in silence. His father and brothers were astonished from his amazing serenity and delicate feelings.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان والده يوبخه وينصجه ألا يكرس كل وقته للعبادة حتي يقدر أن ينال مركزاً مرموقاً ?ي المجتمع كإخوته ?كان يقبل التوبيخ ?ي هدوء وصمت. وكان والده وإخوته يتعجبون من رقة أحاسيسه وهدوئه العجيب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When His father became seriously ill, and his death drew near, he called him saying, “My son pray to the Lord on my behalf that He may not count what I have done to grieve and trouble you with. You were seeking only God, but I have behaved with worldly perception.? He held the hand of his son and cried. The father gathered his children and pointed to Abib, saying, “From now on this is your father and teacher. Behave with a good conscience as he tells you.? The children were greatly moved seeing eternity before their eyes as their father delivered up his soul. After the departure of his father, he received the inheritance which he divided rightly among his brothers. He took his share and distributed among the poor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أشتد المرض بوالده ولما حضرته الو?اة ناداه وقال له: " صلي يابنى إلي الرب لكى لا يحاسبنى علي ما سببته لك من أحزان ومضايقات. لقد كنت أنت تطلب الله وحده أما أنا ?كنت أسلك بم?اهيم العالم" وأمسك بيدي إبنه وبكى. ثم جمع أولاده، وأشار إلي أبيب قائلاً : " من الآن هذا هو أبوكم ومعلمكم. إسلكوا بضمير حيٌ كما يقول لكم " ?تأثر الأبناء جداً. وتجلت الأبدية أمام أعينهم بينما كان والدهم يسلم الروح. وبعد نياحته أستلم أبيب الميراث ووزعه علي إخوته بالعدل أما هو ?أخذ نصيبه ووزعه علي ال?قراء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of his father, he went to one of the monasteries along with his friend Apollo. Each one lived in a cell, practicing life of seclusion and asceticism in an evangelic spiritual manner. They met every now and then to support each other in the Lord.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأنطلق أبيب بعد نياحة والده إلي أحد الأديرة مع صديقه أبوللو. حيث سكن كل منهما ?ي قلاية من?ردة يمارسان حياة الوحدة والنسك ب?كر روحى إنجيلي. وكانا يلتقيان من وقت لآخر ليسندا بعضهما بعضاً ?ي الرب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Shortly after, St. Abib became seriously ill, so St. Apollo came in haste to serve him, but Abib apologized saying; “Leave me alone, my brother, to be with the Lord, and when my hour comes I will call you.? St. Apollo left him in obedience for his wish and his eyes were full of tears.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . وبعد ?ترة مرض القديس أبيب بشدة، ?أسرع إليه أبوللو ليخدمه، ?اعتذر له أبيب قائلاً : " إتركني ياأخي بم?ردي مع الرب وعندما تحين ساعتى سأناديك " ?ذهب من عنده مطيعاً لوصيته وعيناه ت?يضان دموعاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the time of the departure of St. Abib from this world drew near, he called his friend Apollo. When he entered his cell he heard him saying; “Hurry, we shall meet in Paradise,? and he delivered up his pure spirit to Paradise. Apollo did not have the chance to bid him farewell, so he kissed him to receive his blessing.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما حانت ساعة انطلاق القديس أبيب من هذا العالم ، أرسل يستدعى صديقه أبوللو. ولما دخل إلى القلايه سمعه يقول: "أسرع سنلتقي ?ى ال?ردوس" ولم يجد أبوللو ?رصة إلا ليقبٌله. ?انطلقت روحه الطاهرة إلي ال?ردوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Apollo mentioned his friend St. Abib often in his conversations. On the commemoration of the departure of St. Abib, St. Apollo said to some of his disciples; “If you pray to the Lord Christ asking for the intercession of St. Abib the Lord will fulfill your request.? Some doubted what St. Apollo had said for he often talked about him. In the same day one of the monks departed, so they all went to receive his blessing before his burial. Suddenly the dead monk rose up and rebuked those who doubted the words of St. Apollo, then departed in peace. They all were filled with the fear of the Lord.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان القديس أبوللو يذكر صديقه أبيب كثيراً ?ي أقواله. و?ي تذكار نياحتة القديس أبيب قال أبوللو لبعض تلاميذه: "أن من يصلي للسيد المسيح طالباً صلوات القديس أبيب ي?ستجاب له" ?تشكك البعض بسبب كثرة كلامه عنه. و?ي ن?س اليوم تنيح أحد الرهبان ، ?ذهب الكل لينالوا بركته قبل د?نه. و?جأة قام الراهب من موته ووبخ المتشككين ?ى كلام القديس أبوللو ثم تنيح بسلام. ?أمتلأ الكل من مخا?ة الله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of the saint Anba Abib be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات القديس الأنبا أبيب ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Consecration of the Church of the martyr Julius El-Akfehasi (Aqfahs), the Writer of the Biography of Martyrs</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تكريس كنيسة الشهيد يوليوس الأ?قهصي كاتب سير الشهداء</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the consecration of the church of St. Julius El-Akfehasi (Aqfahs). This saint was martyred in the city of Towa. When the era of persecution ended, the righteous Emperor Constantine reigned. He heard the reports of St. Julius and how the Lord had chosen him and preserved him along with his men to care for the bodies of the martyrs, and to write their biographies.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي هذا اليوم أيضاً تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار تكريس كنيسة الشهيد يوليوس الأق?هصي. الذي أس?تشهد بطوٌة. وذلك أنه لما إنتهي عصر الاضطهاد وتملك الإمبراطور قسطنطين البار. سمع بخبر القديس يوليوس وعن اهتمامه بأجساد الشهداء وكتابة سيرهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Emperor praised the life story of this saint and so he sent much money to Egypt, and commanded that a church be built after his name in Alexandria. After the church was built, his pure body was relocated to it. The church was consecrated by the saint Abba Alexandros, the 19th patriarch of Alexandria with some bishops. A great feast was celebrated on this day.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               إمتدح الملك سيرة هذا القديس وأرسل أموالاً كثيرة إلى مصر وأمر أن ت?بنى كنيسة باسمه ?ي مدينة الإسكندرية. ولما انتهوا من بنائها نقلوا جسده الطاهر إليها. وكرسها البابا القديس ألكسندروس البطريرك التاسع عشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية ومعه بعض الأساق?ة. وعمل عيداً عظيماً بهذه المناسبة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the martyr Julius El-Akfehasi be with us all and Glory be to our God, forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات الشهيد يوليوس ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً.  آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.26">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Sixth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-sixth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Saint Timon the Apostle</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس تيمون الرسول أحد السبعين رسولاً وأحد الشمامسة السبعة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Timon the Apostle was martyred. He was one of the 70 Apostles, who were chosen by the Lord and sent them to preach the kingdom of heaven. He also was one of the seven deacons.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ت?عيد الكنيسة ?ي هذا اليوم بعيد أستشهاد القديس تيمون، وهو أحد السبعين رسولاً الذين عينهم الرب وأرسلهم للكرازة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint received the gifts of healing the sick and casting out the evil spirits. He accompanied the Lord until His Ascension into heaven and after that, he continued to be with the disciples and received the grace of the Holy Spirit along with them on the day of Pentecost.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ونال هذا القديس مواهب ش?اء الأمراض وإخراج الشياطين، ولازم الرب حتي صعوده الى السماء ، وبعدها لازم الرسل ونال معهم نعمة الروح القدس يوم الخمسين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Disciples appointed him one of the Seven Deacons, who were full of the Holy Spirit and wisdom. (Acts 6:2-6)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم إنتخبه الرسل ضمن السبعة شمامسة الذين أقامهم الرسل وكانوا مملوئين نعمة وحكمة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After he had remained in the deaconate for a period of time, the apostles laid their hands on him, a bishop of the city of Bostra, in Arabia. He preached the Lord Christ to them and baptized many of its people. The Governor became angry and seized him, and inflicted him with many tortures. He finally burned him alive and thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد أن أقام مدة ?ي الخدمة الشّماسية وضع عليه الرسل اليد أسق?اً علي البصرة ببلاد العرب ، حيث بشر ?يها بالسيد المسيح ، وعمٌد الكثيرين من أهلها ?غضب الوالى وقبض عليه وعذبه بعذابات كثيرة ، وأخيراً أمر بحرقه حياً ?أحرقه بالنار ، ?نال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Seven Martyrs on the Mount of St. Antonius</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار السبعة الشهداء بجبل أنطونيوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1382 A.D. was the martyrdom of the Seven Martyrs on the mount of St. Antonius. They were martyred by the Berbers on the mount of the great Saint Abba Antonius, the father of all monks, in the eastern desert.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار السبعة شهداء الذين قتلهم البربر بجبل القديس العظيم الأنبا أنطونيوس أب الرهبان الصحراء الشرقية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.27">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Seventh Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-seventh day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Macarius, Bishop of Edko (Tkoou)</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس مكاريوس أسق? قاو</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 167 of the martyrs (451 A.D.), St. Macarius, Bishop of Edko (Kaw) , was martyred.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ١ - ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 367 للشهداء (451 م) إستشهد القديس مكاريوس أسق? قاو.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint had reached a high level of holiness, for every time he went up on the pulpit to preach to the people, he wept. When he was asked for the reason for his weeping, he answered that he saw the sins of the people. On another occasion he saw our Lord Christ in the sanctuary, and the angels bringing unto Him the works of the people, one after the other. Anba Macarius heard a voice saying to him, "Why, O bishop, are you slacking in preaching to your people?" He replied, "My Lord, they do not accept my words." So the Lord said to him, "It is meet for the bishop to preach to the people and if they do not accept his words, their blood be upon their own heads."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               نال هذا القديس مرتبة عالية من القداسة ?كان يرى خطايا الشعب ?يبكى عليها. وقد رأى مرة السيد المسيح ?ي الهيكل ، والملائكة يقدمون له أعمال الشعب، وسمع صوتاً يقول له: " لاتغ?ل يا أسق? عن شعبك، لأنه يجب علي الأسق? أن يعظ الشعب، ?إن قبلوا ?لخيرهم وإلا ?دمهم علي رؤسهم".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Abba Dioscorus, the 25th pope of Alexandria, took Abba Macarius with him to attend the council of Chalcedon. On his way to the council on the ship he performed two miracles: healed a young man from a blinding illness and restored the apparel of his disciple which was stolen by one of the sailors.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأخذه القديس الأنبا ديسقورس معه لحضور مجمع خلقيدونية، وحدثت منه إعجوبتان وهو ?ي الس?ينة ?ش?ي غلاماً مهدداً بالعمي، وأسترجع ثوب تلميذه الذى كان قد سرقه أحد البحارة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On arriving to the council, the guards prevented him from entering because of his modest clothes, until Abba Dioscorus told them that he was the bishop of Edko. When he had gone in and heard what the infidels were saying about the Lord Christ, he condemned it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي المجمع لَم يدعْه الجنود يدخل لبساطة ملابسه ، ولكن لما عر?وا أنه أسق? سمحوا له ، ?دخل وعند سماعه لقول المخال?ين إستنكره.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the illegal session of the council, they reviewed with Pope Dioscorus and Abba Macarius the Tome of Leo and the resolution of the council, so St. Dioscorus wrote on it the words of excommunication.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد الجلسة غير القانونية للمجمع. أطلعوا البابا ديسقورس والقديس مكاريوس علي طومس لاون ، ?كتب عليه القديس ديسقورس عبارات الحرمان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Abba Macarius also signed condemning this erroneous faith. Emperor Marcian exiled him along with Anba Dioscorus to the island of Gagra. From there Abba Dioscorus sent him with a Christian merchant to Alexandria saying to him, "There you have a crown of martyrdom awaiting you."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وإشترك معه هذا الآب ?ي توقيع الحرمان علي هذا المعتقد. ?ن?اهم الملك مركيان مع البطريرك الأنبا ديسقورس إلي جزيرة  غاغرا. ومنها أرسله البابا ديسقورس إلي الإسكندرية بصحبة رجل تاجر مسيحي مؤمن قائلا له: "إن لك هناك إكليل شهادة".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Shortly after, he arrived to the city of Alexandria; the messenger of Emperor Marcian arrived also with the Tome of Leo which stated the two natures of Christ. The Emperor had commanded him saying that, "He who endorses this creed first will be the Patriarch of the city of Alexandria, and he who does not endorse it, be killed.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وعندما وصل إلي الإسكندرية إت?ق وصول رسول الملك مركيان ومعه طومس لاون الذي يحوي الإيمان بالطبيعتين وأوصاه الملك قائلا: " مَنْ يوا?ق علي هذه العقيدة أولاً يصير بطريركاً علي الإسكندرية ومن لا يوا?ق عليها ??يقتل".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Emperor's messenger met St. Macarius in Alexandria, he presented to him the tome of Leo but he refused to sign it. The envoy of the Emperor jumped over the Bishop and kicked him with a deadly Kick. St. Macarius died instantly and thus received the crown of martyrdom for keeping his Orthodox faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقابل رسول الملك القديس مكاريوس بالإسكندرية ولما عرض عليه طومس لاون ر?ض التوقيع عليه ، ?ضربه رسول الملك ضربة بقدمه أصابت ?يه مقتلاً ?تنيح ?ي الحال ونال إكليل الشهادة على إيمانه الأرثوذكسي المستقيم .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The believers took his pure body and buried it with the bodies of St. John the Baptist and Elisha the Prophet. That fulfilled what these two saints had told Abba Macarius, in a vision that his body would be with their bodies. His body presently located in a reliquary in the monastery of St. Macarius the great in the wilderness of Scetis along with the bodies of the saints Abba Macarii and St. John the short.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?أخذ المؤمنون جسده الطاهر وجعلوه مع جسدي يوحنا المعمدان وأليشع النبي، ?تحقق بذلك ما قاله هذان القديسان لهذا الأب الأسق? ?ي رؤيا. أن جسده سيكون مع جسديهما. ومازال جسده موجوداً ?ي مقصورة بدير القديس مكاريوس الكبير ببرية شيهيت تحوي أجساد القديسين الثلاثة مقارات والقديس يوحنا القصير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.28">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Eighth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-eighth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">Martyrdom of the Sts. Marcian (Marcianus) and Mercurius</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديسين مركيانوس ومركوريوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 67 of the martyrs (351 A.D.), the two great saints Marcianus and Mercurius were martyred. They were disciples of St. Paul the Martyr, Patriarch of Constantinople.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 67 للشهداء ( 351 م ) أستشهد القديسان العظيمان مركيانوس ومركوريوس وقد كانا تلميذين للقديس بولس الشهيد بطريرك إنطاكية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Constantius, the son of Constantine the Great, adopted the belief of Arius, Abba Paul the Patriarch opposed him refusing his erroneous belief, so he exiled him to Armenia, where he was killed by strangulation.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وسبب إستشهادهما هو أن الملك قسطنطينوس بن قسطنطين لما تبع بدعة أريوس ، لم يوا?قه البطريرك علي معتقده ?ن?اه إلى بلاد الأرمن حيث قتل مخنوقاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               These two saints cried over their father St. Paul. They characterized the Arian faith of the Emperor as corrupt and condemned.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?بكى هذان القديسان على أبيهما وكانا يقولان أن أعتقاد الملك ?اسد ومحروم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Some Arian men made an accusation against them to the Emperor. He had them brought to him and ordered them slain with the sword, so they received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?وشي بهما الأريوسيون لدى الملك ، ?إستحضرهما وأمر بقتلهما بالسي? ?نالا إكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They were buried where they were killed, and their bodies remained there until the time of St. John Chrysostom (of the Golden Mouth). When he knew their account, he sent and brought their honorable bodies to the city of Constantinople. He built a church for them and relocated their bodies with great veneration to it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ود?نا حيث قتلا وظل جسداهما ?ي ذلك المكان إلى زمن القديس يوحنا ذهبي ال?م الذي لما عر? خبرهما بنى لهما كنيسة ?ى القسطنطينية ونقل جسديهما إليها بإكرام جزيل .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.29">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Ninth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-ninth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع والعشرون من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The commemoration of the Three Major Feasts of the Lord</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار الأعياد الثلاثة السيدية " البشارة والميلاد والقيامة "</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The church arranged to celebrate on this day the commemoration of the three major feasts: the Annunciation, the Nativity and the Resurrection of the Lord. The rite of the liturgy is prayed with the joyful tune.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               رتبت الكنيسة أن تحت?ل اليوم بتذكار الثلاثة أعياد السيدية الكبري "البشارة والميلاد والقيامة" وي?صلي بالطقس ال?رايحي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of these feasts of our Good Savior be with us all. Amen            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة هذه الأعياد السيدية التي لمخلصنا الصالح ?لتكن معنا أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Demetrius of Thessalonica</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">إستشهاد القديس ديمتريوس التسالونيكى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, St. Demetrius of Thessalonica, was martyred, in the days of Emperor Maximianus (284 – 312 A.D.).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي مثل هذا اليوم استشهد القديس ديمتريوس التسالونيكى ?ى زمن الملك مكسيميانوس (سنة 284 – 312 م ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was a pious Christian young man from the city of Thessalonica. He learned various subjects, and most of all, those of the Church. He taught and preached diligently and converted many to the faith of the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان هذا القديس شاباً نقياً حصل علي علوم كثيرة وبالأكثر علوم الكنيسة وكان يعلم ويعظ ويرد كثيرين إلى الإيمان بالسيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Some made accusations against him to Emperor Maximianus who had him brought to him. The Emperor ordered him to offer incense to his gods and worship them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث أن وشي به بعض الأشرار لدي الملك ?أستحضره وأمره أن يبخر لآلهته ويسجد لها .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When St. Demetrius refused, the Emperor ordered to thrust spears at him until his body was torn to pieces and he delivered his pure soul in the hand of the Lord whom he loved. Accordingly he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?لم يوا?ق، ?أمر بطعنه بالحراب إلي أن تهرأ جسده وأسلم روحه الطاهرة بيد الرب الذى أحبه ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When they threw away his holy body, the believers took it and laid it in a coffin made out of marble. The body remained hidden until the end of the days of persecution. A great church was built for him in Thessalonica, and they laid his body therein.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?أخذ المؤمنون جسده الطاهر ووضعوه ?ي تابوت من رخام حتي إنقضاء زمن الإضطهاد. ?ب?نيت له كنيسة عظيمة ?ى تسالونيكى ووضعوا جسده ?يها .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Many great signs and wonders were manifested from his body. .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت تحدث منه آيات وعجائب كثيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Gabriel VII, the 95th Pope of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا القديس غبريال السابع البطريرك الخامس والتسعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1285 of the martyr (1568 A.D.) the holy father Pope Gabriel VII, the 95th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضآ من سنة 1285 للشهداء ( 1568 م ) تنيح البابا القديس غبريال السابع البطريرك الخامس والتسعون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint was born in the area around al-Muharraq monastery by the name “Raphael?. His parents raised him in a true Christian upbringing. When he grew, he went and became a monk in the monastery of St. Mary known as El-Suryan in the wilderness of Scetis. He lived there a distinguished monastic life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولد هذا القديس بمنشية الدير المحرق بإسم رو?ائيل. ورباه أبواه تربية مسيحية حقيقية ، ولما كبر مضي وترهب بدير القديسة العذراء المعرو? بالسريان ?ي برية شيهيت وسار سيرة رهبانية ?اضلة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Youannes (John) XIII, departed, the bishops and the lay-leaders (Archons) unanimously agreed to choose him a Patriarch. He was consecrated on Sunday the 4th of Paope, year 1242 of the martyrs (1525 A.D.).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تنيح البابا يؤنس الثالث عشر أجتمع رأي الأساق?ة والأراخنة علي أختياره بطريركاً، ?رسموه يوم الأحد 4 بابه سنة 1242 للشهداء ( 1525 م ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Pope spared no effort in renovating and populating St. Anthony’s monastery and St. Paula’s monastery in the Eastern desert after being in ruins for a long time.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبذل هذا البابا مجهوداً كبيراً ?ي تعمير ديري الأنبا أنطونيوس والأنبا بولا بالصحراء الشرقية بعد خرابهما مدة طويلة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He consecrated Anba Yousab III (Joseph), a metropolitan for Ethiopia in the year 1547 A.D. The relation between the two churches was re-established after a long estrangement.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد رًسم الأنبا يوساب الثالث مطراناً على الحبشة سنة 1547 م ?عادت العلاقات بين الكنيستين بعد مدة من القطيعة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was on his way to the monastery of St. Antonios, he embarked a boat at al-Maymon going to the Eastern shore of the Nile, but he departed while in the boat. They instead took his body and buried him in the church of Abu Saifain in Old Cairo. He remained on the throne of St. Mark for 43 years and 25 days.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث ذات مرة أنه كان ?ي طريقه إلى دير الأنبا أنطونيوس ، ونزل ?ى المركب عند الميمون متوجهاً إلى الناحية الشرقية للنيل ولكنه تنيح ?ي المركب ?نقلوه ود?نوه ?ى كنيسة القديس مرقوريوس أبي سي?ين بمصر القديمة بعد ان قضي على الكرسي المرقسى 43 سنة و25يوماً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paope.30">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Thirtieth Day of the Blessed Month of Paope</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثلاثون من شهر بابه المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the thirtieth day of the blessed month of Paope. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثلاثون من شهر بابه المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Appearance of the Holy Head of St. Mark the Evangelist and the Consecration of his Church</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">ظهور رأس القديس مارمرقس الإنجيلي الرسول ، وتكريس كنيسته</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the church celebrates the appearance of the head of St. Mark the Evangelist and the consecration of the church that was built for the holy head.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي هذا اليوم تعيد الكنيسة بظهور رأس القديس مارمرقس الإنجيلي وتكريس الكنيسة التى بًنيت عليها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The body of St. Mark remained with his head in the same reliquary till the year 644 A.D. This sarcophagus was kept in the church of St. Mark in Bokalia or the place of cows (Dar El-Bakar) in Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ظل جسد القديس مارمرقس ورأسه معاً ?ي  تابوت واحد حتى سنة 644م. وكان هذا التابوت مح?وظاً ?ى كنيسة بوكاليا أو دار البقر بالإسكندرية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day of the year 644 A.D., one of the Arab sailors entered the church, and found this reliquary. He thrust his hand into the sarcophagus of St. Mark, thinking that he would find gold. His hand came upon the head so he stole the expensive shrouds and took the head with him, and hid it in the lower part of the ship and did not tell anyone.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي أحد الأيام من سنة 644م، دخل أحد البحارة العرب إلي الكنيسة ، ?وجد التابوت وتوهم أن ?يه ذهباً ووضع يده ?ي التابوت، ?وقعت يده علي الرأس ?أخذها ?ي الليل وأخ?اها ?ي أس?ل المركب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Amr Ibn El-As was about to leave Alexandria, all the ships sailed except the one that had the head of St. Mark which did not move in spite of all the attempts of the sailors to move it. They realized that a hidden item on board must have been involved. Amr Ibn El-As ordered to search the ship, and they found the head hidden in it. When they took the head off the ship, it sailed right away. Amr Ibn El-As and those with him realized that the reason for the inability of the ship to move was the presence of the holy head on it. He summoned the sailor who hid the head, and he confessed his crime so Amr punished him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما عزم عمرو بن العاص على المسير ، أبحرت كل الس?ن وخرجت من ميناء الإسكندية، ماعدا تلك الس?ينة التى بها الرأس. ?لم تتحرك اطلاقاً رغم محاولات البحارة ?ى بذل جهودهم لإخراجها عند ذلك علموا أن ?ي الأمر سراً. ?أمر عمرو بن العاص بت?تيش الس?ينة، ?وجدوا الرأس مخبأة ?يها ، ?أخرجوها من الس?ينة، واحت?ظ بها عمرو بن العاص. وبعدها تحركت الس?ينة كان بسبب وجود الرأس المقدسة ?يها، ?أخرجوها من الس?ينة حالاً. ??هم عمرو بن العاص ومن معه أن تأخًر الس?ينة كان بسبب وجود الرأس المقدسة ?يها. ?أحضر البحار الذي خبأها، ?إعتر? بجريمته ?عاقبه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Amr Ibn El-As inquired about the Pope of the Coptic people, who was Anba Benjamin I, the 38th Patriarch of Alexandria. The Pope had fled away and disappeared in the monasteries of Upper Egypt. He sent a circular to all the cities of Egypt directing that the Pope's hiding place be kept safe and secure. He asked the Pope to come back to his people and his church. Pope Benjamin came back and Amr turned over the holy head to him. Amr Ibn El-As narrated to the Pope the great miracle that had happened because of the head. He gave the Pope ten thousand dinars to build a great cathedral in the name of the person that this head belonged to.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم سأل عمرو بن العاص عن بابا الأقباط وكان هوالأنبا بنيامين البطريرك الثامن والثلاثين، وكان هارباً ومخت?ياً بأديرة الصعيد. ?كتب له عمرو بن العاص خطاب بخط يده يطمئنه ويعطيه الأمان، ويطلب منه الحضور.  ?حضر البابا بنيامين وإستلم منه الرأس المقدس، بعدما قصٌْ عليه عمرو بن العاص المعجزة العظيمة التى حدثت منها. ثم أعطاه عشرة آلا? دينار ليبنى بها كنيسة عظيمة علي اسم صاحب هذه الرأس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Pope thanked him and kept the holy head in his cell in the monastery of Metra until the completion of the building of the church. He started building the church which was known by the name of El-Mualaka in Alexandria, which is located in the Masalah Street in Alexandria. However, he could not finish it, so his successor Pope Agathon completed and consecrated it on this day, and relocated the holy head to it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?شكره البابا واحت?ظ بالرأس ?ي قلايته بدير مطرا إلي أن يتم بناء الكنيسة ثم بدأ ?ي بناء الكنيسة التى عًر?ت بإسم المعلقة بالإسكندرية الكائنة ?ي شارع المسلة – بالثغر. ولكنه لم يستطع إكمالها، ?أتمها خلي?ته البابا أغاثون وكرسٌها ?ي مثل هذا اليوم. ووضع ?يها الرأس المقدس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               As a part of the rites of consecrating the patriarchs, the successors of St. Mark the apostle, the newly elected pope used to go on the second day of enthronement to the head of St. Mark the Evangelist and Apostle, accompanied by the bishops, priests, and people. He would prostrate himself before the holy head, then raise incense, and read the introduction of the Gospel of St. Mark before the holy head. He would then conclude the prayer by the absolution and the blessing. Then he would enter a room by himself, place the holy head on his lap, remove the old covering, and re-dress it with a new silk covering and then seal it. Then he would go out to the people so they could kiss it, each one according to his rank. Then he would receive the blessing of the founder of the See of St. Mark.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان من طقس رسامة البطاركة خل?اء القديس مارمرقس الرسول أن يتوجه البابا ثان يوم رسامته إلى رأس مارمرقس الإنجيلى الرسول وصحبة الأساق?ة والكهنة والشعب ?يضرب المطانية أمام الرأس المقدس. ثم ير?ع البخور أمام الرأس ويقرأ مقدمة إنجيل مرقس. ويختم الصلاة بالتحليل والبركة. ثم يدخل إلى حجرة وحده ، ويأخذ الرأس المقدس ويضعها ?ى حجره ، وينزع عنها الكسوة القديمة ، ويكسوها بكسوة جديدة من الحرير ويخيط عليها. وبعد ذلك يظهر للناس وهى ?ي حجره ليقبلوها واحداً ?واحداً حسب رتبتهم ويتبارك هو من مؤسس الكرازة المرقسية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of the apostle St. Mark the Evangelist be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات القديس مارمرقس الإنجيلى الرسول ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Ibrahim El-Menofy, the Hermit</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس إبراهيم المتوحد</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, St. Ibrahim, the hermit, departed. He was born in the city of Menuf, to rich, Christian parents. His parents raised him in a Christian upbringing and refined him with evangelical manners.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً تنيح القديس إبراهيم المتوحد. ولد بمنو? من أبوين مسيحيين غنيين، ?ربياة بالتربية المسيحية وأدباه بالآداب الإنجيلية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he grew up he longed for the monastic life. He went to Akhmeem and from there he came to St. Pachomius, father of the Koinonia, who put the monastic garb on him. St. Ibrahim lived-in asceticism and ardent worship. He stayed with St. Pachomius for 23 years, and then he desired the solitary life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?لما كبر أشتاق إلى السيرة الرهبانية، ?قصد بلاد أخميم ومن هناك وصل إلى القديس باخوميوس أب الشركة، حيث ألبسه ثياب الرهبنة وأقام عنده ثلاث وعشرين سنة بالنسك والعبادة الحارة، ثم سمح له القديس باخوميوس بالتوحٌد ?ي إحدي المغارات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Pachomius permitted him to live a solitary life in one of the caves. He made nets to catch fish. One of the laymen used to come, take the work of his hands to sell, buy for him his needs, and give the rest of the money to the poor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?عاش ?يها يشتغل بصناعة الشباك وكان أحد المؤمنين يبيع له عمل يديه ويشترى له إحتياجاته ويوزع الباقى علي ال?قراء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He dwelt in this cave for 16 years. He ate each evening some of salty beans soaked in water. He covered himself with a piece of sackcloth (Khaish).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأقام ?ي هذه المغارة ستة عشر سنة يأكل ?يها عند مساء كل يوم بعض ال?ول المبلول المملح، وكان يستر جسده بقطع من الخيش.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The devil fought much against him. They disturbed him with strange voices and terrified him with fearful images. But with the power of prayers and with God’s help, he used to overcome them and drive them away.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد حورب كثيراً من الشياطين، وكانوا يزعجونه بأصوات غريبة وخيالات مخي?ة ، ?كان ينتصر عليهم بالصلاة واللجوء الي الله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When his departure drew near, he sent the lay brother who used to serve him to bring Abba Tadros, the disciple of St. Pachomius. When Abba Tadros came, St. Ibrahim bowed down and asked for his blessing. Then he rose up and prayed with St. Tadros. Then, laid down facing the east and delivered up his pure soul in the hand of the Lord whom he loved.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما دنت و?اته، أرسل الرجل الذي يخدمه إلي القديس تادرس تلميذ الأنبا باخوميوس يستدعيه، ?لما حضر تبارك منه ثم قاما وصليا ، ثم رقد متوجهاً الى الشرق ، وأسلم روحه الطاهرة بيد الرب الذي أحبه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Tadros sent the news to the monastery, and consequently the monks came and carried him to the church. They prayed over him, and then laid him along with the bodies of the saints.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?أرسل القديس تادرس إلي الدير، ?حضر الرهبان وحملوه إلى الكنيسة وصلوا عليه ثم وضعوه مع أحد القديسين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season></Document>