<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Season id="Paremhotep.1">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The First Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الأول من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the first day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الأول من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Makronius and Thecla</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسين مقرونيوس وتكلا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day was the martyrdom of the two saints Makronius and Thecla.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم استشهد القديسين مقرونيوس وتكلا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهما فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Alexandrus, the Soldier</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس ألكسندروس الجندى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 13 of the martyrs (297 A.D.) St. Alexandrus (Alexander) the soldier was martyred. This saint was born in Rome and was raised there. He was a soldier in the army of Emperor Maximianus.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 13 للشهداء ( 297 م ) أستشهد القديس ألكسندروس الجندى. ولد هذا القديس بمدينة روما وتربى فيها. وكان جندياً فى جيش الإمبراطور مكسيميانوس (وعينه الإمبراطور دقلديانوس سنة 286 م مساعداً له على إيطاليا وأفريقيا).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               It so happened that the saint believed in Christianity. The Emperor heard of that so he summoned the saint and asked him to raise incense for the idols but he refused. When the Emperor insisted the saint answered bravely and politely: "You have the authority, O Emperor. I revere you and would be happy to accept what you impose upon me. I revere you as an emperor, but I love my God more than you."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث أن آمن القديس بالمسيحية فسمع بذلك الإمبراطور فاستدعاه وطلب منه التبخير للأوثان فرفض. ولما أصر الإمبراطور أجابه القديس بشجاعة مملوءة أدباً: "إنك صاحب سلطان أيها الإمبراطور لك أن تفرضه على وأنا سعيد ، إنى أهابك كإمبراطور لكنى أحب إلهى أكثر منك".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Emperor threatened him with death if he did not slaughter sacrifices for the idols. He replied: "Death that you think you are threatening me with, in the eyes of the Christian is life." The Emperor became angry and ordered him hung by his hands and to tie a stone to his feet. He also ordered to beat him and burnt alive. However the Lord in all of this healed and strengthened him. Finally he ordered to behead him, thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فهدده الإمبراطور بالموت ما لم يذبح للأوثان. فأجابه: "الموت الذى تظن أنك تهددنى به هو فى نظر المسيحيين الحياة". فغضب الإمبراطور وأمر بتعليقه من يديه وُيربط حجر فى رجليه ، ثم أمر أيضاً بضربه وبحرقه حياً ، وكان الرب في كل هذا يقيمه سالما ً ويقويه. وأخيرا ً أمر بقطع رأسه. فنال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Narcissus, Bishop of Jerusalem</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس نركيسوس أسقف بيت المقدس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 212 A.D. the Holy Father St. Narcissus, bishop of Jerusalem, departed. This saint was well known for his apostolic zeal, holiness and public speaking. They chose him a bishop for Jerusalem and he shepherded his flock and guided them in the way of righteousness. He suffered from the persecution of Emperor Maximianus against the Christians. God granted this father the gift of performing miracles.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 222 م تنيح الأب القديس نركيسوس أسقف بيت المقدس ، وكان هذا الأب قديساً كاملاً فأقاموه أسقفا ًعلى بيت المقدس بأورشليم ، فى عهد الإمبراطور سبتميوس ساويرس (كانت فترة حكمه من سنة 193 – 211 م) فرعى شعب المسيح رعاية رسولية حقيقية ، غير أن هدوء الكنيسة لم يدم طويلا ًلموت الإمبراطور سبتميوس ساويرس وقيام أباطرة بعده أثاروا الاضطهاد على المسيحيين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the eve of the feast of Resurrection, the oil in the lamps ran out, so he ordered the lamps to be filled with water and they were lit.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Satan envied him so he moved some wicked men who accused him according to three false witnesses. When St. Narcissus realized the harm that might affect his flock, he forsook the world and relinquished his episcopate. He lived in seclusion in the wilderness completely submitting to the will of God without anyone knowing where he was.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               As of those who falsely witnessed against him, God punished them, the first his house burnt, the second struck with painful boils in all his body and the third lost his eye sight. The flock of St. Narcissus became convinced of the innocence of their bishop.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They diligently searched for him until they found the saint and asked him incessantly to return to his parish. He returned with them and continued his strife and exerted himself in serving the souls. Through his exhortations and his eloquent discourses brought many back to the faith of the Lord Christ. The Lord performed many miracles and signs by his hand.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After he completed his good endeavor departed in peace.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Anba Marcura, the Bishop</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس مرقورة الأسقف</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also the church celebrates the departure of the Holy Father Anba Marcura the bishop.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى مثل هذا اليوم تعيد الكنيسة بنياحة  القديس الأنبا مرقورة الأسقف.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Monk George (Guirguis) EbN El-A’ameed known as Ebn el-Makeen</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  الراهب جرجس بن العميد الشهير بابن المكين</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Also on this day was the departure of the monk George (Guirguis) EbN el-A’ameed known as Ebn el-Makeen. This saint was educated from his youth in the ecclesiastical sciences, excelling in his studies due to his high level of asceticism. Eventually, he left the world and its riches behind to consecrate his life to prayer, learning, and meditating on the greatness of God in the monastery of St. John Kolobos (“the Dwarf”) in Tora, near Cairo. There he was given the holy eskeem. This father was concerned with learning the Coptic, Greek, and Arabic languages, as well as learning logic, philosophy, and history. He compiled four valuable treatises. This saint had a brother named al-Asʿad Ibrahīm who was a scribe for the army of Al-Malik al-ʿĀdil in the thirteenth century AD.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً تنيح الراهب جرجس بن العميد الشهير بأبن المكين. تعلم هذا القديس منذ صباه علوم الكنيسة ونبغ فيها ولشدة نسكه وزهده ترك العالم وغناه وكرس حياته للعبادة والصلاة مع البحث والدراسة والتأمل فى عظائم الله فى دير الأنبا يوأنس القصير في طرة بالقاهرة. حيث لبس الإسكيم الرهبانى وقد اهتم هذا الأب بدراسة اللغات القبطية والعربية واليونانية. كما درس المنطق والفلك والتاريخ ووضع أربعة مؤلفات نافعة.  وقد كان لهذا القديس أخ يسمى الأسعد إبراهيم وكان يعمل كاتبا ًلجيوش الملك العادل فى القرن الثالث عشر الميلادى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the monk St. George (Guirguis) completed his good struggle, he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل القديس الراهب جرجس جهاده الحسن تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائما ًأبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.2">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Second Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثانى من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the second day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثانى من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Macrobius (Macrawy) the Bishop</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس الأنبا مكراوى الأسقف</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 21 of the martyrs (305 A.D.) the Holy Father Anba Macrobius (Macrawy), the bishop, was martyred. This saint was born in Ashmun Grais (Ashmun Kharirat), Menofia governorate to Christian parents who were rich in piety, faith, and also possessions. They raised him up with a true Christian upbringing. When he grew up he devoted himself to fasting, praying and reading the Holy Books.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 21 للشهداء ( 305 م) أستشهد القديس الأنبا مكراوى الأسقف. ولد هذا القديس بأشمون جريس بمحافظة المنوفية من أبوين مسيحيين غنيين فى التقوى والإيمان والمال أيضاً. فربياه تربية مسيحية. ولما كبر عكف على الصوم والصلاة وقراءة الكتب المقدسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When his virtues became well known, they ordained him a bishop for the City of Nikiu (Nakiyos) . He strived in teaching and confirming his people in the Orthodox faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               المقدسة حتى ذاعت فضائله الكثيرة. فرسموه أسقفا ً على مدينه نيقيوس (حاليا ًهى قرية زاوية رزين بمحافظة المنوفية). فأقام مجاهدا ً ومعلما ً ومثبتا ً شعبه على الأيمان الأرثوذكسي المستقيم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Youfanyous, the governor, heard of him, he summoned the saint and offered him to worship the idols. When he refused he ordered him beaten, insulted and poured melted lime in vinegar down his throat. However God strengthened, and healed him. As the governor was perplexed about him, he sent him to Armanius the governor of Alexandria who imprisoned him. God wrought many signs by his hands. When governor Armanius heard about the signs that were performed by the saint he ordered him crushed by the Hinbazeen and dismembered. Then they cast him to fierce beasts which did not harm him. Finally they beheaded him by the sword, and he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما سمع به يونانيوس الوالى إستحضره وعرض عليه عبادة الأوثان ولما رفض أمر بأن يضرب ويهان ويذاب جير فى خل ويصب فى حلقه ففعلوا به كذلك وكان الله يقويه ويشفيه. ولما أحتار الوالى فى أمره أرسله إلى أرمانيوس والى الإسكندرية  فأودعه السجن وقد أجرى الله على يديه آيات كثيرة. فبلغ إلى مسامع الوالى أرمانيوس ما يفعله هذا القديس من الآيات فأمر بعصره فى الهنبازين وتقطيع أعضائه ثم ألقوه للوحوش الضارية فلم تؤذه. أخيرا ًقطعوا رأسه بحد السيف فنال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Julius el-Akfehasi (of Aqfahs) took his body, shrouded it with great veneration and put a cross on his chest and sent him on a ship, accompanied by his young men to his diocese. The ship stopped at his hometown Ashmun Grais. When they could not move the ship they understood that the Lord wants the body of the saint in this place. The People went out and carried the body, singing praises in front of him and buried the saint with great honor. He lived one hundred and thirty years, sixty nine years of them in his Episcopal rank. Thus he completed his good strife.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فأخذ القديس يوليوس الأقفهصى جسده وكفنه بإكرام عظيم ووضع صليبا ً على صدره وأرسله فى سفينة بصحبه غلمانه إلى مقر كرسيه. فسارت السفينة وتوقفت عند بلدته أشمون جريس. ولما لم يستطيعوا تحريك السفينة فهموا أن الرب يريد أن يكون جسد القديس فى هذا الموضع. فخرج الشعب وحملوه مرتلين أمامه ودفنوه. وكانت مدة حياته مائة وإحدى وثلاثين سنة منها تسع وستون سنة فى الرئاسة الكنائسية. وهكذا أكمل جهاده الحسن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة  صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائما ًأبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.3">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Third Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the third day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Holy Father Pope Cosmas, 58th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس الأنبا قسما البطريرك الثامن والخمسين من بطاركه الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 648 of the martyrs (932 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Cosmas III (Kosma), 58th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. He excelled in studying the Holy Scriptures and the church subjects from a young age. They unanimously chose him for the patriarchate as a successor to Pope Gabriel I. He was consecrated in Alexandria on the 4th day of Paremhotep, in the year 636 of the martyrs (920 A.D.) He presided over the church tending to his people with purity and chastity. He cared for the poor and the needy, taught the people, built churches and consecrated bishops for the vacant dioceses among them were Anba Peter, metropolitan for Ethiopia.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 648 للشهداء (93٢م) تنيح القديس البابا قسما الثالث البطريرك الثامن و الخمسون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. نبغ فى الأسفار الإلهية والعلوم الكنسيه منذ صغره فأجمعوا على إختياره بطريركا ًخلفاً للبابا غبريال الأول.  وكرسوه بالإسكندرية  يوم 4 برمهات 636 للشهداء (920 م). فأقام على الكرسى المرقسي راعياً شعبه بالطهارة والعفاف وأهتم بالفقراء والمساكين وتعليم الشعب وتشييد الكنائس وأقام أساقفة للإيبارشيات الخالية ومن بينهم الأنبا بطرس مطران الحبشة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the days of Pope Kosma, some troubles befell Egypt. The Fatimids conquered the country, which caused a famine, looting and killing. The Pope did not find any mean to help his people except by prayer, fasting and visiting his flock to comfort them. Because of the weakness of the Pope's body from his ascetic life and the sadness that afflicted him, he departed in peace. He remained on the apostolic throne for about twelve years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى أيام البابا قسما حدثت بعض الاضطرابات بسبب دخول الفاطميين إلى مصر مما أدى إلى وجود مجاعات وسلب ونهب وقتل. ولم يجد هذا البابا وسيله أمامه غير الصلاة والصوم وافتقاد شعبه وتعزيتهم. وضعف جسد البابا من كثرة نسكه والحزن الذى أصابه فتنيح بسلام بعد أن قضى على الكرسي المرقسي نحو اثنتى عشر سنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Porphyry</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس برفوريوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the martyrdom of St. Porphyry in the days of Emperor Diocletian. The saint was one of the wealthy people of Banias and the most charitable and caring for the poor and the needy and visiting the prisoners.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أُستشهد القديس برفوريوس فى أيام الإمبراطور دقلديانوس. وكان من كبار أغنياء بانياس وأكثرهم صدقة وعطفاً على الفقراء والمساكين وافتقاد المحبوسين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When persecution was incited against the Christians and called everywhere to worship the idols, this saint heard of the passing by of the Prince, he stood in front of his house and shouted in his face, "I am a Christian - I am a Christian." The Prince tried to dissuade him from his confession of faith, but the saint refused. He ordered to behead him thus he received the crown of martyrdom. The people of his hometown took his body, shrouded him with expensive shrouds and buried him with great veneration.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما ثار الاضطهاد على المسيحيين ونادوا فى كل مكان بالسجود للأصنام وسمع هذا القديس بمرور الأمير وقف أمام بيته وصاح فى وجهه " أنا مسيحى - أنا مسيحى" فحاول الأمير أن يُثنيه عن اعترافه بالإيمان ولكنه رفض فأصدر أمرا  بقطع رأسه فنال إكليل الشهادة وأخذ جسده أهل بلده وكفنوه بأكفان غالية ودفنوه بإكرام جزيل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Porphyry, Bishop of Gaza</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس برفوريوس أسقف غزة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also of the year 136 of the Martyrs (420 A.D.) the Holy Father St. Porphyry, bishop of Gaza, departed. This saint was born in the year 69 of the martyrs (353 A.D.) in the city of Thessalonica to Christian parents who were rich in virtue and money. They raised him on the Christian teachings and taught him the secular subjects. When he was twenty-five years old he undertook the monastic life in the wilderness of Shiheet, where he spent five years living in asceticism, prayer and meditation. Then he dwelt in a cave alone where he practiced austere asceticism until he became very thin and was close to death. He went to Jerusalem, where he recovered by the power of the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 136 للشهداء ( 42٠ م) تنيح الأب القديس برفوريوس أسقف غزة.       ولد هذا القديس سنة 69 للشهداء ( 35٣ م ) فى مدينة تسالونيكى من أبوين مسيحيين غنيين بالفضيلة والمال. فربياه على التعاليم المسيحية وعلماه العلوم العالمية. ولما بلغ الخامسة والعشرين من عمره إتخذ السيرة الرهبانية فى برية الإسقيط حيث أمضى خمس سنوات فى عيشه النسك والصلاة والتأمل ثم انطلق إلى مغارة منفرده وتنسك فيها حتى نحل جسمه وأشرف على الموت فمضى إلى أورشليم حيث تم شفاؤه بقوة السيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Given what was known about him from grace and piety they ordained him a priest, then St. John, archbishop of Jerusalem, ordained him a bishop for Gaza. The natives of the city were heathen and they rebelled against the saint and wanted to slay him but he disappeared away from them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ونظرا ً لما عرف عنه من فضل وتقوى رسموه كاهناً ثم رسمه القديس يوحنا رئيس أساقفة أورشليم أسقفا ً على غزة وكان أكثر أهلها من الوثنيين فثاروا عليه وأرادوا قتله فتوارى عنهم بعيداً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In those days it did not rain and a great famine befell the land of Palestine. So the heathen offered sacrifices to the gods in order for the rain to come down but it did not. They sought St. Porphyry with whose prayers God sent down rain consequently many of the pagans believed and were baptized in the name of the Holy Trinity.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى تلك الأيام لم ينزل المطر فحدث جوع شديد فى بلاد فلسطين فقام الوثنيون بتقدم الذبائح للآلهه لكى ينزل المطر فلم ينزل فلجأوا للقديس برفوريوس الذى بصلواته أنزل الله المطر فآمن كثيرون من الوثنيين وأعتمدوا باسم الثالوث القدوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint built a large church in Gaza City with the help of Empress Eudoxia the wife of Emperor Arcadius. He also shepherd the Church of the Lord with wisdom and piety. He cared for the widows and the needy and he encouraged the young people repeatedly on the life of piety, purity and virginity. When he completed his good endeavor departed in peace after serving the Lord and His church for twenty-four years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بنى هذا القديس كنيسة كبيرة فى مدينه غزة بمساعدة الإمبراطورة أفدوكيا زوجه الإمبراطور أركاديوس كما رعى كنيسة الرب بحكمة وتقوى ودراية وكان يعتنى بالأرامل والمساكين وشجع الشباب كثيراً على حياة الطهارة والتقوى والبتولية. ولما أكمل جهاده الصالح تنيح بسلام بعد أن قضى على الكـرسى مدة أربع وعشرين سنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة  صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Hadid the priest</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس الأنبا حديد القس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1103 of the martyrs (1387 A.D.), Anba Hadid, the presbyter, departed. This saint was born in the village of Singar, nearby el-Borollos Lake to pious parents. His father was a fisherman and they had no children. His mother saw a vision at night, a luminous angel telling her, "God shall grant you a blessed son, that would be a shepherd for the people, and when God fulfill His promise to call him Hadid.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 1103 للشهداء (1387م) تنيح القديس الأنبا حديد القس. ولد هذا القديس فى قرية  سنجار من أعمال البرلس من أبوين تقيين وكان والده يعمل صيادا ً للسمك. ولم يكن لهما ولد. وحدث أن رأت أمه رؤيا فى الليل وإذ ملاك نورانى يقول لها " اعلمى أن الله سيرزقك أبناً مباركاً يكون رئيساً على شعب. ومتى أتم الله وعده تسمينه "حديد ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               God fulfilled his promise and she gave birth to this saint and called him Hadid. They raised him on the Christian teachings and he persevered unceasingly on fasting and prayer.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فأتم الله وعده وأنجبت هذا القديس وأسمته حديد. فربياه على التعاليم المسيحية فواظب على الصوم والصلاة بلا فتور.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he grew his mother proposed to him to get married but he refused. He worked with his father in fishing and his virtues became well known. Fearing the snares of Satan he left and worked as a laborer, donated what he earned and served the needy in his spare time.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما كبر عرضت عليه أمه الزواج فرفض. وكان يعمل مع والده فى صيد السمك فاشتهرت فضائله فخاف من فخاخ الشيطان وذهب وعمل أجيراً وكان يتصدق بكل مايحصل عليه ويخدم المحتاجين فى أوقات فراغه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He desired the monastic life and wanted to go to the wilderness of St. Macarius, but the blessed Virgin St. Mary appeared to him in a vision and told him that the Lord wanted him to reside in a church after her name in the village of "Matobas el-Romman. " He went away to that church and served there faithfully and humbly. He devoted himself to reading and studying the Holy Books. The people of the village unanimously agreed to nominate him to the bishop to be their priest. The father the bishop ordained him a priest for them. He watched over the salvation of his flock, teaching them, giving himself as an example to them in every good work.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأراد أن يمضى ليترهب فى بريه القديس مكاريوس لكن ظهرت له العذراء القديسة مريم فى رؤيا وأعلمته بأن الرب أراد له أن يقيم فى بيعه على إسمها فى قرية  "مطوبس الرمان". فمضى إلى الكنيسة وخدم فيها بأمانه وأتضاع مواظبا ً على قراءة الكتب الإلهية. واتفق رأى شعب القرية  أن يزكوه أمام الأسقف ليكون كاهنا ً عليهم. فرسمه الأب الأسقف قساً فكان يسهر على خلاص رعيته وتعليمهم مقدما ً نفسه قدوة لهم فى كل عمل صالح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He became known for performing healings and signs which brought upon him many tribulations and trials but the Lord saved him from all of them. When he completed his good endeavor he became ill with a severe fever, and he delivered his pure soul to the habitations of the righteous. His people mourned him, shrouded his body and buried him with great veneration.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               واشتهر بصنع الأشفية والعجائب فكانت سببا ً فى تعرضه لتجارب كثيرة ومن جميعها أنقذه الرب. ولما أكمل سعيه الحسن أخذته حمى شديدة وبعدها فاضت روحه الطاهره الى مساكن الأبرار. فبكاه شعبه وكفنوه بإكرام جزيل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة  صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.4">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fourth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fourth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Assembly of a Holy Council on the island of Bani-Omar</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أجتماع مجمع بجزيرة بنى عمر على قوم يُقال لهم الأربعتعشريه بخصوص القيامة المقدسة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day a Holy Council convened on the island of Bani-Omar against those people called the Quartodeciman (Fourteenthians). They celebrated the feast of the Holy Resurrection with the Jews on the fourteenth day of the month of Nisan (April) regardless what day of the week it fell on. The Bishop of the island excommunicated them, and sent to Serapion Patriarch of Antioch, Democratus Archbishop of Rome, Demetrius Patriarch of Alexandria, and Symmachus Patriarch of Jerusalem to inform them of the heresy of these people. Each one of them sent an epistle indicating in it that the feast of Resurrection was only to be celebrated on the Sunday that follows the feast of the Jews and ordered to excommunicate everyone that contradict and disobey that.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم إنعقد مجمع بجزيرة بنى عمر على قوم يقال لهم الأربعتعشرية. هؤلاء كانوا يعيدون عيد القيامة مع اليهود فى اليوم الرابع عشر من شهر نيسان العبرى فى أى يوم اتفق من أيام الأسبوع فحرمهم أسقف الجزيرة وأرسل إلى سرابيون بطريرك إنطاكية وديمقراطس بطريرك روما وديمتريوس بطريرك الإسكندرية وسيماخس بطريرك أورشليم وأعلمهم ببدعة هؤلاء القوم. فأرسل كل منهم رسالة اليه حدد فيها ألا يعمل العيد إلا يوم الأحد الذى يلى عيد اليهود ويحرمون من يتعدى هذا ويخالفه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This council of eighteen bishops convened and the epistles of the fathers the Patriarchs were read to them. Some of them returned from their erroneous opinion and the others insisted on their error. They excommunicated them from the fellowship of the Holy Church. Also, they decided to celebrate the feast of Resurrection as the order of the Holy Apostles who said: "Any one that celebrates the feast of Resurrection on any other day than Sunday had shared the Jews in their feasts and separated himself from the Christians."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هذا المجمع بالجزيرة من ثمانية عشر أسقفاً وتليت عليهم رسائل الآباء البطاركة فرجع من هؤلاء القوم بعض منهم وبقى آخرون على ضلالهم فحرموهم وقرروا عمل عيد القيامه كأوامر الآباء الرسل القديسين القائلين: "إن من يُعيد عيد القيامه فى غير يوم الأحد فقد شارك اليهود فى أعيادهم وافترق عن المسيحيين".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               May the Lord confirm us in the Orthodox faith which the holy apostles handed down to us, the blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الرب يثبتنا على الإيمان المستقيم الذى سلمه لنا الآباء الرسل. بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Haboulyous (Hanulius) the prince</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس هانوليوس الأمير</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also St. Haboulyous (Hanulius) the prince, was martyred, during the reign of Diocletian. This saint was born in the city of Perga in Pamphylia to Christian parents who brought him up with a true Christian upbringing. He loved the Lord and strived in worship and piety. He was the prince (Governor) of the city of Perga.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً استشهد القديس هانوليوس الأمير فى أيام دقلديانوس. ولد هذا القديس فى مدينه بمفيلية ( برجة بمفيلية أع 13 : 13 و أع 14 : 25 ). من أبوين مسيحيين ربياه تربية  مسيحية  حقيقيه فأحب الرب وجاهد فى العبادة  والتقوى وكان أميرا ً على برجة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Diocletian heard that he was a Christian, he sent to Barnabakhas the Governor ordering him to arrest the saint. When he stood before the governor, he declared his Christian faith. The Prince became angry and ordered him crucified. However the Lord comforted and strengthened him and finally he departed in peace and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما سمع الإمبراطور دقلديانوس انه مسيحى أرسل إلى باريناخس الأمير يأمره بالقبض على القديس. ولما وقف القديس هانوليوس أمام الأمير جاهر بالإيمان المسيحى فأمر بصلبه على خشبة وكان الرب يقويه ويعزيه. وأخيرا ً تنيح بسلام ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة  صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.5">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fifth day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fifth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Anba Serapamon, Hegumen of Abba Yehnis (John) monastery</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس الأنبا صرابامون قمص دير القديس الأنبا يحنس القصير</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the ascetic holy father Anba Serapamon the Hegumen of Anba Yehnis (John) monastery , departed. Since his young age, he was raised on a life of piety and virtues. Then he went and became a monk in the monastery of the saint Abu-Yehnis the Short (Colobos). He persevered in worship, asceticism, fasting, and prayers. When his virtues became known they ordained him a Hegumen for the monastery. He added to the works of piety and asceticism. He fasted all day from the day he joined the monastery till the day of his departure. After spending many years in managing the monastery and serving the fathers the monk, he shut himself up in his cell practicing austere asceticism, reading and contemplating.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تنيح القديس الأنبا صرابامون. تربى منذ صغره على حياة التقوى والفضيلة ثم مضى وترهب فى دير القديس أبى يحنس القصير فواظب على النسك والعبادة والصوم والصلاة. ولما ظهرت فضائله أقاموه قمصاً على الدير فتزايد فى بره ونسكه حتى انه كان يصوم طول النهار وذلك من يوم رهبنته إلى يوم نياحته. وبعد أن قضى سنوات طويلة فى تدبير الدير وخدمة الآباء الرهبان إنفرد فى قلايته ومارس فيها النسك الشديد والقراءة والتأمل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When his departure drew near, the angel of the Lord appeared to him in a vision and gave him a cross of fire saying: "Take this cross in your hand". The saint replied: "How can I hold fire in my hand." The angel said: "Do not be afraid for the Lord Christ has not given the fire dominion over you," then the Saint took the cross. The angel told him: "Be strong, partake of the Holy Mysteries and after three days I shall come back to take you".            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما دنت نياحة هذا الأب ظهر له ملاك الرب فى رؤيا وناوله صليبا ًمن نار قائلاً له: خذ هذا بيدك. فقال له القديس: "كيف أستطيع أن أمسك النار بيدى ؟" فقال له الملاك لا تخف لأن السيد المسيح لم يجعل لها عليك سلطاناً فأخذ الصليب ثم أعلمه الملاك قائلاً: "تقو وتقرب من الأسرار المقدسة وبعد ثلاثه أيام سآتى وآخذك".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he woke up from his sleep, he told the elders about his vision. They wept, bid him farewell, and asked him to remember them. He also asked them to remember him in their prayers. He departed in peace on the third day and the elders were around him. They shrouded and buried him with great honor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما استيقظ من النوم أعلم الآباء بالرؤيا فبكوا وودعوه وسألوه أن يذكرهم. فطلب هو أيضاً إليهم أن يداوموا على ذكره فى صلواتهم ثم تنيح بسلام والآباء حوله فكفنوه بإكرام عظيم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Eudoxia (Eutychia)</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسة أوذوكسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 114 A.D. St. Eudoxia was martyred. This Saint was of Samaritan origin, from the city of Ba’albek, in Syria. With the beauty of her face and physical appearance, she caused many to fall into sin, acquiring thereby great wealth.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 114م أستشهدت القديسة أوذوكسية ( كلمة يونانية معناها "ممجدة" ). ولدت هذه القديسة فى بعلبك بالشام من أصل سامرى. وكانت جميلة للغاية وبهذا الجمال جذبت الكثيرين إلى الخطية و أقتنت أموالا ً كثيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               A saintly ascetic monk named Germanus heard about her. He went to her pretending to be one of those who used to visit her, but when they were alone, he exhorted her with many dreadful and fearful words, reminding her of eternal torment. She asked him saying: "Do the bodies rise up after death to be judged?" He replied, "Yes". Then she asked him: "What are the proofs of what you say, since the Torah that God gave to Moses the prophet did not mention this and I did not hear this from my forefathers?" He explained to her with convincing biblical and logical proofs until she was persuaded. She asked him: "If I return repentant to God, would He accept me?" St. Germanus replied: "If you believe in the Lord Christ and that He came to the world, took away our sins by His Crucifixion, and offer a sincere repentance and be baptized in his Name, He will accept you, and will not mention any of what you have done, but you will be as if you just have been born."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . فسمع بها ناسك قديس أسمه جرمانس فدخل إليها فى صورة الرجال الذين اعتادوا الدخول لها ، ووعظها بأقوال رهيبة ومخيفة وذكرها بعقاب جهنم. فأجابته قائلة: "هل بعد الموت تُقام هذه الأجساد وتُحاسب؟". فقال لها نعم. فسألته أيضاً: "وما هو دليلك على ذلك خصوصاً أن توراه موسى النبى لم تذكر هذا الكلام ولا سمعته أنا من أبائى؟". فأثبته لها وأقنعها بالبراهين الشرعية والعقلية. فسألته: "هل إذا رجعت نادمة إلى الله يقبلنى؟" فأجابها القديس: "أعلمى أنك إن آمنت بالسيد المسيح وانه جاء إلى العالم وحمل خطايا البشر بصلبه عنهم ثم قدمت توبة صادقة وأعتمدت على إسمه فأنه يقبلك ولا يذكر لك شيئاً مما صنعتيه بل تكونين كما كنت يوم ولادتك من بطن أمك".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Her heart opened to the faith and he took her to Anba Theodorus, bishop of Baalbek. She confessed before him the Holy Trinity and the Incarnation of God the Word. She repented at his hands and confessed her sins before him, so he baptized her.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فانفتح قلبها إلى الإيمان ومضى بها إلى الأنبا ثيئودورس أسقف بعلبك وأعترفت أمامه بالثالوث الأقدس وبتجسد الله الكلمة وتابت على يديه وأعترفت بخطاياها أمامه فعمدها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Afterwards she distributed all what she owned on the poor and the needy. Then she joined a house of virgins and she fought a good and perfect fight and persevered in prayer, fasting and asceticism. However, Satan became envious of her, and moved some wicked men to accuse her before Emperor Trajan. He summoned her and tried to befriend her to deny her faith in the Lord Christ. When she refused he ordered to behead her thus she received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد ذلك قامت ووزعت كل ماتملك على الفقراء والمساكين ومضت إلى بيت للعذارى وجاهدت جهادا ً كبيراً وداومت على الصلاة والصوم والنسك. فحسدها الشيطان فحرك بعض الناس وسعوا بها عند الإمبراطور تراجان فاستدعاها وحاول أن يستميلها لتنكر الإيمان بالمسيح فرفضت فأمر بقطع رأسها فنالت إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة  صلواتها فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.6">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Sixth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the sixth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Dioscorus</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس ديوسقورى فى زمان العرب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Dioscorus was martyred during the time of the Arabs. This saint was born in the city of Alexandria to Christian parents. For unexplained reason, he left the Christian faith and adopted the faith of the Arabs. When his sister heard what her brother had done she was greatly sorrowful. She sent to him a letter from el-Fayyom saying: "I would have liked to hear the news that you had died a Christian, than that you are alive, and you have abandoned the Faith of the Lord Christ your God." She also said: "Know that this letter marks the end of the relation between you and me.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل اليوم استشهد القديس ديوسقورس. ولد هذا القديس بمدينة الإسكندرية من أبوين مسيحيين وقد حدث له أن ترك الإيمان المسيحى ودخل فى ديانة العرب فلما سمعت به أخته حزنت عظيما ً وأرسلت له رساله من الفيوم تقول: "لقد كنت اشتهى أن أسمع خبر موتك وأنت مسيحى ولا أسمع خبر حياتك وأنت بعيد عن السيد المسيح إلهك".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he had read his sister's letter, it touched him, he wept bitterly, and signed himself with the sign of the cross, and prayed entreating God fervently. Then he rose in haste and girded up his loins, and went out of his house and wandered about in the streets of the city. When the people saw him in this condition, they brought him to the Governor who asked him, “What had happened to you?" The saint replied saying "I have been born Christian, and I shall die Christian, and I do not know except this." The Governor threatened him, scourged him severely then imprisoned him. When he could not change his conviction, he sent him to the Khalifa of Egypt who ordered to burn him. They casted him into the fire and burnt him outside the city thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فتأثر من رسالتها وبكى وقام ورشم على وجهه علامة الصليب وشد على وسطه بزنار وقام ومشى فى شوارع المدينة. فلما رآه الناس هكذا أمسكوه وسلموه للوالى فسأله عن ذلك فأجاب القديس قائلاً: " إنى ولدت مسيحيا ً وأموت مسيحياً ولا أعرف غير هذا". فضربه الوالى كثيراً ثم حبسه ولما لم يقدر عليه أمر بحرقه فحرقوه خارج المدينه ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته. فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Bishop St. Theodotus, the Confessor.</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس ثاؤدوطس الأسقف المعترف</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also St. Theodotus the confessor, bishop of the city of Corinth, on the island of Cyprus, departed. He confessed the Lord Christ before Julius, the Governor of that city during the days of Emperor Diocletian. He demanded the saint to deny his faith in the Lord Christ and to raise incense to the idols. When he refused he ordered to painfully scourge him with whips made of buffalo’s hide, and combed his body with iron combs, tearing up his flesh, then imprisoned him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً تنيح القديس ثاؤدوطس الأسقف المعترف. كان هذا القديس أسقفا ً على مدينه كورنثوس التى فى جزيرة قبرص. أعترف بالسيد المسيح أمام الوالى يوليوس أيام الإمبراطور دقلديانوس وطلب منه الوالى أن ينكر إيمانه بالسيد المسيح ويقدم البخور للأصنام فرفض فأمر بتعذيبه بالجلد وتمشيط جسده بأمشاط حديدية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He remained in prison until the reign of Emperor Constantine, who released him among all those who were imprisoned for the sake of faith. St. Theodotus returned to his Episcopal Seat, and continued to tend to his flock, that the Lord Christ entrusted him with. When he finished his good endeavor, he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم وضعوه فى السجن إلى أن تملك الإمبراطور قسطنطين البار فأطلقه مع جملة القديسين المحبوسين وعاد إلى كرسيه ودوام على رعاية شعبه الذى أؤتمن عليه من قِبل السيد المسيح وبعد أن أكمل جهاده الحسن تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.7">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Seventh day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the seventh day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Sts. Philemon and Apollonius</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسين فليمون وأبلانيوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 21 of the martyrs (305 A.D.) Sts. Philemon and Apollonius were martyred. Philemon was the singer, and Apollonius was the flute-player in the service of Arianus the persecuting governor of Ansena (Antinoe). They were very close friends and they desired to receive the crown of martyrdom. One day, Philemon went to the Governor and confessed the Lord Christ before him, so he ordered to shoot him with arrows, thus he received the crown of martyrdom. Afterwards, Apollonius came before the Governor and he also confessed the Lord Christ. Arianus became angry and ordered to shoot him also with arrows.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 21 للشهداء (305م) إستشهد القديسان فليمون وأبلانيوس. كان القديس فليمون مُغنيا ً لأريانوس والى أنصنا وكان القديس أبلانيوس مُزمرا ً للوالى أيضا ً. وكانت بينهما صداقة فاشتهى الاثنان أن ينالا إكليل الشهادة. فدخل فليمون يوماً على الوالى أريانوس وأعترف أمامه بالسيد المسيح فأمر بأن يُضرب بالسهام فنال إكليل الشهادة. ثم دخل أبلانيوس بعد ذلك وأعترف هو أيضاً بالسيد المسيح فغضب الوالى جداً وأمر أن يُضرب أيضاً بالسهام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               While they were shooting him, one of the arrows glanced back and struck the Governor's eye and that happened before some Christians. One of them told the governor, “If you take from his blood and applied it to your eye, you would regain your sight.” At the beginning he did not believe but because of the severe pain and the loss of his eye, he took some of the blood of St. Apollonius and smeared his eye. He immediately regained his sight, he regretted much all what he had done in tormenting the saints, and he believed in the Lord Christ. Apollonius also completed his strife and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث أثناء ذلك أن رجع السهم إلى ناحية الوالى فأصاب عينه وكان ذلك أمام بعض المسيحيين. فقال أحدهم للوالى: "لو أخذت من دمه ووضعت على عينيك لأبصرت" فلم يصدقه فى أول الأمر لكنه من شدة الألم وضياع عينه أخذ جزءا ًمن دم الشهيد أبلانيوس ووضعه على عينيه فأبصر للوقت وندم كثيرا ً على ما فرط منه فى تعذيب القديسين وآمن بالسيد المسيح. أما القديسان فليمون وأبلانيوس فأكملا جهادهما ونالا اكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهما فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Mary the Israelite</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسة مريم الإسرائيلية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also St. Mary the Israelite was martyred. This saint did not know anything about the Lord Christ and she lived a sinful life. The Lord sent to her a holy man who preached her, and revealed to her the way of salvation and the faith of the Lord Christ. He told her that the soul has to give an answer about all her deeds on judgment day, according to what is mentioned in the Old Testament.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضاً أستشهدت القديسة مريم الإسرائيلية. لم تكن هذه القديسة تعرف شيئا ً عن السيد المسيح وكانت تعيش فى سيرة رديئة في الخطية. فأرسل الرب لها قديسا ً وعظها وعرفها طريق الخلاص والإيمان بالسيد المسيح وأن النفس لابد أن تعطى جوابا ً عن جميع أعمالها يوم الدينونة. مُستندا ًعلى ما جاء فى العهد القديم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When she heard his sayings, she was fearful and trembled. The grace moved her heart and she asked him saying, "Would God accept my repentance, and pardon me for my sins? He replied, "If you believed that the Lord Christ had come to the world for the salvation of mankind, was crucified on our behalf, died and rose from the dead on the third day.” She repented, believed and was baptized with the holy baptism.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما سمعت هذا الكلام خافت وإرتعدت وعملت النعمة فى قلبها وسألته قائلة: " هل يقبل الله توبتى ويسامحنى على أخطائى؟". فأجابها القديس: نعم بشرط الإيمان بالسيد المسيح أنه جاء إلى العالم لخلاص البشر وصُلب من أجلنا ومات وقام فى اليوم الثالث. فتابت وآمنت ثم أعتمدت بالمعمودية المقدسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Governor knew about her, he brought her before him. She confessed her faith in the Lord Christ and she was steadfast in her belief. He tried to change her resolve by promises and threats but she refused his words. He ordered to torture her and finally he behead her with the sword thus she received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما بلغ خبرها إلى الوالى أحضرها أمامه فاعترفت بالسيد المسيح وتمسكت بإيمانها. فحاول أن يثنيها سواء بالوعد أو بالوعيد فلم تقبل منه كلامه. فأمر بتعذيبها. وأخيرا ًقطع رأسها بحد السيف ونالت إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة  صلواتها فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.8">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eighth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eighth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Matthias, the apostle</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس متياس الرسول</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 68 A.D. St. Matthias, the apostle was martyred. He was born in the region of Galilee, followed the apostles and was chosen in place of Judas Iscariot during the apostolic assembly in the upper room of Zion. Our teacher St. Peter the apostle stood up in the midst of the disciples and said, "Men and brethren, this Scripture had to be fulfilled, which the Holy Spirit spoke before by the mouth of David concerning Judas, who became a guide to those who arrested Jesus; for he was numbered with us and obtained a part in this ministry. Now this man purchased a field with the wages of iniquity; and falling headlong, he burst open in the middle and all his entrails gushed out. And it became known to all those dwelling in Jerusalem; so that field is called in their own language, Akel Dama, that is, Field of Blood. For it is written in the book of Psalms: 'Let his habitation be desolate, and let no one live in it'; and, 'Let another take his office.' "Therefore, of these men who have accompanied us all the time that the Lord Jesus went in and out among us, beginning from the baptism of John to that day when He was taken up from us, one of these must become a witness with us of His resurrection."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 68م أستشهد القديس متياس الرسول. ولد هذا القديس بأقليم الجليل وكان من المرافقين للرسل وهو الذى أختير بدلا ًمن يهوذا الإسخريوطى فى إجتماع علية صهيون. وذلك عندما قال معلمنا بطرس الرسول: "أيها الرجال الإخوة كان ينبغى أن يتم هذا المكتوب فى سفر المزامير لتصر داره خراباً ولا يكن فيها ساكن وليأخذ وظيفته آخر. فينبغى أن الرجال الذين أجتمعوا معنا فى الزمان الذى فيه دخل إلينا الرب يسوع وخرج منذ معمودية يوحنا إلى اليوم الذى ارتفع فيه عنا يصير واحد منهم شاهداً بقيامته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               And they proposed two: Joseph called Barsabas, who was surnamed Justus, and Matthias. And they prayed and said, "You, O Lord, who know the hearts of all, show which of these two You have chosen to take part in this ministry and apostleship from which Judas by transgression fell, that he might go to his own place." And they cast their lots, and the lot fell on Matthias. And he was numbered with the eleven apostles. (Acts 1:15-26)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فأقاموا اثنين يوسف الذى يدعى برسابا الملقب يوستس (معناه عادل) ومتياس وصلوا قائلين : "أيها الرب العارف قلوب الجميع عين أنت من هذين الاثنين أيا اخترته ليأخذ قرعة هذه الخدمة الرسولية التى تعداها يهوذا ليذهب إلى مكانه". ثم ألقوا قرعتهم فوقعت القرعة على متياس فحسب مع الأحد عشر رسولاً."(أعمال ١: ١٦-٢٦).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Afterwards St. Matthias was filled with the Holy Spirit that descended upon the apostles on the day of Pentecost. He preached the Gospel in Judea, Samaria, and Cappadocia and it was also said that he went to the country of cannibals. He went on preaching the Gospel until he reached the city of Bartus where he preached the Gospel, but they seized him for its people did not accept the Word and imprisoned him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد هذا امتلأ متياس من الروح القدس الذى حل على الرسل فى يوم الخمسين. وبشر فى اليهودية والسامرية وكبادوكية كما قيل انه ذهب لمدينة آكلى لحوم البشر وذهب ليكرز بالإنجيل حتى وصل إلى مدينة برطس ونادى فيها ببشارة الإنجيل فقُبض عليه أهلها إذ لم يقبلوا الكلمة وأودعوه السجن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Matthias prayed interceding to the Virgin St. Mary who came on a cloud. When she entered the city all the iron therein melted (as wax). She went to the prison, released St. Matthias the apostle and all those who were imprisoned with him for the sake of faith. When the governor of the city heard about what had happened, he requested to see the Virgin St. Mary. She came to him along with St. Matthias the apostle and she healed his son who was possessed. The governor and all the people of the city believed. St. Mary prayed and all the iron changed back to its former state and she went up on a luminous cloud. St. Matthias baptized the people of the city and tarried there teaching and confirming them in the faith. He ordained priests for them and after he was confident of their faith, he left them to resume his evangelism.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فصلى القديس متياس متشفعا ً بالقديسة العذراء مريم فأتت على سحابة وبمجرد دخولها المدينه تحول كل مافيها من حديد إلى ماء فتوجهت إلى السجن وأخرجت متياس الرسول والمسجونين معه من أجل الإيمان ولما سمع والى المدينة بما حدث طلب أن يرى العذراء القديسة مريم فأتت إليه هى والقديس متياس الرسول وأبرأت إبنه الذى كان مجنوناً. فآمن هو وكل أهل المدينة. وصلت القديسة العذراء فأعيد الحديد إلى طبعه الأول وارتفعت القديسة العذراء مريم على سحابة نورانية أما القديس متياس الرسول فعمد جميع أهل المدينة ومكث عندهم يعلمهم ثم رسم لهم كهنة وبعد أن اطمأن عليهم تركهم ومضى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Matthias went to the city of Damascus and preached there in the Name of the Lord Christ. The people of the city became angry, seized and tormented him. They laid him upon an iron bed, they lighted a fire under it which did not harm him but his face was shining like the sun. They marveled exceedingly and they all believed in the Lord Christ at the hands of this saint who baptized, and ordained priests for them. He tarried many days with them confirming them in the faith. When he returned to Jerusalem the Jews stoned him so he was martyred and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم أنطلق إلى دمشق ونادى فيها بالسيد المسيح فغضب أهل المدينة وقبضوا عليه وعذبوه ووضعوه على سرير حديد وأوقدوا النار تحته فلم تؤذه بل كان وجهه يتلألأ بالنور كالشمس. فتعجبوا من ذلك وآمنوا بالرب يسوع على يدى هذا القديس فعمدهم ورسم لهم كهنة وأقام عندهم أياما ً كثيرة. ولما رجع القديس إلى أورشليم رجمه اليهود بالحجارة فمات ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Julian, the Eleventh Pope of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس البابا يوليانوس البطريرك الحادى عشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 188 A.D. the Holy Father Pope Julian, the Eleventh Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This father was a student in the theological school of Alexandria which was established by St. Mark and was a disciple of St. Pantaenus. He excelled and surpassed many in knowledge, righteousness, and purity. He was ordained a priest in the city of Alexandria then Patriarch on the 9th of Paremhotep in the year 178 A.D.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 188م تنيح الأب المغبوط القديس البابا الأنبا يوليانوس البطريرك الحادى عشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. وقد تتلمذ هذا الأب فى المدرسة الإكليريكية التى أنشاها القديس مرقس وكان تلميذاً للقديس بنتينوس وقد نبغ روحيا ً وعلميا ً فرسم قسا ً بمدينة الإسكندرية ثم بطريركا ً فى 9 برمهات سنة 178م.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After his enthronement he gave a great attention to the spiritual growth of his flock. That incited the pagans not to allow him to leave the city of Alexandria, so he used to leave the city in secret to ordain priests everywhere and visit his flock.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Before his departure the angel of the Lord announced to him that the one who will bring him a cluster of grapes, is the one to succeed him on the Patriarchal Throne. One day, while Demetrius the vine dresser, who was a lay person, was trimming his vine, he found a cluster of grapes which was not in season. He decided to present it to the Patriarch Abba Julian as a gift. While the bishops and the lay leaders were gathered around the Pope, he foretold them about who would be on the throne after him. He told them that a person carrying a cluster of grapes would be coming to present it to him; they all marveled and were amazed of what the pope had told them. While they were perplexed Demetrius came carrying the cluster of grapes in his hand and presented it to the pope. Pope Julian rejoiced for the fulfillment of his vision and everyone around him was also pleased. He commanded them to enthrone Demetrius Patriarch after him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد رأى البابا رؤيا قبل نياحته بأن ظهر له ملاك الرب وقال " إن من يأتيك بعنقود عنب هو الذى سيكون بعدك على الكرسى المرقسى". ولم يكن وقتها أوان العنب وحدث فعلا ً أن رجلا ًعاميا ً يدعى ديمتريوس كان كراما ً وبينما هو يصلح كرمه عثر به على عنقود عنب فى غير أوانه فقرر أن يهديه للبابا البطريرك. وبينما كان مجتمعاً حول البابا كبار الشعب وعظماؤه بدأ يخبرهم بمن سيكون على الكرسى من بعده فأخبرهم بما سيحدث من حضور الشخص الذى يحمل عنقود عنب فتحيروا وتعجبوا من كلام البابا هذا وبينما هم متحيرون دخل ديمتريوس وعنقود العنب فى يده وقدمه إلى البابا البطريرك ففرح البابا بتحقيق الرؤيا وفرحوا هم أيضا ً ونفذوا وصية البابا فيما بعد واختاروا ديمتريوس بطريركا من بعده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He occupied the apostolic throne for ten years and after he finished his good endeavor, departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد قضى البابا يوليانوس على الكرسى المرقسى مدة عشرة سنوات أعتنى فيها بشعبه عناية روحية حتى انه من عظم عنايته أن الوثنيين كانوا لا يسمحون له بمغادرة الإسكندرية  فكان يخرج منها سراً ويذهب إلى كل مكان ويرسم كهنة للشعب ويفتقدهم وبعد ذلك أتم جهاده الحسن وتنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Arianus, the Governor of Ansena</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس أريانوس والى أنصنا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 21 of the martyrs (305 A.D.) St. Arianus, governor of Ansena, was martyred. He was a cruel and unjust governor who persecuted Christianity and slew the Christians.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 21 للشهداء (305 م) أستشهد القديس أريانوس والى أنصنا ( هى أنتينوبوليس مركز الولاية على الصعيد الأعلى حاليا ً هى بلده الشيخ عبادة نسبة إلى الأنبا أباديوس أسقف أنصنا الشهيد وموجودة بشرقى ملوى محافظة المنيا). كان والياً قاسياً وحاكما ً ظالما ًإضطهد المسيحية وقتل المسيحيين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               It happened when he ordered to shoot St. Apollonius with arrows, one of the arrows glanced back and struck his eye and destroyed it. That happened before some Christians, and one of them told him, “If you take from his blood and applied it to your eye, you would regain your sight.” At the beginning he did not believe but because of the severe pain and the loss of his eye, he took some of the blood of St. Apollonius and smeared it on his eye. He immediately regained his sight, he believed in the Lord Christ, and regretted much all what he had done in tormenting the saints. Then he rose up, destroyed his idols, and he refrained from torturing any of the believers.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث انه لما أمر بطعن القديس أبلانيوس بالسهام أرتد أحد السهام إلى عينه فقال له أحد المسيحيين: " لو أخذت من دمه ووضعت على عينيك لأبصرت " فأخذ من دمه ووضعه على عينه فأبصر للوقت فآمن بالسيد المسيح. وندم كثيرا ً على ما فرط منه فى تعذيب القديسين. ثم قام وكسر أصنامه ولم يعد يعذب أحداً من المؤمنين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Diocletian heard the report of Arianus, he brought him, and asked him why he had forsaken the worship of his idols. Arianus began to tell him about the signs and wonders which God was working by the hands of the holy martyrs, and how, in spite of the tortures which he had inflicted upon them, and the cutting of their bodies, they rose up again whole. The Emperor became furious because of what he said and ordered to severely torment him, and to cast him into a pit and to cover it until he dies, however the Lord saved him. Diocletian again ordered to place him into a hair sack, and to cast him into the sea, so he delivered his soul and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما اتصل خبره بالملك دقلديانوس أستحضره وأستعلم منه عن السبب الذى رده عن عبادة آلهته. فبدأ القديس بقص عليه الآيات والعجائب التى أجراها الله على أيدى قديسيه وأنهم فى حال تعذيبهم وتقطيع أجسادهم كانوا يعودون أصحاء فاغتاظ الملك من هذا القول وأمر أن يعذب عذابا ً شديدا ً وأن يطرح فى جب ويغطى عليه حتى يموت فأنقذه الرب. وأمر أيضاً بإلقائه فى البحر ففاضت روحه ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Saint had told his kinsfolk when he bid them farewell that the Lord had told him in a vision of the night that He would take care of his body, return it to his home-town, and they could find it on the shore of Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان القديس عندما ودع أهله أخبرهم بأن الرب قد أعلمه فى رؤيا الليل انه سيهتم بجسده ويعيده إلى بلده وانهم سيجدونه على ساحل الإسكندرية .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Lord ordered a dolphin to carry the body of the saint, bring and caste it on the shore of Alexandria. His men took his body, brought it to Ansena, and placed it with the bodies of the Saints Philemon and Apollonius. Thus, he finished his good fight and received the heavenly crown.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد حدث أن أمر الرب درفيلا ً لحمله إلى الإسكندرية وطرحه على البر. فأخذه غلمانه وأتوا به إلى أنصنا ووضعوه مع أجساد القديسين فليمون وأبلانيوس وهكذا أكمل جهاده ونال الإكليل السماوى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.9">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Ninth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the ninth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Konan, the Confessor</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس كونن المعترف</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 50 A.D. St. Konan departed. This Saint was from a city called Antanyos in Syria to heathen parents who worshipped the stars. When he grew, he heard the preaching of the Apostles so he believed and was baptized by their hands. Many virtues as purity, chastity, piety, and mercy were manifested in his life. His parents wished for him to wed, but he refused. They forced him to marry, but he agreed with his wife to keep their virginity and lived as such for a period of time. God granted him the gift of performing miracles and casting out evil spirits. He attracted his parents, his wife and her parents to the faith of the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 50 م تنيح القديس المجاهد كونن. ولد هذا البار فى ضيعة أنطانيوس من بلاد سوريا من أبوين وثنيين يعبدان الكواكب ولما كبر سمع ببشارة الآباء الرسل فآمن واعتمد على أيديهم وظهرت منه فضائل كثيرة كالعفة والطهارة والرحمة.  ولما أراد والداه أن يزوجاه رفض ولكنهما أرغماه على ذلك فأتفق مع زوجته على حفظ البتولية وعاشا على هذه الحالة مدة من الزمن. وقد منحه الله موهبة عمل المعجزات وإخراج الشياطين فاجتذب أبويه وزوجته أيضاً ووالديها إلى الإيمان بالسيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint preached the Gospel and many of the heathens believed at his hands. One day, one of the unbelievers went to a pagan temple to offer a sacrifice to the idols. When St. Konan knew this, he entered the temple and entreated God to uncover the truth to this man. A voice came out of one of the idols declaring that the idol was the work of Satan and not a god. All the people who were present cried out saying: "One is the God of St. Konan," and they believed in the Lord Christ and were baptized.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بشر هذا القديس بالإنجيل فآمن على يديه كثيرون من الوثنيين. وذات مرة دخل أحد الوثنيين ليذبح للشيطان فى معبد وثنى فعلم به هذا القديس فإنتهر الشيطان فصرخ وأعترف أمام كل الناس انه شيطان وليس إلهاً ، فصرخ الحاضرون قائلين : واحد هو إله القديس كونن ثم آمنوا جميعاً بالسيد المسيح وأعتمدوا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the deputy of Emperor Claudius Caesar, heard about the account of this saint, he brought him, and proposed to the saint to worship the idols but he refused and confessed his faith in the Lord Christ. He commanded to bind him and be severely beaten. The people of the city who were present jumped over the soldiers, freed the saint from their hands, brought him to his house, and took care of his wounds until he recovered. When he finished his good strife, he departed in peace. The believers made his house a church and laid his body in it, from which many signs and wonders were manifested.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               سمع نائب الإمبراطور كلوديوس قيصر (ولد فى ليون سنة 10 ق. م. وأقامه الجنود ملكا ً بعد قتل غايوس عمه سنة 41 م ومات فى سنة 54 م) بخبر هذا القديس فاستحضره وعرض عليه عبادة الأوثان فرفض وأقر بإيمانه بالسيد المسيح. فأمر بربطه وضربه ضربا ً شديدا ً فوثب الشعب الحاضر على الجند وخلصوا القديس من أيديهم وأتوا به إلى بيته وضمدوا جراحه حتى شفى ولما أكمل جهاده الصالح تنيح بسلام. فجعل المسيحيون داره كنيسة ووضعوا جسده فيها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Sts. Andrianus, Martha his wife, Eusebius, Armanius, and Forty Martyrs</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسين أندريانوس ومرثا زوجته وأوسابيوس وأرما وأربعين شهيداً</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the martyrdom of Sts. Andrianus, Martha his wife, Eusebius, Armanius, and Forty Martyrs. They were natives of Rome. They suffered many tortures for they refused to worship gods made of gold and silver and they shouted saying; “We worship one God, the creator of heaven and earth our king Jesus Christ.” They were all beheaded by the sword and they received the crows of martyrdom...            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى مثل هذا اليوم استشهد القديسون أندريانوس ومرثا زوجته وأوسابيوس وأرما وأربعون شهيدا ً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة  صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.10">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Tenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم العاشر من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the tenth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم العاشر من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">Commemoration of the Appearance of the Honorable Cross</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار ظهور الصليب المجيد</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The church celebrates today the appearance of the honorable Cross of Our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. When the righteous Empress St. Helen, the mother of Constantine the great, wished to find the honorable Cross, she went to Jerusalem. She asked about the place of the Cross, a Jewish elder called Judas told her the place where she might find the Cross. She ordered the soldiers to clear out the site of Golgotha where they found three crosses. However, they did not know the cross of the Savior. It happened that a funeral procession was passing by, they laid upon him one of the crosses and then the other but he did not rise up however when they laid the third cross upon him he rose up immediately. They realized that this was the Cross of the Lord. The Empress and all the believers kneeled down before the honorable cross. She sent a piece of it with the nails to her son Constantine. She commanded the building of the church of Resurrection which was consecrated by the fathers the patriarchs and placed the honorable cross therein.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تعيد الكنيسة اليوم بتذكار ظهور الصليب المجيد. وذلك لما أرادت الملكة البارة هيلانة والدة الإمبراطور قسطنطين الكبير أن تعثر على الصليب المجيد مضت إلى أورشليم وتقصت عن مكان الصليب فعرفها به شيخ من اليهود أسمه يهوذا. فأمرت الجنود فى الحال بتنظيف الجلجثه حتى ظهرت ثلاثة صلبان. ولما أرادوا أن يتعرفوا على صليب المخلص تصادف مرور جنازة ميت فوضعوا الصليب الأول والثانى على النعش فلم يقم الميت ثم وضعوا عليه الصليب الثالث فقام لوقته فسجدت الملكة وكل الحاضرين للصليب المجيد وأرسلت جزءا ً منه والمسامير إلى ابنها الإمبراطور وأمرت ببناء كنيسة القيامة وكرسها الآباء البطاركة ووضعت فيها الصليب المجيد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The wood of the holy cross remained in the church of Resurrection in Jerusalem until the Persians invaded the holy land. Khosrau II, the Persian king, took possession in the year 614 A.D. of the golden box that had in it the holy cross. He saw a great light shinning from it, he thrust his hand to hold the wood of the cross, but a fire went forth from it which burned his fingers. The Christians told him that this is the Holy Cross and no one was able to touch it except a Christian. He deceived the two deacons who were standing to guard it and gave them much money to carry the cross and go with him to his country. There in the garden of his palace, the Persian king ordered the two deacons to dig a hole and to put the box in it and buried it and then he killed them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وظلت خشبة الصليب المقدس موجودة فى كنيسة القيامة بأورشليم إلى أن غزا الفرس الأراضى المقدسة وإستولى خسرو الثانى ملك الفرس سنة 614 م على التابوت الفضى الذى يحوى الصليب المقدس. وكان يسطع منه ضوء ساطع فمد يده ليمسك خشبة الصليب فخرجت منها نار وأحرقت أصابعه. فأعلمه المسيحيون أن هذا هو الصليب المقدس ولا يستطيع أن يمسه إلا المسيحى فأحضر شماسين وأجزل لهما العطاء ليحملا الصليب يذهبا به معه إلى بلاده. وهناك فى حديقه قصره أمر الشماسين فحفرا حفرة ودفنا التابوت فيها ثم قتلهما.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               It happened that a young girl from the daughters of the priests was captured by the king and placed her in his house. She was looking from the window at this particular moment and saw what had happened.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               واتفق أن صبية من بنات الكهنة كان قد سباها ووضعها فى منزله فتطلعت فى تلك اللحظة من شباك وأبصرت ما حدث.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Later on Emperor Heraclius heard that, he went with his army to Persia, in the year 629 A.D. and during the papacy of Pope Benjamin I (38th Patriarch of Alexandria) fought with the Persians and slew many of them. He traveled about this country searching for the wood of the honorable cross but he could not find it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بعد ذلك قام هرقل الإمبراطور وتوجه بجيشه إلى بلاد الفرس سنة 629 م فى زمن بطريركية البابا بنيامين الأول (38 ) وتحارب معهم وقتل منهم عددا ً كبيرا ً ثم طاف أكثر البلاد يبحث عن خشبة الصليب المجيد فلم يجدها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This young girl took the chance and went to Emperor Heraclius and told him of what she saw. He went with the bishops, priests and the soldiers to the place. They dug there and found the box that contained the honorable cross. They all rejoiced and he took it back to Constantinople. In the year 629 A.D. Emperor Heraclius moved the Holy Cross from Constantinople to Jerusalem.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وإنتهزت الصبية الفرصة وأعلمت الملك هرقل بما رأته فأسرع بجنوده ومعهم الأساقفة والكهنة وبإرشاد الصبية وجد الصليب المجيد ففرح جدا ً وأعاده إلى القسطنطينية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessings of the honorable Cross be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة الصليب المجيد فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.11">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eleventh Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الحادى عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eleventh day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الحادى عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Basil (Basilius) the Bishop</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس باسيليوس أسقف أورشليم</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day St. Basil (Basilius) the bishop was martyred. This Holy Father became well known for his godly and saintly life, therefore Abba Armoun, Patriarch of Jerusalem, ordained him among others as bishops without stated Sees in the year 298 A.D. He sent them to preach the Kingdom of Heaven to the countries that had not received the faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               1 – فى مثل هذا اليوم استشهد القديس باسيليوس أسقف أورشليم. أُشتهر هذا القديس بحياة التقوى والقداسة فرسمه القديس هرمون بطريرك أورشليم أسقفاً عاماً سنة 298م مع أساقفة آخرين ليكرزوا ببشارة الملكوت فى البلاد التى لم يصلها الإيمان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Saint preached in many cities and when he entered the city of Sharsunah, in Syria, he preached the Christian faith, some of its people believed at his hands but the others became angry. They rose up against the saint and drove him out. He went outside the city and dwelt in a cave where he persevered in perpetual prayers and supplications to God that He enlighten their eyes and believe in the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كرز هذا القديس فى بلاد كثيرة ولما دخل مدينة شرصونة ببلاد الشام ونادى فيها بالإيمان المسيحي فآمن على يديه بعض من أهلها وغضب البعض الآخر فثاروا ضده وطردوه. فخرج إلى خارج المدينة مداوما ً على الصلاة إلى الله لكى ينير بصيرتهم ويؤمنوا بالسيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               With God’s providence, the son of the Governor of that city died, he was his only child, and he grieved on him exceedingly. On the day that the Governor had buried his son, he saw him in a vision at night, standing before him saying: "Call St. Basilius and ask him to pray to the Lord Christ on my behalf for I am in a great darkness." When the Governor woke up from his sleep, he took the nobles of the city, and went to the cave of St. Basil. He asked him to enter the city to pray for his son. The Saint agreed, went with them and he prayed to God fervently and the son rose up alive with the power of God.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبسماح من الله مات أبن والى المدينة وكان وحيداً له فحزن عليه كثيراً. وحدث فى الليلة التى دُفن فيها أن رأى الوالى فى رؤيا أبنه واقفاً وهو يقول: "إستدع القديس باسيلاوس واسأله أن يصلى إلى السيد المسيح من أجلى فإنى فى ظلمة عظيمة". فانتبه الوالى من نومه وأخذ عظماء المدينة وأتى إلى مغارة القديس وطلب منه أن يدخل المدينة ليصلى من أجل إبنه. فذهب معهم وصلى صلاة قوية فقام الولد حياً بقوة الله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Governor and all those with him, believed and the saint baptized them. The Jews of the city saw that, became envious of the Saint. They were joined by a group of men who were not Christians, rose up against the Saint, beat him and dragged him in the streets of the city until he delivered up his pure spirit and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فآمن الوالى وكل من معه واعتمدوا على يد القديس. ولما رأى اليهود ذلك حسدوا القديس مع جماعة من غير المسيحيين ووثبوا على القديس وضربوه وجروه فى المدينة حتى فاضت روحه الطاهرة ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.12">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twelfth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثانى عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twelfth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثانى عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Honorable Archangel Michael</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار رئيس الملائكة الطاهر ميخائيل</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the church celebrates the monthly commemoration of the pure Archangel Michael, who is standing before the Lord at all times interceding for mankind.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تعيد الكنيسة اليوم بالتذكار الشهرى لرئيس الملائكة الطاهر ميخائيل القائم أمام الرب فى كل حين يشفع فى جنس البشر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his holy intercession be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة شفاعته المقدسة فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The revealing of the virginity of St. Demetrius, 12th Pope of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">ظهور بتولية البابا ديمتريوس الكرام البطريرك الثانى عشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the church celebrates the commemoration of revealing the virginity of Pope Demetrius, the vine dresser, 12th Patriarch of Alexandria. He was married but he lived with his wife in complete and pure celibate life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار ظهور بتولية البابا ديمتريوس الكرام البطريرك الثانى عشر من بطاركة الكرسى المرقسى. كان هذا القديس يعمل كراماً وكان متزوجاً ولكنه يحيا مع زوجته فى حياة البتولية الكاملة بطهارة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The angel of the Lord shadowed them during their sleep. He was enthroned on the apostolic throne by a divine command to the saintly Pope Julian. Because some people had caused confusion and disturbance, the angel of God appeared to him and commanded him to reveal his relation with his wife and told him, "It is not proper that you save yourself alone and let others be perished because of you. You should fight for the salvation of your people also."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان ملاك الرب يظللهما أثناء النوم فلما ارتقى السدة المرقسية بأمر إلهى للبابا القديس يوليانوس حدثت بلبلة من بعض الناس فظهر له ملاك الرب وأمره أن يظهر أمره مع زوجته وقال له "ليس الواجب أن تخلص نفسك فقط وتدع غيرك يهلك بسببك بل يجب عليك أن تجتهد فى خلاص شعبك أيضاً".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the following Sunday, after he had finished celebrating the Divine Liturgy, he asked the people not to leave the church. He brought his wife from among the women and brought flamed charcoal. He prayed and walked on the blazing charcoal, then he took two pieces of the charcoal, put one in his shawl and the other piece he put it in his wife's shawl. He prayed again for a long time and both shawls did not burn. The congregation marveled and asked him to tell them why he did that. He told them of his account with his wife, and how their fathers married them against their will, and they have lived together as a brother and sister for 48 years since they were married, and how the angel of the Lord each night covered them with his wings. Moreover, no one knew that before now until the angel of the Lord ordered me to reveal this secret so no one of you stumbles because of me.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما كان يوم الأحد صلى القداس وبعد الصلاة أمر الشعب بعدم الانصراف وأحضروا له نارا ً فطلب زوجته من بين النساء وصلى ووقف على النار بقدميه ثم أخذ منها جمرتين ووضع أحدهما فى إزاره والأخرى فى إزار زوجته وظل وقتا ً طويلاً وهو يصلى ولم يحترق شئ من الإزارين فتعجب الشعب وسألوه عن السبب الذى دفعه لهذا العمل فأعلمهم بخبره مع زوجته وأن أبويهما زوجاهما بغير إرادتيهما وأن لهما ثمان وأربعين سنة منذ زواجهما وهما يعيشان عيشة الأخوين يظللهما ملاك الرب بجناحيه وان أحداً لم يعرف ذلك قبل الآن إلى أن أمرنى ملاك الرب باظهار ذلك لئلا يعُثر أحدكم بسببى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The congregation praised God, asked the Saint to pardon them for their misconception and for what they had done or said and to forgive them. He accepted their apology and blessed them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فسبح الشعب الله طالبين من القديس أن يغفر لهم سوء ظنهم فقبل اعتذارهم وباركهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Malachi (Malachious) of Palestine</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس ملاخى بأرض فلسطين</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the righteous St. Malachi (Malachious) was martyred in the land of Palestine.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى مثل هذا اليوم أيضا ً تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار أستشهاد القديس ملاخى بأرض فلسطين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Glathinos in Damascus</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also marks the martyrdom of St. Glathinos (Glazinos). This Saint was from the city of Marmin, nearby Damascus. He was heathen and was fond of the art of acting.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day Glathinos and his fellow actors started to perform the ritual of Christian baptism with mockery and derision. Then they dipped Glathinos in the water, took him out and they put on him a white apparel.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Glathinos after he had come out of the water, he refused to go on acting. He declared that he preferred to die Christian on the Name of the Lord Christ. He also added; "While you were mocking the baptism, I have witnessed a wondrous miracle." They became extremely furious, seized the Saint, and stoned him until he delivered up his soul and received the crown of martyrdom. His family and many Christians came, took his body, and buried him with great honor. They built a church after his name in that place.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.13">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Thirteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the thirteenth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the Forty Martyrs of Sebaste</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد الأربعين شهيدا ً بسبسطية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 36 of the martyrs (320 A.D.) the saintly forty martyrs, of the city of Sebaste in Syria, were martyred. They were high ranking officers in a Roman legion under the command of Lecius who was heathen. They refused to participate in offering sacrifices to the idols. The commander summoned them, and they confessed their faith in the Lord Christ before him. He threatened to strip them off their military ranks. They replied saying; “It is better for us to lose our military positions than to lose our God Jesus Christ.” He imprisoned them and they spent all night praying and the angel of the Lord appeared to strengthen and encourage them to steadfast till the end to receive the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 36 للشهداء (320م) استشهد القديسون الأبرار الأربعين شهيدا ً بمدينة سبسطية ببلاد سوريا. كانوا قوادا ً فى فرقة رومانية تحت قيادة ليسياس الوثنى وامتنعوا عن الاشتراك فى تقديم ذبائح للأوثان. فاستدعاهم الوالى فاعترفوا أمامه بالسيد المسيح. فهددهم بتجريدهم من مناطق الجندية فأجابوا " خير لنا أن نخسر مناطق جنديتنا ولانخسر يسوع المسيح إلهنا ". فأرسلهم إلى السجن حيث قضوا الليل كله فى الصلاة وظهر لهم ملاك الرب يشجعهم ويقويهم على الثبات حتى النهاية لنيل أكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Later on, he commanded his men to stone them however the stones glanced back upon those who were stoning them. Then he ordered to throw them in a nearby lake, which was icy. Their organs were severed because of the excessive cold. One of them, whose faith was weakened, went out of the icy water and entered the hot water bath house nearby the lake. The heat in the bath house melted the ice that was on him however he died quickly.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بعد ذلك أستحضرهم الوالى وأمر برجمهم بالحجاره فكانت الحجارة ترتد على الضاربين.  وكان بالقرب منهم بحيرة ماء متجمدة فأمر بطرحهم فيها فتقطعت أعضاؤهم من شدة البرد. وكان بجوار البركة حمام ماء ساخن فضعف إيمان أحدهم وصعد إلى هذا الحمام فانحلت أعصابه ومات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One of the guards saw angels descending from heaven and in their hands crowns. They placed them over the heads of the thirty nine martyrs and remained one crown in the hand of the angel. The grace of God moved the heart of the guard who went down into the lake shouting "I am Christian...I am Christian." He received the crown that was in the hand of the angel and was counted among the martyrs.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أما الباقون فرأى أحد الحراس ملائكة نزلوا من السماء وبأياديهم أكاليل ووضعوها على رؤوسهم وبقى إكليل بيد الملاك فحركت نعمة  الله قلب الحارس ونزل إلى البركة وهو يصيح بصوت عالي "أنا مسيحى" فنال الإكليل الذى كان معلقا ً بيد الملاك وأنضموا جميعهم إلى صفوف الشهداء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The ruler ordered to carry their bodies and throw them into the sea. On the third day the holy martyrs appeared to the Bishop of Sebaste in a vision and told him; "Go to the sea and take our bodies." He went with the priests, deacons and the people to the sea and found the bodies. They carried them with great honor and placed them in a special place. Many signs and wonders were manifested from their bodies and their account became well known in all the countries.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . فأمر الوالى أن يحملوا أجسادهم ويطرحوها فى البحر وفى اليوم الثالث ظهروا لأسقف سبسطية وقالوا له هلم إلى البحر وخذ أجسادنا. فقام وأخذ الكهنة فوجد الأجساد فحملها باحترام ووضعها فى مكان خاص. وخرجت من هذه الأجساد قوات وآيات كثيرة فشاع ذكرهم فى كل الأقطار.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Dionysius, 14th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا ديونسيوس البطريرك الرابع عشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 264 A.D., the Holy Father Pope Dionysius, 14th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This father was born in Alexandria in the later part of the second century. His parents worshipped the stars (Sabians) and they put emphasis on teaching him all the subjects of that sect. However he had the true inner readiness to accept the faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 264م تنيح القديس البابا ديونسيوس البطريرك الرابع عشر من بطاركه الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا الأب بالإسكندرية  فى أواخر القرن الثانى الميلادى من أبوين يعبدان الكواكب (الصابئة) وقد اهتما بتعليمه كل علوم الصابئة. ولكنه كانت لديه الاستعدادات القلبية الصادقة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day a Christian old woman passed by him, who had with her some pages of a book containing an Epistle of the apostle St. Paul, and he bought them from her. When he read these pages he marveled at what was written. He asked the old woman for the rest of the book. She went and brought him back 3 more epistles. Having read them through he found the book to be still incomplete. He asked her to search for the rest of the book. When she felt his strong desire for reading and knowledge, she told him: "If you want to acquire the complete book, go to the church and there you can find it for free."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . ويوما ً ما مرت به امرأة عجوز مسيحية معها كراسة مكتوب فيها بعض رسائل معلمنا القديس بولس الرسول فاشتراها منها وقرأها فأعجب بها.  وطلب من العجوز البقية فقدمت له ثلاث رسائل أخرى ولما شعرت برغبته الشديدة فى القراءة والمعرفة قالت له اذهب إلى الكنيسة فتجد فيها من يعطى لك هذه المعرفة الروحية مجاناً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He went to the church as the old woman told him. He became a disciple to a deacon called Augustine, read the epistles of our teacher St. Paul, and memorized them. Then he went to St. Demetrius, 12th Pope, and declared his faith in the Lord Christ before him, and the Pope baptized him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فسمع لقولها وذهب وهناك تتلمذ على يد شماس يدعى أوغسطين.  وقرأ رسائل معلمنا بولس الرسول ثم مضى إلى البابا ديمتريوس (12) وأعلن أمامه إيمانه بالسيد المسيح فعمده البابا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He joined the theological school and excelled in the church subjects and the Pope granted him the diaconate rank. When Pope Heraclas (Yaraklas) was enthroned, he ordained him a priest appointed him as the dean of the theological school. He persevered in teaching; exhorting and baptizing those accepted the faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم التحق بالمدرسة اللاهوتية ونبغ فى العلوم المسيحية فمنحه البابا رتبه الشماسية. ولما جاء البابا ياروكلاس (13) رسمه قسا ً وقلده رئاسة المدرسة اللاهوتية فداوم على التعليم والوعظ وتعميد من يقبلون الإيمان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Heraclas (13) departed, they unanimously chose the priest Dionysius. He was consecrated Patriarch on the first day of Tobe, year 246 A.D. He shepherded the flock of Christ with the best of care. When Decius incited the persecution against the Christians, he wanted to seize Pope Dionysius, but the Pope escaped. When Decius died the Pope wrote a compassionate letter to emperor Gallus and accordingly the persecution quieted down.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . ولما تنيح البابا ياروكلاس (13) وقع الاختيار على القس ديونسيوس فرسم بطريركا ً يوم أول طوبه سنة 246 م.  فرعى رعية المسيح بكل أمانة. ولما أثار ديسيوس قيصر الاضطهاد على المسيحيين أراد القبض على البابا ديونسيوس فهرب. ولما مات ديسيوس كتب البابا للقيصر غالوس فهدأ الاضطهاد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Nevertheless another kind of strife arose before the Pope which was the struggle against the heretics. He resisted the two heresies that of Sabilius and Paul of Samosata.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولكن ظهر نوع آخر من الجهاد أمام البابا وهو محاربة الهراطقة فقد قاوم بدعتى سابيليوس وبولس الساموساطى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the Pope had completed his good endeavor departed in a good old age. He wrote many spiritual and doctrinal epistles, most of them still exist till present time.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد أن أتم البابا جهاده تنيح بسلام بعد أن كتب عدة رسائل إيمانية مايزال أغلبها محفوظا ًإلى الآن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Return of the Great Sts. Anba Macarius the Great and Anba Macarius of Alexandria, from Exile</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار عودة القديسين مكاريوس الكبير ومكاريوس الإسكندرى من منفاهما</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also of the year 92 of the martyrs (376 A.D.) marks the return of the two Sts. Anba Macarius the Great and Anba Macarius of Alexandria, from exile on the island of Philae, south of Aswan, in Upper Egypt. Emperor Valens the Arian had exiled them to this island.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 92 للشهداء (376م) عاد القديسان مكاريوس الكبير ومكاريوس الإسكندرى من منفاهما بجزيرة فيلة (هى جزيرة تبعد عن أسوان جنوبا ً ثمانى كيلومترات وتُعرف باسم جزيرة أنس الوجود وقد غمرتها مياة بحيرة السد العالى حالياً) بأعالى الصعيد وكان قد نفاهما إليها الملك فالنس الاريوسى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The natives of this island worshipped idols, and they tortured these two Saints severely for three years. It came to pass, Satan possessed the daughter of the pagan priest of this island and tormented her. St. Macarius the great came forward and prayed over her and the Lord healed her by his prayers. Subsequently the priest and the people of the island believed in the Lord Christ. The Saints taught them the facts of the Christian faith and baptized them in the eve of the feast of Epiphany. They changed the temple on the island into a church wherein the two saints prayed and administered to them the Holy Mysteries.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان أهل تلك المدينة يعبدون الأوثان وقد ألحقوا بالقديسين عذابات شديدة لمده ثلاث سنوات. وحدث أن دخل الشيطان فى إبنة كاهن الوثن بتلك الجزيرة فأتعبها جداً. فتقدم القديس مكاريوس الكبير وصلى عليها فشفاها الرب بصلواته فآمن كاهن الوثن وكل أهل الجزيرة بالسيد المسيح.  وعلمهم القديسان حقائق الدين المسيحى وعمدوهم ليلة عيد الغطاس وحولوا البرابي التى فى الجزيرة إلى كنائس وصلى فيها القديسان وناولاهم من الأسرار المقدسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When they wished to return they did not know the way so the angel of the Lord appeared to them, guided them, until they reached Alexandria. From there they went to the wilderness of Shiheet (Scetis). The monks of the wilderness came out to receive them with great joy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وعندما أرادا العودة لم يعرفا الطريق فظهر لهما ملاك وسار معهما يرشدهما حتى وصلا إلى الإسكندرية ومنها إلى برية شيهيت فتلقاهما الرهبان بفرح شديد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of these two Saints be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهما فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائما ً أبديا ً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.14">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fourteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fourteenth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the Bishops Eugenius, Agathodorus and Elpidius</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد الأساقفة أوجانيوس وأغانورس ووالنديوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the Holy Fathers Eugenius, Agathodorus and Elpidius were martyred. These saints were Christians, through their ancestry, walking faithfully in the way of God. They had a great deal of knowledge about the church subjects. St. Armoun Patriarch of Jerusalem ordained them bishops without stated Sees to go around preaching and teaching the word of God.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم استشهد القديسون أوجانيوس وأغاتودرس والبديوس.كان هؤلاء القديسون مسيحيين عن آبائهم سالكين فى وصايا الرب بكل أمانة وقد حصلوا على قدر كبير من العلوم الدينية فرسمهم القديس هرمون بطريرك أورشليم أساقفة بدون كراسي ليجولوا كارزين ومعلمين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They went to many cities, and the people of one of the cities went out, beat them severely and mercilessly, and then they stoned them until they departed in peace and received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى إحدى المدن خرج عليهم أهلها وضربوهم ضربا ً شديدا ًبدون رحمة ثم رجموهم بالحجارة فتنيحوا بسلام ونالوا أكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Shenouda (Sinouti) El Bahnasawy</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس شنودة البهنساوى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 20 of the martyrs (304 A.D.) St. Shenouda (Sinouti) el-Bahnasawy was martyred. This saint was born in the city of el-Bahnasa, and he was a devout Christian.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 20 للشهداء ( 304 م ) إستشهد القديس شنودة البهنساوى. ولد هذا القديس بمدينة البهنسا وكان مسيحيا ًتقياً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Some wicked men laid accusations against him to prince Maximianus, who was appointed by Diocletian, that he was Christian. He brought the saint, and asked him about his faith. The Saint confessed his faith in the Lord Christ and did not deny it. He ordered his men to throw him on the ground, beat him with hammers until his flesh was torn, and his blood flowed on the ground. Then they cast him into a repulsive smelly prison. The Lord sent Michael the Archangel who healed his wounds, strengthened, encouraged and promised him the crown of glory after he had endured what would befall him from tortures.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فوشى به بعض الأشرار لدى الأمير مكسيموس المُعين من قبل دقلديانوس بأنه مسيحى فاستحضره وسأله عن عقيدته فأقر بإيمانه ولم ينكر فأمر الجند بأن يطرحوه على الأرض ويضربوه بالمطارق حتى تهرأ لحمه وجرى دمه على الأرض. ثم وضعوه فى سجن كريه الرائحة فأرسل الرب رئيس الملائكة ميخائيل الذى أبرأه من جراحاته ثم شجعه ووعده بإكليل المجد بعد أن يحتمل ماسيحل به من عذابات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the next morning the prince ordered his soldiers to go and check on him. They found him standing up praying. When they told the prince about him, he brought the saint and saw him well and unharmed, he was perplexed and said: "He is a sorcerer." Then he ordered them to crucify him upside down, and to light fire under him, which did not harm him. They crushed him with the Hinbazeen and finally beheaded him. Thus, he received the crown of martyrdom. During the night the believers took his pure body, poured expensive perfumes over him, shrouded him in costly wrappings, laid him in a coffin and buried him with great honor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى الصباح التالى أمر الأمير الجند أن يتفقدوه فوجدوه واقفا ً يصلى. ولما أعلموا الأمير بأمره أمر بإحضاره وأبصره سالما ً معاف فبهت وقال أنه ساحر. ثم أمر الجنود فعلقوه منكسا ً وأوقدوا تحته نارا ً فلم تؤثر فيه فعصروه بالمعصرة وأخيرا ً قطعوا رأسه ونال إكليل الشهادة. وفى الليل أخذ المؤمنون جسده الطاهر وسكبوا عليه طيباً كثير الثمن ولفوه بأكفان غالية ووضعوه فى تابوت ثم دفنوه بإكرام جزيل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Anba Kyrillos (Cyril) III, 75th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس البابا كيرلس الثالث البطريرك الخامس والسبعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 959 of the martyrs (1243 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Kyrillos III, 75th Patriarch of Alexandria, who was known as Ebn-Loqloq, departed. He was born in El-Fayyom to Christian parents. When he grew, became a monk in the monastery of Mar Victor nearby Cairo. After the departure of Pope Youannes (John) VI, they chose the monk Daoud Ebn-Loqloq for the patriarchate in the year 1235 A.D.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 959 للشهداء (1243م ) تنيح القديس البابا كيرلس الثالث البطريرك الخامس والسبعون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد بالفيوم من أبوين مسيحيين ولما كبر ترهب بدير مار بقطر بجوار القاهرة. وبعد نياحة البابا يوأنس السادس أقيم الراهب داود بن لقلق بطريركا ً سنة 1235م.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the days of this father a holy council convened, which was attended by 14 bishops and they put down many cannons to reorganize the church from many aspects which were published in 5 books:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد عقد فى أيامه مجمع مقدس حضره أربعة عشر أسقفا ً أصدروا قوانين كثيرة فى تنظيم الكنيسة من كافه الوجوه وسجلوها فى خمسة كتب كالآتى :            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Book one: Legislation and management system of the Patriarchate.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الكتاب الأول : التشريع ونظام إدارة البطريركية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Book two: Baptism, Matrimony and the command to the newly wed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الكتاب الثانى : فى العماد والزواج والوصية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Book three: Endowments and pledges.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الكتاب الثالث : ويشمل الأوقاف والنذور.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Book four: Rituals in the Coptic Church.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الكتاب الرابع : يشمل الطقوس فى الكنيسة القبطية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Book five: The organization of the Patriarchal Court.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الكتاب الخامس : فى تنظيم الديوان البطريركى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Kyrollos III ordained the scholar and Holy Father Paul El-Boushy bishop for Cairo (Miser) who assisted him in managing the affairs of the church. After he sat on the Patriarchal Throne for seven years and seven month, he departed and was buried in El-Shama’a (Wax) monastery nearby Tamouh, in Giza.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ورسم البابا كيرلس الثالث الراهب العالم والقديس بولس البوشى أسقفا ً على مصر الذى ساعده كثيرا ً فى تدبير أمور البيعة. وبعد أن أقام البابا كيرلس الثالث على الكرسى المرقسى مده سبع سنين وسبعة أشهر تنيح ودفن فى دير الشمع قرب طموه بالجيزة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات قديسى هذا اليوم فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائما ً أبديا ً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.15">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fifteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fifteenth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Sarah the Nun</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديسة سارة الراهبة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day St. Sarah the nun, departed. This saint was born in Upper Egypt to wealthy Christian parents. They had no other children and they raised her with a Christian upbringing. They taught her reading the Holy Bible and the biography and sayings of the fathers the monks. She was influenced by their lives and desired the monastic life. She went to one of the convents of Upper Egypt and dwelt there for many years as a novice then she put on the monastic garb.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تنيحت القديسة سارة الراهبة. ولدت هذه القديسة بصعيد مصر من أبوين مسيحيين غنيين ولم يكن لهما أبناء سواها فربياها تربية مسيحية  وعلماها قراءة الكتاب المقدس وسيرة الآباء الرهبان فتأثرت بها واشتاقت إلى حياة الرهبنة وقصدت أحد أديرة العذراى بالصعيد حيث مكثت سنين كثيرة تحت الاختبار ثم لبست زى الرهبنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               She persevered in fighting the devils for thirteen years until Satan was weary of her steadfastness and purity. Then Satan tried to overcome her by the sin of pride. He appeared to her, in the form of an angel, while she was standing praying and said to her: "Blessed are you for you have overcame Satan." She replied: "I am a weak nun, and I am not able to conquer him except by the power of my Lord Jesus Christ" and Satan immediately disappeared.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وظلت تجاهد ضد الشياطين ثلاث عشرة سنة حتى ضجر الشيطان من ثباتها وطهارتها.  فحاول الشيطان إسقاطها فى رذيلة الكبرياء فظهر لها فى شكل ملاك وهى واقفة تصلى وقال لها " طوباك فقد غلبت الشيطان ". فأجابته "إننى راهبة ضعيفة لا أستطيع أن أغلبه إلا بقوة ربى يسوع المسيح" فتوارى الشيطان من أمامها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Saint had many useful sayings that she used to say to the nuns. One of her sayings was: "I never set my foot upon the step of the ladder, and I never go up to the next step without thinking I may die before I raise my leg so that the enemy might not entice me with the hope of a long life." And she also said: "It is better for a man to show mercy, even to satisfy men, for the time will come when it will be done to satisfy God." She also had many other sayings written in the Paradise of the Fathers.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولهذه القديسة أقوال كثيرة نافعة كانت تقولها للعذارى منها " إننى لا أضع رجلى على السلم إلا وأتصور أننى أموت قبل أن أرفعها حتى لا يغرينى العدو بالأمل فى طول الحياة" وقولها "جيد للإنسان أن يفعل الرحمة ولو لإرضاء الناس فسيأتى وقت ويفعلها لإرضاء الله". ولها أقوال أخرى كثيرة مدونة فى بستان الرهبان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint dwelt in a cave on the banks of the river for a long period of time fighting a great fight and no one saw her except when she went to partake of the Holy Mysteries. When she completed her strife, she departed in peace to the eternal bliss when she was eighty years old.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأقامت هذه القديسة فى قلاية على حافة النهر مدة طويلة تجاهد جهادا ًعظيما ًلم يبصرها خلالها أحد إلا عند التناول من الأسرار المقدسة ولما أكملت جهادها بسلام إنتقلت إلى النعيم الدائم بالغة من العمر ثمانين سنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Helias of Ahnas</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس إيلياس الإهناسى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the great St. Helias of Ahnas was martyred. This Holy Father grew up in a village near Ahnas (Ahnasia). He worked as a farmer in the orchards of Prince Klekianos, the heathen governor of Ahnas. He was a devout young man who loved God. He had an uncle whose name was Abba Jacob, a hermit dwelling in the desert near Ahnas. Helias went to him often to learn from him worship and asceticism. His uncle commended him to keep himself pure, saying, “Purity and chastity make us resemble the spiritual angels.” He grew in godliness and the fear of God filled his heart. He was trustworthy in all of his master’s possessions, his field and his house as Joseph in the house of Potiphar.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً استشهد القديس العظيم إيلياس الأهناسى. نشأ هذا القديس فى قرية قرب أهناسيا وكان يعمل فلاحاً فى بساتين الأمير كلكيانوس والى أهناسيا الوثنى. وكان شابا ً تقيا ً محبا ً لله وله خال يدعى أنبا يعقوب متوحد بالصحراء القريبة من أهناسيا. فكان يذهب إليه ايلياس كثيرا ً يتعلم منه العبادة والنسك. وكان خاله يوصيه أن يحفظ نفسه بالطهارة قائلا ً " أن الطهارة تجعلنا نتشبه بالملائكة الروحانيين" فنما فى الفضيلة وسكنت فيه مخافة الله.   وكان أمينا ً فى كل ما لسيده فى حقله وبيته كيوسف الصديق فى بيت فوطيفار.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The prince and his family loved him. He used to bring the fruits to the house of the prince, so the daughter of the prince became affectionately attracted to him. She pursued him to make Helias fall with her into sin. When he realized that, he took the fruits of the orchard to the house and left in a hurry as someone fleeing from a fire. He went often and complained to his uncle Jacob who strongly warned him from listening or looking at her. When the girl continued to intensely pursue him, he went and castrated himself according to his naive thinking to take away any hope of her falling into sin with him. Because of what he had done, he became seriously ill. When the girl knew that she became furious and complained to her father, saying, “Helias is a Christian and tried to force himself on me”, so the prince became enraged.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فأحبه الأمير وأيضاً كل أسرته. فتعلقت به أبنة الأمير فصارت تلاحقه تريد أن تسقطه معها فى الخطية. أما هو فعندما شعر بذلك كان يلقى بالفاكهة داخل باب حجرتها ويهرب كمن يبتعد من النار. وكان يذهب ويشتكى لخاله يعقوب فكان يحذره بشدة من الاستماع أو النظر إليها.  ولما ظلت الفتاة تطارده بشدة ولبساطته مضى وخصى نفسه لينزع عنها كل أمل ومرض بسبب هذا العمل مرضا ً شديدا ً. ولما علمت الفتاة بذلك اغتاظت جدا ً وشكته لأبيها قائلة: "أنه مسيحى ويريد الاعتداء عليها". فغضب الأمير            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He brought Helias and admonished him, but he proved his innocence. The prince asked him to offer a sacrifice to the idols to pardon him, but the saint strongly refused. The prince started tormenting him with severe tortures, but the Lord saved him. Finally, he ordered to behead him; Helias rejoiced and said, “This is the hour that I was seeking.” He asked the soldiers to tarry so he can pray. While he was praying the angel of the Lord appeared to him, saying, “The Lord has accepted your petition and here is Julius of Aqfahs who is nearby you writing your biography. He will shroud your body, and will take it to your uncle. He will keep it until the day the Lord wills to reveal it. The Lord will manifest many signs and wonders from your body.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               واستحضر إيلياس وصار يوبخه ولكنه أثبت براءته. فطلب منه الأمير أن يذبح للأوثان فيعفو عنه فرفض بشدة فصار الأمير يعذبه بعذابات شديدة والرب يخلصه منها وأخيرا ً أمر بقطع رأسه ففرح إيلياس وقال " هذه هى الساعة التى كنت أطلبها ". وطلب من الجنود أن يمهلوه حتى يصلى. وبينما هو يصلى ظهر له ملاك الرب قائلا: "الرب قد قبل طلبتك وهوذا يوليوس الأقفهصى بالقرب منك يكتب سيرتك وهو سيكفن جسدك ويوصله إلى خالك فيحفظه إلى اليوم الذى يريد الرب ظهوره فيه وسيظهر الرب من جسدك آيات وعجائب كثيرة".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Afterwards, he extended his neck to the soldiers who cut his neck. Thus, he received the crown of martyrdom and the sayings of the angel were fulfilled. A church was built in Ahnasia. His body was relocated to it and this church remained in existence till the beginning of the thirteenth century but was destroyed later.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بعد ذلك مد عنقه للجنود فقطعوا رأسه ونال إكليل الشهادة وتمت أقوال الملاك وبنيت له كنيسة فى أهناسيا ووضع جسده فيها وظلت هذه الكنيسة قائمة إلى أوائل القرن الثالث عشر ثم اندثرت.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائما ً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.16">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Sixteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the sixteenth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Apparition of the Virgin St. Mary in the church of St. Demiana in Papadouplo, Shoubra, Cairo, Egypt</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">ظهور القديسة العذراء مريم بكنيسة الشهيدة  دميانة بحى بابا دوبلو بشبرا – القاهرة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 1702 of the martyrs (Tuesday, March 25, 1986 A.D.) the pure Virgin St. Mary appeared above the church of St. Demiana in Papadouplo, Shoubra, Cairo, Egypt. That was in the 15th year of the pontificate of H.H. Pope Shenouda III, 117th Patriarch of Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 1702 للشهداء (الثلاثاء 25 مارس 1986م) تجلت العذراء القديسة الطاهرة مريم فوق كنيسة القديسة دميانة بأرض بابا دبلو بحى شبرا بالقاهرة. وذلك فى السنة الخامسة عشر من حبرية قداسة البابا شنودة الثالث البطريرك المائة والسابع عشر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The apparitions of the Virgin were characterized by; it was for thousands of people, on the domes of the church and was also marked by the innumerable miracles performed by the Virgin to many without distinction. This apparition also continued for many months (1986 – 1991). What happened in the church was tangible and gradual in the form of wondrous light of unknown source then the light started to have form and shape. The people began to feel the occurrence of miracles and signs around them which confirmed the faith in their hearts.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد تميزت ظهورات العذراء أنها كانت لآلاف الناس وعلى قباب الكنيسة كما تميز هذا الظهور بمعجزات أجرتها القديسة العذراء لكثيرين بلا تفريق وقد استمر الظهور شهوراً طويلة. وماحدث فى كنيسة القديسة دميانة  ببابا دوبلو بشبرا القاهرة كان فى تدرج ملموس فى هيئة نور عجيب لا يعرف مصدره ثم بدأ النور يتشكل فبدأ الناس يشعرون بمعجزات تحدث. فتأكد الإيمان فى القلوب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This apparition accompanied by some spiritual phenomena as the repeated apparition of the Virgin in different forms, the appearance of pigeons flying at night, the smell of incense over the church, and a very luminous and radiant unnatural light appearing inside the church towers and also emitted in different places of the church shining to the outside.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وصاحب هذا الظهور بعض الظواهر الروحية كظهور الحمام فى المساء ورائحة البخور والنور الساطع المبهر الذى إنبعث فى أماكن مختلفة بالكنيسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The various news media, both foreign and Arabic, covered this apparition. This apparition was confirmed also by a report issued by the special synodical committee that was entrusted by his H.H. Pope Shenouda to investigate and verify the facts of this glorious apparition.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتحدثت عن هذا الظهور وسائل الإعلام المختلفه أجنبية وعربية. وقد أكد هذا الظهور تقرير أصدرته اللجنة المجمعية المكلفة من قداسة البابا شنودة بتقصى الحقائق.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the intercession of our lady the Virgin St. Mary be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة شفاعة السيدة العذراء مريم فلتكن معنا آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Khail I (Mikhael), 46th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس البابا خائيل الأول البطريرك السادس والأربعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 483 of the martyrs (767 A.D.) Pope Khail I (Mikhail), 46th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This father was a pious monk in the monastery of St. Macarius the great in the wilderness of Shiheet. When Pope Theodorus (Tawadros I) departed, the bishops, priests and lay leaders (Archons) unanimously agreed to chose the holy Father Khail el-Maquary to consecrate him patriarch for what was known of his godliness, piety and knowledge.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 483 للشهداء (767م) تنيح القديس البابا خائيل الأول البطريرك السادس والأربعون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. وهو كان راهبا ًتقيا ً فى دير القديس مكاريوس الكبير ببرية شيهيت فلما تنيح البابا ثيؤدورس اتفق رأى الأساقفة والكهنة والأراخنة على اختيار القديس خائيل المقارى لرسامته بطريركاً نظراً لما أشُتهر به من تقوى وفضيلة وعلم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They seized father Khail against his will and brought him to Alexandria. They consecrated him Patriarch on the 17th day of Thoout, year 460 of the martyrs (743 A.D.) by the name, Pope Khail I.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فأمسكوه رغما ً عنه وأتوا به إلى الإسكندرية  وأقاموه بطريركا ً يوم 17 توت سنة 460 للشهداء (743م) باسم البابا خائيل الأول.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the day of his enthronement, it rained heavily for three days after two consecutive years of drought. The people of Alexandria considered that to be a good omen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى يوم الرسامة هطلت الأمطار بغزارة لمده ثلاثة أيام بعد أن كانت منقطعة سنتين  متواليتين فاستبشر أهل الإسكندرية خيرا ً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Pope endured many hardships from the ruler Abdel-Malek Ebn Marawan for he was beaten, imprisoned, chained, and tortured.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد إحتمل هذا البابا شدائد كثيرة من الوالى عبد الملك بن مروان كالضرب والحبس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Kyriakos, king of Nubia, knew that, he was extremely enraged and he prepared about one hundred thousand soldiers and marched toward Egypt. He encamped around el-Fostat (Capital) threatening to destroy it. When Abdel-Malek the ruler saw the armies of king Kyriakos, and realized that all this had taken place for the sake of the Patriarch, he was terrified and released him from prison. The ruler entreated the Patriarch to mediate a truce between him and the king of Nubia. The Patriarch went out along with some of the clergy to meet the king of Nubia and asked him to accept the truce with Abdel-Malek. The king accepted his mediation and returned to his country.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما علم بذلك كيرياكوس ملك النوبة غضب جدا ً وجهز نحو مائه ألف جندى وسار بهم نحو القطر المصرى وعسكـر حول الفسطاط فلما رأى الوالى عبد الملك بن مروان جيوش الملك كيرياكوس خاف وأطلق سبيل البطريرك والتجأ إليه ليتوسط فى أمر الصلح. فخرج البابا خائيل ومعه لفيف من الإكليروس إلى ملك النوبة وطلبوا منه أن يقبل الصلح مع الوالى فقبل وإنصرف إلى بلاده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The ruler started to respect Pope Khail and lifted up his persecution against his people. Moreover, the Pope prayed for the sake of the ruler's daughter, who was possessed with an unclean spirit, and with his prayers she was healed. Because of that the Governor increased his respect for the Patriarch.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فبدأ الوالى يحترم البابا خائيل ورفع الاضطهادات عن شعبه خصوصا ً عندما صلى البابا من أجل أبنة الوالى التى كان يعتريها روح نجس وبصلواته شفيت.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Khail completed his good endeavor departed in peace. He remained on the apostolic throne for twenty-three years and six months.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل البابا جهاده الحسن تنيح بسلام بعد أن قضى على الكرسى المرقسى ثلاثا ً وعشرين سنة وستة أشهر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة  صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائما ً أبديا ً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.17">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Seventeenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the seventeenth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Lazarus, the beloved of the Lord</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  لعازر حبيب الرب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 34 A.D. the righteous Lazarus, the beloved of the Lord Christ, departed. He was the brother of Martha and Mary and the Lord found His rest in their house. When Lazarus fell sick his sisters sent to the Lord Christ saying: "Lord, behold, he whom You love is sick." When Jesus heard that, He said, "This sickness is not unto death, but for the glory of God, that the Son of God may be glorified through it." Now Jesus loved Martha, her sister Mary and Lazarus. However, He stayed two more days in the place where He was" to magnify the miracle.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 34م تنيح الصديق البار لعازر حبيب الرب وهو أخو مرثا ومريم وكان الرب يستريح فى بيتهم وحدث لما مرض لعازر أن أختيه أرسلتا إلى السيد المسيح قائلتين "ياسيد هوذا الذى تحبه مربض" فلما سمع السيد المسيح قال " هذا المرض ليس للموت بل لأجل مجد الله ليتمجد إبن الله به" (يو 11 : 4 ). وكان الرب يحب لعازر ومرثا ومريم ولكنه مكث فى الموضع الذى كان فيه يومين لتعظيم الآية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Lord came to Bethany, He stood before Lazarus’ tomb and said; "Take away the stone." Martha said to Him, "Lord, by this time there is a stench, for he has been dead four days." Jesus said to her, "Did I not say to you that if you would believe you would see the glory of God?" Then they took away the stone and he cried with a loud voice, "Lazarus, come forth!" And he who had died came out bound hand and foot with grave clothes, and his face was wrapped with a cloth. (John 11:1-45)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم ذهب إلى قرية  بيت عنيا ووقف أمام قبر لعازر وقال "إرفعوا الحجر". فقالت له مرثا "ياسيد قد أنتن لأن له أربعة أيام " فقال لها " ألم أقل لك إن آمنت ترين مجد الله ". فرفعوا الحجر ثم صرخ بصوت عظيم " لعازر هلم خارجا ً " فخرج الميت ويداه ورجلاه مربوطات بأقمطة ووجهه ملفوف بمنديل " ( يو 11 : 43،44 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               That was to manifest the reality of his death, therefore the miracle was significant and for that reason many believed in Him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان ذلك ليتحقق موته ولهذا قد عظمت هذه الآية فآمن به كثيرين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of Lazarus the just be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات لعازر البار فلتكن معنا آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Sidhom Bishay in Domiat</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهد القديس سيدهم بشاى بدمياط</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1561 of the martyrs (1844 A.D.) St. Sidhom Bishay was martyred in Domiat (Damietta). He was born and raised in Damietta until his early youth. He was devout and celibate and he was also in charge of the deacons of his church.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 1561 للشهداء ( 1844 م ) أستشهد القديس سيدهم بشاى بدمياط ولد وتربى بدمياط حتى شبابه المبكر وكان بتولاً تقياً وكان رئيسا ً للشمامسة أيضاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the year 1820 A.D. he moved to Alexandria where he worked as a lumber merchant. He came to Domiat often to buy the lumber. He took interest in restoring the church of the martyr Mari Girgis el-Muzahem (St. George the Zahimian) in the city of Bosat el-Nasarah.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى سنة 1820 م هاجر إلى الإسكندرية وعمل تاجرا ً للأخشاب وكان يأتى إلى دمياط لشراء الأخشاب وإهتم بترميم كنيسة الشهيد مارجرجس المزاحم بناحية بساط النصارى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day, on his way to the church to pray in Domiat, a wicked person obstructed his way to prevent him from going to the church but he did not pay any attention to him. That person became agitated and started to insult and curse him with evil words until some of the boys in the street gathered around him. They attributed false accusations against him and brought St. Sidhom before the court. The judge decided either he would forsake his faith in the Lord Christ or be killed. When he refused, they tormented him, and then dragged him through the streets of the city. That coincided with the passing by of his friend el-Moallem (Master) Apanoub Ibrahim who tried to rescue him, however they beat him also on his head with palm branches and later on he died.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وذات يوم بينما كان فى طريقة إلى الكنيسة للصلاة بدمياط أعترض طريقه أحد الأشرار لمنعه من الذهاب إلى الكنيسة لكنه لم يلتفت إليه فهاج وظل يقذفه بالشتائم الردية حتى تجمهر معه بعض الصبية ونسبوا له اتهامات باطلة فاقتادوه إلى المحكمة التى حكمت عليه أن يترك الإيمان بالمسيح أو يموت فلما لم يقبل عذبوه وجروه فى شوارع المدينة وتصادف مرور صديقه المعلم أبانوب إبراهيم وحاول إنقاذه فضربوه هو أيضاً على رأسه بالجريد فمات بعد ذلك.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The mob continued to insult St. Sidhom Bishay and tortured him in different horrific ways for five consecutive days. He endured it all thankfully saying; “O my Lord Jesus … O my lady the compassionate one” and he meant by that the Lady St. Mary. Finally he delivered his pure spirit in the hand of the Lord and the Virgin St. Mary was present at the time of his departure, thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وظلوا يعذبون القديس سيدهم بشاى على مدى خمسة أيام بعذابات رهيبة وهو يحتمل كل ذلك بشكر ويقول "يايسوع....... ياحنونة" يقصد بهذه السيدة العذراء. أخيراً أستودع روحه الطاهرة بيد الرب وكانت العذراء مريم حاضرة وقت نياحته فنال بذلك إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the matter reached the Khedive, he sent to investigate his death which revealed the innocence of St. Sidhom Bishay from what he was accused of. He ordered to lift up the crosses in his funeral for it was forbidden before.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما بلغ الأمر للخديوى أرسل للتحقيق فظهرت براءة القديس سيدهم بشاى مما نسب له فأمر برفع الصلبان فى جنازته بعد أن كان رفعها ممنوعا .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               All the Christian denominations in the city participated in his funeral. The priest put on their priestly vestments and the procession was guarded by the soldiers. After completing the funeral prayers, the body was buried with great veneration in the ground of St. George church in Domiat. A pillar of light was seen in the night of the burial shined above his tomb. His body still whole kept in a shrine in the Virgin St. Mary’s church in Damietta            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               واشتركت جميع الطوائف المسيحية فى المدينه فى جنازته ولبس الكهنة ملابسهم الكهنوتية وسار الموكب فى حراسة الجنود. وبعد إتمام الصلاة دفُن الجسد بإكرام جزيل بأرض كنيسة مارجرجس بدمياط وقد شوهد ليلة دفنه عمود من النور يسطع فوق مقبرته ومازال جسده كاملا ً ومحفوظا ً فى مقصورة بكنيسة العذراء بدمياط.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of the prayers of this great martyr be with us all. Amen            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Basilius, Bishop of Jerusalem</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة  القديس الأنبا باسيليوس مطران القدس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1615 of the martyrs (1899 A.D.) the Holy Father Anba Basilius, Metropolitan of Jerusalem, departed. This father was born in the year 1818 A.D. in the village of el-Dabah , to godly parents. They nursed him with the milk of piety and faith and taught him the church subjects.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 1615 للشهداء (1899م) تنيح القديس الأنبا باسيليوس مطران القدس. ولد هذا الأب سنة 1818 م ببلده الدابة (هى قرية الرحمانية قبلى بمركز نجع حمادى حالياً) من أبوين تقيين أرضعاه لبن الفضيلة والإيمان وعلماه العلوم الكنسيـة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he was twenty-five years old he became a monk in the monastery of St. Antonios and persevered in worship and asceticism. Because of what he was adorned with from godliness and knowledge they ordained him priest then hegumen and appointed him Abbot for the monastery. He managed the monastery well with gentleness, wisdom and meekness that made Pope Kyrollos IV, father of reformation, to ordain him Metropolitan for Jerusalem.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما بلغ سن الخامسة والعشرين ترهب بدير القديس الأنبا أنطونيوس وثابر على العبادة  والنسك ونظراً لما تحلى به من التقوى والعلم رسموه قساً ثم قمصا ً وتقلد رئاسة الدير فأحسن إدارته بالحكمة والوداعة مما جعل البابا كيرلس الرابع أبا الإصلاح يرسمه مطرانا ً للقدس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was prudent in managing the affairs of his diocese; he cared for building the churches, and bought endowments to care for them. He was loved by everyone, regardless of their religion or political affiliation, for his meekness and wisdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فدبر أيبارشيته أحسن تدبير واهتم ببناء الكنائس وشراء الأوقاف لها وكان محبوبا ً من الجميع على اختلاف أديانهم ومذاهبهم بسبب وداعته وحكمته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his days a dispute rose with the Ethiopian monks because of the ownership of El-Sultan monastery in Jerusalem which belong to the Coptic Church. Because of the vigilance of this father the Ethiopians could not take over the monastery. He spent his days in continuous effort for what was good for the church and his people and when he finished his good endeavor departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى أيامه حدثت منازعات مع الرهبان الأحباش بسبب دير السلطان بالقدس التابع للكنيسة القبطية وبفضل يقظة هذا الأب لم يتمكن الأحباش من الاستيلاء على هذا الدير وقضى أيامه فى جهاد متواصل لأجل خير الكنيسة والشعب. ثم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة  صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of St. George the ascetic, St. Belasius the martyr, and Anba Joseph the bishop</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار القديسين جرجس العابد وبلاسيوس الشهيد والأنبا يوسف الأسقف</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the church celebrates the commemoration of the Sts. George the ascetic, Belasius the martyr, and Anba Joseph (Yousab) the bishop.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً تحتفل الكنيسة بتذكار القديسين جرجس العابد وبلاسيوس الشهيد والأنبا يوسف الأسقف.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.18">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eighteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eighteenth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Isidore, Friend of St. Sina the Soldier</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 21 للشهداء ( 305 م ) أستشهد القديس إيسوذورس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 21 of the martyrs (305 A.D.), St. Isidore was martyred. This saint was born in the city of Deknash (Dafnas) , and he worked as a wool weaver. He had a close friend called Sina, who was a soldier, and both were charitable to the poor and the needy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولد هذا القديس ببلدة دقناش ( حاليا ً قرية مزورة بمركز سمسطا بمحافظة بنى سويف ). وكان يعمل فى صناعة الصوف مع القديس سنا رفيقه. وكانا يتصدقان على الفقراء والمساكين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One night they both saw a vision a virgin with crowns in her hand placed them on their heads. When they woke up they told each other about the vision and realized that the Lord had called them to receive the crown of martyrdom. They went to the Governor of Pelusium (el-Farma) and confessed their faith in the Lord Christ. He ordered to imprison them and the Lord sent His angel in a vision at night to comfort them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وذات ليلة أبصر كل منهما فى رؤيا أن فتاة عذراء بيدها إكليل تضعه على رأسيهما فلما استيقظا أعلم كل منهما الآخر بالرؤيا وعرفا أن الرب دعاهما لنيل إكليل الشهادة. أنطلق الاثنان إلى والى الفرما واعترفا بالسيد المسيح فأمر بسجنهما فأرسل الرب ملاكه فى رؤيا الليل وعزاهما.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Governor sent St. Sina to Alexandria and St. Isidore remained in prison. Shortly after St. Sina was returned back to the prison and his friend St. Isidore rejoiced. They told each other what had happened to them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى الصباح أمر الوالى بإرسال سنا إلى الإسكندرية وبقى إيسوذورس سجيناً. وبعد قليل أعيد سنا إلى السجن ففرح به صديقه وقص كل منهما ما جرى له.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Governor started to torture them severely. He cast St. Isidore into a fiery furnace. St. Isidore prayed asking the Lord Christ to accept his soul thus he received the crown of martyrdom. The mother of St. Sina was standing weeping for the separation of her son from his friend. She saw a multitude of angels ascending with the soul of St. Isidore. She took care of the body, shrouded and buried it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبدأ الوالى فى تعذيبهما فألقى إيسوذورس فى أتون نار. وهو يصلى طالبا ً من السيد المسيح أن يقبل روحه فنال إكليل الشهادة. وكانت والدة القديس سنا واقفه تبكى لحرمان أبنها من صديقه فرأت جماعة من الملائكة تصعد بروح القديس إيسوذورس فاهتمت بالجسد وكفنته ودفنته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.19">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Nineteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the nineteenth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع عشر من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Aristobulus, one of the 70 Apostles</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس أرسطو بولس الرسول أحد السبعين رسولا ً</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day St. Aristobulus, one of the seventy apostles, was martyred. They were chosen by the Lord and sent them to preach before His pas¬sion. He received the grace of the Holy Spirit along with the disciples on the day of Pentecost. He accompanied and preached with them the Life-giving Gospel. He turned many to the path of salvation, believed in the Lord Christ and baptized them. He also taught them the Divine commandments.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم استشهد القديس أرسطوبولس أحد السبعين رسولا ً الذين انتخبهم الرب وأرسلهم للكرازة قبل الآمه وقد نال مع التلاميذ نعمة الروح القدس فى يوم الخمسين ونادى معهم بالبشارة المحيية ورد كثيرين إلى طريق الخلاص فآمنوا بالسيد المسيح وعمدهم وعلمهم الوصايا الإلهية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The disciples consecrated him a bishop for one of the provinces in north France called Abritanias. He preached to its people, exhorted and baptized them. He taught them the divine commandments and the church ordinances. God performed numerous miracles by the hands of this saint which led many to the faith. Many hardships and humiliation befell him from the Jews and the Greeks. They stoned him to death thus he received the crown of martyrdom. St. Paul had mentioned him in his Epistle to the Romans (Ch.16:10).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أقامه التلاميذ أسقفا ً على إحدى مقاطعات شمال فرنسا (مقاطعه أبريطانياس - هى إحدى مقاطعات شمال فرنسا ) فبشر أهلها ووعظهم وعمدهم وعلمهم الوصايا الإلهية والقوانين الكنسية. وقد صنع الله على يدي هذا القديس آيات كثيرة كانت سبباً فى إيمان الكثيرين فلحقت به إهانات شديدة من اليهود واليونانيين. ورجموه بالحجارة فنال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Sts. Alexander, Agabius and their companions</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسين ألكسندروس وأغابيوس ومن معهما</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also of the year 21 of the martyrs (305 A.D.) marks the martyrdom of the seven saints: Alexander, Romulus, Valcsius and Blesius from Alexandria, Agabius from the city of Gaza, Timolaos (Timol) from Pontus, and Dionysius from the city of Tripoli. These seven men were joined together with God’s love. They went to the Governor of Caesarea, Palestine, and confessed the Lord Christ before him. He tried to befriend them and convince them to abandon their faith. When he failed ordered to torment them with severe tortures. They were all martyred and received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 21 للشهداء ( 305 م ) استشهد القديسون ألكسندروس ورومياوس وبليسوس ومليس المصريون وأغابيوس من غزة وتيموثاؤس من البنطس وديوناسيوس من طرابلس. أرتبط هؤلاء السبعة القديسون بالمحبة المسيحية ومضوا إلى والى قيصرية فلسطين واعترفوا أمامه بالسيد المسيح فلاطفهم محاولاً إقناعهم بترك إيمانهم ولما لم يفلح أمر بتعذيبهم بعذابات شديدة فنالوا اكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائما ً أبديا ً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.20">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twentieth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم العشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twentieth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم العشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Khail, 56th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا خائيل الثالث البطريرك السادس والخمسين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 623 of the martyrs (907 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Khail III (Mikhail), 56th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This saint became a monk in the monastery of St. Macarius in the wilderness of Shiheet and lived a virtuous life. When Pope Shenouda I departed, the bishops, priests and archons unanimously agreed to chose him for the patriarchate. He was consecrated on the 30th of Parmoute, year 596 of the martyrs (880 A.D.).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 623 للشهداء ( 907 م ) تنيح الأب القديس البابا خائيل الثالث البطريرك السادس و الخمسون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ترهب هذا القديس بدير القديس مكاريوس ببرية شيهيت وسار سيرة فاضلة ولما تنيح البابا شنودة الأول اجتمع رأى الأساقفة والكهنة والأراخنة على أختياره بطريركاً فرسموه يوم 30 برمودة سنة 596 للشهداء (880 م).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Father faced many hardships from the rulers of the country. An accusation against him came before Ahmad Ibn Tulun (Governor of Egypt) who imprisoned him for one year with the excuse that the Pope had a great sum of money. He did not release the Pope till he agreed to pay twenty thousand dinars.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد نالت هذا الأب شدائد كثيرة من الحكام كما حدثت وشاية ضده عند أحمد بن طولون فسجنه سنة كاملة بحجة أن لديه أموالاً كثيرة ولم يطلق سراحه إلا بعد أن تعهد بدفع عشرين ألف دينار.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Patriarch wrote a promissory note to pay the amount. Since the Pope did not have the funds to pay the fine, the bishops and the people paid half of it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فخرج من السجن ولما لم يكن لديه قيمة الغرامة دفع له الأساقفة والشعب نصفها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Shortly after Ahmed Ibn Tulun died and his son Khumarawaih reigned after him. He called the Patriarch, comforted him, tore up the promissory note and forgave him the debt. When the Lord willed to relieve him from the toil of this world, he rested in the lord. This father spent twenty seven years on the apostolic throne then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم مات أحمد بن طولون وتمِّلك بعده أبنه خماروية فاستدعى البابا البطريرك وطيب خاطره ومزق صك الغرامة. ولما أراد الرب أن يريحه من أتعاب هذا العالم رقد فى الرب بعد أن قضى على الكرسى المرقسى سبعاً وعشرين سنة وشهرا ً واحداً وتسعة أيام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of Raising Lazarus, from the dead</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار إقامة لعازر حبيب الرب من الموت</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the Lord Christ raised his beloved Lazarus from the dead after four days. Because of the greatness of this miracle, many believed in the Lord. We ask our good Savior who rose from the dead to raise us from the death of sin.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً أقام الرب يسوع المسيح لعازر حبيبه من بين الأموات بعد موته بأربعة أيام ولعظم هذا المعجزة آمن به كثيرون نسأل إلهنا الصالح أن يقيمنا معه من موت الخطية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولربنا المجد دائما ً أبديا ً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.21">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty First Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الحادى والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty first day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الحادى والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Theotokos, the Pure Virgin St. Mary</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار والدة الإله القديسة الطاهرة مريم العذراء</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the church celebrates the monthly commemoration of the Theotokos, the Virgin St. Mary the intercessor of mankind.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تعيد الكنيسة اليوم بالتذكار الشهرى لوالدة الإله القديسة مريم العذراء الشفيعة فى جنس البشر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Her holy intercession be with us all. Amen            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               شفاعتها المقدسة فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The visit of the Savior to Bethany and the Consultation of the chief Priests to kill Lazarus, whom the Lord raised from the dead</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">دخول المخلص بيت عنيا وتشاور عظماء الكهنة على قتل لعازر الذى أقامه الرب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also our Lord Jesus Christ along with his disciples came to Bethany, which is nearby Jerusalem, where they made Him a supper. Lazarus, whom the Lord raised from the dead, was one of those who sat at the table with Him. Martha his sister served those who were present. Then Mary took oil of spikenard, anointed the feet of the Savior, and wiped His feet with her hair. The Lord praised her, pointing out to His death by saying, "She has kept this for the day of My burial."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى مثل هذا اليوم حضر ربنا يسوع المسيح مع تلاميذه إلى بيت عنيا القريب من أورشليم حيث كان لعازر الذى أقامه من بين الأموات أحد المتكئين معه. وكانت مرثا أخته تخدم الجمع الحاضر ومريم تدهن قدمى المخلص بالطيب وتمسحهما بشعرها فمدحها الرب وأشار عن موته بقوله " إنها ليوم تكفينى قد حفظته" .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Now a great many of the Jews knew that He was there; and they came, not for Jesus’ sake only, but that they might also see Lazarus, whom He had raised from the dead. The chief priests plotted to put Lazarus to death also, because on account of him many of the Jews went away and believed in Jesus. (John 12:1-11)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فعلم جمع كثير من اليهود انه هناك فجاءوا ليس لأجل يسوع فقط بل لينظروا أيضا ً لعازر الذى أقامه من بين الأموات. فتشاور رؤساء الكهنة ليقتلوا لعازر أيضا ً لأن كثيرين من اليهود كانوا بسببه يذهبون ويؤمنون بيسوع " ( يوحنا 12 : 1 -11 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of our Lord Jesus Christ be upon us and our homes to Him is the glory and honor forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة ربنا يسوع المسيح فلتحل علينا وعلى بيوتنا له كل كرامة ومجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Sts. Theodore and Timothy</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسين تاؤدوروس وتيموثاوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Today also the church celebrates the commemoration of the martyrdom of Sts Theodore and Timothy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار أستشهاد القديسين تاؤدروس وتيموثاوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهما فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.22">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Second Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثانى والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty second day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثانى والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Kyrollos (Cyril), Bishop of Jerusalem</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس كيرلس أسقف أورشليم</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 102 of the martyrs (386 A.D.) the Holy Father St. Kyrollos (Cyril), Bishop of Jerusalem, departed. He was born in Jerusalem in the year 315 A.D. and was raised with a Christian upbringing. He excelled in the spiritual subjects and the Greek literatures. St. Maximus, bishop of Jerusalem, ordained him deacon then priest and delegated to him the instruction of the catechumens of the Jews and the pagans in the church of the Resurrection. He persevered in teaching the doctrines of the Christian religion for sixteen years and the people gathered around him to hear his exhortations and sermons.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 102 للشهداء ( 386 م ) تنيح القديس العظيم كيرلس أسقف أورشليم. ولد هذا الأب بأورشليم سنة 315 م وتربى تربية مسيحية وأتقن العلوم الروحية والآداب اليونانية. رسمه القديس مكسيموس أسقف أورشليم شماسا ً ثم كاهنا ً وأوكل إليه إرشاد الموعوظين من اليهود والوثنيين فى كنيسة القيامة فأقام على ذلك ستة عشر عاما ً يعلم عقائد الديانة المسيحية ويلقى العظات وكل الناس يتزاحمون حوله لسماع عظاته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the bishop of Jerusalem departed, he was chosen as his successor. The scope of learning and teaching expanded before him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تنيح أسقف أورشليم أختاروه أسقفا ً بدلا ًعنه فاتسع أمامه مجال العلم والتعليم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Arian heresy had widely spread and St. Kyrollos strongly resisted it for that reason he was a target for the persecution of the Arian heretics. He was exiled three times from his diocese which he endured patiently and thankfully. He returned to his parish in the year 370 A.D. after the death of the Arian emperor Valens.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت الهرطقة الأريوسية قد انتشرت وكان القديس كيرلس من أشد المقاومين لها لذلك كان هدفا ً لسهام الهراطقة الأريوسيين حتى نفى عن كرسيه ثلاث مرات أحتملها كلها بصبر وشكر ورجع إلى كرسيه سنة 370 م بعد موت الملك فالنس الاريوسى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Kyrollos attended the second universal council at Constantinople in the year 381 A.D. and he was one of the prominent attendee of this council. He wrote many books about the Incarnation, the Creed and the baptism of the catechumens. When he finished his good endeavor departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               حضر هذا الأب مجمع القسطنطينية سنة 381 م وكان من أبرزالحاضرين فى المجمع. كتب هذا القديس كتبا ً كثيرة عن   التجسد وقانون الأيمان وعماد الموعوظين. ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Just Man Joseph of Arimathea</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البار يوسف الرامى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the just man Joseph of Arimathea, departed. He was from Arimathea a city of the Jews, who himself was also waiting for the kingdom of God. He was a wealthy, just and devout man.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً تنيح البار يوسف الرامى. كان من الرامة إحدى بلاد اليهودية وكان غنياً ورجلا ً صالحا ً بارا ً ( لو 23 : 50 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was a member of the Sanhedrim and in the same time a disciple of the Lord Christ . He did not attend the session of the Sanhedrim to plot against the Lord Jesus Christ to put Him to death for he did not agree with the Jews about His crucifixion.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان عضوا ً فى مجمع السنهدريم وفى نفس الوقت تلميذا ً للرب يسوع المسيح ( مت 27 : 57 ). ولم يحضر جلسة مجمع السنهدريم لمحاكمة الرب يسوع المسيح لأنه لم يكن موافقا ً لرأى اليهود على صلبه ( لو 23 : 51 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the death of the Lord Christ on the cross, he asked Pilate for the pure body to shroud and burry it and he commanded the body to be given to him. He took the body down from the Cross. St. Nicodemus participated with him in anointing the body of the Savior with a large quantity of spices and perfumes and wrapped it in linen cloth. “Joseph laid it in his new tomb which he had hewn out of the rock and he rolled a large stone against the door of the tomb and departed .”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد موت السيد المسيح على الصليب طلب من بيلاطس البنطى أن يستلم الجسد الطاهر لتكفينه ودفنه فسمح له فأنزل الجسد من على الصليب ولفه بكتان نقى وأشترك معه نيقوديموس بوضع كمية كبيرة من الحنوط والأطياب على جسد المخلص ثم وضعه يوسف فى قبره الجديد الذى كان قد نحته فى الصخرة ثم دحرج حجرا ً كبيرا ً على باب القبر ومضى" ( مت 27 : 60 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the resurrection of the Lord, he accompanied the apostles and after the coming down of the Holy Spirit he sold all his possessions and placed the proceeds at the hands of the apostles to serve the poor and the needy. Then he devoted himself to preach the faith of the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد قيامة الرب لازم الرسل وبعد حلول الروح القدس باع أملاكه ووضع ثمنها بين يدى الرسل لتوزيعها على الفقراء ثم خرج للبشارة بالسيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Michael, Bishop of Naqadah</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس ميخائيل أسقف نقادة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the honored father Anba Michael bishop of Naqadah, departed. He was consecrated bishop for Naqadah on the 12th of Mesore, year 1391 of the martyrs (1675 A.D.) by the hand of Pope Mettaos IV (102nd). He participated in the consecration of Pope Youannes the 16th (103rd). During his days the Dominican historian the monk Vanseleeb, visited him in Naqadah. After he shepherded his flock with the best of care, he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً تنيح الأب الأسقف صاحب الشيخوخة الحسنة والذكر الجميل الأنبا ميخائيل أسقف نقادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.23">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Third Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty third day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Great Prophet Daniel</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة الصديق العظيم دانيال النبى</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the last year of the reign of Cyrus, King of Babylon, the great and just prophet Daniel, one of the Major prophets, Departed. This prophet was born in the year 621 B.C., from the tribe of Judah in Jerusalem and he lived a virtuous life. He was taken captive when he was sixteen years old during the time of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon. He was captured along with the three holy young children Hananiah (Shadrach), Mishael (Meshach) and Azariah (Abed-Nego). Daniel purposed in his heart that he would not defile himself with the portion of the king’s delicacies. (Daniel 1:8)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               1 – فى مثل هذا اليوم من السنة الأخيرة لملك كورش ملك بابل تنيح الصديق العظيم دانيال النبى أحد الأنبياء الكبار. ولد هذا النبى فى سنة 621 ق. م. من سبط يهوذا بأورشليم وسلك سيرة فاضلة. سُبى إلى بابل وهو فى السادسة عشر من عمره فى زمن نبوخذ نصر ملك بابل. وكان معه الثلاثة فتية القديسين سدراك وميساك و أبدناغو.  وقد جعل فى قلبه أن لا يتنجس بأطايب الملك (دانيال 1 : 8 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the fourth year of captivity king Nebuchadnezzar saw a dream that troubled his spirit. (Daniel 2) When he woke up from his sleep, he could not remember the details of his dream. He gathered all the wise men of Babylon to tell him his dream and its meaning. When they could not he ordered to destroy all the wise men of Babylon including Daniel and the three young men. Daniel and the young men prayed to God to reveal to them the King's dream. God revealed to Daniel the dream and its interpretation. Daniel narrated to the king his dream and told him about the kings that would rule after him, and what would happen to them. Nebuchadnezzar was pleased with Daniel and gave him many great gifts and appointed him chief administrator over all the wise men of Babylon.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى السنة الرابعة من السبى أبصر نبوخذ نصر رؤيا أفزعته ( دا 2 : 1 – الخ ). فلما استيقظ من نومه نسيها فجمع كل حكماء بابل وطلب منهم معرفة مارآه وتفسيرة فلم يعرفوا. فأمر بقتلهم جميعا ً وكان من بينهم دانيال والثلاثة فتية وقد صلوا إلى الله فكشفت الرؤيا لدانيال الذى قص على الملك الرؤيا وأعلمه عن الملوك الذين سيملكون بعده وما سيحدث لهم. فاستحسن الملك قول دانيال ومنحه عطايا جزيلة وجعله رئيسا ً على حكماء بابل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Later on Nebuchadnezzar saw another dream, and Daniel also interpreted the dream for him. He told the king that because of his arrogance, God would drive him away from among men, to dwell among the beasts and would eat grass like oxen for seven years, and then God would bring him back to his kingdom. All what Daniel had told king Nebuchadnezzar were fulfilled. (Daniel 4:10-37)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ورأى الملك حلما ً آخر فسره له أيضا ً دانيال وعرفه أن الله لأجل تكبره سيطرده من بين البشر ويسكنه مع الوحوش سبع سنين يأكل فيها العشب مثل البهائم ثم يعيده إلى ملكه. فتم هذا الأمر للملك نبوخذ نصر ( دا 4 : 10 – 37 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Belshazzar reigned, he saw what the angel of the Lord had written on the wall, when king Belshazzar drank wine in the gold and silver vessels of the temple of the Lord "Mene, Mene, Tekel, and Upharsin” and Daniel interpreted these words to him saying:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما ملك بليشاصر رأى فى رؤيا كتابة:"منا منا تقيل فرسين " ففسرها له دانيال فقال:            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Mene means: God has numbered your kingdom and finished it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               " منا أى أحصى الله ملكوتك وأنهاه            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Tekel means: You have been weighed in the balances and found wanting.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتقيل أى وزنت بالموازين فوجدت ناقصا ً            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Upharsin means: your kingdom has been divided and given to the Medes and Persians.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فرسين أى قسمت مملكتك وأعطيت لفارس ومادى ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               That very night Belshazzar, king of the Chaldeans, was slain, and Darius the Mede received the kingdom. (Daniel 5)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان ذلك لأن الملك شرب خمرا ً فى آنية بيت الرب ( دا 5 : 1 – الخ ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the days of king Darius, he gave thought to setting Daniel over the whole kingdom. Daniel’s enemies asked the king to establish a royal statute; that whoever petitions any god or man for thirty days, except you, O king shall be cast into the den of lions. However, Daniel did not pray except to the God of heaven. They cast Daniel into the den of lions. The Lord sent his angel and shut the lions’ mouths. The next morning the king came to the den and found Daniel alive and he was exceedingly glad. He commanded to take Daniel up out of the den then he brought those men who had accused Daniel and cast them into the den of lions. The lions overpowered them and broke all their bones in pieces before they ever came to the bottom of the den. (Daniel 6:4-24)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى أيام داريوس المادى كان دانيال أول الوزراء فطلب أعداء دانيال من الملك أن يصدر أمرا ً بأن لاتقُدم صلاة إلا للملك فقط لمدة ثلاثين يوما ً. ولكن دانيال لم يصلي إلا إلى إله السماء فطُرح فى جب الأسود فأرسل الرب ملاكه وسد أفواه الأسود وأتى الملك فوجده حيا ً ففرح فأمر بإصعاده من الجب. ثم أنزل الملك الذين اشتكوا دانيال فى جب الأسود فبطشت بهم فى الحال ( دا 6 : 4 – 24 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Daniel prayed before the Lord and confessed the sins and iniquity of his people. In a vision it was revealed to him the seventy weeks to anoint the Most Holy. (Daniel 9)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد صلى دانيال أمام الرب واعترف بخطايا شعبه فأعُلنت له رؤيا السبعين أسبوعاً لمسح قدوس القديسين ( دا 9 : 1 – الخ ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Daniel also prophesied about the last day and the final judgment by saying; “And many of those who sleep in the dust of the earth shall awake, some to everlasting life, some to shame and everlasting contempt. Those who are wise shall shine like the brightness of the firmament, and those who turn many to righteousness like the stars forever and ever.” (Daniel 12:2-3)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتنبأ دانيال عن اليوم الأخير والدينونة العامة بقوله " وكثيرون من الراقدين فى تراب الأرض يستيقظون هؤلاء إلى الحياة الأبدية وهؤلاء إلى العار للازدراء الأبدي. والفاهمون يضيئون كضياء الجَلد والذين ردوا كثيرين إلى البر كالكواكب إلى أبد الدهور (دا 12 : 2 3 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he completed his endeavor, he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما كملت أيام جهاده تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of this great prophet be with us all, and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة هذا النبى العظيم فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.24">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Forth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty forth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Apparition of the Pure Virgin St. Mary on her church in Zeiton</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار ظهور القديسة العذراء مريم بكنيستها بالزيتون</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 1684 of the martyrs which coincided with the 2nd of April 1968 A.D., during the papacy of Pope Kyrollos VI, 116th Patriarch of Alexandria, the Theotokos, the pure Virgin St. Mary started to transfigure in luminous spiritual forms in and around the domes of her church in Zeiton, a suburb of Cairo.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 1684 للشهداء (الموافق 2 إبريل 1968 م ) وفى حبرية البابا كيرلس السادس ال 116 بدأت القديسة الطاهرة مريم والدة الإله فى التجلى بمناظر روحية على قباب كنيستها بالزيتون بالقاهرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This transfiguration continued in some nights for many hours before tens of thousands of people from every race and religion. This apparition lasted for a period of about two years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد استمرت هذه الظهورات الروحية فى بعض الليالى لعدة ساعات وكان ذلك على مدى عامين تقريبا ً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The pure Virgin had transfigured in different forms. At times she appeared in a full figure or in other times in a half figure in a cloud of heavenly white light. She was adorned with an angelic white dress holding in her hand an olive branch. Many spiritual signs accompanied these apparitions as the flying spiritual beings at night in the form of doves and the fragrance of incense whish was seen and smelled by thousands. They came to the church every night from every place inside and outside, the Egyptian land. They kept vigil all night, praising and singing hymns waiting for her blessed apparition.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد شاهدها الإلوف من جميع الأجناس والأديان بمناظر شتى فكانت تظهر أحيانا ً بهيئة كاملة أو نصفية فى سحابة من نور أبيض سماوى متوشحة برداء أبيض وتمسك فى يدها غصن زيتون وكان يصاحب هذا الظهور بعض الظواهر الروحية كالحمام يطير ليلاً والبخور الذى رآه واشتمه الآلاف الذين كانوا يتوافدون على الكنيسة كل ليلة من كل مكان بداخل البلاد المصرية وخارجها ساهرين الليل كله فى التسبيح منتظرين ظهورها المبارك.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               These apparitions accompanied by many healing miracles to many of different religions and races. The greatest miracle that accompanied this apparition is planting the faith and establishing it in the hearts.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد صاحب هذا الظهور معجزات شفاء لكثيرين من كل الأديان والأجناس. ومن أكبر المعجزات التى حققها هذا الظهور زرع الإيمان وتثبيته فى القلوب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The news of this apparition was covered by all the news media inside and outside the country. A great cathedral was built in the place of the garage across from the original church that was consecrated on the 2nd of April, 1989 A.D. by the Hand of Pope Shenouda III.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد تناقلت خبر هذا الظهور وظواهره الروحية جميع وسائل الإعلام الداخلية والخارجية. هذا وقد بنيت فى موضع الجراج المواجة للكنيسة كاتدرائية كبيرة تم تدشينها فى 2 إبريل عام 1989م بيد قداسة البابا شنوده الثالث.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of Our Lady and the pride of our race, the pure Virgin St. Mary be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة سيدتنا كلنا وفخر جنسنا القديسة العذراء الطاهرة. مريم فلتكن معنا آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Macarius I, 59th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا مكاريوس الأول البطريرك التاسع والخمسين من بطاركه الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 668 of the martyrs (952 A.D.) Pope Macarius I, 59th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This Holy Father was born in the city of Shoubra , to godly Christian parents. His father departed while he was young and became an only child to his mother. He desired the monastic life and became a monk in the monastery of St. Macarius in the wilderness of Shiheet (Scetis). He lived a good virtuous life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ًمن سنة 668 للشهداء ( 952 م ) تنيح القديس مكاريوس الأول البطريرك التاسع والخمسون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسة ولد هذا القديس فى بلدة شبرا ( قرية قريبة من دمنهور محافظة البحيرة) من أبوين مسيحيين تقيين توفى والده وهو صغير وأصبح وحيدا ً لأمه واشتاق لحياة الرهبنة فترهب بدير القديس مكاريوس ببرية شيهيت فسار سيرة صالحة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of Pope Kosma III, the bishops, priests and the archons (Lay-leaders) unanimously agreed to choose this father for the patriarchate. He was consecrated in the year 932 A.D., and after his enthronement he went to the monastery of St. Macarius as was the custom of his predecessors.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد نياحة البابا قسما الثالث اتفق رأى الآباء الأساقفة والكهنة والأراخنة على اختياره ليكون بطريركاً فرسموه سنة 932م. وبعد رسامته انطلق إلى دير القديس مكاريوس كعادة أسلافه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On his way back from the monastery, the people of his home town invited him to visit them. When he arrived to his home town, he went to visit his mother who was a righteous woman. When he had come to the house, he found her sitting down weaving and she did not greet him or paid attention to him. He thought that she did not know him, so he said to her; "Don't you know me, I am your son Macarius who had received the Patriarchal rank?" She answered him with tears in her eyes; "I know you and I know what you had received of honor and dignity. I cry on your behalf because before, you were responsible only for your own soul but now you are responsible about the souls of all your flock. Now do not neglect the salvation of your soul and the souls of all your people. Be aware lest the glory of the presidency put a veil on your eyes. Now I have warned you and remember your mother who labored in raising you." She said that and went on weaving as she did before.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وعند عودته من الدير دعاه أهل بلدته لزيارتهم فلَّبى دعوتهم ولما وصل إلى البلدة ذهب لافتقاد والدته وكانت امراة صالحة جالسة فى البيت تغزل فلم تلتفت إليه عند دخوله. فبادرها قائلاً : "ألاتعلمين أنى أنا ابنك مكاريوس الذى نال درجة البطريركية" فاجابته بدموع " إنى أعرفك وأعرف مقدار ما وصلت إليه من كرامة وإننى أبكى لأجلك لأنك كنت قبلاً مسئولا ً عن نفسك فقط أما الآن فسوف يسألك الله عن جميع خطايا الشعب فاهتم أولا ً بخلاص نفسك وأحذر لئلا يضع مجد الرئاسة برقعاً على عينيك ها قد أنذرتك. فأذكر والدتك التى تعبت فى تربيتك " قالت هذا واستأنفت عملها بالمغزل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               These words went on resounding in his ears all his life and an incentive for caring of his own salvation and to faithfully attend to his duties. He persevered in exhorting and guiding his people. He commanded the bishops and the priests to shepherd their flock and to protect them. He was very careful in choosing the bishops and priests following the command of the Holy Bible, “Do not lay hands on anyone hastily.” (1 Tim. 5:22) When he finished his good endeavor departed in peace after he had sat on the apostolic throne for 20 years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أستمرت هذه الكلمات ترن فى أذنيه طوال حياته وكانت سببا ً فى حرصه على خلاص نفسه وإتمام واجباته بأمانة. وكان يداوم على تعليم الشعب وإرشاده وعلى توجيه الأساقفة والكهنة لرعاية الشعب وحراسته كما كان مدققا ً فى إختيار الأساقفة والكهنة منفذاً قول الكتاب المقدس "لا تضع يداً على أحد بالعجلة " ( 1 تى 5 : 22 ). ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام بعد أن جلس على الكرسى المرقسى حوالى 20 عاما ً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. . ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.25">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Fifth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty fifth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Prisca, One of the Seventy Apostles</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس فريسكا أحد السبعين رسولا ً</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the great St. Prisca, one of the seventy apostles departed. This apostle was a Jew of the tribe of Benjamin and his parents kept the Law of Moses. He followed the Savior, listened to His teachings, and witnessed His miracles.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تنيح القديس فريسكا أحد السبعين رسولاً. كان يهوديا ً من سبط بنيامين ابناً لأبوين حافظين للناموس. تبع المخلص وسمع تعاليمه وشاهد معجزاته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Lord appointed the seventy apostles, this saint was one of them. He was present with the disciples in the upper room of Zion at the time of the coming of the Holy Spirit upon them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما عين الرب السبعين تلميذاً كان هذا القديس من بينهم وكان مع التلاميذ فى علية صهيون وقت حلول الروح القدس عليهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He preached the Gospel in many countries. Then he was ordained bishop for Khorinyas, where he preached its people and baptized them. And having finished his holy endeavor, he departed in peace and received the crown of the heavenly glory.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد بشر بالإنجيل فى بلاد كثيرة ثم رسم أسقفا ً على خورانياس فعلم أهلها وعمدهم. وبعد أن أكمل سعيه المقدس تنيح بسلام ونال إكليل المجد السماوى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Paul mentioned him to his disciple Timothy when he told him; “Greet Prisca and Aquila, and the household of Onesiphorus.” (2 Tim. 4:19).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد ذكره القديس بولس الرسول لتلميذه تيموثاوس بقوله :"سلم على فريسكا وأكيلا وبيت أنيسيفورس " ( 2 تى 4 : 19).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Onesiphorous, one of the Seventy Apostles</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس انيسيفورس أحد السبعين رسولا ً</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also St. Onesiphorus, one of the seventy apostles, was martyred. He served in Ephesus. When St. Paul was arrested and imprisoned in Rome, Onesiphorus visited him in prison, assisted and ministered unto him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى مثل هذا اليوم استشهد القديس أنيسيفورس وهو من السبعين رسولا ً خدم فى أفسس ولما قبض على بولس وسُجن فى روما زاره انيسيفورس فى السجن وخدمه وساعده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Later on Adrianus, governor of Ephesus, seized and tortured him severely. He was dragged amid the rocks and thorns, so he delivered his pure soul and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بعد ذلك قبض عليه أدريانوس والى أفسس وعذبه عذاباً شديداً ثم سحبه بين الصخور والأشواك فنال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St Paul praised him in his second epistle to St. Timothy saying; “The Lord grant mercy to the house of Onesiphorus for he often refreshed me and was not ashamed of my chains.” (2 Tim. 1:16-18)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد مدحه بولس الرسول فى رسالته إلى أفسس قائلاً: "ليعط الرب رحمة لبيت انيسيفورس لانه مراراً كثيرة أراحنى". (2 تى 1 : 16 – 18 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Mattheos III, the One Hundredth Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا متاؤس الثالث البطريرك المائة من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1362 of the martyrs (1646 A.D.) Pope Mattheos III, 100th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. He was born in Toukh el-Nasarah , to godly Christian parents who raised him well. They taught him the church books and the grace of God moved him to the angelic life. He became a monk in the monastery of St. Macarius in the wilderness of Shiheet. He lived a Godly life so they ordained him a priest then hegumen and appointed him abbot for the monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 1362 للشهداء ( 1646 م ) تنيح القديس البابا متاؤس الثالث البطريرك المائة من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية.  ولد بناحية طوخ النصارى (إحدى قرى محافظة المنوفية) من أبوين مسيحيين تقيين ربياه أحسن تربية وعلماه كتب الكنيسة ثم حركته نعمة الله إلى السيرة الملائكية. فترهب بدير القديس مكاريوس فسار سيرة صالحة فرسموه قسا ًثم قمصا ورئيسا ًعلى الدير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Yoannis XV departed, the bishops, archons (Lay-leaders) and all the people unanimously agreed to chose him Patriarch. He was consecrated Patriarch by the name of Pope Mattheos III in the year 1631 A.D.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تنيح البابا يوحنا الخامس عشر اجتمع رأى الآباء الأساقفة والأراخنة و الشعب على أختياره بطريركاً فرسموه بطريركا ًباسم البابا متاؤس سنة 1631م.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he was enthroned on the apostolic throne, he shepherded Christ's flock with the best of care. Peace and tranquility prevailed in the church. Nevertheless, Satan envied him so he moved a wicked person against the Pope. He accused him before the ruler of Egypt who asked the Pope to pay a huge fine. His flock cooperated with him in paying this fine.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما جلس على الكرسى المرقسى رعى رعية المسيح أحسن رعاية وشمل الكنيسة هدوء وسلام. لكن الشيطان حسده وحرك أحد الأشرار فوشى به عند الوالى فطلب منه الوالى غرامة كبيره تعاون معه الشعب فى دفعها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his time a great famine befell the land of Egypt because of which many of the people died. This Pope ordained a metropolitan for the Ethiopian church. When he completed his good endeavor departed in peace in his hometown Toukh and was buried in its church.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى زمنه وقع غلاء عظيم فى كل أرض مصر مات بسببه عدد كبير من الشعب. وقد رسم هذا البابا مطرانا ً لبلاد الحبشة. ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام فى بلدة طوخ ودفن بكنيستها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. . ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.26">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Sixth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty sixth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Euphrasia (Eupraxia), the virgin</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديسة براكسيا العذراء</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day St. Euphrasia (Eupraxia) the virgin departed. This saint was born in the city of Rome to a noble family, who was related to Emperor Honorius. Before her father's departure, he asked the Emperor to look after her.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم تنيحت القديسة براكسيا العذراء. ولدت هذه القديسة بمدينة روما من أبوين من عظمائها ومن عائلة الملك أندريوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the repose of her father, her mother went to Egypt to collect the revenues and rent of her estates and orchards, which her husband had left her. She took her daughter, who was nine years of age, with her, and they lodged in one of the convents. The nuns of that convent were on a high degree of asceticism and piety.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد وفاة والدها مضت والدتها إلى مصر لتحصيل أجرة الأراضى التى تركها لها زوجها وأحضرت معها أبنتها وكان عمرها تسع سنوات. فتركت بأحد أديرة العذارى وكانت راهبات ذلك الدير على غاية من النسك والتقشف.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Eupraxia loved the monastic life and asked her mother to leave her in the convent. Because of her persistence and the sincerity of her intentions, her mother gave all her money and goods to the poor and needy, and she lived with her daughter in the convent for many years then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فأحبت الصبية حياة الرهبنة وطلبت من والدتها أن تبقى فى الدير وأمام إلحاحها وصدق نواياها قامت الوالدة بتوزيع أموالها على المساكين وأقامت معها فى الدير عده سنين ثم تنيحت بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Honorius heard that, he sent asking the saint to return to Rome. She answered back saying that she had vowed herself to the Lord Christ. The Emperor marveled at her wisdom and righteousness in spite of her young age and allowed her to stay.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما سمع الملك أندريوس هذا الخبر فأرسل يطلب القديسة فأجابته قائلة بأنها قد نذرت نفسها للسيد المسيح.فتعجب الملك من تقواها رغم صغر سنها وتركها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Eupraxia contended strenuously in the ascetic life, she fasted days at a time; she wore sackcloth and slept on the floor. She dedicated time to study the Holy Scriptures along with incessant praising. Satan envied her, and he smote her with an illness in her legs which gave her severe pain for a long time, until God had compassion on her and healed her. God granted her the gift of healing the sick. She was beloved by all the sisters and the abbess for her humility and immense obedience to them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أما هى فسارت سيرة فاضلة فى نسك وعبادة تطوى الأيام فى الصوم وتلبس المسوح وتفترش الأرض وكانت تكرس وقتا لدراسة الكتاب المقدس مع التسبيح المستمر. فحسدها الشيطان وضربها فى رجلها ضربة آلمتها زمانا ً طويلا ً إلى أن تحنن الرب عليها وشفاها. وقد أنعم الرب عليها بموهبة شفاء المرضى وكانت محبوبة من الأخوات والأم الرئيسة لطاعتها العظيمة لهن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When her departure drew near, she fell ill with a severe fever. The nuns gathered around her and she comforted and encouraged them. She raised her eyes toward the heaven, signed herself with the sign of the cross then delivered her pure soul.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما دنت ساعة انتقالها مرضت بحمى شديدة وقد جلست الراهبات حولها فظلت تشجعهن ثم رفعت عينيها نحو السماء ورشمت نفسها بعلامة الصليب وفاضت روحها الطاهرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Peter VI, 104th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا بطرس السادس البطريرك المائة والرابع من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1442 of the martyrs (1726 A.D.) Pope Peter VI, 104th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This Holy Father was born in the city of Assiut to Christian parents. They called him Mourgan and raised him with a Christian upbringing.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ًمن سنة 1442 للشهداء ( 1726 م ) تنيح القديس البابا بطرس السادس البطريرك المائة والرابع من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا القديس فى مدينة اسيوط من أبوين مسيحيين أسمياه (مرجان) وربياه تربية مسيحية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The grace of God was upon him since his young age. He went and became a monk in the monastery of the saint Anba Antonios. He exerted himself in prayers and reading the holy books. Pope Youannis XVI ordained him a priest and appointed him an abbot for the monastery of the great Saint Anba Paula the first hermit.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               . وكانت نعمة الله حالة عليه منذ صغره فمضى وترهب بدير القديس الأنبا أنطونيوس فكان يُجهد نفسه في الصلوات والقراءات فرسمه البابا يوأنس (١١٦) قساً وعينه رئيساً على دير الأنبا بولا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Youannis (103rd Patriarch) departed and the Patriarchal throne became vacant, the bishops, the priests and the Archons fasted and prayed and the altar lot fell on this father. He was consecrated Patriarch on the 17th of Mesore, year 1434 of the martyrs (1718 A.D.)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما خلا الكرسى البطريركى صام الآباء الأساقفة والكهنة والأراخنة وصلوا فوقعت القرعة عليه ورسموه يوم 17 مسرى 1434 للشهداء ( 1708 م ) بطريركا ً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He shepherded the flock with the best of care and he visited Lower and Upper Egypt and the people of the country rejoiced. He consecrated bishops and built many churches. He emphasized that divorce only be granted in case of adultery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فرعى رعيته أحسن رعاية وقام بافتقاد الوجهين البحرى والقبلى ورسم أساقفة وبنى كنائس عديدة واهتم بأن لا يكون هناك تطليق إلا لعلة الزنا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he finished his good endeavor departed in peace and his flock wept for his departure. He was buried with great veneration in the tomb of the Patriarchs in the church of the martyr Mercurius Abu-Saifain in Old Cairo.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام فبكاه شعبه وكفنوه ودفنوه بإكرام جزيل فى مقبرة الآباء البطاركة بكنيسة الشهيد مرقوريوس أبى سيفين بمصر القديمة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.27">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Seventh Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty seventh day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Crucifixion of Our Lord Jesus Christ</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">صلب ربنا يسوع المسيح بالجسد من أجل خلاص العالم</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 34 A.D Our Lord Jesus Christ was crucified in the flesh for the salvation of the world. The Holy Bible testified that; "From the sixth hour until the ninth hour there was darkness over all the land." (Matthew 27:45) The Lord Christ yielded up His spirit, the veil of the temple was torn, the earth quaked, the rocks were split and many bodies of the saints who had fallen asleep were raised. The Son by His crucifixion has fulfilled the marvelous salvation            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 34 م صلب ربنا بالجسد من أجل خلاص العالم وكانت ظلمة على الأرض كلها من الساعة السادسة إلى الساعة التاسعة ثم فارقت نفس السيد المسيح جسده فتشققت الصخور وانشق حجاب الهيكل وقام كثير من أجساد القديسين الراقدين. وأتم الابن بصليبه الخلاص العجيب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               To Him is the Glory, Power and Dominion forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فليشملنا ببركاته ويعيننا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Macarius the Great</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس مكاريوس الكبير أب رهبان برية شيهيت</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, of the year 106 of the martyrs (390 A.D.) the blessed father, the lamp of the wilderness and the father of all monks of Shiheet, Anba Macarius the great (Maqar), departed. This Saint was born in the village of Shabsheer, district of Menuf in the year 300 A.D. His father was a priest called Abraham and had no children. In a vision he saw the angel of the Lord who told him that God will give him a son, and his repute will be known all over the earth, and will become a father to many spiritual children.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 106 للشهداء ( 390 م ) تنيح الأب المغبوط اللابس الروح أب رهبان برية شيهيت القديس مكاريوس الكبير ولد هذا القديس فى شبشير مركز منوف سنة 300 م. كان والده كاهنا ً اسمه إبراهيم. لم يكن له ولد ورأى فى رؤيا ملاك الرب يقول له أن الله سيرزقه ولدا ً يكون ذكره شائعا ً فى أقطار الأرض ويصير أبا لبنين روحانيين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Shortly after, he begot this saint and called him Macarius which means "Blessed." He was obedient to his parents, and the grace of God was upon him. When he grew up his father pressed him to get married against his will, so he pretended to be ill for several days. Then he asked for his father’s permission to go to the wilderness for rest and seclusion. In the wilderness he saw a vision, a Cherub, with wings, held his hands, and took him up to the top of the hill, and told him; "God has granted this desert to you and your sons after you as an inheritance."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد قليل رزق بهذا القديس فسماه مكاريوس أى الطوباوى. وكان مطيعا ً لوالديه فحلت عليه نعمة الله. ولما كبر زوجه والده بغير إرادته فتظاهر بالمرض أياما ً ثم استسمح أباه أن يمضى إلى البرية ليطلب الخلوة والراحة فسمح له وفى البرية أبصر رؤيا كأن كاروبا ًذا أجنحة أمسك بيده وأصعده على رأس الجبل وقال له " إن الله قد أعطاك هذا الجبل ميراثا ًلك ولبنيك من بعدك".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he returned from the wilderness he found his wife, who was still virgin, had died. Shortly after, his parents departed, and he gave all what they had left for him to the poor. He went to Shanshour and dwelt in a hut in the outskirts of the city. When the fame of his virtues became well known, they took him to the bishop of Ashmun who ordained him a priest for them. They went to him to confess and partake from the Holy Mysteries. They appointed for him a servant to take care of his needs and to sell the work of his hands.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما عاد من البرية وجد أن زوجته قد تنيحت وهى عذراء وبعد ذلك تنيح أبواه فوزع كل ما تركاه له على الفقراء ومضى إلى شنشور وسكن فيها. ولما ذاع صيت فضائله أخذوه إلى أسقف أشمون فرسمه قسا ًعلى شنشور. وكانوا يأتون إليه للتناول من الأسرار المقدسة وعينوا له خادما ً ليبيع له عمل يديه وقضاء ما يحتاجه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Satan saw St. Macarius eminent growth in virtues, he inspired a girl that had defiled herself with a young man to claim that the priest Macarius was the one committed that evil with her. The family of this young girl went to him, insulted and beaten him, they also compelled him to take care of the child and his mother. . When the delivery hour came, the young girl continued to suffer for four days and did not deliver until she confessed her false accusation against the Saint. The family of the girl went to the saint to ask for forgiveness. When St. Macarius heard that, he fled away to the wilderness of Shiheet and he was thirty years old.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لما رأى الشيطان سموه فى الفضيلة أوعز إلى فتاة كانت قد ارتكبت الخطية مع شاب بأن تدعى أن القس مكاريوس هو الذى ارتكب معها هذا الشر. فمضى إليه أهل الفتاة وأهانوه وضربوه وألزموه بأن يتكفل بالطفل وأمه. فلما أتت ساعه الولاده ظلت الفتاة أربعه أيام معذبة ولم تلد حتى أعترفت بافترائها على القديس. فرجع أهل الفتاة يطلبون من القديس المغفرة فهرب ومضى إلى برية شيهيت وهو فى الثلاثين من عمره.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Macarius dwelt in the current location of el-Baramus monastery. He persevered in fasting, prayer, reading the Holy Scriptures and contemplation.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وسكن فى موضع دير البراموس الحالى وواظب على الصلاة والصوم والقراءة والتأمل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Then he went to visit St. Antonios, who received St. Macarius with joy and told him; “You shall be blessed as your name.” St. Antonios put on him the monastic Eskeem. He returned to his place and many gathered around him. His fame became well known and many kings heard about the many miracles that God performed by his hands. He healed the daughter of the king of Antioch that was possessed by an unclean spirit. The angel of the Lord appeared to him, took him up to the top of the hill, nearby the salty western lake, and told him to take this place as his dwelling. He built a cell for himself and a church which is currently known as St. Macarius monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم ذهب القديس لزيارة القديس الأنبا أنطونيوس فأستقبله وقال له " إنك عتيد أن تصير مغبوطا ً كاسمك" وألبسه إسكيم الرهبنة ورجع إلى قلايته فاجتمع حوله كثيرون وذاع صيته وسمع الملوك بكثرة العجائب التى كان يعملها. ثم ظهر له ملاك الرب وأتى به إلى رأس الجبل عند البحيرة الغربية المالحة وأعلمه بأن يتخذ له هذا المكان سكنا ً. فبنى لنفسه قلاية وكنيسة وهى المعروفة حالياً بدير القديس مكاريوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the devil’s warfare intensified against him, he went a second time to Anba Antonius seeking his advice for himself and for the monks that gathered around him. He faced many hardships for the sake of defending the Orthodox faith during the days of the Arian Emperor Valens. He exiled him to the island of Philae, south of Aswan, in Upper Egypt where he saved the daughter of the pagan priest of this island. She was possessed with an evil spirit that tormented her. Subsequently the priest and the people of the island believed in the Lord Christ. Afterwards he returned to his monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما ازدادت عليه حرب العدو مضى مرة أخرى لأخذ نصائح القديس الأنبا أنطونيوس بخصوصه وبخصوص الرهبان الذين اجتمعوا حوله. وقد نال هذا الأب شدائد كثيرة فى سبيل دفاعه عن الإيمان القويم أيام الإمبراطور فالنس الاريوسى الذى نفاه إلى جزيرة فيله جنوب أسوان وهناك أنقذ ابنة كاهن الأوثان من شيطان كان يعذبها فآمن هو وكل سكان الجزيرة بالسيد المسيح وبعدها عاد إلى ديره.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Holy Father distinguished by his meekness, love of his children and his forbearance with them. He also covered their weaknesses to the point that once he heard a voice from heaven saying to him; “Blessed are you O Macarius for you have imitated your creator in covering weaknesses like Him.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و تميز هذا القديس باتضاعه ومحبته لأولاده وطول أناته عليهم وكان يستر على عيوبهم. حتى جاءه صوت من السماء يقول " طوباك يامكاريوس الروحانى يا من تشبهت بخالقك تستر العيوب مثله ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he completed his good endeavor, the Sts. Antonios and Pachomius came with a company of the angels and saints. Then he delivered his pure soul in the hand of the Lord. He was ninety years old and his body still present in his monastery in the wilderness of Shiheet.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل جهاده الحسن حضر القديسان أنطونيوس وباخوميوس وجماعة من الملائكة والقديسين وأستودع روحه الطاهرة بيد الرب عن عمر يناهز التسعين عاما ً ومايزال جسده بديره العامر ببرية شيهيت.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Domicos</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس دوميكيوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 78 of the martyrs (362 A.D.) St. Domicos was martyred. He was a native of the city of Antioch. He lived a pious and righteous life in seclusion in an isolated place. His fame became well known for God had granted him the gift of performing healing signs and casting out demons. Multitudes gathered around him seeking the blessing and healing.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 78 للشهداء ( 362 م ) استشهد القديس دوميكيوس. كان من أهل أنطاكيه عائشا ً فى النسك والتقوى منفردا ً فى مكان منعزل وقد ذاع صيته إذ وهبه الله عمل معجزات الشفاء وإخراج الشياطين فكانت الجموع تتقاطر حوله ملتمسة البركة والشفاء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Julian the infidel passed by that place and saw this multitude of men and women and knew of his account became angry.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأثناء مرور الإمبراطور يوليانوس الكافر رأى هذه الجموع وعرف بخبر هذا القديس فغضب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He brought the saint and told him; "If you are living in this cave to please God so why you are seeking the gratitude of men? And why don't you hide yourself from them?" The Saint replied saying: "I have given my soul and body to the hands of God, the God of heaven and earth, the Lord Jesus Christ, and spent many years in seclusion in this cave as for those who come to me with a strong faith, I can’t dismiss them."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               واستحضره وقال له " إن كنت تقيم فى هذه المغارة لتنال رضى الله فلماذا تتوخى رضى الناس ؟ ولماذا لا تختفى عنهم ؟" فأجابه القديس قائلا ً " لقد سلمت نفسى وجسدى فى يدى الله إله السموات والأرض الرب يسوع المسيح. وقضيت عدة سنين معتزلا ً فى هذه المغارة أما هذه الجماهير الذين يأتون عندى بإيمان قوى فلا أستطيع أن أطردهم ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Emperor heard his answer, he ordered his men to seal the door of the cave on him where he delivered his soul and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما سمع الإمبراطور إجابته أمر جنوده أن يسدوا باب المغارة عليه ففاضت روحه ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.28">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Eighth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty eighth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Emperor Constantine the Great</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة الإمبراطور قسطنطين الكبير</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 53 of the martyrs (337 A.D.) Emperor Constantine the great, departed. He was born in the year 272 A.D. and his father's name was Constantius Chlorus and his mother's name was Helena. Constantius reigned over Byzantium, Maximianus reigned over Rome, and Diocletian reigned over Antioch and Egypt. Constantius was heathen, but loved to do good, compassionate and merciful. Once he went to the city of el-Ruha (Urfa, Edessa) and there he saw Helena and he married her. She was a Christian, and she brought forth Constantine. She raised him up well, sowed in his heart mercy and compassion for the Christians, but she did not dare to have him baptized.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 53 للشهداء ( 337 م ) تنيح الملك البار قسطنطين الكبير. ولد سنة 274 م واسم أبيه قونسطا وأمه القديسة هيلانة. وبينما كان أبوه ملكا ً على بيزنطية كان مكسيمانوس ملكا ًعلى روما ودقلديانوس ملكاً على أنطاكية ومصر. وكان والده قونسطا وثنيا ً إلا انه كان رحوما ًمحبا ً للخير واتفق انه مضى إلى الرها وهناك رأى هيلانة فتزوجها وكانت مسيحية فأنجبت قسطنطين وربته تربية حسنة وكانت تبث فى قلبه الرحمة والشفقة على المسيحيين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Constantine grew up he married Maximianus Caesar’s daughter who bestowed on him the title Caesar, after his father's death in the year 306 A.D. When he received the kingdom, he reigned with justice and integrity, and all the people loved him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما كبر تزوج أبنة مكسيمانوس قيصر بعد وفاة والده سنة 306 م فأعطاه لقب قيصر فتسلم المملكة ونشر العدل والإنصاف فأحبه الجميع.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The nobles of Rome sent asking him to come and save them from the injustice of Maxentius. Constantine marched with his army toward Rome to save them. He asked the Christians to pray for his sake. During the war he saw in the heaven, in the middle of the day, a shining Cross made of stars, and under it was written in Greek; "With this you shall conquer." The light of the Cross was more shinning than that of the sun; he pointed it out to the nobles of his kingdom and the commanders of his army. He ordered to prepare a large flag with the sign of the cross on it. Then he engaged with Maxentius in a war, overcame him, and was drowned in the Tiber River with most of his soldiers. Constantine entered Rome and its entire people welcomed him with joy and gladness. Constantine became the Emperor of the East and the West.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               زحف لمحاربة مكسنديوس ملك إيطاليا وطلب من المسيحيين أن يصلوا من أجله وفى أثناء الحرب رأى فى السماء فى أثناء الحرب رأى فى السماء فى نصف النهار صليبا ًمنيرا ًجدا ًمكونا ًمن كواكب مكتوباً تحته باللغة اليونانية " بهذا تغلب " وكان ضياؤه يشع أكثر من نور الشمس فأراه لوزرائه وقواد جيشه ثم أمر بعمل علم كبير ورسم عليه علامة الصليب. ثم اشتبك فى الحرب مع مكسنديوس فهزمه وأغرقه فى نهر التيبر هو ومعظم جنوده ودخل قسطنطين روما فاستقبله أهلها بالفرح والتهليل وأصبح قسطنطين ملكا ً على الشرق والغرب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When his affairs settled in Rome, he sent throughout the kingdom commanding to set free all the Christians who were imprisoned for the sake of their faith. He also ordered that they should not work during the Passion Week as the Apostles commanded. He also sent his mother Helena to Jerusalem to search for the Holy Cross; she found it, built the church of Resurrection where she placed the Holy Cross.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما استقر به المقام فى روما اعتمد مع أغلب جنوده على يد سلبطرس أسقف روما فى السنة الحادية عشر من ملكه. ثم أصدر أمرا ً فى سائر أنحاء المملكة بإطلاق المسيحيين المسجونين بسبب إيمانهم كما أمر أن لا يشتغل أحد فى أسبوع الآلام كأوامر الرسل. كما أرسل أمه الملكة هيلانة إلى أورشليم للبحث عن الصليب المقدس فوجدته وبنت كنيسة القيامة ووضعت فيها الصليب المقدس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the seventeenth year of his reign, the First Ecumenical Council of the 318 bishops assembled in the city of Nicea in the year 325 A.D. This council condemned the Arian heresy, put down the Nicene Creed of faith, and many other canons which arranged the affairs of the Christian church. Constantine rebuilt the city of Byzantium and called it after his name "Constantinople." He built many churches in it and relocated to them many of the relics of the apostles and the saints.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى السنة السابعة عشر من ملكه والتى توافق 325 م اجتمع المجمع المقدس المسكونى الأول فى مدينة نيقية الذى حرم بدعة أريوس وأصدر قانون الإيمان النيقاوى مع عدة قوانين أخرى رتب بها أمور الكنيسة المسيحية أحسن ترتيب ثم جدد قسطنطين مدينة بيزنطية ودعاها باسمه القسطنطينية وبنى فيها الكثير من الكنائس وأحضر إليها أجساد الكثيرين  من الرسل والقديسين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he finished his good endeavor departed in peace in the city of Nicomedia. They laid him in a gold sarcophagus and carried him to Constantinople. The Patriarch, bishops, priests, and all the people received him with prayers and spiritual hymns, and laid him in the church of the Apostles in the tomb that he had prepared for himself.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام فى نيقوميديا فوضعوه فى تابوت من ذهب وحملوه إلى القسطنطينية فاستقبله البطريرك والكهنة بالصلوات والتسابيح الروحية ودفنوه فى كنيسة الرسل فى المقبرة التى أعدها لنفسه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               To Our God is the glory, might, and dominion and may His mercy and grace be upon us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Peter (Petros) VII, 109thnPatriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة البابا بطرس السابع البطريرك المائة والتاسع من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1568 of the martyrs (1852 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Peter (Petros) VII, 109th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This father was born in the village of Gawly , and he was called Petros el-Gawly. He became a monk in the monastery of the great St. Antonios. Because of his good repute and many virtues he was ordained a priest then hegumen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 1578 للشهداء ( 1852 م ) تنيح القديس البابا بطرس السابع البطريرك المائة والتاسع من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا القديس بقرية الجاولى (قرية بمركز منفلوط محافظة أسيوط). لذلك لقب "بالجاولى" ترهب بدير القديس الأنبا أنطونيوس ولحسن سيرته وكثرة فضائله رسموه قسا ً ثم قمصاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When his report reached Pope Marcus (Mark) VIII, he summoned him to be ordained as a metropolitan for Ethiopia but instead he ordained him a general bishop in the year 1808 A.D. He called him Theophilus and dwelt in the Patriarchal place to assist Pope Marcus in his pastoral duties.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما بلغ خبره إلى البابا مرقس الثامن أستدعاه لكى يرسمه مطرانا ً على الحبشة ولكنه رسمه أسقفاً عاما ًللكرازة سنة 1808م باسم الأنبا ثاوفيلس وأقام فى الدار البطريركية يساعد البابا مرقس فى مهام الرعاية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Marcus departed everyone unanimously agreed to consecrate Anba Theophilus, the general bishop, as his successor. They enthroned him Patriarch by the name Pope Peter VII in the year 1810 A.D.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تنيح البابا مرقس أجمع رأى الجميع على إقامة الأنبا ثاوفيلس الأسقف العام خليفة له فأجلسوه بطريركا ً باسم البابا بطرس السابع سنة 1810م.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint was ascetic in his food and clothing. He was adorned with meekness and humility. He devoted himself to studying, reading and learning the Holy Book. The church during his pontificate enjoyed peace and tranquility. Pope Peter greatly despised simony and did not ordain anyone in any of the priestly ranks unless he was sure of his suitability for such service.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان هذا القديس ناسكا ً فى مأكله وملبسه متوشحا ً بالوداعة والاتضاع واسع الإطلاع وقد نالت الكنيسة فى عهد سلاما وطمأنينة. وكان البابا بطرس يبغض السيمونية جداً ولا يقوم برسامة أحد فى أى رتبة من رتب الكهنوت إلا بعد التأكد من صلاحيته لهذه الخدمة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One year the water of the Nile had substantially decreased. The ruler of Egypt asked the Pope to pray for the rising of the water of the Nile. Pope Peter VII erected a tent on the bank of the river where he celebrated the Divine Liturgy along with the bishops, priests and people. After the prayers of the Divine Liturgy, he washed the Service utensils then he threw the water and a blessed Kourban (Blessed Bread) in the Nile. Immediately the waves of the Nile rose up to the tent wherein they celebrated the Divine Liturgy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى أيامه انخفضت مياه النيل فطلب منه الحاكم الصلاة من أجل ارتفاع مياه النيل فأقام البابا خيمة على شاطئ النيل ورفع فيها صلوات القداس الإلهى هو والأساقفة والكهنة والشعب.  وبعد انتهاء القداس وغسل الأوانى صب بعض الماء فى الأوانى وطرح هذه المياه فى النيل وللحال ارتفع ماء النيل حتى وصل إلى الخيمة التى أقيم فيها القداس الإلهى.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his papacy also Ibrahim Pasha, the son of Muhammad Ali Pasha, who was also the ruler over Syria, knew of the Holy Fire (Light) that proceeds from the Holy Sepulcher on Bright Saturday in Jerusalem. He asked Pope Peter VII to come to Jerusalem to verify the truth of what he had heard. Accordingly he went and the Holy Light appeared and Ibrahim Pasha personally witnessed it. This incident proved the validity of the appearance of the Holy Light. Ibrahim Pasha revered Pope Petros el-Gawly and he returned to Cairo with great honor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى عهده وصل الخبر إلى إبراهيم باشا الذى كان والياً على الشام بأن النور المقدس يظهر من قبر السيد المسيح يوم سبت النور. فاستدعى إبراهيم باشا البابا بطرس الجاولى ليحضر إلى أورشليم ليتحقق منه صدق هذا الكلام. وفعلا ً ظهر النور المقدس ورآه إبراهيم باشا بنفسه وبهذا الحدث تأكدت صحة الإيمان فى النور المقدس وكرم إبراهيم باشا البابا بطرس الجاولى وأعاده إلى القاهرة بكل إكرام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One of the great events that immortalized the memory of Pope Petros and assured the patriotism of the Coptic Church; the Russian Caesar sent to the Pope a Prince offering to put the Coptic Church under the protection of Caesar. The Pope refused the proposal graciously, with a spiritual wisdom and deep-rooted patriotism by asking; "Does your Caesar live forever?" When the envoy answered that he would die like all human beings, the Pope replied; “We are under the protection of the King that does not die that is the Lord Jesus Christ.” The prince admired the Pope's faith and patriotism. When Mohammed Ali the ruler of Egypt heard that, he exalted the Pope and admired him and was assured of the patriotism of the Coptic Church. When Pope Petros VII finished his good endeavor departed in peace. He was buried in St. Mark church in El-Azbakiah.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ومن الأحداث الشهيرة التى خلدت ذكرى البابا بطرس وأكدت وطنية الكنيسة القبطية أن قيصر روسيا أوفد إلى البابا أحد الأمراء ليعرض عليه أن يتم وضع الكنيسة القبطية تحت حماية القبصر فرفض البابا هذا العرض بحكمة روحية ووطنية أصيله إذ سأل الأمير :"هل ملككم سيموت؟" قال له الأمير :" نعم "  ، فقال البابا "نحن تحت حماية ملك لايموت وهو الرب يسوع المسيح". ولما سمع الوالى محمد على بهذا الكلام ارتفع قدر البابا بطرس الجاولى فى عينيه كثيرا ً وتأكد من وطنية الكنيسة القبطية. ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام ودفن فى الكنيسة المرقسية الكبرى بالأزبكية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Anba Sarabamon, known as "Abu Tarha" Bishop of El-Menufia</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس الإنبا صرابامون الشهير بأبى طرحة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1569 of the martyrs (1853 A.D.) the Holy Father Anba Sarabamon, known as "Abu Tarha, The Veiled " Bishop of El-Monufia, departed. He was born in one of the villages of el-Sharqia to pious Christian parents. They called him Saleeb and raised him up with a true Christian upbringing.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 1569 للشهداء ( 1853 م ) تنيح القديس الأنبا صرابامون أسقف المنوفية الشهير "بأبى طرحة" (سُمى بأبى طرحة لانه كان يضع شالا ً على رأسه نازلاً على وجهه). ولد هذا القديس بإحدى بلاد الشرقية من أبوين مسيحيين تقيين أسمياه "صليب" ربياه تربية مسيحية حقيقية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he grew he worked in selling oil. One day an evil woman accused him of killing her son in the market. Saleeb asked God to exonerate him from this false accusation. In the court and before the judge, Anba Sarabamon ordered the dead child to rise up to tell the judge the truth. The child rose up and testified to the innocence of the saint before everyone. As a result of this miracle Saleeb fled the vainglory and went immediately to St. Antonius monastery where he became a monk.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما كبر اشتغل ببيع الزيت وحدث أن أمرأة شريرة أدعت عليه بانه قتل أبنها ووصل الأمر إلى القاضى فأمر الأنبا صرابامون الطفل الميت بالقيام ليخبر القاضى بالحقيقة فقام الطفل وشهد ببراءته أمام الجميع وعلى أثر هذه المعجزة ذهب وترهب بدير القديس الأنبا أنطونيوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the monastery, he grew in virtues until Pope Petros el-Gawly chose him a Bishop for El-Monufia against his wish. He was one of Pope Petros famous bishops. God had granted him the gift of healing the sick, and casting out evil spirits.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وهناك نما فى الفضيلة حتى أختير أسقفا ً لكرسي المنوفية على غير إرادته وقد منحه الله موهبة شفاء الأمراض وإخراج الأرواح الشريرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He cast out an unclean spirit from princes Zahra the daughter of Mohammed Ali Pasha. He cast out many evil spirits by the power of the cross.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فقد أخرج الروح النجس من الأميرة زهرة أبنة محمد على باشا وأرواح نجسة كثيره كان يخرجها بقوة الصليب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint loved giving in secret. He carried a basket that had gifts which he distributed himself to the needy without anyone knowing his identity. He was also known for his simplicity and wisdom. The Lord hearkened to his prayers especially for those asked him to pray to the Lord to grant them children. He had spiritual transparency for he could foretell some future events. After he finished his good strife departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان هذا القديس محبا ً للعطاء فى الخفاء فكان يحمل قفصا ً به بعض العطايا يوزعها بنفسه على المحتاجين دون أن يعرفه أحد واشتهر أيضا ً بالبساطة والحكمة وكان الرب يسمع صلواته خصوصاً عمن يطلب منه أن يصلى من أجله لكى يعطيه الرب نسلا ً كما كانت له الشفافية الروحية التى بها يعرف بعض الأمور المستقبلية. وبعد أن أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. . ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.29">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Ninth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty ninth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع والعشرون من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Feast of the Glorious Annunciation</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">عيد البشارة المجيد</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The church celebrates today the glorious feast of Annunciation. When the appointed time by God since eternity for the salvation of mankind had come, God sent Gabriel the Archangel to a city of Galilee named Nazareth, to a virgin betrothed to a man whose name was Joseph, of the house of David. The virgin's name was Mary. And having come in, the angel said to her, "Rejoice, highly favored one, the Lord is with you; blessed are you among women!" But when she saw him, she was troubled at his saying, and considered what manner of greeting this was. Then the angel said to her, "Do not be afraid, Mary, for you have found favor with God. And behold, you will conceive in your womb and bring forth a Son, and shall call His name JESUS. He will be great, and will be called the Son of the Highest; and the Lord God will give Him the throne of His father David. And He will reign over the house of Jacob forever, and of His kingdom there will be no end." Then Mary said to the angel, "How can this be, since I do not know a man?" And the angel answered and said to her, "The Holy Spirit will come upon you, and the power of the Highest will overshadow you; therefore, also, that Holy One who is to be born will be called the Son of God … For with God nothing will be impossible." Then Mary said, "Behold the maidservant of the Lord! Let it be to me according to your word." And the angel departed from her. (Luke 1:26-36)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تحتفل الكنيسة اليوم بعيد البشارة المجيد. فانه لما جاء الوقت المعين منذ الأزل من الله لخلاص جنسنا أرسل الله رئيس الملائكة جبرائيل " إلى مدينة من الجليل اسمها ناصرة إلى عذراء مخطوبة لرجل من بيت داود اسمه يوسف واسم العذراء مريم فدخل إليها الملاك وقال " سلام لك أيتها الممتلئة نعمة الرب معك مباركة أنت فى النساء " فلما رأته اضطربت من كلامه وفكرت ما عسى أن تكون هذه التحية. فقال لها الملاك: "لا تخافى يامريم لأنك وجدت نعمة عند الله وها أنت ستحبلين وتلدين ابناً وتسمينه يسوع هذا يكون عظيما ً وابن العلى يدعى ويعطيه الرب الإله كرسى داود أبيه ويملك على بيت يعقوب إلى الأبد ولا يكون لملكه نهاية "فقالت مريم للملاك : " كيف يكون هذا وأنا لست اعرف رجلا ً ؟ " فأجاب الملاك وقال لها : " الروح القدس يحل عليك وقوة العلى تظللك فلذلك أيضا ً القدوس المولود منك يدعى أبن الله ... لانه ليس شئ غير ممكن لدى الله ". فقالت مريم : "هوذا أنا أمة الرب ليكن لى كقولك فمضى من عندها الملاك " ( لو 1 : 26 – 38 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Since this moment the Only Begotten Son, the Word of God came and dwelt in the womb of our Lady the Virgin St. Mary.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ومن تلك اللحظه حل فى أحشاء السيدة العذراء الابن الوحيد الكلمة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This day then is the first-born of all the major feasts of the Lord, for in it was the glad tidings of the salvation of the world.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هذا اليوم هو بكر الأعياد السيدية الكبرى لأن فيه كانت البشرى بخلاص العالم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of this glorious Annunciation be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة بشرى الخلاص فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Resurrection of the Lord Christ from the dead</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار قيامة السيد المسيح من الأموات</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 34 A.D. the Lord fulfilled the economy of salvation and redemption with His Holy Resurrection from the dead and became the first-fruits of those who have fallen asleep.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً من سنة 34 م أكمل الرب تدبير الخلاص والفداء بقيامته المقدسة من بين الأموات وصار بكر الراقدين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               We ask our Good Savior to raise us from the death of sin, forgive our trespasses and grant us the Eternal Life and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               نسأل إلهنا الصالح أن يقيمنا من موت الخطية ويغفر لنا آثامنا وينعم لنا بالحياة الأبدية. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Paremhotep.30">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Thirtieth Day of the Blessed Month of Paremhotep</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثلاثون من شهر برمهات المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the thirtieth day of the blessed month of Paremhotep. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثلاثون من شهر برمهات المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم في هدوء واطمئنان، مغفوري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Archangel Gabriel the Announcer</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار رئيس الملائكة غبريال المبشر</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, the church celebrates the commemoration of the honorable Archangel Gabriel, the announcer. For he was worthy to announce the birth of His only begotten Son to the virgin St. Mary . He also foretold Daniel the prophet about the return of the people of Israel from exile , about the advent of the Lord Christ, for the salvation of the world and to bring an end to animal sacrifices . He also prophesied about what would happen in the last days and he also announced Zacharias the priest about the birth of the forerunner John the Baptizer . For what God had done for us through him it is meet for us to honor and venerate him and ask for his intercession at all times.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فى هذا اليوم تعيد الكنيسة بتذكار رئيس الملائكة الجليل جبرائيل المبشر الذى استحق أن يحمل البشارة بتجسد الابن الوحيد إلى العذراء القديسة مريم ( لو 1 : 26 – 38 ). وهو الذى سبق فأنبأ دانيال النبى عن عودة الشعب من السبى ( دا 9 : 21 – 25 ). وعن مجئ السيد المسيح لخلاص العالم وإيطال الذبائح ( دا 9 : 25 – 27 ) وعما سيحدث فى الأيام الأخيرة ( دا 10 11 12 ). كما انه بشر زكريا الكاهن بميلاد يوحنا المعمدان السابق الصابغ ( لو 1 : 11 – 20 ). فلهذا نكرمه ونطلب شفاعته فى كل حين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               His holy intercession be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               شفاعته المقدسة فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Samson, One of the Judges of Israel</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة شمشون أحد قضاة بنى إسرائيل</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also Samson, one of the Judges of Israel, departed. He was from the tribe of Dan and was born in Zorah by a divine revelation. The angel of the Lord appeared to his barren mother and announced her of his birth. He commanded her not to drink wine nor to eat unclean food all the days of her pregnancy. The angel also commanded her that no razor should come on his head, for the child was to be a Nazirite (dedicated) unto God from the womb, and that he would deliver Israel out of the hands of the Philistines. The angel also appeared to his father Manoah and announced him with the same words.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً تنيح شمشون أحد قضاة بنى إسرائيل. هو من سبط دان وولد فى صرعه (هي مدينة فى ساحل يهوذا تبعد 14 ميلا ً غربى القدس – أورشليم). بإعلان إلهى إذ ظهر ملاك الرب لوالدته العاقر وبشرها بميلاده وأمرها أن تتجنب الخمر والمسكر ولا تحلق رأسه لانه يكون نذيرا ً لله ( قض 13 : 3 – 5 ). كما ظهر لوالده منوح وكلمه بنفس البشارة ( قض 13 : 11 – 20 ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The woman conceived, and gave birth to Samson, and God blessed him and the Spirit of the Lord began to move upon him at Mahaneh Dan between Zorah and Eshtaol. Samson married a gentile woman from Timnah and on his way to her, to his surprise a young lion came roaring against him. And the Spirit of the Lord came mighty upon him, and he tore the lion apart as one would have torn apart a young goat. Thought he had nothing in his hand.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فحبلت المرأة وولدت شمشون فكبر الصبى وباركه الرب وابتدأ روح الرب يحركه فى محلة دان بين صرعة وأشتأول ( قض 13 : 24 25 ).  تزوج شمشون بامرأة أممية من بلده تمنه وفى الطريق إليها إذا بشبل أسد يزمجر للقائه فحل عليه روح الرب فشقه كشق الجدى وليس فى يده شئ.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On his way back, he turned aside to see the carcass of the lion. And behold a swarm of bees and honey. He took some of it and ate and gave to his parents and they also ate. Samson went to Timnah another time where he gave a feast there. He told the Philistines a riddle; “Out of the eater came something to eat, and out of the strong came something sweet.” When they could not correctly solve and explain the riddle, they said to Samson’s wife, “Entice your husband that he may explain the riddle to us, or else we will burn you and your father’s house with fire.” Samson’s wife wept before him until he told her. So the men of the city said to him on the seventh day of the feast, “What is sweeter than honey? And what is stronger than a lion?” And he said to them: “If you had not plowed with my heifer, you would not have solved my riddle!” Then the Spirit of Lord came upon him mightily, and he went down to Ashkelon and killed thirty of their men. So his anger was aroused and he went back up to his father’s house, and Samson’s wife was given to his companion. When Samson went back to take his wife, her father refused to hand her to him and offered him her younger sister to take her instead. Samson was enraged, burned up the shocks and the standing grain, as well as the vineyards and olive groves of the Philistines then he went down and dwelt in the cleft of a rock.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفى طريق العودة مال وإذا فى جوف الأسد عسل نحل فأخذ منه وأكل وأعطى لأبويه ثم ذهب شمشون إلى تمنة مرة أخرى حيث أقيمت وليمة هناك وقال للفلسطينيين"من الآكل خرج أكل ومن الجافى خرجت حلاوة".  فلم يفهموا ما هو المقصود وقالوا لامرأة شمشون تملقى رجلك لكى يظهر لنا الأحجية لئلا نحرقك وبيت أبيك بنار. فبكت أمراة شمشون لديه حتى أخبرها. فقال له رجال المدينة فى اليوم السابع للوليمة "أى شئ أحلى من العسل وماأجفى من الأسد ". فقال لهم " لو لم تحرثوا على عجلتى لما وجدتم أحجيتى". وحل عليه روح الرب فنزل إلى أشقلون وقتل منهم ثلاثين رجلاً. وحمى غضبه وصعد إلى بيت أبيه فصارت امرأة شمشون لصاحبه ( قض 14 : 1 – الخ ) فلما عاد ليأخذ زوجته رفض والدها أن يعطيها له وعرض عليه الزواج بأختها فغضب شمشون وأحرق زرع الفلسطينيين وكل كرومهم ونزل وأقام فى صخرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Philistines rose against the tribe of Judah and asked its men to hand Samson to them. Three thousand men of Judah went to him and asked him to go down with them and promised not to harm him. They bound him with two new ropes and brought him up from the rock. When they brought him to the Philistines, the Spirit of the Lord came mightily upon him, and his bonds broke loose off his hands. He found a fresh jawbone of a donkey, reached out and took it with his hand and killed a thousand men with it. He judged Israel twenty years in the days of the Philistines.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم نزل الفلسطينيون فى يهوذا وطلبوا من رجالها أن يسلموا لهم شمشون. فمضى إليه ثلاثة آلاف رجل من يهوذا وطلبوا إليه أن ينزل معهم ووعدوه أن لا يفعلوا به شرا فأوثقوه بحبلين جديدين وأصعدوه من الصخرة. ولما التقى بالفلسطينيين حل عليه روح الرب فانحل الوثاق عن يديه ووجد لحى حمار طريا ً فأخذه وضرب به ألف رجل. وقضى لإسرائيل فى أيام الفلسطينيين عشرين سنة ( قض 15 : 1 –  الخ ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Then Samson went to Gaza, and its people were told, “Samson has come here!” The Philistines surrounded the place all the night at the gate of the city. Samson arose at midnight, took hold of the doors of the gate, pulled them up, put them on his shoulders, and carried them to the top of the hill. The lords of the Philistines came up to Delilah, and asked her to entice Samson to find out the secret of his strength. After many attempts, finally he told her all what was in his heart and said to her, “No razor has ever come upon my head, for I have been a Nazirite to God from my mother’s womb.” She went and told the Philistines. She lulled him to sleep on her knees, and called for a man to shave off the locks of his hair and his strength left him. The Philistines took him and put out his eyes and brought him down to Gaza. They bound him with bronze fetters, and he became a grinder in the prison.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم ذهب شمشون إلى غزة فقيل لأهلها قدأتى شمشون فأحاطوا به الليل كله عند باب المدينة. فقام وأخذ مصراعى باب المدينة والقائمتين وقلعهما مع العارضة ووضعها على كتفيه وصعد بها إلى رأس الجبل وطلب أقطاب الفلسطينيين من دليلة أن تعرف منه سبب قوته وبعد محاولات كثيرة أخبرها بكل ما فى قلبه وقال لها " لم يعل موسى رأسى لأنى نذير الله من بطن أمى ". فمضت وأخبرت الفلسطينيين وأنامته على ركبتيها وحلقت خصل شعره فضاعت قوته وقبض عليه الفلسطينيون وقلعوا عينيه وأوثقوه بسلاسل نحاس وكان يطحن فى بيت السجن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               However, the hair of his head began to grow again and his strength came back to him. The lords of the Philistines gathered together to offer a great sacrifice to Dagon their god and they said: “Our god has delivered into our hands Samson our enemy!” Then they called for Samson from the prison and he performed for them, and they stationed him between the pillars. Then Samson called to the Lord saying; “O Lord God, remember me, I pray, just this once, O God, that I may with one blow take vengeance on the Philistines for my two eyes!” Samson took hold of the two middle pillars and said, "Let me die with the Philistines." The temple fell and three thousands of the Philistines died. So the dead that he killed on his death were more than he killed in his life. His brothers came down and took him, and brought him up and buried him in the tomb of his father Manoah. (Judges 13-16)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               اجتمع أقطاب الفلسطينيين ليذبحوا لإلههم داجون وقالوا قد دفع إلهنا ليدنا شمشون عدونا. ثم دعوا شمشون من بيت السجن وأوقفوه بين الأعمدة ليلعب أمامهم وكان قد نبت شعره. فدعا الرب وقال " أذكرنى وشددنى يا الله هذه المرة فقط فأنتقم نقمة واحدة عن عينى من الفلسطينيين ". وقبض على العمودين المتوسطين وقال " لتمت نفسى مع الفلسطينيين ". فسقط البيت ومات ثلاثة آلاف رجل. ومات شمشون. فنزل إخوته وصعدوا به ودفنوه فى قبر منوح أبيه ( قض 16 : 1 – الخ ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               To our God is the glory forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركته المقدسة فلتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Relocation of the Relies of St. James the Persian, known as Intercisus or Sawn-Asunder</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار نقل أعضاء القديس يعقوب الفارسى الشهير بالمقطع</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, was the relocation of the relic of St. James the Persian from the city of Gaza to the land of Egypt. A church was built after his name in Old Cairo where his body was laid. The account of his martyrdom is mentioned under the twenty seventh day of the month of Hathor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وفيه أيضا ً تم نقل جسد القديس يعقوب الفارسى الشهير بالمقطع من مدينة غزة إلى ديار مصر حيث بنيت على اسمه  كنيسة بمصر القديمه ووضع جسده فيها وتجد خبر أستشهاده تحت يوم 27 هاتور.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته فلتكن معنا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season></Document>