<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Season id="Parmoute.1">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The First Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الأول من شهر برمودة المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the first day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الأول من شهر برمودة المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Silvanus the monk</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">ـ  نياحة القديس سلوانس الراهب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the Holy Father Abba Silvanus the monk departed. This blessed man became a monk since his youth under the guidance of St. Macarius the great in the wilderness of Shiheet. He pursued every narrow path by long fasting, many vigils, humility, austere asceticism and love.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم تنٌيح الأب القديس سلوانس الراهب، ترٌهب هذا القديس منذ صغره عند القديس الأنبا مكاريوس الكبير ببرية شهيت. وسار ?ي كل طريق ضيق، بالصوم الطويل والسهر الكثير وال?نسك الزائد والاتضاع والمحبة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He left the wilderness in the year 407 A.D. during the first raid of the Berbers. He went to Sinai and later on he returned to Shiheet where he completed his spiritual strife.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد ترك البرية سنة 407 م، أثناء غارة البربر الأولي، وذهب إلي سيناء ثم عاد إلي شيهيت حيث أكمل جهاده ?يها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day he prostrated his face down to the ground and remained as such for a long period of time. When he raised his head, the brethren asked him insistently to narrate to them what had happened to him. He replied saying; “My mind was taken up to paradise. There I saw many of the Lay people, and then they took me to the places of torment where I saw many of the monks being taken there. When I saw that I wept. A luminous angel came and told me; “Listen to me for I will let you know the reality of what you had seen. The monks that were taken to Hades, those who drove themselves to the love of possessions, opinionated, had forsaken praising God and reading the Holy Scriptures. As of the lay people who went to paradise, were those who were patient and giving thanks to the Lord for whatever happened to them.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي أحد الأيام سقط علي وجهه ?ترة ولما ر?ع رأسه ، سأله إخوته بإلحاح أن يحكي لهم ما حدث معه. ?قال لهم اخت?ط? عقلي إلي ال?ردوس ?رأيت? هناك كثيرآ من العلمانيين، وبعدها مضوا بي إلي مواضع العذاب ?رأيت? كثيرآ من الرهبان ي?ساقون إلي هناك. ?لما  رأيت ذلك  بكيت. ?أتي إليٌ ملاك نوراني وقال لي "اسمع مني لأعرٌ?ك  حقيقة ما رأيت، الرهبان الذين يساقون إلي الجحيم هم الذين د?عوا ذواتهم إلي محبة القنية والتمسك  برأيهم  وتركوا عنهم تسبيح الله وتلاوة كتبه، وأمآ العٌلمانيون الذين مضوا  إلي النعيم ?هم الصابرون الشاكرون للرب علي كل ما ينزل بهم".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He commanded his disciples never to cease working with their hands, and to give alms with what exceeded their needs. He commanded them also to persevere in prayer and reading the Holy Books.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هذا وقد كان القديس سلوانس عمٌالاً وكان يوصي أولاده أن يهتموا بعمل اليد بمقدار ، ويداوموا علي الصلاة والقراءة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day a monk came to the monastery and saw the monks working with their hands. He said to them: "Do not labor for the food which perishes" for it is written: "Mary has chosen that good part, which will not be taken away from her." When the old man Abba Silvanus heard that, he told his disciple: "Give him a book and take him to a cell wherein there is nothing." When the ninth hour came the old man and his disciples ate and did not invite that monk. During that time the monk was gazing with his eyes toward the door waiting for someone to invite him to eat. When he became very hungry, he left the cell and asked the old man: "Have the brethren eaten today?" and St. Silvanus replied "Yes". The monk asked: "Why you did not call me to eat with them?" He replied: "You are a spiritual man has no need for food for the body. You have chosen the good part, but we are corporeal beings in need of food for the body, for this reason we need to work." The monk knew that he had transgressed with his words and he bowed before the holy man asking for his forgiveness. The holy man told the monk: "O my son we need to work, for Mary needs Martha, and through Martha, Mary was praised." Thus the monk had greatly benefited from this lesson.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي أحد الأيام جاء إلي الدير راهب ?وجد الرهبان يعملون عمل اليد ?قال لهم: " لاتعملوا للطعام ال?اني ?إن مريم أختارت النصيب الصالح".  ?قال القديس لتلميذه" أعط الأخ كتاباً وأدخله قلاية". و?ي موعد الأكل أكل الرهبان دون دعوة الأخ ?سأل القديس " لماذا لم تدع?ني للأكل مع الإخوة؟". ?قال له القديس "أنت رجل روحاني لاتحتاج إلي الأكل، أما نحن ?نعمل لنأكل". ?علم الأخ أنه أخطأ، ?ضرب مطانية م?ستغ?رآ. ?أجابه القديس  "ياب?نيٌ لابد لمريم أن تحتاج لمرثا، لأن بمرثا مدحت مريم". ?انت?ع الأخ.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This father wrote many valuable discourses about the spiritual strife. When he finished his strife in a good old age, God made it known to him the time of his departure. He called the fathers the monks and asked them to pray on his behalf then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد وضع هذا القديس أقوالاً نا?عة ?ي الجهاد الروحي. ولما أكمل جهاده، أعلمه الله بموعد نياحته، ?استدعي الآباء الرهبان وسألهم الصلاة من أجله، ثم تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا، آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Aaron the priest</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">ـ  نياحة هارون الكاهن</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the righteous Aaron the priest, son of Amram , who was from the tribe of Levi and the brother of Moses the Arch-prophet, departed. When he was eighty three years old, God entrusted him to participate with Moses in delivering the Hebrews out of Egypt. He spoke with the elders of the children of Israel with all the words which the Lord had spoken to Moses. Then he did the signs in the sight of the people. So the people believed . He carried Moses’ rod before Pharaoh and before the people . He was a part of the war against Amalek, Aaron and Hur supported Moses’ hands in Rephidim until Israel prevailed . He was present with his two sons Nadab and Abihu and seventy of the elders of Israel when God made a covenant with Moses and the people . Nevertheless, when Moses delayed coming down from the mountain , Aaron portrayed weakness of faith when he made a golden calf for the people and built an altar before it. However God forgave him this transgression and consecrated him and his offspring to minister unto the Lord . Moses anointed them with the anointing oil to consecrate them for the service during the celebration of consecrating the tabernacle .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  تنيٌح البار هارون الكاهن بن عمرام من سبط لاوي ، شقيق موسي رئيس الأنبياء. ولما بلغ الثالثة والثمانين من عمره كٌل?ه? الله أن يشترك مع موسي ?ي إخراج العبرانيين من مصر، وتكلم مع شيوخ بني إسرائيل عن الكلام الذي كلٌم الرب موسي به وصنع الآيات أمام عيون الشعب. ?آمن الشعب . وكان يحمل عصا موسي أمام الشعب وأمام ?رعون . واشترك ?ي الحرب مع عماليق وأمسك بيديٌ موسي مع حور ?ي واقعة ر?ديم ، حتي تحقق النصر. وحضر مع أبنيه ناداب وأبيهو وسبعين من شيوخ إسرائيل العهد  الذي صنعه الله مع موسي للشعب. غير أن هارون أظهر ضع? الإيمان وذلك لما تأخر موسي علي الجبل صنع للشعب عجلاً ذهبياً وبني له مذبحاً ، ومع ذلك غ?ر الله له هذه الخطية وقدسه ليكون كاهناً  هو ونسله ، ومسحهم  بدهن المسحة لتقديسهم للخدمة أثناء الإحت?ال بتقديس المسكن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Aaron served as chief priest for forty years in which he faced many hardships. The Lord put to death his two sons Nadab and Abihu for they offered profane fire before Him. Moses warned him and his two sons Eleazar and Ithamar from showing their grief for them . When Aaron and Miriam spoke against Moses for he had married an Ethiopian woman, Mariam became leprous. As of Aaron, he asked for the mercy of the Lord and confessed his sin and God forgave him and his sister . The Lord also saved him and Moses from the wrath of those who raised up against them, the sons of Korah, by commanding the earth to open its mouth and swallowed them .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد خدم هارون رئيسا ً للكهنة أربعين سنة، تعرض ?يها لتجارب كثيرة منها أن الرب أمات أبنيه ناداب وأبيهو لانهما قدٌما ناراً غريبة، وحذٌره هو وأبنيه ألعازر وإيثامار من إظهار حزنهم عليهما.  ولما تكلم هارون ومريم أخته علي موسي عندما تزوج بالمرأة الكوشية ، أبتلي الرب مريم بالبرص أما هارون ?طلب رحمة الرب واعتر? بالخطأ ، ?ع?ا عنه وعن أخته. كما أن الرب أنقذه هو وموسي من غضب المنشقين عليهما من بني قورح ، وجعل الأرض تنشق وتبتلعهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Lord demonstrated His contentment with Aaron when He made the rod of Aaron sprouted and put forth buds excluding the other rods of the leaders of Israel in spite of the fact that Moses and Aaron did not hallow the Lord before the assembly when they asked for water to drink . Therefore Aaron and Moses were forbidden from entering the Promised Land along with the assembly. Aaron died on the top of Mount Hor after he had taken of his priestly vestments and put them on his son Eleazar.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أظهر الرب رضاه عن هارون بأن جعل عصاه  ت?رخ دون رؤساء الشعب، علي الرغم أنه هو وموسي لم ي?قدٌسا الرب أمام الجماعة حينما طلبوا ماء ليشربوا. ولذلك ح?رم هو وموسي من الدخول مع الشعب إلي أرض الميعاد . ثم مات هارون ?ي جبل هور بعد أن خلع ملابسه الكهنوتية وألبسها لابنه ألعازر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا، آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Raid of the Arabs of Upper Egypt on the Wilderness of Shiheet (Scetis)</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">ـ  تذكار غارة ع?ربان الصعيد علي برية شهييت</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 582 of the martyrs (866 A.D.) the Arabs of Upper Egypt (Bedouins) rose up and attacked the desert of the great St. Macarius (wilderness of Shiheet). They plundered what was in the churches and monasteries. The monks gathered together, prayed, and interceded with the Virgin St. Mary, the angels and the saints. God answered these prayers, drove them out and saved the monks from their wickedness.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً   من سنة 582 للشهداء ( 866 م )، أغار ع?ربان الصعيد علي برية شيهيت إسقيط القديس مكاريوس ، ونهبوا الكنائس والأديرة. ?صلي الآباء وتش?عوا بالقديسة العذراء مريم والملائكة والقديسين، ?استجاب الله لهذه الصلوات وطردهم ونجٌي الرهبان من شرٌهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               May the Lord guard us all from the vices of the evil one and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ليح?ظنا الرب من مكائد الشرير، ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.2">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Second Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثاني من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the second day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثاني من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Christopher</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس خرستو?ورس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day St. Christopher was martyred. This saint had unsightly look and the body of a giant but his soul was good and gentle.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم أستشهد القديس خرستو?ورس، وكان هذا القديس ذا هيئة بشعة وجسم كجسم الجبابرة. ولكن ن?سه كانت وديعة صالحة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he was captured by the soldiers of the pagan Emperor Decius, he admonished them for afflicting the Christians. The captain of these soldiers beat him severely however St. Christopher told him: "If it was not for the command of Christ which teaches me not to do unto others as they do unto us, otherwise you and your soldiers could not be delivered from my hands." When Decius knew about him, he sent two hundred soldiers to bring him. On their way, they ran out of bread except for a little of it. He prayed and God blessed that little of bread and became in abundance. The soldiers marveled and believed on the Lord Christ the God of Christopher. When they arrived to Antioch they were baptized by the hands of Abba Paul the Patriarch.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما وقع أسيراً ?ي يد جند الإمبراطور ديسيوس الملك الوثني ، أخذ ي?وبٌخ الجند علي تعذيبهم للمسيحيين. ?ضربه رئيس الجند ?قال له القديس:"لولا وصية المسيح التي ت?عٌلمني ألا أقابل الإساءة بمثلها ، لما ك?نت أنت وجنودك ت?حسَبون شيئاً أمامي". ولما علَم ديسيوس بأمره ، أرسل مائتي جندي لإحضاره، ?حضر معهم وحدث ?ي الطريق أن الخبز ?رغ منهم إلا قليلاً منه. ?صلي القديس وبارك الله ?ي هذا القليل ?صار كثيراً ، ?أكل الجند متعجبين ، وآمنوا بالسيد المسيح إله خرستو?ورس. ولما وصلوا إلي إنطاكية اعتمدوا علي يد الأنبا بولا البطريرك.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When St. Christopher came before Decius, he became frightened from his appearance but he tried to charm, persuade and deceive him to deny Christ. Then he sent two beautiful women to make him fall into sin with them. He exhorted them and they believed in the Lord Christ. They confessed their faith before the Emperor, who ordered to behead them thus they received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما وق? خرستو?ورس أمام ديسيوس، ارتعب من هول منظره، ?لاط?ه وخادعه وصر?ه من أمامه.ثم أرسل إليه امرأتين جميلتين ليستميلاه إلي الخطية، ?وعظهما وآمنتا علي يديه معتر?تين بالسيد المسيح أمام الملك. ?أمر الملك بقطع رأسيهما ونالتا إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               As of this Saint, he was cast into a huge cauldron over hot fire, but no harm came upon him. The people who were present were amazed and they believed in the Lord Christ. They came forward to remove him out of the cauldron but the Emperor ordered to behead them. The emperor finally ordered to hang a heavy rock from the neck of the saint and be thrown into a pit however the angel of the Lord took him out safely. When the Emperor became weary, he ordered to cut St. Christopher's neck thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أما هذا القديس ?طرحوه ?ي قدر كبير ?وق نار متقدة، ?لم تمسه النار بأذي. ?تعجب الحاضرون وآمنوا بالسيد المسيح. ثم تقدموا لإخراج القديس من القدر، ?أمر الملك بقطع رؤوسهم. وأخيراً أمر الملك أن يعلق ?ي عنق القديس حجرا ً ثقيلا ً ويلقي ?ي ج?ب، ?أنتشله ملاك الرب سالماً. ?لما تحير الملك أمر بضرب عنقه ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا، آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Yoannis IX, 81st Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا يوأنس التاسع البطريرك الحادي والثمانين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1043 of the martyrs (1327 A.D.) Pope Yoannis IX, 81st Patriarch of Alexandria departed. This Holy Father was born in the city of Nakiyos (Nikiu) . When he grew he went to one of the monasteries of Naqadah in Upper Egypt. He became a monk by the name of Yoannis el-Naqady. He lived in asceticism, prayers and fasting along with reading and contemplation.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً من سنة 1043 للشهداء (1327م)، تنيٌح القديس البابا يوأنس التاسع البطريرك الحادي والثمانون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. و?لد هذا القديس ?ي مدينة نقيوس . ولما كبر مضي إلي إحدي أديرة نقادة  بالصعيد ، وترٌهب باسم الراهب يوأنس النقادي. وعاش ?ي نسك وصلوات وأصوام مع القراءة والتأمل.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the fame of his virtues became well known, the bishops and the Lay-leaders (Archons) unanimously agreed to choose him Patriarch after the departure of his predecessor Pope Yoannis VIII. He was consecrated Pope by the name Yoannis IX on the first day of Paope, year 1037 of the martyrs (1320 A.D.).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما ذاع صيت ?ضائله أختاره الآباء الآساق?ة والأراخنة ليكون بطريركياً بعد نياحة سل?ه البابا يوأنس الثامن. ور?سم بإسم البابا يوأنس التاسع يوم أول بابه 1037 للشهداء ( 1320 م ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his days, a vulgar street person incited mob action against the Copts and destroyed many churches. Sultan Muhammad Ibn Qalawun desired to punish those incited the civil disobedience. However the Mameluke princes calmed his outburst by claiming that this devastation was the will of God. The Mameluke and the princes desired the Coptic money and their endowments. One month later many fires were ignited and blamed the Copts for setting them up to revenge what was destroyed of churches.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي أيامه استثار أحد العامة الغوغاء ضد الأقباط ?دمروا الكنائس وكان السلطان محمد بن قلاوون يرغب ?ي معاقبة م?سببي ال?تنة. ولكن الأمراء المماليك هدأوا ثورته بادعائهم أن هذا التخريب بأمر الله. وقد طمع المماليك والأمراء ?ي أموال وأوقا? الأقباط. وبعد شهر إندلعت النار، ?اتهموا الأقباط بإضرامها انتقاماً منهم لما تهدم من الكنائس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               El-Sultan summoned the Pope and introduced to him three Christians confessed of putting on the fires. The Pope wept and said; “Christianity commands us to love and forgive.? However God willed to vindicate the Copts from these accusations for later on it was proved that the ones caused these fires were non-Copts.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?استدعي السلطان البابا ، وقدم له ثلاثة من المسيحيين اعتر?وا بأنهم أشعلوا النار. ?بكي البابا، وقال "إن المسيحية تأمرنا بالمحبة والتسامح". ولكن الله أراد تبرئة الأقباط من هذه التهمة إذ قد ثبت أن المتسببين ?ي الحريق كانوا من غير الأقباط الأرثوذكس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In spite of that the devastation continued for months, many churches were destroyed and hundreds of Copts were martyred. Sultan Qalawun issued an order for the Christian to wear blue turbans and forbade them from riding horses and mules. The one who ride his donkey has to ride it backward. He forbade the Christians from attending public bathes without a bell hanging from their necks. He forbade the princes from employing Christian scribes and he expelled those who were employed by the Sultan. Because of the frequent attacks against the Christians, that forced them to avoid walking in the streets.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ورغم هذا ?قد استمر التخريب لبضعة شهور. وتهدمت كنائس كثيرة. واستشهد مئات الناس. وصدرت أوامر من السلطان قلاوون أن يلبس المسيحيون العمائم الزرقاء ، وحرم عليهم ركوب الخيل والبغال ، والذي يركب حماره يركبه مقلوباً ، وألا يدخل مسيحي حماماً إلا و?ي عنقه جرس، وألا يستعمل الأمراء كاتباً من المسيحيين. وطرد مَنْ كان منهم ?ي خدمة السلطان. ومن كثرة الهجمات اضطر المسيحيون لعدم الخروج إلي الشوارع.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Grief overcame the Pope for he could not go to the monastery of St. Macarius to consecrate the Holy Myron nor take a pastoral visit to his wounded flock. Bishops and priests could not leave their places except after sunset so they dedicated themselves to prayers until the storm had calmed down.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد طغي الحزن علي البابا، اذ لم يستطع أن يذهب لدير القديس مكاريوس لتكريس الميرون، ولا أن يقوم برحلة رعوية لت?قد شعبه الجريح. كما أنه لم يستطع أسق? أو كاهن أن يخرج من مقره إلا بعد مغيب الشمس. وهكذا انصر?وا للصلاة حتي هدأت العاص?ة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Yoannis did not enjoy the peace for he did not live long he departed after he had stayed on the apostolic throne for 6 years and 6 month. He departed at Haret Zewaila and was buried in El Nastur monastery            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولم ينعم البابا بالسلام لأنه لم يعش طويلاً. ?تنيح بعد أن أقام علي الكرسي ست سنوات وخمسة أشهر وأثنين وعشرين يوما ً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.3">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Third Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the third day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Michael II, 71st Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا ميخائيل الثاني البطريرك الحادى والسبعين من بطاركة لكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 862 of the martyrs (1146 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Michael II, 71st Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. He was born in a village called Daqadus . When he grew he became a monk in the monastery of St. Macarius the great in the wilderness of Shiheet. He lived in austere asceticism persevering in prayer and reading until the repute of his virtues became well known.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 862 للشهداء ( 1146 م )، تنيٌح القديس البابا ميخائيل الثاني البطريرك الحادي والسبعون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. و?لد هذا الأب بقرية دقادوس (1) ولما كبر ترٌهب بديرالقديس مكاريوس الكبير ببرية شيهيت. ?عاش ?ي نسك زائد مواظباً علي الصلاة والقراءة إلي أن ذاع صيت ?ضائله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Gabriel II, 70th Patriarch, departed, a monk called Yoannis EbN Kedran expressed his desire to nominate himself and he was supported by Anba Jacob, bishop of Lekanah , Anba Christodolus, bishop of Fowa , and Anba Michael, bishop of Tanta. Nevertheless, the bishops of Upper Egypt, the priests of Alexandria and the lay leaders of Cairo did not accept that choice. They choose three monks and cast an altar lot among them which fell on the monk Michael. They consecrated him Patriarch on the 5th day of Mesore, year 861 of the martyrs (1145 A.D.).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تنيٌح البابا غبريال الثاني، البطريرك السبعون، تقدم راهب يدعي يوأنس بن كدران، يريد أن يرشح ن?سه. وعاونه ?ي ذلك الأنبا يعقوب أسق? لقانة والأنبا خريستوذولوس أسق? ?وه، والأنبا ميخائيل أسق? طنطا ، إلا أن أساق?ة الصعيد وكهنة الأسكندرية وأراخنة مصر لم يقبلوا ذلك، وإختاروا ثلاثة من الرهبان، وألقوا قرعة هيكلية بينهم، ?وقعت علي الراهب ميخائيل. ?رسموه بطريركياً يوم 5 مسري 861 للشهداء ( 1145 م ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Holy Father was an honorable old man who loved the poor and the needy. He knew how to reach the hearts of his flock by his exhortations and instructions. He persevered in teaching the people and confirming them in the Orthodox Faith. They gathered around him with love and loyalty accepting his guidance with joy. This father continued in his asceticism, piety and contentment.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان هذا الأب شيخاً جليلاً محباً لل?قراء والمساكين. وكان يعر? كي? يصل إلي القلوب  بوعظه وإرشاده ?داوم علي تعليم الشعب وتثبيتهم علي الإيمان. ?الت?وا حوله ?ي محبة وولاء وتقبلوا إرشاداته ب?رح. وقد أستمر هذا الأب ?ي نسكه وتقش?ه وقناعته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He had five vacant dioceses, so he prayed entreating God to guide him to who were fit for this responsibility. God guided him to five godly monks. He consecrated them and provided them with his advices and blessings.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت هناك خمس إيبارشيات خالية، ?صام مصلياً إلي الله ليختار من يصلح لهذه المسئولية. ?أرشده الرب إلي خمسة من الرهبان الأتقياء، ?رسمهم وزودهم بالنصائح والبركات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The days of this Pope were short for he fell ill what forced him to go back to the wilderness of Shiheet where he departed in peace. He remained on the apostolic throne for only 8 months.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولكن أيام هذا البابا كانت قصيرة، ?مرض وتوجه إلي برية شيهيت، وهناك تنيٌح  بسلام، بعد أن أقام علي الكرسي ثمانية شهور.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. John, Bishop of Jerusalem</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس يوحنا أسق? أورشليم</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also Anba John, Bishop of Jerusalem, departed. He was born to Jewish parents, who kept the Law of the Torah. They instructed and taught him well and he excelled in the Law of Moses.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  تنيٌح الأب القديس الأنبا يوحنا أسق? أورشليم. و?لد من أبوين يهوديين حا?ظين التوراة، ?هذباه وعلٌماه كثيراً حتي نبغ ?ي علٌم الشريعة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He debated the Christians and argued with them and they proved to him the advent of the Lord Christ and that He is the true God. He went to St. Justus, Bishop of Jerusalem, believed at his hand, and was ordained deacon. Because of his knowledge and virtues they chose him a bishop for Jerusalem after the departure of St. Justus.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان يجادل المسيحيين ويناظرهم، ?ثبت له مجئ السيد المسيح، وأنه إله حقيقي.  ثم ذهب إلي القديس يسطس أسق? أورشليم ، ?آمن علي يديه وصار شماساً. ونظرا لعلٌمه و?ضيلته أنتخبوه أسق?ا علي أورشليم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Hadrian (117-138) reigned, he commanded to rebuild the ruined parts of the city and he built a tower on the western gate, the gate of the Jewish temple. He hanged an engraved tablet with his name on the door of that gate. Jerusalem during his days became crowded with the Jews and Gentiles.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?لما ملك أدريانوس الملقب أيليا، أمر ببناء ماه?دم من المدينة. ثم بني برجاً علي باب هيكل اليهود ووضع علي بابه لوحاً من رخام مكتوباً عليه اسمه. وامتلأت أورشليم ?ي زمانه من اليهود والأمم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the Gentiles saw the Christians coming to Golgotha to pray they prevented them. A temple for the goddess Venus was built over the site of Golgotha and the Christians were forbidden from passing thru that place. Therefore the Jews and Gentiles became powerful and troubled the Christians much. Because of that, many tribulations and sorrows befell this father, so he asked God to receive him. His supplication was accepted and he departed in peace after he had stayed on the Episcopal Chair for two years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أبصرالأمم المسيحيين يأتون إلي الجلجلة ليصلوا منعوهم، وبنوا هناك هيكلاً باسم الزهرة، ومنعوا المسيحيين من العبور ?ي ذلك المكان. ولهذا ?قد اشتد ساعد اليهود والأمم، ?ضايقوا المسيحيين كثيراً. ?أصاب هذا الأب من جراء ذلك كثير من البلايا والأحزان. ولما أكمل جهاده تنيٌح بسلام. بعد أن أقام علي كرسي الأسق?ية سنتين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.4">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fourth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fourth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Sts. Victor, Decius, Eirene the Virgin and those who were with them; men, women and virgins</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">شهادة القديسين بقطر وأكاكيوس وداكيوس وإيريني العذراء ومن معهم من رجال ونساء وعذاري</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the saints Victor, Decius, Acacius, Eirene the virgin and those who were with them from men, women and virgins were martyred. These saints were during the reign of Emperor Constantine and his son after him. They destroyed many pagan temples and transformed them to churches.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي هذا اليوم ت?عيد الكنيسة  بتذكار أستشهاد القديسين بقطر وأكاكيوس وداكيوس وإيريني العذراء ومن معهم من رجال ونساء وعذاري. هؤلاء الذين كانوا ?ي زمان الملك قسطنطين الكبير وأبنه من بعده. وقد هدموا معابد وثنية وحولوها إلي كنائس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Emperor Julian the apostate reigned, he supported idol worshipping, honored their priests, and slew a great number of Christians. When he knew what these saints had done to the temples, he seized them. He tormented them with different kinds of tortures by beating, hanging and combing their bodies with iron combs then finally beheaded them, thus they received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد أن تملك يوليانوس الجاحد، عضد عبادة الأوثان، وقتل عددا كبيرا من المسيحيين. ولما علٌم بما ?عله هؤلاء القديسون بالبراربي، قبض عليهم، وعذٌبهم تارة بالضرب والتعليق، وأخري بتمشيط أجسادهم بأمشاط من حديد. ثم قطع رؤوسهم ?نالوا اكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Okeen</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس أوكين</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 96 of the martyrs (380 A.D.) St. Okeen departed. He was born in Qulzum nearby the Red Sea. He was a contemporary of the Holy Father Anba Antonius the father of all monks. He worked as a diver into the deep waters of the sea to catch precious pearls and sea shells. He sold them to sustain him-self and contributed the rest to the poor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 96 للشهداء (380م)، تنيٌح القديس أوكين. و?لدَ بالقلزم بالقرب من البحر الأحمر، وكان معاصرا للقديس الأنبا أنطونيوس أب الرهبان، وكانت صناعته التقاط الأصدا? واللآلئ الثمينة من قاع البحر، يبيعها ويعيش من ثمنها ويتصدق علي ال?قراء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He longed for the monastic life so he went to one of the monasteries OF Anba Pachomius in Upper Egypt where he became a monk. After a while he returned to his hometown then moved to Mesopotamia along with seventy monks who became his disciples. There he dwelt in a cave nearby Nisibis surrounded by his disciples. Many followed his example till they counted 250 monks. He built a monastery for them accordingly he was the one to establish the monastic life in these countries.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               اشتاق إلي حياة الرهبنة. ?ذهب إلي أحد أديرة الأنبا باخوميوس بالصعيد وترٌهب ?يه. وبعد مدة  رجع إلي بلده ومنها إلي بلاد ما بين النهرين، ومعه سبعون راهبا تتلمذوا علي يديه. وهناك سكن ?ي مغارة بالقرب من نصيبين وحوله تلاميذه والت? حوله كثيرون حتي بلغوا 250 راهبا، ?بني لهم ديرا، وبذلك أسس الحياة الرهبانية ?ي تلك البلاد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He became an acquaintance of St. James and prophesied for him that he would be the bishop of Nisibis. His prophesy was fulfilled and a strong spiritual friendship developed between them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتعر? بالقديس يعقوب، وتنبأ له بأنه سيصبح أسق?ا علي نصيبين، ?تحققت نبوءته، وصارت بينهما صداقة روحية قوية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Lord performed many signs, wonders and healing miracles by his hands. His fame became well known and was the reason for many of the pagans to believe.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وصنع الرب علي يديه آيات وعجائب وأش?ية كثيرة، ?ذاع صيته وكان سببا ?ي إيمان كثيرين من الوثنيين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he aged and the time of his departure drew near, he gathered his disciples, blessed and comforted them. One of his disciples saw an angel had come to receive his spirit. St. Okeen prayed a short prayer and delivered his spirit into the hand of the Lord whom he loved. The cell was filled with a sweet smelling aroma. His disciples prayed over him and buried him in his monastery nearby Nisibis.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما شاخ وقرب موعد نياحته جمع تلاميذه وباركهم وعزاهم، ورأي أحد تلاميذه ملاكا قد حضرلأخذ روحه. ?صلي القديس صلاة قصيرة، وأسلم روحه بيد الرب الذي أحبه، وامتلأت القلاية من رائحة طيب ذكي. ?صلي عليه تلاميذه، ود?نوه ?ي ديره بقرب نصيبين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Mar Okeen (Mar Augen) monastery is located on the southern slope of mount Izlo overlooking the city of Nisibis. The monastery is affiliated with the Syrian Orthodox church.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ومازال دير مار أوكين ( مار أوجين ) موجودا ?ي س?ح جبل الأزل المطل علي نصيبين وهو تابع لكنيسة السريان الأرثوذكس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.5">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fifth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس من شهر برمودة المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fifth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس من شهر برمودة المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the Prophet Ezekiel, son of Buzi</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد النبي حزقيال بن بوزي</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 576 B.C. the great prophet Ezekiel the priest, the son of Buzi , was martyred. He was one of the four Major Prophets. He was born around the year 624 B.C. and was raised in the land of Palestine. He was exiled to Babylon by the River Chebar along with king Jehoiachin, king of Judah, at the hands of Nebuchadnezzar in the year 598 B.C.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 576 ق.م ، أستشهد النبي حزقيال بن بوزي الكاهن. وهو أحد الأنبياء الأربعة الكبار. و?لدَ نحو سنة 624 ق.م. ونشأ ?ي ?لسطين ثم سبي مع يهوياكين ملك يهوذا بواسطة نبوخذ نصر إلي بابل عند نهر خابور وذلك سنة 598 ق.م.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the land of the Chaldeans, the spirit of the Lord was upon him, and he prophesied about wondrous things for twenty-two years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وهناك حلٌ عليه روح الرب ?تنبأ بأمور عجيبة مدة اثنتين وعشرين سنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He admonished the priests for forsaking teaching the people. He warned them for God would ask from them their souls if they neglect teaching them. (Ez. 34)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ومن هذه النبوات أنه بكَّت الكهنة علي تركهم تعليم الشعب، وحذرهم من ذلك مبيناً لهم أن الله يطلب ن?وس الشعب منهم إن هم أهملوا تعليمهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He prophesied concerning the baptism that sanctify the soul of the man and his body, soften his stony heart, and make him a son of God by the descent of the Holy Spirit upon him. (Ez. 36:25-27)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتنبأ أيضاً عن المعمودية التي تقدس ن?س الإنسان وجسده وتليين قلبه الحجري وتجعله أبناً لله بحلول الروح القدس عليه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He prophesied concerning the common resurrection and the rising of the bodies with their souls, and about their rewards for whatever they deserve. (Ez. 37:1-14)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم تنبأ عن قيامة الأجساد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Finally, he spoke concerning the birth of the Lord Christ from the Virgin St. Mary and her perpetual virginity, he said; "Then He brought me back to the outer gate of the sanctuary which faces toward the east, but it was shut. And the LORD said to me, "This gate shall be shut; it shall not be opened, and no man shall enter by it, because the LORD God of Israel has entered by it; therefore it shall be shut" (Ez. 44:1-2).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأخيراً تنبأ عن ميلاد المخلص من القديسة مريم وبقاء بتوليتها مختومة، إذ قال "هذا الباب يكون م?غلقاً لا ي?تح ولا يدخل منه إنسان لأن الرب إله إسرائيل دخل منه، ?يكون م?غلقاً".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He also wrote many useful sayings. God manifested through him many signs and great wonders. When the children of Israel worshipped idols in Babylon, he rebuked them; their leaders rose up against Ezekiel and killed him. They buried him in the tomb of Shem and Arphaxad.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وذكر أقوالاً أخري نا?عة. وقد أظهرالله علي يديه آيات عظيمة. ولما عبد بنو إسرائيل الأصنام ?ي بابل بكتهم ?وثب عليه رؤساؤهم وقتلوه ، ثم د?نوه ?ي مد?ن سام وأر?كشاد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا . آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Hepatius, Bishop of Gangara</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس هيباتيوس أسق? غنغرة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 41 of the martyrs (325 A.D.) St. Hepatius, Bishop of Gangara, was martyred. He was consecrated a bishop in the early part of the fourth century. He was one of the great fathers who defended the Divinity of the Lord Christ and His equality with His Father in essence. He refuted the error of the Arian heretics and others.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 41 للشهداء ( 325م )، أستشهد القديس هيباتيوس أسق? غنغرة. ر?سم أسق?اً ?ي أوائل القرن الرابع الميلادي، وكان من الآباء العظام الذين دا?عوا عن ألوهية السيد المسيح ومساواته لأبيه ?ي الجوهر ، م?نداً ضلال الهراطقة الأريوسيين وغيرهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               God had honored him with the gift of performing wonders, and was called the wonder worker. He attended the first Universal Council at Nicea in the year 325 A.D. On his way back, after attending the sessions of the Council, to Gangara, a group of the heretics were waiting for him by the road, attacked him and stoned him thus he was martyred. Then they threw his body in a hay barn. When the people of the city of Gangara knew they came in hast to the place where he was martyred. They took the holy body and buried him in the city with great veneration.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد شر?ه الله بموهبة صنع العجائب ولهذا ل?قب بالعجائبي، وقد حضر هذا الأب مجمع نيقية سنة 325م وبعد إنتهاء جلسات المجمع، و?يما هو عائد إلي بلده خرج عليه ?ريق من الهراطقة، ووثبوا عليه ورجموه  بالحجارة ثم طرحوا جسده ?ي مخزن تبن. ?لما عٌلم أهالي غنغرة أسرعوا إلي مكان الجسد ونقلوه حيث د?نوه بإكرام عظيم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.6">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Sixth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس من شهر برمودة المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the sixth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس من شهر برمودة المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Mary of Egypt, the Anchorite</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار نياحة القديسة مريم المصرية السائحة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 137 of the martyrs (421 A.D.) the hermit St. Mary of Egypt departed. She was born in the city of Alexandria about the year 61 of the martyrs (345 A.D.) to Christian parents. When she became 12 years old, Satan the enemy of good, deceived her and through her, he caught innumerable souls in doing evil.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               1 – ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 137 للشهداء (421م) تنٌيحت القديسة السائحة مريم القبطية وقد و?لدت بالإسكندرية نحو 61 للشهداء (345 م) من أبوين مسيحيين. ولما بلغت أثني عشرة سنة خدعها عدو الخير وأصطاد بها ن?وساً كثيرة لعمل الشر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               She continued in this sinful life for 17 years until the grace of God touched her life. She met people from Alexandria going to Jerusalem so she went with them. She also went on her sinful life there. Until one day she wished to enter through the door of the church of Resurrection, but she felt a power preventing her from entering the church and that was repeated for several times. Right away she realized that, what was happening because of her corruption.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ومكثت علي هذه الحالة الآثمة سبعة عشر سنة حتي أدركتها نعمة الله. ?رأت قوماً من الإسكندرية م?سا?رين إلي بيت المقدس. ?سلمت ذاتها لهم حتي وصلت بيت المقدس ، وهناك استمرت أيضاً ?ي الخطية. و?ي أحد الأيام أرادت الدخول من باب كنيسة القيامة ، ?شعرت بقوة تمنعها من الدخول وتكرر ذلك عدة مرات. وللحال تحققت أنه بسبب نجاستها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               She lifted up her eyes with a broken heart before the icon of the Virgin St. Mary she wept and interceded with her for the Lord to forgive her sins. She confirmed her strong intention of leaving the life of sin and the world totally. Then she entered the church without any hindrance. She wept profusely and rejoiced for the acceptance of her repentance. She entreated God to guide her for what was pleasing to Him and to guide her new life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               عندئذ ر?عت عينيها لأيقونة القديسة العذراء، وتش?عت بها أن يغ?ر لها الرب خطاياها وهي مستعدة أن تترك خطاياها، وأن تترك الخطية والعالم نهائياً. وبعد أن دخلت الكنيسة بدون ممانعة سكبت دموعاً غزيرة، و?رحت جداً لقبول الله توبتها، وطلبت من الله أن يرشدها ويستلم حياتها الجديدة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               She stood before the icon of the blessed Virgin St. Mary and asked for her intercession. She heard a voice coming out of the icon saying: "If you cross the Jordan River you will find rest and salvation." She left the church after she had confessed and partook of the Holy Mysteries. When she left the church and on her way she met a man who gave her three silver coins with which she bought bread. Then she crossed the Jordan River to the wilderness where she dwelt for 17 years fighting the lusts and the evil desires. She fought as she was fighting against real beasts until she overcame the enemy with the grace of God. She sustained herself with the herbs and plants of the desert.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ووق?ت أمام أيقونة القديسة العذراء وطلبت ش?اعتها. عندئذ سمعت صوتها من ناحية الأيقونة يقول "أعبري الأردن تجدي مكاناً لخلاصك". ?خرجت من الكنيسة بعد أن أعتر?ت وتناولت من الأسرار المقدسة. و?ي الطريق قابلها إنسان وأعطاها ثلاثة دراهم من ال?ضة، أبتاعت بها ثلاثة أرغ?ة من الخبز. ثم عبرت الأردن إلي البرية ومكثت سبعة عشرة سنة تحارب الشهوات غير المرئية مثلما تحارب وحوشاً حقيقية حتي تغلبت علي العدو. وأثناء هذه السنوات كانت تقتات من الحشائش.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the forty fifth year of her seclusion St. Zosima went to the wilderness, according to the custom of the monks of Palestine during the holy great fast for devotion and asceticism. Near the end of the fast he saw on his way back this Saint from far and he thought that she was a phantom. She fled from him however he ran after her until she hid herself behind a rock. She talked to him saying: "O my father Zosima, forgive me, if you wish to talk to me, throw me something to cover myself for I am naked." He marveled for she called him by his name. He threw to her his cloak and she covered herself with it. She asked him to bless her for he was a priest. He was amazed for she knew of his priesthood and instead he asked her to bless him. He asked her about her life story. She told him about all what had happened to her and asked him to go back to his monastery and not to tell anyone about her. She also asked him to bring with him in the next year the Holy Eucharist to partake of it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي السنة الخامسة والأربعين لسياحتها خرج القديس زوسيما القس إلي البرية حسب عادة الرهبان ?ي الصوم الكبير للإختلاء والتنسك. وقرب نهاية الصوم رأي ?ي طريق عودته هذه القديسة ?ظنها خيالاً ، ?هربت منه ?جري وراءها حتي اختبأت وراء صخرة. ?خاطبته قائلة "ياأبي زوسيما سامحني وان شئت أن تخاطبني ?اترك شيئاً أستتر به لأني عارية". ?تعجب جداً  إذ دعته باسمه. ?رمي لها رداءه ?استترت به ،  وطلبت منه أن يباركها لأنه كان كاهناً. ?تعجب من معر?تها بكهنوته ، ولم يتمالك ن?سه وطلب منها أن تباركه. ثم أستوضحها عن سيرتها، ?قصت عليه كل ما جري لها. وطلبت منه أن يعود إلي ديره ولا يحكي لأحد عنها ثم يحضر معه التناول المقدس ليناولها ?ي العام القادم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the next year she met him by the Jordan River and he was standing on the western shore of the river. She made the sign of the cross and walked over the water to the western shore. He marveled at that and she partook of the Holy Mysteries. She asked him to come to her in the next year. When he came to her in the following year Fr. Zosima found that she had departed while she was kneeling so he prayed over her. He found beside her a writing saying “My father Zosima, bury the body of Mary, the wretched woman, and leave to the dust this sinful body, and pray on my behalf." After he had buried her, he returned to his monastery, and told the monks her blessed biography. The Holy Father St. Zosima visited her cave every year. All the years of her life were 76 years spent 47 of them in the wilderness.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي العام التالي قابلته عند نهر الأردن وكان ?ي الشاطئ الغربي، ?رشمت علامة الصليب ومشت علي الماء ?تعجب من هذا وناولها. وسألته أن يعود إليها ?ي العام المقبل. و?ي الميعاد المحدد من العام التالي حضر القديس زوسيما، ?وجدها قد تنيٌحت وهي ساجدة، ?صلي عليها ووجد عند رأسها مكتوباً:  "ياأبي زوسيما أد?ن هنا جسد مريم البائسة وأترك للتراب جسد الخطية هذا وصلي من أجلي".  وبعد أن د?نها عاد إلي ديره وأخبر الآباء الرهبان بسيرتها المباركة. وكان القديس الأنبا زوسيما يزور مغارتها كل عام. وكانت سنو حياتها ستا وسبعين سنة قضت منها سبعة وأربعين سنة ?ي البرية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.7">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Seventh Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع من شهر برمودة المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the seventh day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع من شهر برمودة المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of the Righteous St. Joachim, the Father of the Blessed Virgin St. Mary</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة الصديق يواقيم والد القديسة العذراء مريم</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the just man St. Joachim the father of the blessed Virgin St. Mary, departed. He was born in the city of Nazareth, a descendant of King David and of the tribe of Judah.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم تنيٌح الصديق يواقيم والد القديسة العذراء مريم. و?لد بمدينةٌ الناصرة وهو من نسل داود من سبط يهوذا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               His wife Hannah was barren, and they both prayed and entreated God continually to give them a child. God gave them a good fruit which is the Virgin St. Mary. After God had pleased him with the birth of St. Mary, he presented her to the temple to serve as he vowed. He departed in peace at an age of 80 years when the Virgin was three years old.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت زوجته (حنٌة) عاقراً. وبمداومته معها علي الصلاة والطلبة إلي الله رزقهما الله ثمرة صالحة وهي القديسة مريم العذراء. وبعد أن أقر الله عينيه بموٌلد القديسة مريم قدمها إلي الهيكل لتخدم ?يه. ثم تنيٌح بسلام وهو ?ي الثمانين من عمره وكات القديسة العذراء ابنة ثلاثة سنين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Macrobius</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس مقرو?يوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the saint Anba Macrobius, the son of the governor of the city of Kaw, departed. When Anba Severus, Patriarch of Antioch, was wondering around the cities of Upper Egypt, he came to the city of Kaw and Macrobius ministered unto him. He accompanied Anba Severus on his visit to the monastery of Anba Moises. From what Macrobius saw from the holiness of the monks and their asceticism made him ask Anba Moises to accept him as a monk. Anba Moises explained to him the hardships of the monastic life.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  تنيٌح القديس الأنبا مقرو?يوس أبن حاكم مدينة قاو. ولما كان الأنبا ساويرس البطريرك الإنطاكي يجول ?ي الصعيد ووصل إلي مدينة قاو، كان مقرو?يوس قائماً بخدمته. ثم صحبه ?ي رحلته إلي دير القديس مويسيس القريب من العرابة المد?ونة. وهناك رأي مقرو?يوس قداسة الآباء الرهبان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Anba Moises asked him to resign his position and to relinquish all his money and possessions. He went to Kaw, appointed his brother in his place, returned to the monastery and put on the monastic garb. When his brothers Paul, Elias, and Joseph saw what their brother had done, they came to him and became monks by the hand of Anba Moises.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?طلب منه أن يترك وظي?ته وأمواله وممتلكاته. ?ذهب إلي قاون وعيٌن أخاه مكانه ثم رجع بعد هذا وترٌهب. ولما علم إخوته بولس وإيلياس ويوس? حضروا إليه وترٌهبوا علي يد الأنبا مويسيس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Anba Macrobius built many monasteries. There were about a thousand monks and about a thousand nuns under his guidance. He built many places for the poor and the needy, also built many churches and monasteries. God granted St. Macrobius the gift of healing the sick.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد شٌيد أنبا مقرو?يوس جملة أديرة. وكان تحت إشرا?ه نحو أل? راهب وأل? راهبة، وبني كثيراً من الأماكن لل?قراء والمحتاجين، وكنائس وأديرة عديدة ووهب الله القديس مقرو?يوس موهبة الش?اء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Theodosius, 33rd Patriarch, heard of him, he wrote praising and encouraging him. He asked him to come for the people of Alexandria could receive his blessing. When he came the Pope ordained him a priest then he returned to hi monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما سمع به البابا ثيؤدوسيوس البطريرك الثالث والثلاثون، كتب يمدحه ويشجعه ويستدعيه ليتبارك منه شعب الإسكندرية. ولما ذهب رسمه البابا قساً ثم عاد إلي ديره.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After he finished his good strife, he departed in peace. Multitudes gathered from all the nearby cities and his brother Anba Yousab, who was appointed as his successor in running the monasteries prayed over his brother Anba Macrobius and buried him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد أن أكمل جهاده تنيح بسلام، وك?نه أخوه الأنبا يوساب الذي صار خل?اً له ?ي تدبير الأديرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The appearance of his body was on the seventh day of Tobe, seven hundred thirty three years after his departure. That was in the days of Anba Yousab, bishop of Akhmeem and the Archon Isaac the scribe of prince Eiz-Eldeen El-Hamawy. Anba Yousab took the body out of its tomb in the mountain, down to the church of the monastery, where they buried him with hymns and praises.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هذا وقد كان ظهور جسده ?ي اليوم السابع من طوبة بعد نياحته بسبعمائة وثلاثة وثلاثين عامآ ?ي أيام الأنبا يوساب أسق? أخميم، والأرخن إسحق كاتب الأمير عز الدين الحمودي. ?تولي أسق? أخميم إخراج الجسد من مقبرته بالجبل ونزل به إلي كنيسة الدير. وهناك د?نوه بالتراتيل والتسابيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Sts. Agapius and Theodora</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسين أغابيوس وثيؤدورة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also is the commemoration of the martyrdom of Sts. Agapius and Theodora.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  تذكار أستشهاد القديسين أغابيوس وثيؤدوره.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.8">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eighth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن من شهر برمودة المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eighth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن من شهر برمودة المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the Holy Virgins: Agape, Eirene, and Shiona</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد العذاري القديسات أغابي وإيريني وشيونية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 20 of the martyrs (304 A.D.) the three holy virgins: Agape, Eirene, and Shiona were martyred. They were natives of Thessalonica, and worshipped the Lord Christ as their parents. They chose the life of chastity and vowed themselves to the Lord Christ. They persevered in fasting and praying, visited the convents often and practiced asceticism along with the nuns.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 20 للشهداء (304م) ، استشهدت القديسات أغابي وإيريني وشيونية. هؤلاء كن من أهل تسالونيكي، وكنٌ عابدات للسيد المسيح عن آبائهن. وقد نذرن أن?سهن للسيد المسيح. وك?ن مداومات علي الأصوام والصلوات ومترددات علي أديرة العذاري، متنسكات مع الراهبات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Maximianus reigned, he restored the worship of idols and persecuted the Christians. These saints were afraid and they fled to the mountain and hid themselves in a cave devoting themselves to their worship and asceticism.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تقلد ماكسيميانوس الحكم أعاد عبادة الأوثان وصار يضطهد المسيحيين. عندئذ خا?ت هؤلاء العذاري وهربن إلي الجبل إلي مغارة ، وظللن مداومات على نسكهن وعبادتهن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               An old Christian woman visited them weekly to bring them food and take the work of their hands to sell it, and donated the remainder as alms on their behalf to the poor. One day a wicked person observed the frequent visits of this old woman to the mountain, so he followed her secretly until he knew the cave that she entered. He hid himself so she would not see him on her way back, for he thought that she was hiding precious things in it. After she left the cave he entered it and found the precious pearls the brides of Christ standing praying. He informed the governor of Thessalonica about them. When they stood before the governor they confessed a good confession and refused to offer sacrifices to the gods. The Governor became furious, severely tortured them, then cast them into the fire thus they received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت إمرأة عجوز مسيحية تأتي إليهن بالطعام ، وتأخذ عمل أيديهن لتبيعه وتتصدق عنهن بما ي?ضل. وحدث أن أحد الأشرار رأى كثرة خروج هذه العجوز إلي الجبل، ?تبعها عن ب?عد إلي أن عر? المغارة ، ?اختبأ حتي لا تراه عند عودتها. وكان يظن أنها تخبئ أشياء ثمينة. ?لما خرجت من المغارة ، دخل إليها ?وجد الجواهر الن?يسة عرائس المسيح يصلين ، ?أبلغ عنهن. ولما وق?ن أمام الوالي اعتر?ن اعترا?اً حسناً ور?ضن تقديم القرابين للآلهة. ?حنق الوالي عليهن وعذٌبهن كثيراً ثم طرحهن ?ي النار، ونلن اكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهن ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the 150 believers by the hand of king of Persia</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد المائة والخمسين مؤمناً علي يد ملك ال?رس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also is the commemoration of the martyrdom of one hundred and fifty of the believers by the hand of the king of Persia. This king besieged Christian cities which were nearby the borders of his country, and captured many of the Christians. When they refused to worship the sun and the stars, he commanded to behead them thus they received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  تذكار أستشهاد مائة وخمسين من المؤمنين علي يد ملك ال??رس. وذلك أن هذا الملك كان قد أغار علي البلاد المسيحيين المتاخمة لحدود بلاده وسبي منهم كثيرين. ولما لم يطيعوه ويعبدوا الشمس والكواكب، أمر بقطع رؤوسهم، ?نالوا اكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.9">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Ninth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the ninth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Zosima (Zosimus) the Priest</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس الأنبا زوسيما القس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 141 of the martyrs (425 A.D.) the ascetic Holy Father Abba Zosima the priest, departed. He was born in the year 326 A.D. to godly Christian parents, who were natives of Palestine. When he was five years old his parents handed him to a righteous old monk, who raised him up in a Christian manner and taught him the church subjects. Shortly after he was ordained a deacon, then he became a righteous monk and grew in virtues.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذااليوم من سنة 241 للشهداء ( 525م )، تنٌيح الأب العابد الراهب المجاهد القس زوسيما. و?لد هذا القديس سنة 426م من أبوين مسيحيين قديسين من أهل ?لسطين. و?ي السنة الخامسة من عمره سلمه أبواه لراهب شيخ قديس. ?رباه تربية مسيحية وعٌلمه العلوم الدينية. وبعد قليل ر?سم شماساً. ثم صار راهباً تقياً ونما ?ي ال?ضيلة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He devoted himself to praising God and reading the Holy Scriptures day and night and during work also. When he had completed thirty five years in the monastery he was ordained a priest. Accordingly he increased his ascetic labors and spiritual struggle.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان ملازماً للتسبيح والقراءة ليل نهار و?ي وقت العمل أيضاً . ولما أكمل خمسا وثلاثين سنة ?ي الدير ر?سم قساً ?تزايد ?ي نسكه وزهده وجهاده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After spending thirteen years in the priesthood the enemy of good sowed in his mind that he surpassed all his contemporaries in virtues and righteousness. But the mercy of God willed to turn him away from this thought. God sent him an angel who commanded him to go to the monastery which was nearby the Jordan River. He rose up and went to the monastery where he found therein holy old men who were perfect in their way of life. He realized that he was far from what he thought of himself and he stayed with them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد أن قضي ثلاث عشرة سنة ?ي القسيسية ، زرع عدو الخير ?ي ?كره أنه قد أصبح ي?وق كل أهل زمانه ?ي التقوى وال?ضيلة. ولكن شاءت رحمة الله أن ترده عن هذا الظن ?أرسل الله ملاكاً أمره بالانتقال إلي الدير القريب من الأردن ?قام ومضي إليه. ?وجد شيوخاً قديسين كاملين ?ي سيرتهم. ?تبين له عندئذ أنه كان بعيداً عما ظنه ?ي ن?سه ?أقام عندهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The custom of these monks during the Holy Lent; after they partook of the Holy Communion on the first Sunday of the fast, they left the monastery. They wondered in the desert of Jordan each one carried out his spiritual fight by himself. St. Zosimus used to go out with them each year wondering in the desert asking God to show him what was profitable for him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان من عادة هؤلاء الشيوخ أنهم ?ي أيام الصوم الكبير ، و?ي الأحد الأول يتقربون من الأسرار المقدسة ثم يخرجون من الدير إلي براري الأردن، يجاهد كل منهم علي حدة. ?صار القديس زوسيما يخرج مثلهم ?ي البرية سائلاً من الله أن يريه ما ينت?ع منه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day as he was wondering about he encountered St. Mary the Egyptian (Coptic). He learned from her about her life story and the reason for her wondering in the desert. She told him and asked him to visit her in the next year and to bring her the Holy Mysteries. In the following year he found that she had departed. He prayed over her and buried her. When he returned he told the monks of the monastery her life story and her spiritual strife. He lived ninety nine years then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي إحدي المرات وجد القديسة مريم القبطية ، ?استعلم منها عن سيرتها، ?أعلمته وطلبت منه أن يأتي لها ?ي العام المقبل بالأسرار المقدسة. و?ي العام الذي يليه وجدها قد تنيٌحت ?صلي عليها ود?نها. ولما رجع قص سيرتها علي الآباء الرهبان. وبعد أن عاش تسعا وتسعين سنة تنيٌح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The commemoration of the Sign that took place by the hands of Pope Shenouda I, 55th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار الأعجوبة التي ص?نعت علي يد القديس البابا شنودة الأول البطريرك الخامس والخمسين</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 582 of the martyrs (866 A.D.) a great sign took place by the hands of our holy father Pope Shenouda I, 55th Patriarch of Alexandria. This honorable father had an annual custom to go to the monastery of St. Macarius to spend the Passion Week in the monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 582 للشهداء ( 866م ) ظهرت آية عظيمة علي يد أبينا القديس البابا شنودة الأول البطريرك الخامس والخمسين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. وهي أنه كان لهذا الأب الجليل عادة  سنوية أن يصعد إلي دير القديس مكاريوس ليقضي أسبوع الآلام بالدير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On Palm Sunday, of one of these times, the Berbers came to plunder the monasteries. They stood on the rock east of the church of St. Macarius. Their swords were drawn in their hands ready to kill and steal. The bishops and the monks gathered together and decided to leave the desert before the Holy Feast of Resurrection. When they told Pope Shenouda about what had happened he told them; "As for me I will not leave the desert until I complete the Pascal week.? On Maundy Thursday the situation became worse and the Pope comforted them with words of grace. After the Divine Liturgy of Holy Thursday, he took his staff that had the sign of the cross on it and he wanted to go out to meet the Berbers saying: "It is better for me to die with the people of God." When the Berbers saw him coming out alone without an armor in his hand, they retreated before his extraordinary courage and fled away as if they were pursued by an army and from this day onwards they never came back to do any harm.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي إحدي المرات وبعد أن صلي قداس خميس العهد خرج الآباء الرهبان إلي صوامعهم، عندئذ أقبل عليهم البربر ورموهم بالحجارة. ?رجع الآباء هاربين إلي البابا ليعر?وه بما حدث ، ?طمأنهم بكلمات النعمة. ثم أخذ البابا عكازه الذي عليه علامة الصليب ، وخرج لملاقاة  الأعداء قائلاً: "الأ?ضل لي أن أموت مع شعب الله". وحين رآه البربر خارجاً وحده أعزل من السلاح ، تراجعوا أمام شجاعته النادرة، كأن جنوداً قد صدوهم عن ذلك المكان ولم يعودوا إليه من ذلك اليوم بقصد ردئ.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.10">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Tenth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم العاشر من شهر برمودة  لمبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the tenth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم العاشر من شهر برمودة  لمبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Anba Isaac, the Disciple of Anba Apollo</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة الأنبا إيساك تلميذ الأنبا أبٌلوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the Holy Father Anba Isaac the disciple of the great Anba Apollo, departed. This holy man renounced the world since his young age. He became a monk in the wilderness of Shiheet (Scetis) under the guidance of Anba Apollo for twenty-five years. He exerted himself with a strenuous spiritual fight.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم تنيٌح الأب المجاهد الأنبا إيساك تلميذ الأب الكبير الأنبا أبلوس. وقد زهد هذا القديس العالم منذ صغره وترهب ?ي شيهيت علي يد الأنبا أبلوس مدة خمسة وعشرين سنة أجهد ن?سه ?يها جهاداً أذاب به جسده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He mastered the virtue of silence and quietness especially during the prayers and the Liturgies. He used to stand during the liturgy with his hands clasped and his head bent down until the end of the prayer then he returned to his cell, shutting his door, and did not associate with any one that day. When they asked him: "Why do you not talk to anyone who wished to talk to you during prayers or the Liturgy?" He answered saying: "There is time for talking and there is time for praying."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كما إنه أتقن ?ضيلة الصمت والهدوء أثناء الصلوات والقداسات. وكان من عادته وقت القداس أن يظل مكتو? اليدين مطامن الرأس حتي نهاية الصلاة ، ثم يعود إلي قلايته وي?غلق بابها عليه . ولا يقابل أحداً ?ي ذلك اليوم. ولما سألوه "لماذا لا تكلم من يريد الكلام معك وقت الصلاة أو القداس"، أجابهم قائلاً: "للكلام وقت وللصلاة وقت".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When his departure drew near the fathers the monks gathered around him to receive his blessing and they asked him: "Why did you flee from men." He answered them: "I was not fleeing from men but from Satan. For if a man hold a lighted lamp in the wind, it will be extinguished. So, it is with us when our minds enlightened during the prayers and the Liturgy then we occupies ourselves by talking with each other, our minds become darkened."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما دنا وقت نياحته ، أجتمع عنده الآباء الرهبان لنيل بركته وسألوه "لماذا كنت تهرب من الناس؟"، ?أجابهم "ما كنت أهرب من الناس بل من الشيطان ، لأن الإنسان إذا أمسك مصباح متقد ?ي الهواء ينط?ئ ، وهكذا نحن إذا أضاء عقلنا وقت الصلاة والقداس ، ثم تشاغلنا بالأحاديث ، ?إن عقلنا يظلم".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he finished his good endeavor departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل جهاده الصالح تنيٌح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Gabriel II, 70th patriarch of Alexandria, known as Ibn Turayk</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا غبريال الثاني البطريرك السبعين الشهير بابن تريك</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 861 of the martyrs (1145 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Gabriel II, 70th Patriarch of Alexandria, who was known as Ibn Turayk, departed. This saint was born in Old Cairo in the year 800 of the martyrs (1084 A.D.). His father was a pious priest who raised him with a Christian upbringing. His name was Abu el-Alaa Sa-eid Ibn Turayk and was ordained a deacon at a young age. He was wise, loving to everyone, well versed in the Holy Scriptures and the religious subjects.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي مثل هذا اليوم أيضاً  من سنة861 للشهداء (1145م)، تنيٌح الأب القديس البابا غبريال الثاني البطريرك السبعون من بطاركة الكرازة  المرقسية الشهير بابن تريك. و?لد هذا القديس بمصر القديمة سنة 800 للشهداء (1084م) بأسم أبو العلا  وكان والده كاهناً تقياً ?رباه تربية مسيحية. وصار أبو العلا صاعد بن تريك شماساً حكيماً محباً للجميع ومتضلعاً ?ي الأس?ارالإلهية والعلوم الدينية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Abu el-Alaa was also a scribe in the court of el-Khalifa. After a while he wanted to devout himself to serve the church of the martyr Abu Saifain however the Khalifa allowed him on condition of keeping his position as a scribe.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان أبو العلا أيضاً كاتباً بديوان الخلي?ة ، وبعد ?ترة أراد تكريس ن?سه لخدمة كنيسة الشهيد أبو سي?ين ?سمح له الوزير علي أساس أن يحت?ظ بوظي?ته ككاتب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the later days of Pope Macarius, someone working in the court of el-Khalifa falsely accused the Copts before him that they take the revenue of the churches and pass it on to the Europeans in secret. El-Khalifa became angry and ordered to take the revenue of the churches to the treasury. For this reason the Copts did not dare to take permission to elect a new Patriarch. They waited about two years until those accused the Copts were killed and the affairs had quieted down. Subsequently el-Khalifa permitted them to elect a new Patriarch.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي أواخر حياة البابا مكاريوس كان بديوان الخلي?ة من وشي له بأن الأقباط يأخذون أموال الكنائس ويمدون بها الأ?رنج سراً. ?غضب الخلي?ة وأمر بأخذها إلي بيت المال. لذلك لم يجسر الأقباط علي الإستئذان ?ي انتخاب البطريرك الجديد. وانتظروا حوالي سنتين حتي قتل الذين وشوا بالأقباط ?هدأت الأحوال ?أذن لهم الخلي?ة برسامة بطريرك.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               A group of people went to the wilderness of St. Macarius where they met Anba Youssef the abbot of St. John Kama’s monastery who told them; “Return O my children to Miser (Cairo) for the one who is chosen from God is the deacon Abu al-Alaa Ibn Turayk.? They returned to Cairo and took Abu Alaa to Alexandria. He was consecrated on the 9th of Meshir, year 847 of the martyrs (1131 A.D.). He was forty seven years old and was called Gabriel II.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               عندئذ ذهب مجموعة من الشعب إلي برية القديس مكاريوس وهناك تقابلوا مع الأنبا يوس? أب دير القديس أنبا يوأنس كاما. ?قال لهم "عودوا يا أولادي إلي مصر لأن المختار من الله هو الشماس أبو العلا بن تريك". ?عادوا إلي مصر وأخذوا أبا العلا إلي الإسكندرية ور?سم ?ي التاسع من أمشير سنة 847 للشهداء (1131م). وكان عمره حينئذ سبع وأربعين سنة وس?مي غبريال الثاني.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the enthronement he went to St. Macarius monastery in Shiheet where he celebrated the Divine Liturgy. At the end of the Liturgy, he added to the confession this sentence "He made it one with His Divinity.? When the fathers objected he informed them that this statement was added by the Holy Synod. After a lengthy deliberation, they asked him to add this sentence: "Without mingling, without confusion, and without alteration," because of the fear of falling into the heresy of Eutyches, and the Pope agreed with them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بعد الرسامة ذهب البابا غبريال إلي دير أنبا مكاريوس بشيهيت حيث صلي القداس الإلهي ، وأضا? للإعترا? الأخير النص القائل : "وجعله واحداً مع لاهوته". ?أحتج عليه الآباء الرهبان  لتلك الإضا?ة ، ?أ?ادهم بأن هذا النص هو قرار المجمع المقدس. وبعد التداول معه طلبوا منه إضا?ة عبارة "بغير إختلاط ولا إمتزاج ولا تغيير" خشية الإنسياق لهراطقة أوطاخي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his papacy, he ordained 53 bishops and many priests. He completely refused simony for ordinations.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد رسم قداسته ?ي عهده ثلاثة وخمسين أسق?ا ، وقد ر?ض السيمونية تماماً ?ي الرسامات، حتي أنه حضر إليه قس يدعي "بقيرة" يريد رسامته أسق?ا علي أخميم نظير مبلغ من المال. ولما ر?ض البابا مطلبه ذهب القس إلي أبن الخلي?ة يطلب وساطته. ?كتب البابا للخلي?ة قائلاً:  "إن ديني يمنعني من رسامة كاهن يبغي شراء هذه الكرامة بالمال".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Gabriel had many splendid achievements, of them:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد كان لهذا القديس البابا أعمال جليلة منها:            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               First: He commanded the reading of the epistles and the Gospels in Arabic after reading them in Coptic, also the sermons so that the people could understand the readings and the sermons.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أولاً :أصدر أمره بقراءة الرسائل والأناجيل باللغة العربية بعد قراءتها بالقبطية، وكذلك العظات، حتي يتسني للشعب أن ي?هم القراءات والعظات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Second: The Pope realized the difficulty of reading the Holy Bible, the two testaments, in Passion Week. He arranged certain readings for that purpose then Anba Peter (Petros) bishop of El-Bahnasa added the proper prophecies and sermons for each hour to form the Katameros (Lectionary) of the Holy Pascha which the Church still uses today.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثانياً: رأي البابا صعوبة قراءة الكتاب المقدس بعهديه  ?ي إسبوع البصخة . ?نظم قراءات معينة لذلك ?كانت نواة قطماروس البصخة المقدسة ، ثم أضا? الأنبا بطرس أسق? البهسنا بعض النبوات والمواعظ، حتي أصبح قطمارس البصخة كما هو عليه الآن .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Anba Peter also arranged for the four Gospels to be read during the Passion Week: the gospel of St. Matthew on Tuesday, the gospel of St. Mark on Wednesday, the gospel of St. Luke on Thursday and the gospel of St. John to be read in the eve of the Holy Resurrection.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كما أضا? الأنبا بطرس قراءة أناجيل متي يوم ثلاثاء البصخة، ومرقس يوم الأربعاء، ولوقا يوم الخميس ويوحنا ليلة القيامة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He also arranged the reading of the one hundred fifty one psalms, in the eve of bright Saturday.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               والمائة وواحد وخمسين مزموراً ليلة سبت ال?رح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Third: Pope Gabriel issued some canons in three books:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثالثاً : أصدر البابا غبريال بعض القوانين ?ي ثلاثة كتب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               First Book: it contained thirty two canons concerning the organization of the affairs of the church, and the civil and religious relation of the people with the church.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الكتاب الأول منها يشمل إثنين وثلاثين قانوناً ويختص بتنظيم أمور البيعة وعلاقة الشعب بها دينياً ومدنياً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Second Book: Was about the organization of all things concerning the clergy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               والكتاب الثاني يختص بتنظيم أمور الاكليروس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Book Three: Was about inheritance.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               والكتاب الثالث بالمواريث.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After this saint had completed his good endeavor he had a serious illness. During his sickness, he saw in a dream a group of priests and monks carrying gospels, censers and crosses and heard them saying; “You will be healed, however we will come back to you after one year to take you to be with us.? He was cured and after one year he departed in peace. He remained on the Apostolic Throne for fourteen years and three month.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد أن أدي هذا القديس واجبه مرض مرضاً شديداً. و?ي أثناء مرضه رأي ?ي حلم مجموعة من الكهنة والرهبان يحملون الأناجيل والمجامر والصلبان وسمعهم يقولون "ستنال الش?اء. وبعد سنة تتنيٌح، وبعد ذلك بسنة ?علاً تنيح البابا غبريال بعد أن قضي علي الكرسي المرقسي أربعة عشر سنة وثلاثة أشهر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was buried in the church of the martyr St. Mercurius Abu Saifain. During the papacy of Pope Marcus III, 73rd Patriarch of Alexandria, the body of Pope Gabriel II was relocated along with the body of Anba Youannes V to the monastery of St. Macarius in Shiheet. That was during the Holy Fast of the year 1170 A.D. in a great celebration.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ك?نوه ود?نوه بأكرام بكنيسة الشهيد مرقوريوس أبي سي?ين ، و?ي عهد البابا مرقس الثالث بن زرعة البطريرك الثالث والسبعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية تم نقل جسد البابا غبريال الثاني مع جسد الأنبا يوأنس الخامس إلي دير القديس مكاريوس بشيهيت ، وذلك ?ي ?ترة الصوم الكبير سنة 1170م بإحت?ال كبير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.11">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eleventh Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الحادي عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eleventh day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الحادي عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Theodora the Nun</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديسة ثيؤدورا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, the pure and holy mother (Amma ) Theodora departed. This holy woman, who was born in Alexandria, was the only daughter of Christian wealthy parents in Alexandria .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم تنيٌحت القديسة الطاهرة الأم ثيؤدورا (وكانت تدعي أماً مما يدل علي أن الكلمة أما كلمة قبطية) و?لدت هذه القديسة بالإسكندرية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When she became a young woman her parents wished to give her in marriage so they provided for her costly apparels and much jewelry. She refused for she desired in her heart the worship of God, asceticism and consecration. She sold all what her parents bought her, gave to the needy, and then she built a church west of Alexandria, she also built inside the walls of the church a private room as her private residence. She looked after the poor, needy, infirm and prisoners.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت أبنة وحيدة لوالدين من أغنياء الإسكندرية المسيحيين. ولما بلغت سن الشباب أراد أبواها أن يزوجاها ، ?أحضرا إليها الكثير من الحلي والملابس ال?اخرة. ?لم تقبل ذلك لأنها كانت تميل بقلبها إلي عبادة الله والن?سك والتكريس. ?باعت كل ما أحضره لها والداها ووزعت منه علي المساكين ثم بنيت كنيسة غربي الإسكندرية. وبنت داخل أسوار الكنيسة غر?ة لسكنها الخاص. وكانت تعتني بال?قراء والمحتاجين والمرضي والمسجونين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After a while she went to Pope Athanasius, the apostolic and asked him to tonsure her nun. When he was assured of her desire and knew everything about her dedication, he shaved her head and ordained her nun in one of the convents. She devoted herself to austere asceticism and fought a great spiritual fight, and became worthy to see divine visions, discern the spirits and the thoughts.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد ?ترة ذهبت إلي البابا أثناسيوس الرسولي وطلبت منه أن يجعلها راهبة. ?لما تحقق من رغبتها وعر? كل شئ عن تكريسها ، قص شعرها ورهبنها بأحد الأديرة. ?تنسكت نسكاً زائداً وجاهدت جهاداً روحياً حتي أستحقت أن تنظر المناظر الإلهية وتمييز الأرواح والأ?كار.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Athanasius visited her often with his teachings. When he was exiled, he sent her many epistles full of valuable discourses. She was contemporary to five Patriarchs: Alexandros, Athanasius, Peter II, Timothy I and Theophilus. She was also contemporary to Abba Pachom of the Koinonia and three of his successors.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان البابا أثناسيوس ي?تقدها كثيراً بتعاليمه. حتي إنه لما ن?ي كان يكاتبها من من?اه بالعظات الم?يدة. وقد عاصرت هذه القديسة خمسة من البطاركة وهم : ألكسندروس وأثناسيوس وبطرس وتيموثاوس وثاؤ?يلس. كذلك عاصرت الأنبا باخوم أب الشركة وثلاثة من خل?ائه وهم بترونيوس وأورسيسيوس وثيؤدورس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               She put down many useful sayings with the guidance of God and from what she learned from these Holy Fathers.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد وضعت أقوالاً نا?عة بإرشاد من الله ومما تعلمته من أولئك الآباء منها :            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               First: On Humility            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أولاً عن الإتضاع :            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               No asceticism, nor vigils, nor any labor can save a person but the true humility. A hermit had the gift of casting out evil spirits, once asked them what drive you out? Is with fasting? They answered we do not eat or drink. He asked, is with vigils? They replied we do not sleep. He then asked, is by seclusion from the world? They answered we live in the wilderness. Then what power drives you out, he asked. They replied; nothing overcomes us but humility. Now see my children how humility overcomes the devils.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لا الن?سك ولا السهر ولا أي تعب يقدر أن يخلص غير الإتضاع الحقيقي[. كان يوجد متوحد يخرج الشياطين. سألهم بماذا تخرجون ؟ هل تخرجون بالصوم ؟ أجابوا نحن لا نأكل ولا نشرب. أ بالسهر ؟، أجابوا نحن نعيش ?ي البراري، عندئذ قال لهم بأية قوة تخرجون ؟ قالوا ليس شئ يغلبنا سوي الإتضاع. أنظروا كي? يغلب الإتضاع الشياطين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Second: On fulfilling the commandments            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثانياً عن عمل الوصية :            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               A man once cursed a godly man who in turn answered him saying: “I am able to answer you in reply to your words but the law of God shut my mouth.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               حدث أن إنساناً شتم إنساناً تقياً ?أجابه: "كنت قادراً أن أجيبك مما يوا?ق كلامك، لكن ناموس الله يغلق ?مي".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Third: On the necessity of striving (Labor – Fight of Faith)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثالثاً ضرورة الجهاد :            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               A monk said, because of the fury of temptations that befell him; “Let me leave that place.? When he started to put his sandals on, he saw a person putting also his sandals on. He asked him; “Where are you also going?? He replied, “I am going to wherever you are going, for because of you I am staying in this place, so if you wanted to move from her, in turn I will follow you. I shall be wherever you dwell.? The monk decided to stay where he was and did not move.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               قال راهب من شدة التجارب التي تلاحقه "لنمض من ههنا". وإذ انتعل حذاءه، رأي شخصآ ينتعل حذاءه أيضاً. ?قال له "إلي أنت ماض أيضاً؟"، أجابه "إلي الموضع الذي أنت ماض إليه ، لأني من أجلك أنا مقيم ?ي هذا الموضع. ?إن أردت الإنتقال من ههنا ?سو? أنتقل بدوري، لأني ملازم لك حيثما سكنت" ?مكث الراهب ?ي مكانه ولم يغيره.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Fourth: On enduring tribulations and afflictions            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               رابعاً إحتمال الضيقات:            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               We have to strife to “Enter by the narrow gate … because narrow is the gate and difficult is the way which leads to life ? As the tree if it is not subjected to the winter storms it will not bring forth fruits. So we also in this age we face a stormy winter of tribulations and various trials to be able to inherit the kingdom of God.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لنجاهد أن ندخل من الباب الضيق ، لأنه كما أن الشجرة إذ لم تتعرض لعواص? الشتاء لايمكنها أن تأتي بثمر ، هكذا الحال بالنسبة لنا أيضاً. هذا الدهر شتاء عاص? ، ?قط بالضيقات والتجارب المتنوعة يمكننا أن نرث ملكوت الله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Once St. Theodora asked Pope Theophilus about the saying of the apostle Paul; “redeeming the time. ? He replied saying; “This saying shows us how to gain in all our circumstance. If it is a time of insult or contempt, you can benefit from that time by humility and patience. So in all our adverse circumstances if we desire we can turn them into a spiritual gain for us.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هذا وقد سألت هذه القديسة البابا ثاؤ?يلس عن قول الرسول بولس "م?تدين الوقت" (كو 4 : 5)، ?أجابها "هذا القول ي?ظهر لنا كي? نربح كل أوقاتنا. كمثال إن كنت ?ي وقت هو ان أقتنيه بالصبر وارتجيه. هكذا كل الأمور المضادة لنا يمكننا -  إن أردنا – أن نصيرها ربحاً لنا".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When St. Theodora finished her strife, she departed in peace and she was one hundred years old.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكملت هذة القديسة جهادها تنيٌحت بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. John, Bishop of Gaza</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس يوحنا أسق? غزة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the Holy Father Anba John, Bishop of Gaza, departed. He was contemporary for five Patriarchs and they were: Pope Alexandros (19), Pope Athanasius the Apostolic (20), Pope Peter II (21), Pope Timothy I (22) and Pope Theophilus (23).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  تنيٌح القديس الأنبا يوحنا أسق? غزة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.12">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twelfth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثاني عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twelfth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثاني عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Honorable Archangel Michael</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار رئيس الملائكة الجليل ميخائيل</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of every Coptic month the church celebrates a commemoration for the honorable Archangel Michael the head of the heavenly hosts and the intercessor of mankind.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من كل شهر قبطي ت?عيد الكنيسة بتذكار رئيس الملائكة الجليل ميخائيل رئيس السمائيين والش?يع ?ي جنس البشر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his holy intercession be with us all. Amen            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة ش?اعته المقدسة ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Alexander, the Confessor, Bishop of Jerusalem</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس ألكسندروس المعتر? أسق? أورشليم</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 250 A.D. the Holy Father Anba Alexander, the confessor, bishop of Jerusalem, departed. He was a fellow student of the scholar Origen in the Theological School of Alexandria. He studied at the hands of St. Pantaenus and his successor St. Clement of Alexandria, and he grew in virtue and knowledge.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 250م تنيٌح الأب القديس ألكسندروس المعتر? أسق? أورشليم. كان هذا الأب ر?يقاً للعلامة أوريجانوس ?ي التلمذة بمدرسة الإسكندرية اللاهوتية وقد درس علي يدي القديس بنتينوس وخلي?ته القديس أكليمنضدس السكندري. وقد نما هذا الأب ?ي ال?ضيلة والعلٌم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Holy Father was chosen a bishop for one of the cities of Cappadocia. In the year 202 A.D., he confessed the Lord Christ before Emperor Septimius Severus who seized, tortured and imprisoned him for many years. After his release and with divine providence he went to Jerusalem to receive the blessing of the holy places and then return to his country.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي سنة 202م قبض عليه الإمبراطور سبتميوس ساويرس ?شهد للسيد المسيح أمامه بكل شجاعة. ?سجنه عدة سنوات وبعد خروجه  من السجن ذهب إلي أورشليم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Narcissus, who was the Bishop of Jerusalem at that time, was advanced in age. When St. Alexander finished his visit and decided to return to his diocese in Cappadocia, the people of Jerusalem heard a voice from heaven saying: "Go to the gate of the city, and the first one to enter it, seize him and make him stay with St. Narcissus to assist him." When they went to the gate they met the Bishop Alexander, and they pleaded with him to stay with Abba Narcissus to assist him. He refused because he could not leave his flock that the Lord Christ had entrusted him with. They told him about the voice which they heard and that it was God's Will. He accepted and wrote to the people of his parish. He remained in Jerusalem, assisting its bishop Anba Narcissus, for about 3 years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وصار أسق?اً مساعداً لأسق?ها نركسيوس نظراً لكبر سنه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of St. Narcissus, he continued to shepherd the people of Jerusalem with the best of care. In the year 216 A.D. the scholar Origen went to Palestine and his old friend Alexandros welcomed him. He ordained him a priest what displeased Pope Demetrius the vine dresser, 12th Patriarch of Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي سنة 216م ذهب العلامة أوريجانوس إلي ?لسطين ?رحب به صديقه القديم ألكسندروس ورسمه قساً مما ضايق البابا الإسكندري ديمتريوس الكرام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Emperor Maximianus seized St. Alexander, inflicted him with many tortures and then imprisoned him. When Emperor Gordian III reigned, he released the saint. This father sat on the Episcopal throne in quietness and peace until Decius rose, killed Emperor Philip, and reigned in his stead.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد ذلك قبض الإمبراطور مكسيميوس علي الأسق? ألكسندروس وعذبه كثيراً ثم أودعه ?ي السجن، ولما جاء الملك غورديان الثالث أطلق سراحه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Decius incited persecution against the Christians; he seized this Holy Father and many other believers and tortured them severely. He cast St. Alexander in prison where he remained until he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولكن لما جاء الملك ديسيوس قبض علي هذا القديس مع كثيرين من المؤمنين وعذٌبهم ثم طرحهم ?ي السجن وظل القديس ?ي السجن حتي تنيٌح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Antonios, Bishop of Thmoui</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس أنطونيوس أسق? طمويه</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the departure of the Holy Father St. Antonios, Bishop of Thmoui.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  تنيٌح القديس أنطونيوس أسق? طمويه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.13">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Thirteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the thirteenth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of Sts. Joshua and Joseph</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسين يشوع ويوس?</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the holy monks Anba Joshua and Anba Joseph were martyred. They were disciples of St. Milius of mount Khorasan .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم إستشهد القديسان الراهبان الأنبا يشوع والأنبا يوس?، تلميذا الأب القديس ميليوس بجبل خوراسان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               These two saints lived a life of asceticism and spiritual strive along with their teacher St. Milius in a cave on mount Khorasan.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان هذان القديسان يعيشان حياة النسك والجهاد الروحي مع معلٌمهما القديس ميليوس ?ي مغارة بجبل خوراسان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               One day the two sons of the king of Khorasan went out to hunt wild beasts. They set their traps up which caught St. Milius. When they knew that he was Christian, they asked him to raise incense to the Sun and fire but he refused. They became enraged at the saint and his two disciples Joshua and Joseph. They seized the two disciples, tortured and slew them thus they received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث أن خرج و?لدا ملك خورسان لصيد الوحوش ونصبا شباكهما ، ?وقع القديس ميليوس داخل الشبكة. ولما عر?ا أنه مسيحي أمراه أن يقرب البخور للشمس والنار  ?ر?ض. ?حنق الإثنان عليه وعلي تلميذيه يشوع ويوس?، ?أمسكا بالتلميذين وعذباهما وقتلاهما ?نالا إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهما ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Yoannis XVII, 105th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا يوأنس السابع عشر البطريرك الخامس بعد المائة من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1461 of the martyrs (1745 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Yoannis (John) the seventeenth, 105th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. He was born in the city of Mallawy, in Upper Egypt by the name Abdel-Sayed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 1461  للشهداء (1745م)، تنيٌح القديس البابا يوأنس السابع عشر البطريرك الخامس  بعد المائة من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. و?لد هذا القديس بمدينة ملوي باسم عبد السيد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he was 25 years old, he became a monk in the monastery of St. Antonios where he lived a life of asceticism, fasting and prayer. When Pope Yoannis the 16th wished to renovate the monastery of Anba Paula which was ruined, the monk Abdel-Sayed was one of the four monks he choose to populate and renovate the monastery. He did not spare any effort to renovate and rebuild the monastery. He also exerted himself in worship, and learning reading and writing, and then he thoroughly studied the holy books. Pope Yoannis, 103rd Patriarch ordained him priest along with his fellow monk Mourgan El-Assuity, who became, later on, Pope Petros VI, 104th Patriarch.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي الخامسة والعشرين من عمره، ترٌهب بدير القديس الأنبا أنطونيوس ، حيث عاش ?ي نسك وصوم وصلاة. ولما أراد البابا يوأنس السادس عشر أن يعمر دير القديس الأنبا بولا أهتم بتعمير الدير ، كما أجهد ن?سه ?ي النسك والقراءة والكتابة ، ?رسمه البابا يوأنس السادس عشر قساً ومعه الراهب مرجان الذي تولي الكرسي البطريركي باسم البابا بطرس السادس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the throne became vacant after the departure of Pope Petros VI, the bishops, priests, and lay leaders prayed and cast an altar lot which fell on Fr. Abdel-Sayed. He was consecrated Patriarch in the church of the martyr Mercurius Abu-Saifain in Old Cairo on the 6th day of Tobe, year 1443 of the martyrs (1727 A.D.) When he went down to the tomb of his predecessor to retrieve the staff and the cross, according to the existing custom, he heard the bones rattled and that frightened him. This was the reason for abolishing this custom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما خلا الكرسي بنياحة البابا بطرس السادس، صلي الآباء الأساق?ة والأراخنة، وألقوا قرعة هيكلية ?وقعت علي الراهب عبد السيد ورسموه بطريركياً بكنيسة الشهيد مرقوريوس أبي سي?ين بمصر القديمة ?ي يوم 6 طوبه سنة 1443 للشهداء (1727م).وحسب العادة الجارية  نزل البابا الجديد إلي مقبرة سل?ه ليستلم العكاز والصليب ، أحدثت العظام صوتاً ?ي وجه ??زع، وكانت هذه الحادثة سبباً ?ي أبطال هذه العادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Pope paid a great attention for building a church in the monastery of Anba Antonios and another one in the monastery of Anba Paula. The archon (El-Moallem) Girgis of Serugh paid for the building of these two churches. He also ordained a Metropolitan for Ethiopia.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد اهتم هذا البابا ببناء كنيسة بدير الأنبا أنطونيوس وأخري بدير الأنبا بولا ، علي ن?قة المعلٌم جرجس السروجي. كما قام برسامة مطرانا للحبشة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the days of this Pope, Pope Clement the 12th, Pope of Rome, wanted to attract the Copts to the Catholic Church. He established in Rome a school to teach the students methods of propaganda in conjunction with their theological studies. Then he sent the graduates of this school to Upper Egypt obliging them to search for the smart Coptic young men and to facilitate for them the enrolment in the Catholic schools to pave the way to send them to Rome. He endowed a large sum of money for this undertaken. Among those who studied in Rome was Raphael el-Toukhy who was ordained a bishop for el-Fayyom. Shortly after his ordination, the Roman Pontiff summoned him to print the Coptic Orthodox Liturgical books of prayers after making the necessary changes to make them in accordance to the Catholic faith. Later on they also recruited Antonius, bishop of Girga and Akhmim, and consequently the Orthodox Church excommunicated him and he fled to Rome where he died.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأيضاً ?ي أيام هذا البابا أراد البابا أكليمنضس الثاني عشر بابا روما أن يستميل الأقباط إلي الكنيسة الكاثوليكية ?أنشأ ?ي روما مدرسة يلقن ?يها الطلبة وسائل للدعاية لذلك، بالإضا?ة إلي دراستهم اللاهوتية. ثم بعث بخريجي هذه المدرسة إلي بلاد الصعيد بعد أن ألزمهم بالبحث عن الصبية الأقباط الأذكياء وإدخالهم المدارس الكاثوليكية تمهيدآ لإرسالهم إلي روما ورصد لذلك أموالاً كثيرة. ومن الذين تعلموا ?ي روما رو?ائيل الطوخي الذي ر?سم أسق?ـا علي ال?يوم، وبعد الرسامة ب?ترة أستدعاه الحبر الروماني لكي يطبع كتب الصلوات الطقسية القبطية الأرثوذكسية مع إجراء التغييرات اللازمة لجعلها تت?ق مع العقيدة الكاثوليكية. و?يما بعد إستمالوا إليهم أنطونيوس أسق? جرجا وأخميم، ?حرمته الكنيسة الأرثوذكسية وهرب إلي روما ومات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Yoannis realized these Catholic efforts, he greatly cared for educating his flock explaining to them the sound Orthodox faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما رأي البابا يوأنس هذه المجهودات الكاثوليكية ، اهتم جداً بتوعية شعبه وشرح العقيدة الأرثوذكسية السليمة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he completed his good endeavor, he departed in peace. They prayed the funeral rites in the church of the Virgin St. Mary in Haret el-Rum then he was taken to the church of the martyr Abu Safain where he was buried in the tomb of our fathers the Patriarchs.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيٌح بسلام، ?ك?نوه وصلوا عليه بكنيسة القديسة مريم بحارة الروم، ثم مضوا به إلي كنيسة الشهيد مرقوريوس أبي سي?ين ود?نوه هناك بمقبرة الآباء البطاركة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessings of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Dionisa (Denisa) the Deaconess</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديسة ديونيسة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This day also marks the commemoration of the departure of St. Dionisa (Denisa), the deaconess who was appointed by the apostles to serve women.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي مثل هذا اليوم أيضاً  ت?عيٌد الكنيسة بنياحة القديسة ديونيسة الشماسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Midius</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس ميديوس الشهيد</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the church celebrates the commemoration of the martyrdom of St. Midius.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  ت?عيٌد الكنيسة بتذكار أستشهاد القديس ميديوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.14">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fourteenth Day of the Blessed Mouth of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fourteenth day of the blessed mouth of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Maximus, 15th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا مكسيموس البطريرك الخامس عشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, of the year 282 A.D. the Holy Father Pope Maximus, 15th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. He was born in Alexandria to Christian parents. They enrolled him in the Theological School of Alexandria. He excelled in the Greek language, Philosophy and the church subjects. He was pious and feared God.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 282م تنيٌح القديس البابا مكسيموس البطريرك الخامس عشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية . و?لد هذا القديس بمدينة الإسكندرية من أبوين مسيحيين. ?أدخلاه مدرسة الإسكندرية اللاهوتية ?أتقن اللغة اليونانية وال?لس?ة وعلوم الكنيسة وكان تقياً يخا? الله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Heraclas ordained him deacon then Pope Dionysius ordained him priest for St. Mark church in Alexandria and delegated to him the exhortation of the people of the city. He was dedicated in serving the people and teaching them. He endured the suffering that afflicted the Christians under Emperor Decius.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               رسمه البابا ياروكلاس شماسآ علي كنيسة الإسكندرية ثم رسمه البابا دينيسيوس قساً وعينه  واعظاً بالكنيسة المرقسية. ?ت?اني ?ي خدمة الشعب وتعليمه وقد تحمل آلام الاضطهاد من الإمبراطور ديسيوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of Pope Dionysius, he was consecrated Patriarch in the year 264 A.D. During his days the heresy of Mani spread from the Persian country to Egypt. This heresy forbade marriage and eating meats. The Pope paid a special attention to exhorting the people, visiting them and confirming them in the Orthodox Faith through his sermons and teachings.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد نياحة البابا ديونيسيوس تمت رسامته بطريركياً ?ي سنة 264م. و?ي أيامه ظهرت بدعة ماني من بلاد ?ارس ?أهتم البابا بتعليم الشعب وأ?تقاده مثبتاً اياهم بعظاته وتعاليمه علي الإيمان المستقيم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he finished his good endeavor departed in peace after he sat on the apostolic throne for 17 years and 5 month.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل جهاده الصالح تنيٌح بسلام بعد أن جلس علي الكرسي المرقسي سبع عشر سنة وخمسة أشهر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessings of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Ehron the Syrian</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس أهرون السرياني</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 105 of the martyrs (389 A.D.) St. Ehron of Serugh, the Syrian, departed. This Holy Father was born in Serugh in Mesopotamia to godly Christian parents. They raised him with a Christian upbringing and taught him the evangelical manners. He adored since his young age the life of prayer and worship.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 105 للشهداء (389م)، تنيٌح القديس أهرون السروجي السرياني. و?لد هذا القديس ?ي سروج من بلاد ما بين النهرين من أبوين مسيحيين تقيين ، ?ربياه تربية مسيحية وعلماه الآداب الإنجيلية ، ?أحب منذ صغره الصلاة والعبادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he became a young man, he went along with the shepherds to tend to his father’s sheep where he saw a monastery. He went to it and saw how the monks were perfect in virtue and worship. He listened to their prayers and admired their life. He asked the abbot of the monastery to accept him. He rejoiced and accepted him as he also prophesied that he would be a blessing for many. He dwelt in the monastery for many years in strife and worship then he left and lived in a cave on the mount that was nearby the monastery for three years. Afterwards he went to the mount of the Armenians and became a disciple to a hermit called Gregory. Later on he went to Jerusalem to receive the blessings of the holy places then he returned again to the mount of the Armenians. He established a monastery and many gathered around him. They became his disciples and God granted him many gifts.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أصبح شاباً خرج مع الرعاه ليرعي غنم أبيه وهناك أبصر ديراً به رهبان كاملون ?ي ال?ضيلة والعبادة. ?ذهب إليه ورأي الرهبان وسمع صلواتهم ?أع?جب بهذه الحياة وطلب من رئيس الدير أن يقبله ??رح به وتنبأ له أنه سيكون بركة لكثيرين. مكث ?ي الدير عدة سنوات ?ي الجهاد والعبادة ثم خرج وسكن ?ي مغارة بالجبل القريب من الدير ثلاث سنوات. بعدها رحل إلي جبل الأرمن وتتلمذ لمتوحد ي?دعي غريغوريوس. ذهب بعد ذلك إلي أورشليم وتبارك من الأماكن المقدسة ثم رجع إلي جبل الأرمن مرة أخري.  وهناك بني ديراً ?ألت? حوله كثيرون تتلمذوا علي يديه، وقد أعطاه الله مواهب كثيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he grew old and his departure drew near, he gathered his disciples, blessed them and instructed them with monastic commandments important for their life then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما شاخ وقربت نياحته جمع تلاميذه وباركهم وأوصاهم وصايا رهبانية هامة لحياتهم ثم تنيٌح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessings of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.15">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Fifteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس عشر من شهر برمودة المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the fifteenth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God begin it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس عشر من شهر برمودة المبارك، أحسن الله إستقباله، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Consecration of the church of St. Agabus, one of the Seventy Disciples</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تكريس كنيسة القديس أغابوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day was the consecration of the church of St. Agabus, one of the Seventy Apostles. He prophesied about the events that befell St. Paul saying: "Thus says the Holy Spirit, 'So shall the Jews at Jerusalem bind the man who owns this belt, and deliver him into the hands of the Gentiles.'" (Acts 21:10-11)            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم تم تكريس كنيسة القديس أغابوس الرسول أحد السبعين وهو الذي تنبأ عـما أصاب القديس بولس الرسول إذ قال "الرجل الذي له هذه المنطقة سيربطه اليهود هكذا ?ي أورشليم ويسلمونه إلي أيدي الأمم" (أع : 21 : 11.).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessings of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Alexandra, the Empress</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسة ألكسندرة الملكة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the martyrdom of St. Alexandra, the Empress and the wife of Emperor Dadianus.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 20 للشهداء (304م)، استشهدت القديسة ألكسندرة الملكة زوجة الإمبراطور دقلديانوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               While this tyrant emperor was tormenting the great martyr St. George of Cappadocia, the Empress saw these tortures and the endurance of the saint and his steadfastness in the faith. Her heart moved and asked the saint about the secret of the power of his endurance. The Saint explained to her the Divinity of the Lord Christ and interpreted to her parts of the Holy Scriptures. His words touched her heart and she believed in the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وذلك انه بينما كان هذا الملك القاسي يعذٌب الشهيد مارجرجس الروماني شاهدت الملكة هذه العذابات وأحتمال القديس لها وثباته علي الإيمان. ?تحرك قلبها وأست?سرت من القديس عن سر هذه القوة ?حدثها عن الوهية السيد المسيح و?سر لها جزءً من الكتاب المقدس ?دخل كلامه إلي قلبها وآمنت بالسيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When St. George stood before the idols, he prayed to the Lord Christ, and the idols were destroyed. The Emperor and those with him were humiliated and enraged. When the Emperor returned sorrowful to the palace, told the Empress what had happened. She had already heard about the miracle which deepened her fait; she told him: "Did I not tell you not to oppose the Christians, for their God is powerful?" Diocletian became extremely raged and knew that she believed in the Lord Christ. He tortured her severely, and then threw her in prison where she departed in peace and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث لما وق? الشهيد مارجرجس أمام الأصنام صلي للسيد المسيح ?تحطمت ?غضب الملك جداً وعلم أنها آمنت بالسيد المسيح، ?عذبها كثيراً ثم القاها ?ي السجن حيث تنيٌحت بسلام ونالت إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessings of her prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتها ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Mark VI, 101st Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا مرقس السادس البطريرك الأول بعد المائة من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1372 of the martyrs (1656 A.D) Pope Mark (Marcus) VI, 101st Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. This Holy Father was born to pious parents in the city of Bahgorah . When he was a young man, became a monk in the monastery of St. Antonios. He lived an ascetic life persevering in reading the church books until he learned much of the religious subjects.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 1372 للشهداء (1656م)، تنيٌح القديس البابا مرقس السادس البطريرك الأول بعد المائة من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. و?لد هذا القديس من أبوين تقيين ?ي بلدة بهجورة. ولما أصبح شاباً ترهب بدير الأنبا أنطونيوس وعاش ?ي الدير عابداً وناسكاً مداوماً علي الإطلاع ?ي الكتب والمخطوطات حتي أستوعب الكثير من العلوم الدينية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Pope Matthew III (Mettaos) departed, the bishops, priests and the Archons unanimously agreed to consecrate the monk Marcus el-Antony, patriarch. The consecration took place on the 15th day of Parmoute, year 1362 of the martyrs (1646 A.D.) by the name of Pope Mark VI.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تنيٌح البابا متاؤس الثالث ات?ق رأي الأساق?ة والكهنة والأراخنة علي رسامة الراهب مرقس الأنطوني بطريركا وتم ذلك ?ي يوم 15 برمودة  سنة 1362 للشهداء (1646م) بإسم البابا مرقس السادس و?ور جلوسه علي السدة المرقسية أمر بعودة الرهبان إلي أديرتهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Right after his enthronement he ordered the fathers the monks to return to their monasteries preventing them from living in the world. One of the monks was unhappy so he accused him before the ruler who levied a large fine on the Pope and the Coptic people. He ordered also the monks to wear blue apparels. The Pope suffered many tribulations which he endured patiently.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?غضب أحد الرهبان ووشي به عند الوالي الذي ?رض غرامة كبيرة علي البابا والأقباط وأمر أن يلبس الرهبان ملابس زرقاء. وقد قاسي البابا بعض الإضطهادات التي أحتملها بصبر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He departed in peace after he sat on the apostolic throne for ten years. He was entombed in the church of the martyr Mercurius Abu Safain in Old Cairo.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وتنيٌح بسلام بعد أن جلس علي الكرسي المرقسي عشر سنوات ود?ن ?ي كنيسة الشهيد مرقوريوس أبي سي?ين بمصر القديمة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessings of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.16">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Sixteenth day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the sixteenth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Antipas, Bishop of Pergamos</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس أنتيباس أسق? برغامس تلميذ القديس يوحنا الرسول</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the later part of the first Christian century St. Antipas, bishop of Pergamos , was martyred. He was a disciple of St. John the evangelist who mentioned him in his Revelation (Rev. 2:12-16).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من أواخر القرن الأول المسيحي استشهد القديس أنتيباس أسق? برغامس وتلميذ القديس يوحنا الرسول. وقد ذكره ?ي رؤياه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This saint was during the reign of Emperor Domitian who severely persecuted the Christians and viciously slew many of them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان هذا القديس ?ي أيام الملك دومتيانوس قيصر الذي أضطهد المسيحيين كثيراً وقتل بعضهم بوحشية شديدة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Satan saw the growth of the Christian religion at the hands of St. Antipas, he spoke to the heathens from inside the idol saying; “I can’t stay in the city as long as Antipas is present in it.? The pagan people rose up, seized St. Antipas and brought him to the ruler of the city. He ordered the saint to offer sacrifices to the idols, but he refused. Instead he started to explain to him the principles of the Christian faith however the ruler tormented him with severe tortures then imprisoned him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما رأي الشيطان نمو الديانة المسيحية  علي يد القديس أنتيباس خاطب الوثنيين من داخل الوثن قائلاً أنه لا يستطيع الإقامة ?ي المدينة طالما يوجد ?يها أنتيباس.  ?قبضوا علي القديس أنتيباس وأتوا به إلي الوالي الذي أمر أن يقدم القرابين للأوثان ?ر?ض. وبدأ يكلمه عن حقائق الإيمان المسيحي ?عذبه عذابات شديدة ثم وضعه ?ي السجن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his imprisonment, St. John the evangelist sent him a message to comfort and strengthen him. In his message, he called him the faithful priest and the good shepherd.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?أرسل له القديس يوحنا الأنجيلي رسالة مملوءة تعزية دعاه ?يها الكاهن الأمين والراعي الصالح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Finally, when the ruler failed to persuade him, he placed him inside a statue of a bull made of brass and lighted fire under him. While he was inside the bull he praised God thanking Him for making him worthy to be martyred for His names’ sake. He delivered up his soul in peace and received the crown of martyrdom. The heathens took his body out of the statue and threw it away. The believers took his pure body and placed it with great veneration inside the church.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما لم يقدر الوالي عليه وضعه ?ي تمثال مصنوع من النحاس وأمر أن يوقدوا تحته وهو بداخله يسبح الرب ويشكره الذي أهله أن يستشهد من أجل إسمه ثم تنيٌح بسلام ونال إكليل الشهادة. ولما رمي الوثنيون جسده الطاهر أخذه المؤمنون بإكرام جزيل ووضعوه ?ي الكنيسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">the Commemoration of Enoch the Just, being taken alive to Heaven</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار إصعاد أخنوخ البار حياً إلي السماء</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also the church commemorate Enoch the Just, being taken alive to Heaven. He was the son of Jared and our teacher St. Jude the apostle called him ; “Enoch the seventh from Adam.? His son was Methuselah the longest living man for he lived 969 years.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  تحت?ل الكنيسة بتذكار إصعاد البار أخنوخ السابع من آدم (3) وهو ابن متوشالح الذي عمٌر علي الأرض أكثر من أي إنسان آخر إذ عاش 969 سنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Holy Bible testified about Enoch the just that he walked with God meaning that he pleased God with his good conduct, living in His obedience among a wicked generation full of corruption and profanity; “And Enoch walked with God and he was not, for God took him .? And took him meant God ascended him to heaven alive with his body (mortal flesh) and did not taste death. Exactly as what happened later on with Elijah the prophet.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ويشهد الكتاب المقدس عن أخنوخ البار أنه سار مع الله أي أرضي الله بسيرته الحسنة وعاش ?ي طاعته ?ي وسط جيل أستشري ?يه ال?ساد وت?اقمت ?يه الرزيلة "وسار أخنوخ مع الله ولم يوجد لأن الله أخذه"، ومعني أخذه أي أصعده إلي السماء حياً بجسده ولم يذق الموت تماماً كما حدث بعد ذلك مع إيليا النبي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               These two saints will remain with their bodies in heaven until they come and the beast will make war against them and kill them so they will taste death as all humans.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وسيظل هذان القديسان إلي أن يأتيا ويحاربا الوحش ?يقتلهما ويذوقان الموت كباقي الناس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Enoch lived 365 years before he was taken alive to heaven.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               عاش إخنوخ 365 سنة قبل إص?عاده حياً إلي السماء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.17">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Seventeenth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the seventeenth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. James One of the Twelve Apostles and the Brother of St. John the Beloved</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس يعقوب الكبير أحد الإثني عشر رسولاً وشقيق القديس يوحنا الحبيب</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 44 A.D. St. James the Apostle, the son of Zebedee, and the brother of St. John, the beloved, was martyred. He was called James the Elder to identify him from St. James the Less, the son of Alphaeus. He was born and raised in Bethsaida, the city of Andrew and Peter, a city of Galilee. He was celibate as his brother John.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم سنة 44م أستشهد القديس يعقوب الرسول بن زبدي ويدعي يعقوب الكبير تم?ييزاً له عن يعقوب الصغير بن حل?ي . و?لد وتربي ?ي بيت صيدا إحدي بلاد الجليل ومدينة القديسين بطرس وأندراوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Lord Christ called him for the ministry along with his brother John in the same day that He called Peter and Andrew. And immediately they left the boat and their father and followed the Lord . The Lord Christ chose him to be a witness along with peter and John to some important events as the raising of Jairus’ daughter, the transfiguration and in the garden of Gethsemane the night of His passion.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               دعاه السيد المسيح للخدمة مع أخيه يوحنا ?ي ن?س المرة التي دعا ?يها بطرس وأندراوس، ?تركا الس?ينة وأباهما زبدي وتبعا السيد المسيح. اختاره الرب يسوع ليكون شاهداً مع بطرس ويوحنا لبعض الأحداث الهامة مثل إقامة ابنة يايرس والتجلي على جبل تابور وأيضاً ?ي بستان جثسيماني ليلة آلامه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the coming down of the Holy Spirit upon the disciples, this saint preached the Gospel in Judea and Samaria. He always advised his flock to give alms to the poor, the needy, and the weak. That provoked the hostility of the Jews so they accused him before King Herod Agrippa that he was instigating the people not to give the taxes to Caesar but to give it to the poor and the churches. Herod arrested him and as he wanted to please the Jews he ordered to behead him with the sword thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد حلول الروح القدس علي التلاميذ بشٌر هذا القديس ?ي اليهودية والسامرة مما أثار عداوة اليهود ، ?ثاروا ضده ووشوا به لدي الملك هيرودس أغريباس بأنه يدعو الناس ألا يعطوا الجزية لقيصر بل يصر?وها علي ال?قراء والمساكين. ?قبض عليه هيرودس وأراد أن يكسب رضي اليهود ?أمر بقطع رأس القديس بحد السي? ?نال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. James is the first to be martyred from the fathers the apostles and he is the only one among the apostles that the Holy Bible recorded the account of his martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وي?عتبر هذا القديس أول من استشهد من الآباء الرسل وهو الوحيد بين الرسل الذي سجل لنا الكتاب المقدس خبر أستشهاده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               His body is currently located in the city of Compostela in Spain in a splendid cathedral after his name.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Nicodemus</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس نيقوديموس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also St. Nicodemus, who anointed the body of the Savior, departed. He was a Pharisee and a member of the Sanhedrim. He came to the Lord Christ at night and the Lord explained to him the issue of the second birth and convinced him. He defended the Lord Christ before his fellow members of the Sanhedrim.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  تنيٌح القديس نيقوديموس الذي وضع الأطياب علي جسد المخلص عند تك?ينه. كان ?ريسياً وعضواً ?ي مجمع السنهدريم، وقد جاء إلي السيد المسيح لكي يباحثه ?ي موضوع الميلاد الثاني واقتنع بكلامه. وقد دا?ع عن السيد المسيح أمام زملائه أعضاء مجمع السنهدريم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               His love for the Lord Christ was clearly evident at the time of His crucifixion. “He came bringing a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about a hundred pounds. Joseph of Arimathea and Nicodemus took the body of Jesus and bound it in strips of linen with the spices as the custom of the Jews is to bury. ? That indicated his wealth, generosity and profound love for the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد تجلت محبته للسيد المسيح عند صلبه ?قد أشترك مع يوس? الرامي ?ي تك?ين جسده الطاهر ، "وأحضر مزيج مر وعود نحو مائة منا" [أي ما يعادل قنطاراً مصرياً من الأطياب]، مما يدل علي غناه وسخائه ومحبته ال?ياضة للسيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He believed in the Lord Christ and lived a distinguished Christian life then departed in peace            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               آمن بالسيد المسيح وسار سيرة مسيحية ?اضلة ثم تنيٌح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.18">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Eighteenth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the eighteenth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Arsenius, the Disciple of St. Sousnyous</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس أرسانيوس تلميذ القديس سوسنيوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 21 of the martyrs (305 A.D.) St. Arsenius, the disciple of St. Sousnyous, was martyred. When Emperor Diocletian was torturing St. Sousnyous, they informed him that Arsenius was of the same faith as his teacher.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 21 للشهداء (305م) أستشهد القديس أرسانيوس تلميذ القديس سوسنيوس ، وذلك انه لما كان الإمبراطور ديقلديانوس يعذٌب القديس سوسنيوس. أعلموه عن أرسانيوس أنه علي رأي سيده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Emperor brought Arsenius and asked him about his belief. He confessed his faith in the Lord Christ. The Emperor tried to befriend him and persuade him to change his conviction. He refused and also admonished the Emperor for deserting the worship of the true God and worshiping the idols. The Emperor became furious and ordered to torment him with different kinds of tortures and finally ordered to behead him before his teacher, and thus he received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?استحضره واستعلٌم منه عن معتقده. ?أقر واعتر? بالسيد المسيح ?لاط?ه الملك كثيراً ليثنيه عن رأيه. ?لم يقبل بل وبخ الملك علي كونه يعبد الأوثان وتركه عبادة الإله الحقيقي. ?حنق عليه الإمبراطور وأمر بتعذيبه بكل أنواع العذاب، وأخيراً أمر بقطع رأسه أمام معلمه، ?نال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Apollo, the disciple of St. Samuel the Confessor</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس أبوللو تلميذ القديس الأنبا صموئيل المعتر?</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also St. Apollo the disciple of St. Samuel the confessor, departed. This father became a disciple of St. Samuel on the Qalamun mount and he was one of his distinguished disciples. He was energetic and obedient to his spiritual father. He assisted his teacher in managing the affairs of the monastery and its restoration.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً تنيٌح القديس أبوللو تلميذ الأنبا صموئيل المعتر?. تتلمذ هذا الأب علي القديس الأنبا صموئيل ?ي جبل القلمون ، وكان أحد تلاميذه المتقدمين. كما كان نشيطاً ومطيعاً لأبيه. ساعد أباه ?ي إدارة شئون الدير وتعميره.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Anba Samuel started in building the church of the Virgin St. Mary, Apollo brought the building material needed from the surrounding villages to the monastery on camels. He also helped him in solving the difficult problems for his wisdom, knowledge and discernment. Once three monks desired to leave the monastery, he exhorted them from the holy Bible and from the biographies of the fathers until they changed their view and remained in the monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?عندما شرع الأنبا صموئيل ?ي بناء كنيسة القديسة العذراء مريم كان أبوللو يحمٌل مايلزم علي الجمال من الري? إلي الدير. وساعده أيضاً  ?ي حل المشاكل الصعبة لحكمته وعلٌمه وإ?رازه. منها أن ثلاثة من الرهبان أرادوا ترك الدير ?وعظهم من الكتب المقدسة ومن سير الرهبان ?رجعوا عن رأيهم وبقوا بالدير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Anba Samuel desired the life of quietness and seclusion, he appointed Apollo to oversee the affairs of the brethren which he did well. He sought God’s help whenever he faced any difficulty. Once the monastery ran out of bread, he prayed saying; “O God of the Holy Father Anba Samuel the confessor answer my prayer and send unto us today your blessings for my soul has disturbed me much for the sake of the multitudes that gathered in the monastery. And as You have not forsaken our father Anba Samuel so also please don’t forsake me for it is written; “The blessing of the Lord makes one rich, and He adds no sorrow with it .? The Lord answered his prayers and he found the bread storage room full, so he took from the blessings of the Lord and offered it to his guests.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أراد الأنبا صموئيل أن يحيا ?ي الوحدة والسكون، أقام أبوللو مدبراً علي الإخوة ?قام بهذا العمل خير قيام ، وكان يلجأ إلي الله ?يما يصعب عليه. منها أنه ?ي إحدي المرات ن?ذ الخبز من الدير ?صلي وقال "يا إله القديس الأنبا صموئيل المعتر?  استجب لي وإرسل إلينا اليوم بركتك ?إن ن?سي قلقت جداً من أجل الجموع التي اجتمعت بالدير ، وكما أنك لم تتخل عن أبينا الأنبا صموئيل ?لا تتركني أنا أيضاً لأنه مكتوب أن بركة الرب ت?غني ولا يزيد معها أي تعب". ولما دخل الخازن إلي المخزن وجد خبزاً وقدمه للضيو?.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the saint Anba Samuel departed, he remained the overseer of the monks until he departed in peace and left many spiritual sons.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تنيٌح القديس  الأنبا صموئيل بقي الأنبا أبوللو مدبراً للرهبان، حتي تنيٌح بسلام، وقد صار له أولاد كثيرين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.19">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Nineteenth Day of the Blessed Mouth of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the nineteenth day of the blessed mouth of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع عشر من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Simeon the Armenian, Bishop of the country of Persia</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس سمعان الأرمني اسق? بلاد ?ارس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Simeon the Armenian, Bishop of the country of Persia, was martyred. That was during the reign of Sapor (Shapur), the son of Hormiz, king of Persia, who persecuted the Christians and treated            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم إستشهد القديس سمعان الأرمني أسق? بلاد ?ارس ?ي زمان الملك سابور بن هرمز ملك ال?رس الذي كان يضطهد المسيحيين ويعاملهم بكل قساوة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The divine providence chose him to be bishop for the Persian country. He paid a great deal of attention shepherding his people, visiting them, teaching and exhorting them. He led them in the path of holiness as he confirmed them in the true faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أختارت العناية الإلهية هذا القديس ليكون أسق?ـا علي بلاد ?ارس ?أهتم برعاية شعبه وإ?تقادهم وتعليمهم ووعظهم وقيادتهم ?ي طريق القداسة ، كما ثبتهم علي الإيمان الأرثوذكسي الصحيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When King Sapor heard of him, he sent him a message asking him to forsake his faith and worship idols made by hands. The Saint replied by a letter said in it: "Those whom the Lord Christ has bought with His honorable Blood had rid themselves from the servitude of evil, and it is not conceivable for them to worship what was made by hands." When the king read the letter, he became exceedingly angry. He brought the saint, bound him with iron fetters, and cast him in prison. He found in jail some prisoners who worshipped the sun, the Saint preached and taught them, and they believed in the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما سمع به سابور ملك ال?رس ، بعث له رسالة يدعوه ?يها أن يترك إيمانه ويعبد الأوثان المصنوعة بالأيدي. ?رد عليه القديس برسالة يقول ?يها "إن الذين أشتراهم السيد المسيح بدمه الطاهر قد تخلصوا من عبودية الشر ، ولا يجوز لهم أن يتعبدوا لمصنوعات الأيدي". ?لما قرأ الملك الرسالة غضب جداً وأستحضر القديس وربطه بالحديد وألقاه ?ي السجن، ?وجد بعض المحبوسين يعبدون الشمس ?علٌمهم ووعظهم حتي آمنوا علي يديه ?ي الحبس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They confessed their faith before the king, who ordered to behead them. He brought the Saint from prison along with 150 persons had believed at his hands in prison. One of them weakened and wanted to deny his faith however the saint preached and encouraged him to endure saying; “the strike of the sword is nothing if your eyes were closed.? They tortured then beheaded him thus he received the crown of life. The king ordered to behead also the other one hundred and forty nine so they received the crowns of martyrdom .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ضع? أحدهم أمام العذابات وأراد أن ينكر إيمانه ?وعظه القديس وشجعه علي الإحتمال قائلاً له: "ليست الضربة شيئاً إذا أغمضت عينيك"، ?عذٌبوه وقطعوا رأسه ?نال إكليل الحياة ثم أمر الملك بقطع رؤوس المائة والتسعة والاربعين أيضاً. ?نالوا جميعاً اكاليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After all the attempts with St. Simeon had failed he ordered to behead him thus he also received the crown of martyrdom. He was one hundred twenty years old at the time of his martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد أن ?شلت المحاولات مع القديس سمعان أمر بقطع رأسه ?نال هو أيضاً إكليل الشهادة وكان عمره وقتئذ مائة وعشرين سنة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the blessed Youhanna (John) Abu Nagaah El-Kabeer, the Vizier Abu Elaala Fahd ibn Ibrahim and their companions</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد الشهداء يوحنا أبو نجاح الكبير والرئيس أبو العلا ?هد بن إبراهيم وزملائهما</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, of the year 719 of the martyrs (1003 A.D.) the blessed Youhanna (John) Abu Nagaah El-Kabeer, the Vizier Abu Elaala Fahd Ibn Ibrahim and others, were martyred. Youhanna was one of the noble Copts in the tenth century and during the reign of Al-Hakim Be-Amr Ellah the Fatimid Caliph. He was the head scribe in his time, as he was the lay leader and he also was contemporary to Pope Philotheos, 63rd Patriarch.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 719 للشهداء ( 1003 م ) أستشهد القديس يوحنا أبو نجاح والرئيس أبو العلا ?هد بن إبراهيم وآخرون. كان يوحنا أبو نجاح من عظماء الأقباط ?ي القرن العاشر ?ي عهد الحاكم بأمر الله ال?اطمي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Youhanna was a devout Christian, righteous, charitable to the poor, loving to the church and zealous for the Orthodox faith. The Caliph called him, along with nine others, and told him; “I want you to leave your faith and adopt my faith, Islam. I will make you my minister to manage the affairs of my kingdom." Youhanna replied saying: "Give me a chance until tomorrow to deliberate the matter with myself"            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان باراً تقياً غيوراً علي الإيمان الأرثوذكسي ، يحب كنيسته القبطية ويحسن إلي ال?قراء والمساكين. عمل كبيراً للكتاب المباشرين. أرسل إليه الخلي?ة مع تسعة آخرين وقال له " أريد أن تترك دينك وتدخل ?ي ديني ?أجعلك وزيري الخاص وتقوم بتدبير مملكتي".?أجابه يوحنا قائلاً: " أمهلني إلي الغد".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Youhanna called his friends and told them: "I am ready to die in the Name of the Lord Christ, now my brothers, do not seek this vainglory, for you will lose the everlasting eternal glory of the Lord Christ Who satisfied us with the richness of the world, and now with His mercy, He had called us to the Kingdom of Heaven, so strengthen your hearts."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?جمع أصدقاءه وقال لهم "أنا مستعد أن أموت علي أسم السيد المسيح ، ?لا تطلبوا المجد ال?اني ?يضيع عليكم مجد المسيح الباقي".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The next morning, Youhanna went to Al-Hakim Be-Amr Ellah who asked him: "O Nagaah, have you decided?" Youhanna (John) replied saying steadfastly and with courage: "Yes, I will remain in my faith."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي الغد مضي إلي الحاكم الذي سأله قائلاً "هل طابت ن?سك ؟"، ?أجاب يوحنا وقال: "نعم وسأبقي علي ديني".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Governor became furious and ordered him be scourged one thousand lashes. After he was beaten three hundred lashes, he said: "I am thirsty." They informed the Governor who said: "Water him after you tell him forsake your religion." Youhanna replied: "Take the water back to him, for I do not need it, because My Master Jesus Christ had watered me and quenched my thirst." The people who were standing around testified that they saw water dripping from his beard. When he said that, he departed in peace and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?غضب الخلي?ة وأمر أن يجلدوه أل? جلدة ، ?لما أكمل ثلاثمائة قال "أنا عطشان". ?أعلٌموا الحاكم الذي قال "اسقوه بعد أن تقولوا له أن يرجع عن دينه". ?أجاب يوحنا قائلاً: "أعيدوا الماء لأن سيدي يسوع قد سقاني وأط?أ ظمأي"، ثم تنيٌح بسلام ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When they told the tyrant Governor, he ordered them to beat the dead body to complete the one thousand lashes.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?أمر الخلي?ة أن يضربوه وهو جسد ميت إلي تمام أل? جلدة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Caliph later on brought the Vizier Abu Elaala Fahd ibn Ibrahim. He was charitable to the poor, one of the prominent men of the government and was greatly devoted to his church. The Caliph told him: "You know that I have chosen and appointed you ahead of all the men in my government, then listen to me and be with me in my religion, so I will promote you more than what you are in now and be like a brother to me." When he did not answer him, he ordered him beheaded and to burn his body thus he received the crown of martyrdom. The fire went on burning for three days and the body was not harmed, and his right hand that he extended to give alms remained untouched.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بعد ذلك أرسل الخلي?ة واستحضر أبو العلا ?هد بن إبراهيم، الذي كان مخلصاً لكنيسته ومحباً للمساكين وكان من أكابر رجال الدولة. ?قال له الخلي?ة "أنت تعلٌم إني قدمتك علي كل من هو ?ي دولتي، ?أسمع مني وكن معي ?ي ديني ?أر?عك أكثر مما أنت ?يه وتكون لي مثل أخ" ، ?لم يجبه إلي قوله. ?أمر بقطع رأسه وحرق جسده بالنار ، وظلت النار مشتعلة ثلاثة أيام ولم يحترق جسده، وبقيت يده اليمني التي كان يمدها للصدقة سليمة. ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               God took revenge from the wicked people that discredited Abu Elaala Fahd before the Caliph.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد إنتقم الله من الذين سعوا به لدي الخلي?ة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               As of the rest of the ten, the Caliph tortured them, one of them died, four of them weakened but they returned confessing the Lord Chris and received the crowns of martyrdom. The remaining three returned to their Christian faith later on.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أما بقية العشرة ?عذٌبهم الخلي?ة ?مات أحدهم وضع? منهم أربعة ثم عادوا واعتر?وا بالسيد المسيح ونالوا اكاليل الشهادة. وبقي ثلاثة منهم عادوا إلي مسيحيتهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات هؤلاء الشهداء جميعاً ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the Monk Daoud (David) ibn Ghobrial el-Bargy</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد الراهب داود بن غبريال</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 1099 of the martyrs (1383 A.D.), Daoud Ibn Ghobrial El-Bargy, the monk, was martyred. He was from the village of Berkit Karmout. He was tortured severely but did not forsake the faith of the Lord Christ. After they were weary of torturing him he was beheaded with the sword. He received the crown of martyrdom and that was during the days of Pope Matthew I (87).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 1099 للشهداء ( 1383 م ) استشهد الراهب داود بن غبريال البرجي من بركة قرموط. وقد عذٌب هذا القديس كثيراً ولم ينكر الإيمان بالسيد المسيح. وبعد أن تعبوا من تعذيبه قطعوا رأسه بحد السي?. ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.20">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twentieth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم العشرون من شهر برمودة المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twentieth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم العشرون من شهر برمودة المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Babnuda (Paphnute) of Dendereh</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس ببنودة الذي من دندرة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Babnuda (Paphnute), who was from Dandara (Dendereh), was martyred. This Saint was a hermit monk living a solitary life. The angel of the Lord appeared to him and told him; “go appear before Arianus, the governor.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم أستشهد القديس ببنوده من دندره. كان هذا القديس راهباً متوحداً ، ?ظهر له ملاك الرب وقال له "إذهب لمقابلة أريانوس الوالي".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Arianus’ ship embarked by the city of Dandara and he was earnestly looking for that Saint. The Saint came to Arianus and cried out in his face with a loud voice, saying: "I am Christian, and I believe in the Lord Christ." When the Governor knew that he was the anchorite that he was looking for, he seized him, and severely tortured him. Then he chained him with iron fetters and cast him in a dark prison. A heavenly light shone upon him and an angel of the Lord appeared to him, healed his wounds, and comforted him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان هذا الوالي راسياً بس?ينته عند دندرة وكان يبحث باهتمام عن هذا القديس. ?لما جاء إليه القديس اعتر? أمامه قائلاً:  "أنا مسيحي مؤمن بالسيد المسيح". ?لما عر? الوالي أنه ذلك المتوحد الذي يبحث عنه قبض عليه وعذَّبه عذاباً شديداً ثم قيده بالحديد وطرحه ?ي سجن مظلم ?أشرق عليه نور سماوي وظهر له ملاك الرب وش?اه من جراحاته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               There was in the city a man, whose name was Kyrillos, with his wife, his daughter, and twelve other young men, who believed through the teachings of the saint and his preaching. They were all martyred by beheading and they received the crowns of martyrdom. The Governor was enraged of him when he knew that and ordered to hang a rock in his neck and cast him in the Nile, thus St. Babnuda received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان ?ي المدينة رجل أسمه كيرلس وزوجته وإبنته وإثني عشر صبياً آخرون كانوا قد آمنوا بتعاليم القديس ووعظه ?إستشهدوا جميعاً بقطع رؤوسهم. ?نالوا اكاليل الشهادة ولما عر? الوالي ذلك غضب وأمر ?علقوا به حجرا كبيرا وطرحوه ?ي النيل ?نال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.21">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty First Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الحادي والعشرون من شهر برمودة المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty first day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الحادي والعشرون من شهر برمودة المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of the Virgin St. Mary, the Theotokos</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار القديسة العذراء مريم والدة الإله</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of every Coptic month the church celebrates the commemoration of the Virgin St. Mary, the Mother of God.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من كل شهر قبطي ت?عَّيد الكنيسة بتذكار القديسة مريم العذراء والدة الإله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of her holy intercession be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة ش?اعتها المقدسة ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Hierotheos, Bishop of Athens</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس بروثاؤس أسق? أثينا</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, St. Hierotheos (Brutawos) the Areopagite, departed. He was the second bishop for the city of Athens after St. Dionysius the Areopagite. This father was one of the Athenian philosophers and a member of the Areopagus. He met the Apostle St. Paul, and many discussions took place between them which led to his believe in the Lord Christ. He baptized, taught him the Christian commandments and ordained him a priest for the city of Athens. He preached the good news of salvation and brought back many to the knowledge of Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي مثل هذا اليوم أيضاً  تنيح القديس بروثاؤس الأريوباغي. هذا الأب هو ثاني أسق? علي مدينة أثينا بعد القديس ديونيسيوس الأريوباغي. وكان بروثاؤس ضمن ?لاس?ة أثينا وأحد أعضاء الأريوباغوس المنشقة  وقد إهتدي إلي الإيمان المسيحي علي يد القديس بولس الرسول، وجرت بينهما مباحثات أدت إلي أن يؤمن علي يده، ?عمٌّده وعلمه كل ال?رائض المسيحية، ورسمه قساً علي مدينة أثينا. ?كرز ببشري الخلاص ورد كثيرين إلي معر?ة السيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of St. Dionysius the Areopagite, bishop of Athens who was his teacher and guide, the people wanted to ordain him bishop instead of his teacher. He refused saying; “I wish that I can only fulfill my priestly duties.? However he later on accepted and was ordained bishop for Athens.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد نياحة القديس ديونيسيوس الأريوباغي أسق? أثينا الذي كان له استاذاً ومعلماً ، أراد الشعب رسامته أسق?اً بدلاً من معلمه ?لم يقبل. وقال "ليتني أقدر علي  القيام بواجبات القسيسية". وبعد ذلك رسموه أسق?اً علي أثينا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This bishop was contemporary to our fathers the apostles and the disciples and met many of them. He learned from them many of the teachings of the Lord.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد عاصر هذا الأسق? الآباء الرسل والتلاميذ، واجتمع بكثير منهم وأخذ منهم الكثير من تعاليم الرب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This Saint was present at the time of the departure of the Lady Virgin St. Mary. He composed many melodies for St. Mary after her departure which he sang accompanied by musical instruments.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد حضر هذا القديس يوم نياحة القديسة العذراء مريم والدة الإله. هذا وقد نظم مدائح للقديسة مريم بعد نياحتها ولحنها بالموسيقي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He also wrote some books and spiritual hymns. This saint brought back a great multitude of the Jews and the Gentiles to the knowledge of the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كما كتب بعض الكتابات والتراتيل الحسنة. وقد ردّ هذا القديس جماعة كبيرة من اليهود والأمم إلي معر?ة السيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Having finished his good endeavor, he rested in the Lord at the beginning of the second century.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح رقد ?ي الرب ?ي أوائل القرن الثاني الميلادي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.22">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Second Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثاني والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty second day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثاني والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Alexander I, 19th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا الكسندروس الأول البطريرك التاسع عشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 44 of the martyrs (328 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Alexander (Alexandros), 19th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. He was born in the city of Alexandria to Christian parents. Pope Maximus ordained him a reader, Pope Theonas promoted him to the rank of deacon and then Pope Peter (Petros the Seal of the Martyrs) ordained him a priest.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 44 للشهداء ( 328م ) تنيَّح القديس الكسندروس البطريرك التاسع عشر من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا القديس بالإسكندرية من أبوين مسيحين. رسمه البابا مكسيموس أغنسطسا ورقاه البابا ثاؤنا الي رتبة الشماسية الكاملة ثم رسمه البابا بطرس قساً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the departure of Pope Archillas (Archilaous) they unanimously chose him Patriarch. He was consecrated on the 3rd day of Epep, year 28 of the martyrs (312 A.D.) Arius became exasperated for he desired this honor and when he tried to receive Pope Alexander’s absolution, the Pope told his delegates; “My Holy Father Pope Petros commanded me not to accept him. So let him repents from what sin he had committed and when the Savior accepts his repentance, He will give me a sign to absolve him.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد نياحة البابا أرشلاوس كان قد تقدم ?ي الأيام ?أنتخبوه بطريركياً ورسموه يوم 3 أبيب سنة 28 للشهداء (312م). عند ذلك اغتاظ أريوس لأنه كان يطمع ?ي هذه الكرامة. وعندما حاول أن ينال منه الحل ، قال البابا لمندوبي أريوس "لقد أوصاني أبي القديس البابا بطرس أن لا أقبله، ?ليتب عما إرتكبه من خطية. ومتي قبل ال?ادي توبته ?ليعطيني علامة لكي أحله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Arius expanded and insisted on his error, Pope Alexander convened for him a council to hear his statement of faith, the council judged to admonish and rebuke him for his heresy however he did not hearken to them. Shortly after he convened another council of 100 bishops and they all excommunicated him except for two Libyan bishops. The contentions between Pope Alexander and Arius continued for the later denied the Divinity of Christ. Arius spread his heresy through hymns and songs. He persuaded Eusebius bishop of Nicomedia who was devious and eloquent.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما تمادي أريوس، عقد له البابا مجمعاً مؤل?اً من مائة أسق? لسماع أقواله. ?حكم المجمع بتوبيخه وتعني?ه علي هرطقته ?لم يست?د. بعدها عقد مجمعا آخرا مؤل?ا من مائة أسق?. ?حرمه الجميع ما عدا أسق?ين ليبين واستمر الصراع بين البابا الكسندروس وأريوس حيث أنكر الأخير لاهوت المسيح ، ونشر بدعته من خلال التراتيل و الألحان. وقد استمال إليه أوسابيوس أسق? نيقوميديا وكان ماكراً و?صيحاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Alexandros convened many councils in different parts of Egypt. He wrote many epistles in conjunction with a treatise that included a complete review of the Orthodox faith with a summary of the Arian heresy. Some of the bishops were influenced by Arius power of persuasion. They wrote to the Pope asking him to pardon Arius. The Pope wrote them a message based on the saying of St. John the Evangelist; “In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God .? He urged them to confirm and ratify what he wrote with their signatures as their brothers the bishops of Asia, Syria and Libya. Many of them agreed with him what made Eusebius convince Emperor Constantine to send a letter to Pope Alexander asking him to absolve Arius however Pope Alexander refused.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أما البابا الكسندروس ?عقد عدة مجامع ?ي مختل? البلاد المصرية، وكتب كثيراً من الرسائل ، ش?عها برسالة دورية ?يها عرض كامل للإيمان الأرثوذكسي وتلخيص لبدعة أريوس ، وحدث أن تأثر بعض الأساق?ة من بدعة أريوس ?كتبوا للبابا يرجون الع?و عنه. ?رد البابا برسالة بناها علي قول القديس يوحنا الإنجيلي "?ي البدء كان الكلمة. والكلمة كان عند الله. وكان الكلمة الله."( يوحنا 1 : 1). ورجا من إخوته الأساق?ة أن يصادقوا بتوقيعاتهم علي ما كتب أسوة بإخوتهم أساق?ة آسيا وسوريا وليبيا. وقد أستجاب العديد منهم ، مما جعل أوسابيوس يقنع الإمبراطور قسطنطين بأن يرسل خطاباً للبابا السكندري يطلب حل أريوس ?لم يقبل البابا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Alexandrian Pope sent an epistle to Alexandros bishop of Constantinople explaining in it the sound faith which known historically as the Tome of Alexandros. He also sent it to the bishops of the universal church, the bishops of Egypt, Cappadocia, Pamphylia and Asia signed it and they were 250 bishops.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم بعث البابا الإسكندري برسالة إلي الكسندروس أسق? بيزنطة يشرح ?يها الإيمان القويم، ت?عرّ? هذه الرسالة تاريخياً باسم بطومس الكسندروس. وقد بعث بهذا الطومس إلي أساق?ة المسكونة، ?وقع عليه أساق?ة مصر وكبادوكيا وبم?يليا وآسيا وكان عددهم مائتين وخمسين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the dispute intensified, the Emperor entrusted bishop Hosius, bishop of Cordova in Spain to mediate between Pope Alexander and Arius but he could not for he was convinced with the words of Pope Alexander. He agreed with the Pope to convene a universal council which was held at Nicaea in the year 325 A.D. and was attended by 318 bishops. They excommunicated Arius and deposed him from his clerical rank. The council formulated the first part of the Creed of faith, drew up the canons, put down the regulations for Lent and the feast of Resurrection as they ruled in many other issues. They also put down other canons to regulate the pastoral care.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما اشتد الخلا? كل? الإمبراطور الأسق? أوسيوس أسق? قرطبة بأسبانيا لإنهاء الخلا? بين البابا الكسندروس وأريوس ، ?لم يستطع لأنه اقتنع بكلام البابا ألكسندروس. عندئذ ات?ق مع البابا الكسندروس علي عقد مجمع مسكوني وهو المجمع الذي انعقد ?ي نيقية سنة ٣٢٥م وحضره ثلاثمائة وثمانية عشرأسق?اً، وحكموا بقطع أريوس من الكهنوت ، كما وضع المجمع الجزء الأول من قانون الإيمان وقوانين أخري ، ثم رتب صوم الأربعين وعيد القيامة وحكم ?ي قضايا أخري ووضع قوانين أخرى لتنظيم العمل الرعوي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the conclusion of the council Pope Alexander returned to his See with the grace of God victoriously. He shepherded his flock with the best of care. He sat on the apostolic throne for 15 years, 9 months and 20 days, and then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد إنتهاء المجمع عاد البابا الكسندروس إلي مقر كرسيه غالباً ?ائزاً بنعمة الله. ورعي رعيته أحسن رعاية ثم تنيّح بسلام. وكانت مدة جلوسه علي الكرسي خمسة عشر سنة وتسعة أشهر وعشرين يوماً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Mark II, 49th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا مرقس الثاني البطريرك التاسع والأربعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, of the year 535 of the martyrs (819 A.D.) the blessed father Pope Mark II (Marcus), 49th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 535 للشهداء ( 819م ) تنّيح البابا مرقس الثاني البطريرك التاسع والأربعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was born in Alexandria, and desired the virtuous life since his young age. Pope John (Yoannis) ordained him a deacon then a priest. The Pope entrusted him with the administration of the patriarchate. He continued to oversee this responsibility until the departure of Pope Yoannis.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?لد بالإسكندرية وأحب ال?ضيلة. ?رسمه البابا يوأنس شماساً ثم قساً وسلم له تدبير البطريركية حتي تنّيح البابا يوأنس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They deliberated to consecrate him patriarch however he fled to the desert. When they caught up with him, bound him and brought him back. He was enthroned in Alexandria in the 2nd day of Meshir, year 515 of the martyrs (799 A.D.). On the day of his consecration he explained to the people the reasons for refusing the decisions of the council of Chalcedon.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?تشاوروا ليرسموه بطريركياً ?هرب، وعندما وجدوه قيدوه ورسموه ?ي الأسكندرية بطريركياً ?ي الثاني من أمشير 515 للشهداء (799م). و?ي يوم رسامته شرح للشعب أسباب ر?ض قرارات مجمع خلقيدونية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After his enthronement he went to el-Zugag monastery for seclusion. After his return he met the ruler in el-Fostat who honored him and answered his request of building the churches and restoring the ruined ones. Pope Mark rebuilt the church of Ep-Soteer (The Savior) and consecrated it in Alexandria.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد انتهاء الرسامة سا?ر إلي دير الزجاج ليعتك?. وبعد عودته قابل الوالي بال?سطاط الذي أكرمه وأجابه إلي طلبه ببناء الكنائس وترميم المتهدم منها. وقد أعاد البابا مرقس بناء كنيسة أبسوتير (المخلص) وكرسها بمدينة الإسكندرية والبحيرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his papacy swarms of locusts covered Alexandria and el-Beheira which destroyed every plant of the land and all the fruits of the trees. The Pope asked the clergy and the people to go out with the censers, crosses and the bibles and entreat God to left up his wrath. He went out with them to where the locusts were and they all prayed until the locusts fled away, drowned and died in the sea.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي أيامه ظهر جراد ?ي الإسكندرية والبحيرة مما أتل? ثمار الأرض والكروم. ?أمر الشعب أن يخرجوا بالبخور والصلبان والأناجيل ويسألوا الله أن ير?ع غضبه ، وخرج معهم إلي موضع الجراد وصلوا جميعاً حتي هرب الجراد ونزل ?ي البحر ومات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In his days, the Muslims of Spain, the Andalusians, conquered some of the Greek Isles, captured many of their men, women and children, brought them to Alexandria, and sold them. The Pope was able to buy six thousands of them and gave them the choice either to return to their country on his own expense or remain in Egypt. Those decided to stay in Egypt, he handed them to trusted teachers to teach them the sound doctrines. The Pope comforted his people during all these difficulties. When the Andalusians continued to trouble and oppress the Pope, he left Alexandria and moved from town to town for five years. The Archon Makary El-Amir sent a letter to Abd el-Aziz the ruler of the East who granted him a permission to host the Pope in his house in the city of Nabarouh until peace and security be established in the country.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد و?اة هارون الرشيد اختصم أبناه علي الخلا?ة. كان المأمون هو الأكبر لكن أمه كانت جارية، بينما الأمين ابن الحرة وهو الأصغر. وتحول الخصام إلي حرب طاحنة. كل من الأخوين عين واليـا ليحكم مصر بإسمه. ?أنتصر أنصار والي الأمين وقتلوا والي المأمون.  وأثناء التطاحن رأي الإمبراطور بالقسطنطينية أن ال?رصة مواتية ?ي إسترجاع حكمه علي مصر ?أرسل أسطوله ليغزوا دمياط. و?ي ن?س الوقت أنتهز أحد الخوارج ال?رصة وأعلن ن?سه واليـا علي مصر. بعد هذا جاء خمسة عشر ال? من الأندلسيين إلي مصر بعد أن ?شلت ثورتهم ضد الخلي?ة الأموي الذي أمر بن?يهم. وبرغم إنهم أوجدوا الإستقرار ?ي مصر ، لكنهم أ?سدوها باضرام النار ?ي بيوت العبادة ، وتحرشوا بالمصريين ، وانقضوا علي جزائر اليونانيين يسلبون وينهبون ويخط?ون الرجال والنساء والأط?ال ثم يبعونهم ?ي الإسكندرية. وقد إشتري البابا منهم ستة آلا? وكان يخيرهم بين العودة إلي بلادهم بعد أخذ الاجرة للس?ر ، أو البقاء ?ي مصر حيث سلمهم إلي معلّمين موثوق بهم ?ي العقيدة. وكان البابا يعزي شعبه ?ي هذه المحن.  وبعد أن ضيق الأندلسيون عليه الخناق، غادر الإسكندرية وظل يتنقل خمس سنوات. ثم أرسل الأرخن "مكاري الأمير" إلي "الوالي عبد العزيز" والي المشرق الذي أعطاه خطابـا باستضا?ة البابا ?ي منزله بنبروه ريثما يتمكن من إحلال الأمن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the last days of this Pope the Berbers raided the monasteries of Wadi el-Natrun, slew the monks and destroyed their cells and churches. The Pope supplicated the Lord with tears to end his life. He became ill with a fever and departed in peace after staying on the apostolic throne for 20 years, 2 months and 21 days.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي آخر أيام هذا البابا أغار البربر علي أديرة وادي النطرون، وقتلوا الرهبان وهدموا الصوامع والكنائس ، ?بكي البابا إلي الله وتضرع أن ي?نهي حياته، ?أخذته حمي وتنيّح بسلام بعد أن أمضي علي الكرسي المرقسي عشرين سنة وشهرين وواحد وعشرين يومـا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Michael II, 53rd Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا خائيل الثاني البطريرك الثالث والخمسين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 567 of the martyrs (851 A.D.) the Holy Father Pope Michael II (Khail), 53rd Patriarch of Alexandria, departed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 567 للشهداء (851 م)، تنيّح البابا خائيل الثاني البطريرك الثالث والخمسون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This father was a righteous monk, and he was ordained presbyter for the monastery of the saint Abba John (Yehness). Because of his good repute, he was chosen Patriarch, and was consecrated in the 24th day of Hathor, year 566 of the martyrs (849 A.D.) during the reign of al-Mutawakkil the son of al-Mo’atasim.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان راهبآ قديساً ?ر?سم قساً علي دير القديس الأنبا يحنس. وكان ذا سيرة صالحة ?اختاروه بطريركياً ?ي الرابع والعشرين من هاتور سنة 566 للشهداء ( 849م )، ?ي عهد خلا?ة المتوكل بن المعتصم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After his enthronement the unjust rulers opposed him. They asked the Pope either to pay a large sum of money as a bribe or prevent his enthronement on the apostolic throne and he was forced to sell some of the possessions of the church.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وعقب جلوسه تعرض له الولاة الظالمون طالبين منه إما أن يعطيهم مبالغ طائلة من المال علي سبيل الرشوة أو يمنعونه من الجلوس علي الكرسي المرقسي ?اضطر أن يبيع ممتلكات الكنيسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the Holy Fast of the year 567 of the martyrs, he went to the wilderness to keep the fast and celebrate the feast of Resurrection. He remembered his earlier life in the wilderness, so he asked God with tears and supplication saying: "O God, you know how much I love solitary life and I have no aptitude for this position." The Lord accepted his petition and he departed in peace after the feast of Resurrection. He stayed on the apostolic throne for one year, four months and twenty-eight days. He was the first Patriarch to be entombed in the monastery of St. Macarius and they placed his body in the church of St. Macarius.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما كان الصوم الكبير سنة 567 للشهداء توجه إلي البرية ليصلي عيد القيامة،  ?تذكر حياته الأولي ?ي البرية ?سأل ببكاء وتضرع قائلاً:  "أنت تعلّم يارب أني لا أزال أهوي الوحدة، وليس لي طاقة علي هذا المركز". ?قبل الله صلاته وتنيّح بسلام بعد أن قضي علي الكرسي سنة واحدة وأربعة أشهر وثمانية وعشرين يوماً. وكان أول من د??ن من البطاركة بدير القديس مكاريوس وجعلوا جسده ?ي بيعة القديس مكاريوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Isaac (Ishaq), of Hourin</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس إسحق الهوريني</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Also on this day the Holy Father Anba Isaac (Is-haq) departed. He was born in the city of Hourin , district of Shabas, to unblemished parents. His mother departed when he was a child, and his father, shortly after, married another woman. A great famine took place in those days, and his step-mother hated him. She only gave him a little of bread, which he gave to the shepherds and he fasted until sunset, although he was only five years old. When his father knew that, he wanted to inquire into what his son was doing. Knowing the matter, before his father came to him, he tied up three pieces of mud in his cloak, so that his father might think when he saw them from far that they were bread. When his father came and unrolled the cloak, he found three pieces of bread. The shepherds who were present testified that the boy had given them all what he had of bread, and others saw him tying the pieces of mud in his cloak. His father marveled and glorified God.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  تنيّح الأب القديس الأنبا إسحق. و?لد بمدينة هورين (1) من أعمال شباس من أبوين طاهرين. تو?يت والدته ?تزوج والده بغير أمه. وات?ق أن حدث غلاء عظيم ، وكانت امرأة أبيه تبغضه ولا تعطيه من الخبز إلا القليل، الذي كان يوزعه علي الرعاة ويبقي صائماً إلي الغروب. وشعر والده بالأمر وأراد التحقق منه.?لما علّم الصبي أسحق ربط ثلاث قطع من الطين ?ي طر? عباءته حتي يظنها أبوه من بعيد إنه خبز. ?لما أتي والده وحل العباءة وجد الطين خبزاً. وشهد الحضور أن الصبي وزع مامعه من الخبز ، ورآه البعض وهو يربط الطين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When Isaac grew up, he went and became a monk under the guidance of a Holy Father whose name was Elias, and he lived with him until the time of Anba Elias’ departure. Then Isaac went to mount Barnug and dwelt with an old holy man whose name was Anba Zacharias. His father meanwhile was looking for Isaac and when he found him asked him to return with him to his hometown. His teacher Anba Zacharias advised him to obey his father and return with him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما كبر مضي وترّهب عند قديس اسمه الأنبا إيليا حتي تنيّح ، وبعدها مضي إلي جبل برنوج وأقام عند شيخ قديس اسمه الأنبا زخارياس. وكان أبوه يبحث عنه ?لما وجده طلب منه الرجوع معه ، ?أشار عليه معلٌمه ان يطيع والده، ?رجع معه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He returned and stayed until his father departed. He distributed all what his father had left him then lived in seclusion in a place he built for himself nearby the city. He persevered on his asceticism and worship until he departed in peace. They buried him in his place of worship.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ومكث حتي مات أبوه. ??رق ما تركه له وان?رد ?ي مكان بناه لن?سه بالقرب من المدينة. وداوم علي الن?سك والعبادة إلي أن تنيّح بسلام ?د?نوه ?ي محل عبادته.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After many years, God willed to reveal his body; a great light appeared above his grave, which was seen by reapers for three consecutive days. The believers came, took his body, laid it on a camel, and journeyed with it until they came to a place between Horein and Nashrat where the camel stopped. They knew that this was the Lord's Will and they built a church for him in that place where they placed the body with great honor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد سنوات طويلة أراد الرب إظهار جسده ، ?ظهر نور عظيم علي قبره رآه جماعة من الحصادين ثلاثة أيام متوالية.   ?جاء المؤمنون ور?عوا جسده ووضعوه علي جمل وساروا به حتي وصلوا إلي مكان بين هورين ونشرت ?وق? الجمل الذي كان يحمل الجسد ?علم الجميع أن هذه إرادة الله وبنوا كنيسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.23">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Third Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثالث والعشرين من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty third day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثالث والعشرين من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. George Prince of the Martyrs</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">شهادة القديس جورجيوس العظيم من الشهداء</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the great among the martyrs St. George (Gawargios, Mari Girgis) was martyred. He was born in Cappadocia in Asia Minor (Nowadays Turkey); in the first half of the third century to a wealthy and godly Christian family. His father's name was Anastasius who was the governor of Melitene in Cappadocia. His mother's name was Kira Theognosta (Theopista) the daughter of the governor of Lydda in Palestine. St. George had two sisters named Kasia and Mathrona.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 19 للشهداء ( 303م )  أستشهد القديس جورجيوس أمير الشهداء، و?لد هذا القديس حوالي سنة 280م ?ي إحدي مدن إقليم كبادوكية من أسرة شري?ة مسيحية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Their father died while they were still young and their godly mother took charge of raising them up on Christian piety. His mother took them back to the city of Lydda in Palestine, her homeland.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مات أبوه وهو ?ي الرابعة عشرة من عمره. ?رحلت أمه إلي بلدة اللدّ ب?لسطين حيث موطنها الأصلي وممتلكاتها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When George grew to be a courageous and brilliant young man, Justus, the governor of Palestine, took interest and enlisted him in the army. He learnt horsemanship and was promoted in the ranks until he reached the rank of a commander. Meanwhile, Justus the pious governor of Palestine departed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد هذا التحق جورجيوس بخدمة الجيش برتبة قائد مائة ، وسرعان ما ترقي حتي أصبح مشيراً ?ي ديوان الإمبراطور دقلديانوس. تو?يت والدته وهو ?ي سن العشرين ?انطلق إلي مدينة نيقوميديا مركز المملكة الشرقية حيث كان يقيم دقلديانوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Dadianus, a Persian king, was ruling in the city of Tyre in Syria. When George returned from the army and went to Lydda to visit his mother, he found that the king had issued an edict to worship the idols and torture the Christians who do not obey his orders. Accordingly most of the people worshipped the idols and raised incense to them and no one dared to resist or profess Christianity openly.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي الثالث والعشرين من ?براير 303م أصدر دقلديانوس منشوراً بإضطهاد المسيحيين. عندئذ عتق جورجيوس جميع عبيده ووزع أمواله وبدأ يستعد للأستشهاد على أسم السيد المسيح. ثم ذهب ومزق منشور دقلديانوس الذي كان معلقـا علي حوائط قصره ?ي نيقوديمية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               George came before King Dadianus and confessed the Lord Christ. The king marveled at his appearance and courage and was informed that he was the son of an eminent governor. The king befriended him and tried to persuade him with many promises to offer incense to the idols to grant him all his wishes. George refused all the earthly futile promises, and stood firm in his loyalty to his Christ and his faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم دخل جورجيوس علي الملك دقلديانوس وعاتبه علي إضطهاده للمسيحيين وأعلن له مسيحيته. ?أمر الملك بطرده من البلاط الملكي وإيداعه السجن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The king was furious and ordered to torment him with the severest and horrific kinds of tortures.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي السجن وضعوا رجليه ?ي مقطرة  وحجراً ثقيلاً علي صدره            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They placed him in the Hinbazeen which tore his body and his blood flew. Then they cast him in quicklime for three days but the Lord protected him. However, the king attributed that to sorcery. They put on him shoes made of iron with red hot nails beating him with sticks to force him to walk while mocking him. They scourged him with ox tails until his blood flew and in all theses tortures the Lord consoled him and healed his wounds. George kept his serenity and calm face that the king and the provincial governors who were condemning him to all these tortures, marveled.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم وضعوه ?ي الهنبازين حتي تمزق لحمه ، وأثناء ذلك شاهدوا وجـهه يشع نوراً و?ي ثياب بيضاء. بعدها رأوا القديس ?ي معبد أبوللون معا?ي سليماً طليقاً. ثم أمر دقلديانوس بطرحه ?ي الجير الحي لمدة ثلاثة أيام ، ?أقامه الرب أيضاً وهو م?عا?ي. وكان الإمبراطور ينسب كل هذا للسحر. ثم البسوه حذاء من حديد و?يه مسامير محماه بالنار، وكانوا يضربونه بالعصي ليمشي وهم يهزأون به. و?ي اليوم التالي أحضروه أمام دقلديانوس سليماً ، ?اغتاظ وأمر بجلده بأعصاب البقر حتي سال دمه، و?ي كل ذلك  ظل القديس محت?ظاً بهدوئه وببشاشته وكان الرب يش?يه ويقويه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The King brought a magician, whose name was Athanasius, who gave George a cup full of deadly poison to drink. St. George made the sign of the cross over the cup then drank it, and no harm came upon him. They gave him another cup after they had tied his arms behind his back. He asked them pointing with his head; “do you want me to drink from her or from there or from her or her.? This way he made the sign of the cross over the cup with his head. Then he drank it but again it did not harm him. Athanasius the magician believed in the Lord Christ, the King ordered to behead him thus he received the crown of martyrdom. The King and his fellow governors because of their stubbornness attributed the miracle again to sorcery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               استدعي الإمبراطور الساحر أثناسيوس الذي قدم له كأساً مملوءة سمـاً ، ?شربها بعد أن رشم عليها علامة الصليب ?لم تؤثر ?يه. بعدها قدموا له كأساً ثانية بعد أن قيدوه، ?قال لهم مشيراً برأسه "أتريدوني أن أشربها من هنا أم من هنا أم من هنا؟" ورشم بذلك علامة الصليب وشربها ?لم تؤذه أيضاً (1). وقال القديس للملك "لقد وعدنا السيد المسيح بأن من يؤمن به يعمل الأعمال التي عملها هو". است?سر الملك عن هذه الأعمال ، ?شرح له أعمال المسيح المعجزية ومنها إقامة الموتي. ?أحضروا له إنسانـا ميتـا ?أقامه القديس. عندئذ آمن الساحر بالسيد المسيح ، ولكن الملك وأكابر مملكته بسبب عنادهم نسبوا المعجزة للسحر وأمر الملك بقتل الساحر ?نال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Dadianus asked Mari Girgis to accompany him to the pagan temple to offer incense to the gods. The Saint pretended to agree and the King rejoiced. He gathered all the noble men of his kingdom and St. George went along with the King. In the temple the Saint talked to the idol and asked him to state clearly his true identity. The devil was forced to speak from the idol and said, “I am not a god myself or any other idol like me. But the true God is the One that you are proclaiming.? Immediately after, all the idols fell and were destroyed. The priests of the idols became furious and stirred up the people screaming in the face of the King saying; “Take his life for we can’t tolerate seeing him anymore.?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بعد هذه السلسلة من العذابات ، رأي القديس الرب يسوع ?ي حلم وأعلّمه بانتقاله وأراه إكليلاً. ولم ييأس دقلديانوس من أن يظ?ر بالقديس. و?ي محاولة أخيرة استخدم معه اللين وطلب منه أن يصحبه إلي معبد أبوللون، ?ذهب معه القديس. وهناك خاطب القديس الصنم لي?صح عن حقيقته. ?نطق الشيطان من التمثال مرغماً وقال: "أنا لست إلهـا ، لا أنا ولا أي صنم مثلي. لكن الإله واحد ?قط الذي تنادي به". بعد ذلك سقطت التماثيل وتحطمت، ?هاج كهنة الأوثان ووثبوا علي القديس ، وهيجوا الشعب الذي وثب علي الشهيد وقيدوه، ثم صرخوا نحو الملك قائلين: "ار?ع هذا من الحياة ، ?إننا لم نعد نحتمل رؤية هذه المناظر".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Because of this miracle Queen Alexandra, Dadianus wife, believed in the Lord Christ and was martyred.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبسبب هذه الحادثة آمنت بالسيد المسيح الملكة الكسندرة زوجة دقلديانوس واستشهدت علي إسم السيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Finally, Dadianus ordered to behead the Saint. In the place of execution St. George prayed a fervent prayer then extended his neck to the swordsman who cut off his holy head and he received the crown of martyrdom. A Christian took the body and the head, wrapped them in expensive shrouds, and took them to his hometown Lydda in Palestine where they built a church after his name and placed his pure body in it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وأخيرا حكم الملك بقطع رأس القديس. و?ي مكان الإعدام صلي صلاة حارة ومد رقبته للسيا? ?قطع هامته ونال إكليل الشهادة. وأخذ أحد المسيحيين جسده ول?ه بأك?ان ?اخرة ومضي به إلي بلده اللدّ وبنوا هناك كنيسة علي إسمه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات الشهيد العظيم مارجرجس ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.24">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty-Fourth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الرابع والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty-fourth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الرابع والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Sina, the Soldier</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس سنا الجندي ر?يق القديس إيسوذورس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day St. Sina, the soldier, the companion of St. Isidore , was martyred. After the Governor of Farma had tortured the two friends and St. Isidore was martyred, he kept St. Sina in prison until he was removed from his position. When the new Governor took charge with the command not to keep any one who confessed the name of Christ. He heard about the presence of Sina in prison, and that he was a high ranking officer and he was tortured much without turning away from his counsel. The Governor immediately ordered to behead him and his mother was beside him during his martyrdom. She saw his soul ascending as she saw St. Isidore's soul at the time of his martyrdom before.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم استشهد القديس سنا الجندي ر?يق القديس إيسوذورس المذكور ?ي اليوم الثامن عشر من شهر برمهات. وذلك أنه بعدما ع?ذب الاثنان واستشهد إيسوذورس بقي سنا ?ي السجن إلي أن ع?زل والي ال?رما وتولي غيره بوصية بألا يبقي أحداً ممن يعتر? بإسم المسيح.  ولما سمع بوجوده ?ي السجن وإنه من أكابر الجنود وأنه ع?ذب كثيراً ولم يتراجع عن رأيه ، أمر ?ي الحال بقطع رأسه. وكانت أمه بجواره عند أستشهاده ?رأت روحه صاعدة ، كما رأت روح إيسوذورس وقت أستشهاده أيضاً .            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After the martyrdom of St. Sina the believers took his body, shrouded it and laid it with the body of his friend St. Isidore. Their bodies at present time located in the city of Samannoud where they celebrate their feasts. Many signs and wonders are manifested from their bodies to those who seek them with faith.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد أستشهاد سنا أخذ بعض المؤمنين جسده وك?نوه ووضعوه مع جسد ر?يقه. وجسداهما إلي الآن بسمنود وي?عيد لهما ?يها. وتظهر منهما عجائب لمن يقصدهما بأمانة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهما ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Sinuthius (Shenouda I), 55th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا شنودة الأول البطريرك الخامس والخمسين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also of the year 596 of the martyrs (880 A.D.), the Holy Father Pope Sinuthius (Shenouda I), 55th Patriarch of Alexandria, departed. He was born in el-Batanon, Monufia governorate. He became a monk in the monastery of St. Macarius. When he advanced in righteousness and worship, they ordained him hegumen for the church of the monastery.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  من سنة 596 للشهداء ( 880م )، تنيّح القديس البابا شنودة الأول البطريرك الخامس والخمسون من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ولد هذا القديس بالبتانون بمحا?ظة المنو?ية. وترّهب بدير القديس مكاريوس. وإذ تذايد ?ي ال?ضيلة والعبادة عينوه قمصاً علي كنيسة الدير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Shortly after, he was chosen for the Patriarchate with the recommendation of the clergy and people. He was consecrated on the 13th day of Tobe, year 575 of the martyrs (859 A.D.) He was knowledgeable, wise and godly.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم أخ?تير بعدها بطريركياً بتزكية الإكليروس والشعب ور?سم ?ي الثالث عشر من شهر طوبة سنة 575 للشهداء ( 858م ). وكان هذا البطريرك عالماً حكيماً تقياً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his days, some men, in a village called Boukhnessa, one of the villages of Marriot, said that the body did not truly suffer the passion of the Lord Christ but was imaginary. The Pope replied saying, "God the Word, the Lord Christ, was incarnate of the Holy Spirit and of the Virgin Mary and became man. He suffered for us in His Body, and His Divinity was not separated from His humanity, not for a twinkling of an eye even at the time of His passion. The pain and suffering did not touch and affect the Divinity. The Pope used the example of the union of iron and fire. The fire keeps its properties in spite of being united with the iron. The same, the iron keeps its properties in spite of melting with fire. When you hammer a red hot iron, the iron suffers from the hammering but not the flame in spite of being united with the iron.? The Divinity was not separated from the body in the tomb and the disciples saw him with the body that was hung on the cross. The passion that, the Son, the Word had tasted and endured actually and physically had also fallen morally on the Divinity. Since the Divinity was completely and truly united with the humanity (Hypostatic Union) which gave infinite value for the passion that Christ, God Incarnate, had to endure. With this true and sound faith they returned away from their erroneous believe.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكان ?ي عهده بقرية بوخنسا من قري مريوط قوم يقولون أن آلام السيد المسيح لم تقع علي الجسد حقيقة ولكنها كانت خيالية. ?قال لهم البابا: "ان السيد المسيح أتخذ جسداً من العذراء  وجعله متحداً بلاهوته ولم ي?ترقا لحظة واحدة ولا طر?ة عين. وحينما جاز السيد المسيح الألام تألم بجسده ولم تمس الآلام لاهوته ، مع إن اللاهوت لم ي?ترق عن الناسوت ساعة الآمه ".  وقد استعان البابا بالرمز وهو اتحاد الحديد بالنار. ?النار تظل محت?ظة بطبيعتها النارية مع كونها متحدة بالحديد محت?ظاً بطبيعته رغم إنصهاره بالنار. والمطرقة حينما تنزل علي الحديد لا تؤلم النار رغم إتحادها بالحديد. ?اللاهوت لم ين?صل عن الناسوت ?ي القبر ورآه التلاميذ بالجسد الذي ع?لق علي الصليب. وأذا كانت الآلام التي تحملها وذاقها الإبن الكلمة قد وقعت حسياً علي الناسوت، ?هي أيضاً  وقعت معنوياً وأدبياً علي اللاهوت، حيث كان اللاهوت متحداً اتحاداً كاملاً وحقيقياً بالناسوت. الأمر الذي أعطي قيمة لا نهائية (إلهية) للآلام التي إجتازها المسيح الإله المتأنس. وبهذا الرأي السليم رجعوا عن ضلالتهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the Pope’s visit to Upper Egypt and when he arrived to Al-Ballyana, he learned that some believed; “that when Christ died on the cross, the Divinity died along with His humanity.? He explained to them the hypostatic union of the Divinity with the Humanity and the Divinity did not die for He raised the Humanity in the tomb.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي رحلة البابا للصعيد وصل إلي مدينة البلينا. ?علم أن البعض سقطوا ?ي بدعة مؤداها : "أن المسيح مات علي الصليب بلاهوته وناسوته." ?وضح لهم إتحاد اللاهوت بالناسوت وأن اللاهوت لم يمت لانه هو الذي أقام الناسوت ?ي القبر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the reign of A’anbassa Ebn Is-haq who ruled Egypt after Abd el-Wahid and he was just in his dealings with everyone. The Pope seized the opportunity to renovate the ruined churches and monasteries. After A’anbassa had left the government to the Turkish rulers chaos befell the country. The Pope wanted to do what could benefit the afflicted people of Egypt. He dug through the streets of Alexandria small streams to supply its people with fresh water what made the lands green like paradise.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي عهد الوالي عنبسه بن إسحق الذي تولي علي مصر بعد الوالي عبد الواحد ، وقد كان هذا الوالي عادلاً ?ي المعاملة مع الجميع. انتهز البابا ال?رصة لتجديد الكنائس والأديرة الخربة. وبعد أن ترك عنبسه الولاية للولاة الاتراك، عم الإضطراب الناتج عن إند?اع هؤلاء الحكام وراء نزواتهم، و?ي هذه الأثناء أراد البابا أن يعمل شيئاً يعود بالمن?عة علي الشعب المصري المعذب ?ح?ر ?ي شوارع الإسكندرية قنوات تحمل الماء العذب لسكانها. ?تحولت الاراضي إلي جنات و?راديس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During his days also were great tribulations and severe persecutions. They levied taxes on the monks, clergy, the endowments of the churches and monasteries. The Pope had to send envoy to the Caliph twice to issue his orders to left up the unjust and each time he granted him his request.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي أيام هذا البابا اشتد الاضطهاد، و??رضت الضرائب علي الرهبان ورجال الدين وأوقا? الكنائس والأديرة ووقع نهب كثير. وقد أرسل البابا رجلين إلي الخلي?ة ?ي بغداد لكي يصدر أمره إلي (عاملة بن المدير) بأن ير?ع المظالم ?أجاب الخلي?ة طلبهم ور?ع الجزية عن الكهنة والرهبان وخ?ضها علي باقي الناس. وقد تكرر هذا الطلب أيام الخلي?ة المهتدي ، ?تأيد الأمر الأول.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               It happened also a drought in the city of Marriot for three years. This father came to the church of St. Mina to celebrate his feast. The inhabitants of the area complained to the Pope about the lack of water so he consoled and comforted them. After he celebrated the Divine Liturgy, he supplicated God to have mercy upon His creation. The rain descended like a flood, until the wells, the vineyards, and the farms were filled with water.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث أيضاً  أن امتنع ماء المطر عن مريوط ثلاث سنوات ، ?جاء البابا الي كنيسة الشهيد مار مينا بمريوط ليصلي عيد الشهيد مارمينا. ?شكا له السكان عن عدم وجود الماء ?عزاهم وصبرهم. وبعد صلاة القداس حدث رعد وبرق ونزل المطر كالسيل حتي امتلأت البقاع من الماء.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In the year 866 A.D. this father went to the wilderness to observe Passion Week in the monastery of St. Macarius, the Berbers came to the desert of Shiheet to plunder the monasteries and kill the monks. After Pope Shenouda I had finished the divine liturgy on Maundy Thursday, he took his staff, holding the cross high and he went forth to meet them without any weapon. When they saw him coming out alone they retreated before his extraordinary courage and fled away.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي سنة 866م علم البربر أن البابا عزم أن يصلي أسبوع الآلام بدير أبي مقار، ?قدموا سراً وإستولوا علي كنيسة أبي مقار وتوابعها ونهبوا ما ?يها من متاع وزاد. وهكذا ?علوا بالاديرة الأخري. ولما ?رغ البابا من صلاة خميس العهد،?وجئ الرهبان عند عودتهم إلي صوامعهم بوابل من الحجارة من البربرعندئذ خرج البابا بم?رده را?عاً الصليب ليواجه البربر بدون سلاح. وعندما رأوه خارجاً بم?رده تراجعوا أمام شجاعته النادرة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Shenouda I cared greatly to renovate St. Macarius monastery and surrounded it with a fortified wall to protect the monks from any harm. He also built and renovated the cells of the monks along with silos for grain storage within the walls of the monastery. The Pope paid a great attention to the affairs of the churches and monasteries, their buildings, and their needs. Whatever money was left to him, he gave to the poor and the needy. When he finished his good endeavor departed in peace after staying on the apostolic throne for 21 years, 3 months and 11 days.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد عانت هذه الاديرة كثيراً من المصائب ، ?لقد ألقي الأعراب رجالهم ?ي الصحراء ، وأخذوا يرقبون خروج الرهبان للتزود بالماء ، ?ينقضون عليهم ويأخذون مامعهم. ولما عادت السكينة إهتم هذا البابا بترميم دير أبي مقار وأحاطه بسور منيع لحماية الرهبان من الأذي بعد أن بني لهم صوامع داخل السور.  وكان هذا البابا كثير الإهتمام بأمور الكنائس والأديرة. وكان كل ماي?ضل عنه يتصدق به ولما أكمل سعيه الصالح تنيّح بسلام بعد أن اقام علي الكرسي المرقسي واحد وعشرين سنة وثلاثة أشهر وأحد عشر يوماً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.25">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Fifth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الخامس والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty fifth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الخامس والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Sarah and her two sons</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديسة سارة وولداها</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Sarah and her two sons were martyred. She was from the city of Antioch, the wife of a man whose name was Socrates. He was one of the army commanders of Emperor Diocletian. This commander had denied Christ to please Diocletian, pretending before his wife that he was forced to do that because he feared the Emperor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم أستشهدت القديسة سارة وولداها. وهذه كانت من أهل أنطاكية زوجة لرجل أسمه سقراط أحد قواد دقلديانوس. كان هذا القائد قد ترك إيمانه المسيحي خو?اً من الإمبراطور دقلديانوس ، وكان يتظاهر أمام زوجته أنه ?عل هذا رغماً عنه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               God granted Sarah two sons; however she could not baptize them in Antioch, because of her fear from the Emperor and her husband. She took them and sailed to Alexandria to baptize them there. God willed to reveal the greatness of her faith as a lesson to the generations to come. God brought forth a great tempest and the ship was about to be wrecked and drown. Sarah was afraid that her sons would be drowned without being baptized. She prayed a long prayer then she wounded her right breast, took some of her blood, anointed them making the sign of the cross upon their foreheads, and over the hearts. Then she dipped them in the sea three times saying: "In the Name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث أن رزقهما الله بولدين ?لم تسطتع والدتهما أن تعمّدهما خو?اً من الملك ومن زوجها. ?أخذتهما ومعها غلامان وسا?رت إلي الإسكندرية لتعمّدهما هناك. ?أراد الله أن يظهر عظم أمانتها من?عة للأجيال. ?أهاج ريحاً شديدة كادت ت?غرق المركب. ?خا?ت المرأة أن يموت ولداها بغير عماد. ?صلت صلاة  طويلة ثم شرطت ثديها الأيـمن وأخذت من الدم وصلبت علي ولديها وقلبيهما، ثم غطستهما ?ي البحر ثلاث مرات بإسم الآب والإبن والروح القدس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               After that, the winds died down, a great calm came on the sea, and the ship sailed peacefully toward Alexandria. When she arrived, she took her sons, went to the church, and handed them to Pope Peter, the seal of the martyrs to baptize them along with the children of the city. When the Pope carried one of her sons to baptize him, the water froze. The Pope marveled and went on baptizing other children and the water returned to its nature. When he came back to her sons, the water froze again. The same thing occurred also on the third attempt. The Pope was amazed and asked their mother about her story. She told him about all what happened to her at sea and what she had done to her sons. He glorified God and said: "It is indeed one baptism."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد ذلك هدأت الرياح وسكن البحر وسارت المركب بسلام.  وعند وصولها إلي الإسكندرية دخلت الكنيسة وقدمت ولديها للبابا بطرس خاتم الشهداء ليعمّدهما مع أط?ال المدينة. ?لما أخذ الولدين ليعمّدهما تجمد ماء المعمودية كالحجر. ?تعجب البابا من ذلك وتركهما وأخذ غيرهما من الأط?ال ?عاد الماء إلي طبيعته. ثم عاد ?أخذ الولدين مرة ثانية ?عاد الماء ?تجمد وهكذا ثلاث مرات. ?استغرب البابا وأستخبر من والدتهما عن الأمر. ?عر?ته مما جري لها ?ي البحر وما عملته لولديها. ?مجد الله قائلاً: "حقاً إنها معمودية واحدة".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the woman returned to Antioch, her husband denounced what she had done. He related what happened to the Emperor accusing his wife with adultery. The Emperor brought her and reproached her saying: "Why did you go to Alexandria to commit adultery with the Christians?" The Saint answered him: "Christians do not commit adultery, and do not worship idols, and after this does what you wish, for you will not hear another word from me."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما عادت المرأة إلي أنطاكية أنكر عليها زوجها ما ?علته. وأخبر دقلديانوس بذلك ?إستحضرها ووبخها قائلاً: "لماذا ذهبت إلي الإسكندرية هل لتزني مع النصاري؟" ?أجابت القديسة قائلة: "إن النصاري لا يزنون ولا يعبدون الأصنام. ومهما أردت بعد هذا إ?عله وسو? لا تسمع مني كلمة أخري".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Emperor asked her: "Tell me what did you do in Alexandria?" When she did not answer him, he ordered to tie her hands behind her, and to place her two sons on her belly, and to burn all three of them. She turned her face to the east and prayed. She delivered up her pure soul along with her two sons, and they all received the crowns of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?قال لها: "عر?ينى ماذا ?علت? بالاسكندرية؟" ، ?لم تجبه. ?أمر بشد يديها إلي خل?ها ووضع ولديها علي بطنها ثم أحرقهم بالنار. ?حولت وجهها إلي الشرق وصلت ثم أسلمت روحها الطاهرة مع و?لديها.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ونالوا جمعيهم اكاليل الشهادة. بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Commemoration of St. Theodore the hermit and the One hundred and twenty martyrs</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس تاوضروس العابد والمائة والعشرين شهيداً</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               This day also marks the martyrdom of St. Theodore the hermit and the one hundred and twenty martyrs, who were martyred in Persia.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  استشهد القديس تاوضروس العابد ومائة وعشرون شهيداً، استشهدوا جميعآ ببلاد العجم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all and glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.26">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Sixth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السادس والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty sixth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السادس والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Sousnyos</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">شهادة القديس سوسنيوس ومعه أل? ومائة شخص</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 21 of the martyrs (305 A.D.) St. Sousnyos was martyred. This Saint was the son of Sosipater an officer of Diocletian’s household. The angel of the Lord had appeared to him and strengthened his heart on receiving the crown of martyrdom, and he kept this in his heart. The Emperor sent him to the city of Nicomedia to restore the worship of idols and the Saint was exceedingly sorrowful. He sent for a Christian priest and inquired from him about the facts of the Christian faith. He taught him the doctrines of the church, the true facts of Christianity and then baptized him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 21 للشهداء ( 305م ) أستشهد القديس سوسنيوس. وهو كان إبناً لأحد خواص الملك دقلديانوس اسمه سوسيبطرس. وكان قد ظهر ملاك الرب للقديس وقوي عزمه لنيل إكليل الشهادة ?ح?ظ الامر ?ي قلبه.  وحدث أن ارسله الملك إلي مدينة نيقوميدية لتجديد عبادة الأوثان. ?حزن القديس جداً، واستحضر كاهن مسيحي واستعلم منه عن كل أمور الدين المسيحي حتي عر? حقائقه ، ثم إعتمد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he returned to his hometown his father knew about his Christian faith. He tried to kill his son then he accused him to the Emperor that he did not worship the idols. The Emperor summoned him to offer incense to the idols. When he entered the temple of the idols, he commanded them with the power of the Lord Christ to descend to hell. The earth opened its mouth and swallowed them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما عاد إلي مدينته علم أبوه حاله وأراد قتله ، وسعي به لدي الملك أنه لا يعبد الأوثان. ?أمر الملك أن يستدعوه ليبخر للأوثان. ?لما دخل إلي هيكل الأصنام أمرهم بقوة السيد المسيح أن يهبطوا إلي الهاوية. ??تحت الأرض ?اها وإبتلعتهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The news of the destruction of the idols by the prayers of the Saint spread. The Emperor was exasperated and ordered to torment him with severe tortures. He was beaten with pins and crushed with a thresher then dragged him throughout the city. However the Lord strengthened and comforted the saint and sent His angel to console him. Finally, they beheaded him, and he received the crown of martyrdom. The numbers of those who witnessed his passion and believed because of him were eleven hundreds. They were beheaded and received the crowns of martyrdom,            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?شاع الخبر بهلاك الآلهة بواسطة القديس. ?حنق الملك وأمر أن يعذب أشد العذاب. ?ضرب بالدبابيس ، وع?صر ، وس?حق بالنورج ، ثم جروه ?ي المدينة. وكان الرب يقويه ويصبره وملاكه ي?تقده. أخيراً قطعوا رأسه ونال إكليل الشهادة. وكان عدد الذين شاهدوه وقت العذاب  وآمنوا بسببه ثم نالوا اكاليل الشهادة، أل? ومائة شخص.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of their prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواتهم ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of Pope Yoannis VII, 78th Patriarch of Alexandria</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس البابا يوأنس السابع البطريرك الثامن والسبعين من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, of the year 1009 of the martyrs (1293 A.D.), Pope Yoannis VII, 78th Patriarch, departed. After the departure of Pope Athanasius III, the 76th Patriarch, there were two nominees for the patriarchate, the first was Yoannis Ebn Abi-Saaid El-Soukary and the second was Ghobrial the nephew of Anba Peter, bishop of Tanbady. The numbers of electoral votes were split equal in the Holy Synod. Yoannis (John) was supported by the archons (lay leaders) of Old Cairo but Ghobrial was supported by the wealthy people of Cairo, for this reason the bishops were divided into two groups.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ى مثل هذا اليوم أيضاً  من سنة 1009 للشهداء ( 1293م)،تنيح القديس البابا يوأنس السابع البطريرك الثامن والسبعيـن من بطاركة الكرازة المرقسية. ?بعد نياحة البابا أثناسيوس الثالث البطريرك السادس والسبعين، كان يوجد مرشحان لدرجة البطريركية ، الأول يوحنا بن أبي سعيد السكري ، والثاني غبريال أبن أخت الأنبا بطرس أسق? طنبدي. ولما كانت أصوات ناخبيهم ?ي المجمع المقدس متساوية ، وكان يوحنا معضداً من أكابر الطائ?ة بمصر القديمة ، وغبريال معضداً  من أعيان القاهرة ، لذلك انقسم الأساق?ة إلي قسمين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Finally they decided to cast an altar lot which fell on Gabriel, which did not satisfy the other side. They went to appease the rulers to support them in electing Yoannis. They were able to consecrate him patriarch on the 6th of Tobe, year 978 of the martyrs (1262 A.D.).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أخيراً ات?قوا علي أجراء قرعة هيكلية ?طلعت بإسم غبريال. ومع ذلك لم يرضي الحزب الآخر. ?عمـدوا علي إسترضاء  الحكام ليعضدوهم ?ي أمر إنتخاب يوحنا ، حتي تقووا وثبتت اقدامهم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He remained on the Patriarchal throne for a period of six years, nine months, and nineteen days which was dominated by problems, disturbances and contentions. During that time the supporters of Gabriel were able to depose the Patriarch Yoannis to one of the monasteries.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?تمكنوا من إقامته بطريركياً لمدة ست سنوات وتسعة أشهر وتسعة عشر يوماً. كانت كلها منا?سة ومعاكسة وخصام. و?ي خلالها تقوي حزب غبريال ?عزلوا يوحنا بأحد الأديرة وولوا غبريال ?ي الرابع والعشرين من بابة سنة 985 للشهداء ( 1268م ).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They consecrated Gabriel on the 24th of Paope, year 985 of the martyrs (1268 A.D.). Pope Gabriel III, 77th Patriarch, continued to manage the affairs of the church for a period of two years, two month and ten days. During this period the heat of dissension did not die down until Pope Gabriel departed on the 6th day of Tobe, year 987 of the martyrs (1271 A.D.) They unanimously agreed to bring back Pope Yoannis on the 7th day of Tobe, year 987 of the martyrs (1271 A.D.) during the reign of al-Zahir Baybars.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               استمر البابا غبريال الثالث البطريرك السابع والسبعون، يدّبر الكنيسة سنتين وشهرين وعشرة أيام، كانت ال?تنة ?ي خلالها لا تخمد نارها، حتي تنّيح البابا غبريال ?ي السادس من طوبة 987 للشهداء ( 1271م ) أيام الظاهر بيبرس. ?أتحدت كلمة الجميع على أعادة البابا يؤانس  (يوحنا) ?ي السابع من طوبة ٩٨٧ للشهداء ١٢٧١ م.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Yoannis VII had an exalted standing, was venerable, and of vast knowledge. He worked on removing the animosity between his people which glorified his fame. He also prepared the Holy Myron.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان البابا يوأنس السابع جليل القدر ، وقوراً واسع العلم، ?عمل إلي إزالة الوحشة بين الأحزاب، ?عظمت شهرته. وقد قام بعمل الميرون المقدس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the time of this Pope, he consecrated a Coptic Metropolitan for Ethiopia instead of the Antiochian metropolitan. There was also an Egyptian merchant who had sent a large sum of money to a partner in Ethiopia. Later on that partner died and he could not regain his money. He wrote to the ruler of Egypt complaining about the injustice that befell him. The King referred the complaint to Pope Yoannis who gave him a letter to the emperor of Ethiopia. The Emperor returned to him the money along with some gifts.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد قام البابا أيضاً برسم مطراناً قبطياً للحبشة بدلاً من المطران الإنطاكي. وكان هناك أيضاً  تاجر مصري قد أرسل لشريك له ?ي الحبشة مالا وبعدها مات الشريك. ?ر?ع التاجر مظلمة لملك مصر ليساعده ?ي الحصول علي ماله. ?أ?حيلت الشكوي إلي البابا يوأنس الذي أعطاه كتابـا للإمبراطور بالحبشة، ?أعاد إليه المال واعطاه هدايا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The political climate during his papacy was difficult because of the riots and unrest that spread in all Egypt because of the high and excessive taxes. Also they forced the Copts to wear special clothes and allowing the vulgar street people to attack them without any deterrent. The Pope exerted great efforts for the sake of his people for it was very disturbing for him to see his flock weaken and abandoning the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكانت الحالة السياسية ?ي أيام هذا البابا عصيبة، بسبب ما ساد مصر من ال?تن والقلاقل. وكان الدا?ع لهذه ال?تن ?داحة الضرائب المتزايدة، والتشدد ?ي ?رض ملابس خاصة علي الأقباط، وترك العامة يتهجمون عليهم بلا رادع. ?بذل البابا جهودا كبيرة ?ي سبيل شعبه إذ راعه أن يجد الكثيرين منهم يضع?ون ?يجحدون السيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               During the reign of El-Sultan Qalawon who ordered to dig a huge pit and throw the Christians in it, to be burned and that was in the year 980 of the martyrs. He also demanded from the Pope to pay fifty thousand Dinars to release the Christians, which took two years to collect them. The Christians suffered many hardships during his time, and also the bishops were greatly afflicted.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي أيام السلطان قلاوون أمر أن يح?روا ح?رة كبيرة ويجمعوا ?يها النصاري ويحرقوهم، وكان ذلك ?ي 980 للشهداء. وعندئذ طلب السلطان قلاوون من البابا أن يد?ع له خمسين أل? دينار ?ي نظير أن يطلق النصاري. وهكذا أقاموا سنتين يحصلونها. هذا وقد جرت علي النصاري شدائد كثيرة ?ي أيامه يطول شرحها ، وقاسي الأساق?ة الكثير.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pope Yoannis remained on the apostolic throne in his second time 22 years, 3 months, and 29 days, and departed in peace. He was buried in El-Nastor monastery in el-Basateen during the reign of el-Sultan Al-Nasir.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وظل البابا يوأنس علي الكرسي ?ي المدة الثانية اثنتين وعشرين سنة وثلاثة أشهر وتسعة عشر يوم وتنيّح بسلام ود??ن بدير النسطور بالبساتين ?ي أيام السلطان الملك الناصر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.27">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Seventh Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم السابع والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty seventh day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم السابع والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Boctor Ebn Romanus</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">شهادة القديس بقطر بن رومانوس</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 22 of the martyrs (306 A.D.) the honorable St. Boctor (Victor) Ebn Romanus, was martyred. He was a high ranking officer, Stratelates, in Emperor Diocletian’s army. His mother was a Christian woman called Martha and she reared him on the Christian ethics. He was promoted in the ranks in the kingdom until he became the third in succession while he was still a young man. He prayed often and fasted and he despised the vanity of the world and its glory.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 22 للشهداء ( 306م ) أستشهد القديس الجليل بقطر بن رومانوس وزير دقلديانوس. وكانت أمه إمـرأة مسيحية أسمها مرثا قد ربته علي المبادئ المسيحية، وارتقي ?ي رتب المملكة حتي أصبح الثالث ?ي المرتبة وهو بعد شاباً صغيراً. وكان كثير الصلاة والصوم ، يحتقر أباطيل العالم وكل مجده.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Victor had a profound friendship with Prince Claudius his cousin. When Diocletian abandoned the faith Victor and Claudius refused to worship the idols. The men of the royal court kept this fact from the emperor for their love to these two princes.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أرتبط بقطر بصداقة قوية مع الأمير إقلاديوس أبن خالته. ولما جحد دقلديانوس الإيمان ر?ض الأميران بقطر وإقلاديوس السجود للأوثان. وقد أخ?ي رجال البلاط هذا الخبر عن الملك لحبهم لهذين الأميرين.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They visited the prisoners, cared for the needs of the poor and buried the bodies of the saintly martyrs. When they beheaded St. Theodata, the mother of Sts. Cosmas and Damian, her body remained thrown down and no one dared to bury her because they feared the Emperor. St. Cosmas cried out at those present saying; “O men of this city is there not one merciful person among you who will cover the body of this poor old widow and bury her?? This Saint went forth and took the body, shrouded it, then buried her, not caring about the Emperor's order.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان الأميران يت?قدان المسجونين ، ويهتمان بإحتياجات المعوزين ، ويد?نان  أجساد الشهداء القديسين.  ولما ق?طعت رأس القديسة ثيؤدورة أم الشهيدين قزمان ودميان ، بقي جسدها مطروحاً لم يجسر أحد أن يد?نه. ?صرخ قزمان قائلاً:  "ياأهل المدينة ألا يوجد أحد قلبه رحيم يتقدم ?يستر جسد هذه الأرملة العجوز ويد?نها؟". عندئذ تقدم القديس بقطر وأخذ الجسد وك?نه ثم د?نه غير مبال بأمر ديقلديانوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When his father heard about what he had done he called him to inquire from him about his action. However St. Boctor admonished his father for worshipping the idols and forsaken his faith in the Living God. His father became angry at him and accused him before the Emperor. The Emperor brought Boctor and treated him amiably. Boctor cordially admonished the emperor for forsaking the faith and asked him to return to his Savior and to cease of his opposition to the Christian faith. The emperor became furious and ordered to send him to Alexandria to torture and slay him there away from Antioch.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?سمع والده بذلك ولما إستدعاه لسؤاله ، قام بتبكيت والده علي عبادة الأوثان ، وتركه عبادة الله الحي. ?غضب أبيه عليه وسعي به إلي الملك الذي إستدعاه وصار يلاط?ه. وكان بقطر ?ي محبة يوبخ الملك علي جحده الإيمان  ،طالباً منه أن يرجع إلي مخلصه الصالح ويك? عن مقاومته للإيمان المسيحي. ?غضب الملك عليه وأمر بإرساله إلي الإسكندرية لتعذيبه وقتله بعيداً عن إنطاكية.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On his way he met his mother who was crying for him. He told her: “Do not cry about me but rather cry about your husband Romanus that the Lord might direct him to the way of truth.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي طريقه إلتقي بأمه التي كانت تبكي عليه. ?قال لها ياأمي لا تبكي عليّ ولكن ابكي علي زوجك رومانوس لعل الرب يهديه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When he arrived to Alexandria, the governor Armanius tormented him with cruel tortures. He placed him on an iron bed and lit a blazing fire under it however the Lord saved him from the fire. When the governor became exasperated, he threw him in prison. A daughter of one of the noble men of the city was watching from her palace which faced the prison. She was looking at the imprisoned Christian. She fell down and died. St. Victor asked to bring the dead body to him to pray for her. With the prayers of the saint she was raised from the dead. Her parents rejoiced and they all believed in the Lord Christ. Later on the girl was married and had a child and she called him Victor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي الإسكندرية عذبه الوالي أرمانيوس بعذابات عظيمة منها أنه وضعه علي سرير من حديد وأوقد تحته النار ، ولكن الرب خلصه من النار. ولما إغتاظ الوالي ألقاه ?ي السجن. وهناك كانت إبنة أحد الأمراء تتطلع من قصرها الذي يطل علي السجن لتنظر المسيحيين المسجونين ، ?سقطت جثة هامدة. ?طلب القديس بقطر أن يحضروا له الجثمان ليصلي عليه. وبصلاة القديس عادت ال?تاة للحياة ??رح والداها وأمنوا جميعاً بالسيد المسيح.  وقد تزوجت هذه ال?تاة ?يما بعد وأنجبت ط?لاً دعته (بقطر).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The governor shortly after crushed St. Victor’s body but the Lord sent Archangel Michael who healed and strengthened him. When the governor returned home depressed, his wife harshly rebuked him for torturing St. Victor. He threatened her for he considered what happened to the saint was sorcery. When he became weary of him, he sent him to the governor of Ansena for he was afraid to kill him lest his father Romanus take revenge for his son’s death.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعدها قام الوالي بتعذيب القديس بقطر ، ولكن الرب أرسل رئيس الملائكة الجليل ميخائيل ليسنده. ولما عاد الوالي إلي بيته كئيباً وبخته زوجته بعن? لتعذيبه للقديس بقطر. ?صار يهددها حاسباً أن ما حدث لبقطر إنما هو من قبل السحر. ولما ضاق الأمر به أرسله إلي والي أنصنا لأنه خا? أن يقتله ?ينتقم منه والده رومانوس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the way to Ansena the boat docked at Taha where Victor met a friend who was a soldier called Bifam. He was a Christian in secret however St. Victor encouraged him to declare his faith in the Lord Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي الطريق إلي أنصنا رست الس?ينة ?ي طحا حيث التقي بقطر بصديق له جندي يدعي بي?ام. وكان بي?ام مسيحياً مخت?ياً ، ?شجعه القديس بقطر أن ي?علن إيمانه بالسيد المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When St. Victor arrived to Arianus the governor of Ansena, who wanted to slay him but his advisors asked him to place him in an abandoned place and not kill him lest his father Romanus take revenge against him. However Arianus cut off his tongue and placed red hot iron nails in his sides then sent him to the abandoned palace to die there.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما وصل القديس بقطر إلي إريانوس والي أنصنا أراد قتله ، ولكن مستشاريه طلبوا منه أن يضعه ?ي قصر مهجور ، ولا يقتله لئلا ينتقم منه والده رومانوس. ولكن إريانوس قطع لسانه وجعل ?ي جنبه مسامير محماة. وبعدها أرسله الي القصر المهجور ليموت هناك.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Saint knew carpentry and was able to make chairs. He sold his handiwork and lived on half and contributed the rest. His mother sent Arion the faithful soldier who accompanied him from Antioch to that palace to check on the condition of her son. When he arrived to the palace, he met St. Victor who asked him to assure his mother about his condition.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وإذ كان يعر? صنعة النجارة ، ?كان يعمل كراسيا ويبيعها ويقتات منها بالنص? ويتصدق بالباقي.  و?ي هذا القصر أرسلت والدته هاريون الجندى الأمين الذي جاء من أنطاكية ، لكي يطمئنها علي إبنها. ولما وصل الجندى هاريون تقابل مع القديس بقطر وأ?همه القديس أن يطمئن والدته علي أحواله.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Shortly after a new governor came to Ansena and was informed about the account of the Saint. He brought him and tried to befriend him but the saint refused. They smote his mouth, hung a heavy rock to his hands and then threw him into a fiery furnace. They boiled tar and oil and poured it over him. Then they placed him in quicklime and vinegar. After all that they plucked out his eyes and hung him head down. The Lord strengthened and comforted him every time. During the passion of St. Victor many believed among them were soldiers and they all received the crowns of martyrdom. The governor arranged for a magician to prepare a poison for the saint which did not harm him. The magician believed and accepted martyrdom with joy. Finally the governor ordered to behead St. Victor.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبعد ?ترة جاء إلي أنصنا والي جديد ، ?أعلموه بخبر القديس بقطر. ?استحضره وحاول أن يلاط?ه ولكنه ر?ض. ?ضربوه علي ?مه وعلقوا ?ي يديه حجراً ثقيلاً ، وأمر الوالي أن ي?طرح ?ي أتون النار ، وي?غلي ز?ت وزيت ثم ي?سكب عليه ، ثم يوضع ?ي الجير والخل. وبعد كل هذا قلعوا عينيه وعلقوه منكساً ، وكان ?ي كل مرة الرب يقويه ويصبره.  وقد آمن كثيرون أثناء عذاب القديس بقطر ، منهم بعض الجند ، ونالوا اكاليل الشهادة. وكان قد أعد الوالي ساحراً ليصنع سماً للقديس بقطر. ولكن القديس بقطر  أستطاع أن يقنعه بالإيمان المسيحي ?أمن الساحر وقبل الأستشهاد ب?رح.  أخيرا أمر الوالي بقطع رأس القديس بقطر.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               A young girl saw a crown coming down over the head of the saint. She declared her faith, they tore her body between two palm trees then beheaded her, and thus she received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               رأت ?تاة صغيرة الإكليل ينزل علي رأس الشهيد، ?أعلنت إيمانها باله القديس بقطر ، ?مزقوا جسدها بين نخلتين وقطعوا رأسها ?نالت هي أيضاً إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the mother of the saint knew what happened to her son Victor, she came and took his body to Antioch. The people of Upper Egypt bid him Farwell with respect, veneration and everyone received his blessing.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما علمت والدة الشهيد بما حدث لإبنها بقطر جاءت وأخذت جسده إلي أنطاكية ، بعد أن ودعه أهل الصعيد بمهابة عظيمة وتكريم وكان الكل يتباركون منه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.28">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Eighth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثامن والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty eighth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثامن والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of St. Milius, the Ascetic</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس ميليوس الناسك</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day, St. Milius, the ascetic, was martyred. This father was an ascetic and striver all the days of his life. He dwelt in a cave with his two disciples Anba Joshua and Anba Joseph in mount Khurasan .            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               1 – ?ي مثل هذا اليوم أستشهد القديس ميليوس. كان هذا الأب ناسكاً ومجاهداً طول أيامه. ساكناً مع تلميذيه الأنبا يشوع والأنبا يوس? ?ي مغارة بجبل خوراسان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The two sons of the king of Khurasan went out to hunt wild animals and they set up their nets. This Saint fell in their net, and he was dressed in sackcloth made of hair, and his hair was exceedingly long. When they saw him they were afraid of him and asked him: "Who are you and from where?" He replied: "I am a sinful man and I dwell here in this mount to worship the Lord Jesus Christ the Son of the Living God." They told him: "There is no God except the sun and the fire, now come and worship them lest we kill you." He answered them: "These things have been created by God. You are not aware of the truth. It is preferable for you to worship the true God, the creator of all these things."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحدث أن خرج ولدا ملك خوراسان لصيد الوحوش ونصبا شباكهما ، ?وقع هذا القديس داخلها. وكان هذا القديس لابسا ثوبا من الشعر. ?لما رأياه خا?ا منه وسألاه قائلين: "من أنت ومن أين أتيت؟". ?أجابهما قائلاً :" أناإنسان خاطئ ساكن ?ي هذا الجبل لعبادة الرب يسوع ابن الله الحي"  ?قالا له: "ليس إله إلا الشمس والنار ?تقدم وقدم لهما قرباناً الأن وإلا قتلناك ". ?أجابهما: "إن هذه من صنع الله وأنتما لا تعر?ان الحق ،  والأ?ضل لكما أن تعبدا الإله الحقيقي خالق هذه كلها".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They asked him: "Do you claim that he Whom the Jews crucified is God?" He said to them: "Yes, He Who was crucified for our sins, and Who was killed and rose from the dead, is God indeed." The two princes were raged of him. They seized his two disciples, tortured them, and then slew them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?قالوا له: "أتزعم أن المصلوب من اليهود إله؟"". ?قال: "نعم ذاك الذي صلب الخطية وأمات الموت هو الإله". ?حنق الإثنان عليه وأمسكا تلميذيه وعذّباهما وقتلاهما.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               As for St. Milius, they continued to torture him for two weeks. Finally, they made him stand up between them and shot arrows at him until he departed in peace and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وظلا يعذبان القديس مدة إسبوعين. أخيرا وق? أحدهما من خل?ه والآخرمن الأمام ليضرباه بالنشاب. ورماه الواحد من هنا والآخر من هناك حتي تنّيح بسلام ونال إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the following day they went on hunting, followed a wild beast, and shot arrows at him, and God turned their arrows into their own hearts killing them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي الغد ركضا وراء وحش وضرباه بالسهام، ?عاد سهم كل واحد منهما إلي قلبه، ?مات الإثنان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The prayers of this Saint be with us and Glory be to our God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.29">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Twenty Ninth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم التاسع والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the twenty ninth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم التاسع والعشرون من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The commemoration of the Three Major Feasts of the Lord</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">تذكار الأعياد السيدية البشارة والميلاد والقيامة</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day the church celebrates the commemoration of the three major feasts of the Lord: the Annunciation, the Nativity and the Resurrection of the Lord. The rite of the liturgy is prayed in the joyful tune, no strict abstinence or prostrations.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي هذا اليوم ت?عّيد الكنيسة بتذكار الأعياد السيدية الكبري البشارة والميلاد والقيامة. وي?صلي بالطقس ال?رايحي ويمنع الصوم الإنقطاعي والميطانيات.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of our Good Savior be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة السيد المسيح مخلصنا الصالح ?لتكن معنا. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Erastus, the Apostle</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس أرسطوس أحد السبعين رسـولاً</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, St. Erastus, one of the Seventy Apostles, departed. He received the grace of the Holy Spirit in the upper room of Zion along with the holy Disciple and afterward he preached the good news of salvation.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ي مثل هذا اليوم تنيّح القديس أرسطوس. كان هذا القديس أحد السبعين رسـولا و قبَل نعمة الروح القدس المعزي مع الآباء الرسل ?ي علية صهيون. وبعدها كرز ببشارة الخلاص.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The Book of Acts tells us that when the apostle St. Paul was in Asia and decided to return to Jerusalem, “He sent into Macedonia two of those who ministered to him, Timothy and Erastus.? This saint endured many sufferings in his ministry with St. Paul then returned to Jerusalem to serve there. He taught and exhorted the people in it and in many other cities.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وقد ورد ?ي س?ر الأعمال أن القديس بولس الرسول عندما كان ?ي آسيا ، ووطد عزمه علي العودة إلي أورشليم ، أرسل اثنين من تلاميذه إلي مقدونية وهما القديسان تيموثاوس وأرسطوس. وقد نال هذا القديس آلام كثيرة ?ي خدمته مع الرسول بولس. وبعد ذلك عاد إلي أورشليم ليخدم بها.?قام بالتعليم ?يها و?ي غيرها من البلدان.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               They laid the hands on Erastus ordaining him a bishop for the city of Paneas. He preached the Lord Christ to its people and enlightened their minds. He demolished many temples and built churches. God worked many signs and miracles by his hands. He changed bitter salty water to sweet water, sprouted dry wood to bring fruits and healed many incurable illnesses. After he reached a good old age, he departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم وضعوا عليه اليد ورسموه أسق?اً علي مدينة باناطس. ?كرز ?يها بالسيد المسيح ، وأضاء عقول أهلها وهدم برابي كثيرة وبني كنائس. وقد أجري الله علي يديه أيات كثيرة منها أنه حول مياه مالحة إلي عذبة. وأيضاً جعل أخشاب يابسة تنبت وتخرج ?روعاً وجعلها تثمر. وش?ي أمراضاً صعبة. وبعد أن وصل إلي سن الشيخوخة تنيح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Departure of St. Acacius, Bishop of Jerusalem</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">نياحة القديس أكاكيوس أسق? أورشليم</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also, St. Acacius, Bishop of Jerusalem, departed. He was raised in a life of purity and godliness. He endured persecution for a long time, and God wrought many signs and wonders by his hands, and then departed in peace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً  تنيّح القديس أكاكيوس أسق? أورشليم. وكان قد نشأ ?ي حياة البر والتقوي. وقد أحتمل الإضطهادات زمانا طويلاً. و?د أجري الله علي يديه أيات وعجائب. ثم تنيّح بسلام.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلواته ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season>   <Season id="Parmoute.30">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Thirtieth Day of the Blessed Month of Parmoute</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">اليوم الثلاثون من شهر برمودة  المبارك</Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Today is the thirtieth day of the blessed month of Parmoute. May God end it in goodness and renew it for us in peace and tranquility, while our sins and iniquities are forgiven through the tender mercies of our Lord, O my fathers and my brethren. Amen.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اليوم الثلاثون من شهر برمودة  المبارك، أحسن الله إنقضاؤه، وأعاده علينا وعليكم ونحن وأنتم ?ي هدوء واطمئنان، مغ?وري الخطايا والاثام والزلات، من قبل مراحم الرب يا ابائي وإخوتي. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">The Martyrdom of the Great Saint Mark, the Apostle, the Evangelist of the Land of Egypt</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">أستشهاد القديس مار مرقس الرسول الإنجيلي كاروز الديار المصرية</Language>         </Title>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day of the year 68 A.D. the great saint Mari Marcus (Mark), the evangelist and one of the seventy apostles, was martyred.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?ى مثل هذا اليوم من سنة 68 م أستشهد القديس العظيم مار مرقس الإنجيلي أحد السبعين رسولاً.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               He was Jewish in faith of the tribe of Levi. His name was John, whose surname (Roman name) was Mark . He was born in Cyrene one of the five Western cities, Pentapolis, in Libya. His father’s name was Aristopolus a cousin of St. Peter’s wife, his mother’s name was Mary. She was one of the Mary’s who followed the Lord Christ. She was the sister of St. Barnabas. St. Mark was also related to St. Thomas the apostle.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كان هذا القديس يهوديـا من سبط لاوي ودعي بإسم يوحنا وإسمه الروماني مرقس (1). و?لد ?ي درنابوليس إحدي الخمس مدن الغربية بليبيا. وكـان والده أرسطوبولس هو أبن عم او ابن عمة زوجة بطرس الرسول ، وأمه مريم هي إحدي المريمات اللاتي تبعن السيد المسيح ، وهي أخت برنابا الرسول. ويمت القديس مرقس أيضاً  بصلة قرابة للقديس توما الرسول.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The barbarian tribes in North Africa attacked the properties of his family in his native land Libya and plunder it. The family was forced to immigrate to Palestine. His house was the first Christian church, where the Lord met with His disciples. St. Mark was the man who was carrying pitcher of water, where the Lord Christ prepared and made ready for the Passover in the upper room of his house. After the Resurrection of the Lord Christ, He appeared to His disciples and to St. Thomas in its upper room where also the Holy Spirit came upon them. St. Peter came to his house after the angel of the Lord had delivered him from prison.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هجمت القبائل الهمجية علي أملاك أسرته ?ي موطنه بليبيا ونهبته ?اضطرت الاسرة للهجرة إلي ?لسطين. وكان بيت مار مرقس هو المكان الذي يجتمع ?يه الرب مع تلاميذه (أع 1 : 13 ، 14)، و?يه حل الروح القدس يوم الخمسين (أع 2 :1 - 4)، واليه لجأ القديس بطرس بعد أن أخرجه الملاك من السجن (أع 12 : 12) ومرقس هو الرجل حامل جرة الماء حيث أعد السيد المسيح ال?صح ?ي علية بيته (مر 14 : 13 - 15).            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The first one St. Mark attracted to the faith was his father Aristopolus. Once they were walking near the Jordan River, they encountered a raving lion. When the father wanted to save his son by escaping, Mark told him; "Christ, in whose hands our lives are committed, will not let it harm us." Saying this, he prayed, made the sign of the cross and immediately the lion fell dead and split open. His father marveled and believed in the Lord Christ at the hands of his son who baptized him. The symbol of St. Mark is the lion because of this miracle and also because the beginning of his Gospel; “The voice of one crying in the wilderness .?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وكـان أول شخص أجتذبه القديس مرقس الي الإيمان هو أبوه أرسطوبولس حيث كانا سائرين ?ي طريقهما إلي الاردن ?لاقاهما أسد م?ترس، ولما أراد الاب أن ينقذ ابنه بالهروب ، قال القديس مرقس لأبيه: "إن السيد المسيح الذي بيده نسمة كل منا سو? لا يدعه يؤذينا ، ثم صلي ورشم عليه علامة الصليب ?انشق الوحش ومات ، ?أمن أرسطوبولس بالمسيح. وأصبح شعار مرقس الرسول هو الأسد بسبب هذه الحادثة وأيضاً لأن بداية إنجيله "صوت صارخ ?ي البرية ".            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               In about the year 45 A.D., Mark accompanied Paul and Barnabas on their firs missionary journey. He preached with them in Antioch, Seleucia, Cyprus, Salamis, and Perga Pamphylia where he left them and returned to Jerusalem which troubled St. Paul’s heart. He refused to take Mark with him on his second missionary journey which led to a contention between Paul and Barnabas that they parted from one another. Paul took Silas with him, and Barnabas took Mark and sailed to Cyprus . However later on St. Paul recognized the importance of St. Mark for the ministry. He called Mark to serve along with him in Colossi. It is also well known that St. Mark participated with Paul in establishing the Church of Rome. The people of Venice and L’Aquila in Italy claimed also that St. Mark had preached them. However his main areas of proclaiming the gospel were in Alexandria and the five western cities. The See of St. Mark was expanded after his martyrdom to Nubia, Sudan and Ethiopia.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وحوالي سنة 45م صاحب مرقس بولس وبرنابا ?ي رحلتهما الأولي وبشر معهما ?ي سلوكية (2) وقبرص ، وذهب معهما حتي برجة بم?يلية ثم ?ارقهما ورجع إلي أورشليم (3)  مما أحزن قـلب القديس بولس ?ر?ض أن يأخذ معه مرقس ?ي رحلته التبشيرية الثانية ، وبسبب هذا حدثت مشاجرة بين بولس وبرنابا حتي ?ارق احدهما الاخر، ?أخذ بولس معه سيلا ، أما برنابا ?أخذ معه مرقس ابن اخته وذهب إلي قبرص (4). علي أن القديس بولس عاد ?عر? أهمية مرقس للخدمة ?استدعاه للخدمة ?ي كولوسي. ومن المعرو? أن القديس مرقس اشترك مع القديس بولس ?ي تأسيس كنيسة روما ، كما أن أهل البندقية وأكويلا بإيطاليا يقولون أيضاً أنه بشرهم ، ولكن كرازته الأساسية كانت ?ي الإسكندرية والخمس مدن الغربية ، وقد إمتد كرازة مار مرقس بعد أستشهاده إلي النوبة والسودان وأثيوبيا.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Mark arrived to Alexandria about the year 60 or 61 A. D.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وصل القديس مرقس إلي الإسكندرية سنة 60م أو 61م.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               And when he entered the city, his sandal was torn because of the long distance that he had to walk. He went to a cobbler called Anianus to repair it. While he was repairing it the awl pierced his finger. Anianus shouted in Greek saying "EIS THEOS" which means "O, ONE GOD". When St. Mark heard these words his heart rejoiced exceedingly. He found it suitable to talk to him about the One God. The Apostle took some clay, spat on it and applied it to Anianus' finger, saying in the Name of Jesus Christ the Son of God, and the wound healed immediately, as if nothing had happened to it.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما دخل اليها تمزق حذاءه من كثرة المشي. ?مال إلي إنيانوس الإسكا?ي الذي أخذ ?ي إصلاح الحذاء ?دخل المخراز ?ي يده ، ?صرخ قائلآ: ......."أيس ثيـئوس" أي "يا الله الواحد" ?ت?ل القديس مرقس علي الأرض وصنع طيناً وطلي الإصبع ?التأم الجرح ?ي الحال.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Anianus was exceedingly amazed from this miracle that happened in the Name of Jesus Christ. St. Mark started explaining to him about the Lord Christ, the salvation that He fulfilled on the cross, and His life giving Resurrection. Anianus and his entire household believed and St. Mark baptized them.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وبدأ يحدثه عن السيد المسيح والخلاص الذي صنعه علي الصليب والقيامة المحيية ، حتي آمن إنيانوس وكل بيته ، ?عمّدهم القديس مرقس.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Mark used his house as a place of evangelism and meeting with the believers. After many had believed Mari Marcus established the theological school and entrusted its management to St. Justus who became later on the 6th Patriarch of Alexandria. St. Mark put down for the church the liturgy that is known now by the Liturgy of St. Cyril.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               واتخذ من بيت إنيانوس مكاناً يجتمع ?يه للخدمة والتبشير. وبعد أن آمن كثيرون بالمسيحية أسس مار مرقس المدرسة اللاهوتية وعهد بإدارتها إلي القديس يسطس ، الذي صار ?يما بعد البطريرك السادس للإسكندرية. ثم وضع القديس مرقس القداس المعرو? الآن بالقداس الكيرلسي.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               When the number of believers increased and the church in Alexandria flourished the heathen people of the city were raged with anger and thought of slaying St. Mark. The faithful advised him to get away for a short while. St. Mark ordained St. Anianus a Bishop for Alexandria, about the year 62 A.D., along with three priests and seven deacons.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ولما ازدهرت الكنيسة بالإسكندرية ، اغتاظ الوثنيون و?كروا ?ي قتله ?نصحه المؤمنون أن يبتعد قليلاً ، ?رسم إنيانوس اسق?ـا علي الإسكندرية حوالي ٦٣ م ومعه ثلاثة من الكهنة وسبعة من الشمامسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               St. Mark went to the Five Western Cities, remained there for two years preaching, and then went to Rome and witnessed the martyrdom of the Sts. Peter and Paul in the year 67 A.D. Then he returned to Alexandria where he found the believers had increased in number, and he built a church for them in the place known as Bokalia (The place of cows), east of Alexandria on the sea shore. He persevered in his pastoral care and evangelism.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم ذهب مار مرقس إلي الخمس مدن الغربية من سنة 63م إلي سنة 65م. وبعد ذلك ذهب إلي روما وحضر أستشهاد القديسين بطرس وبولس سنة 67م. وبعد ذلك رجع إلي الإسكندرية وعك? علي الرعاية والكرازة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the 29th day of Parmoute, year 68 A.D. the Christians were celebrating the feast of Resurrection, the same day coincided with the feast of the pagan god Syrabis. A multitude of the pagans attacked the church at Bokalia. They seized St. Mark, bound him with a thick rope and dragged him while shouting, "Drag the dragon in the place of Cows." After they had cruelly dragged him, his flesh was torn and the streets of the city were covered with his blood, they threw him into a dark prison. The angel of the Lord appeared to him, in the middle of the night, healed and strengthened him, and then the Lord Christ appeared to St. Mark to console him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي اليوم التاسع والعشرين من برمودة سنة 68م، كان المسيحيون يحت?لون بعيد القيامة المجيد ?ي كنيسة بوكاليا، وقد كان عيد الإله سيرابيس ?ي ن?س اليوم ، ?هجم الوثنيون علي الكنيسة وقبضوا علي القديس مرقس وجروه وهم يصيحون: "جروا التنين ?ي دار البقر". وبعد أن جروه وسحلوه ?ي شوارع الأسكندرية وضعوه ?ي سجن مظلم.  و?ي نص? الليل ظهر له ملاك الرب وش?اه وقواه ، ثم ظهر له الرب المخلص وعزاه.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               On the next morning, the 30th day of Parmoute, the pagans dragged him again through the streets of Alexandria. Finally, St. Mark delivered up his pure soul and received the crown of martyrdom.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?ي صباح يوم الثلاثين من برمودة ، جروه أيضاً  ?ي شوارع الإسكندرية ?تهرأ لحمه وسال دمه ونال بهذا إكليل الشهادة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Nevertheless, St. Mark's death did not satisfy the rage of the pagans and their hatred. They tried to burn his body however a severe storm blew and heavy rains fell which extinguished the fire. The pagans were frightened and fled away.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم ?كروا ?ي حرق الجسد الطاهر ?هبت عاص?ة مصحوبة بمطر غزير ، ?إنط?أت النيران وت?رق الشعب.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The believers came and took his pure body. St Anianus, the clergy and people prayed over him, then buried him in the church with great veneration.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?أخذ المؤمنون جسده الطاهر ، وصلي عليه القديس إنيانوس والكهنة والشعب ود?نوه ?ي الكنيسة بإكرام عظيم.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               The blessing of his prayers be with us all and glory be to our God for ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بركة صلوات القديس مارمرقس الرسول كاروز الديار المصرية ?لتكن معنا. ولإلهنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season></Document>