<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 109 - The Lord said to my Lord...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 109 - Demikianlah firman TUHAN kepada tuanku:          </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والتاسعُ - قالَ الربُّ لربِّي...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            The Lord said to my Lord, “Sit on My right hand, until I place Your enemies under Your feet.” A rod of power, the Lord shall send out for You out of Zion, and You shall rule in the midst of Your enemies. With You is dominion in the day of Your power, in the splendor of the saints. From the womb before the morning star I have begotten You.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Demikianlah firman TUHAN kepada tuanku: "“Duduklah di sebelah kanan-Ku, sampai Kubuat musuh-musuhmu menjadi tumpuan kakimu.”</div><div>Tongkat kekuatanmu akan diulurkan TUHAN dari Sion: memerintahlah di antara musuhmu! Pada hari tentaramu bangsamu merelakan diri untuk maju dengan berhiaskan kekudusan; dari kandungan fajar tampil bagimu keremajaanmu seperti embun.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            قالَ الربُّ لربِّي: اجلسْ عن يميني حتَّى أضعَ أعداءَكَ تحتَ موطِئِ قدمَيكَ. عصا قوةٍ يُرسِلُ لكَ الربُّ مِنْ صِهيَونَ وتسودُ في وسَطِ أعدائِكَ. معَكَ الرياسةُ في يومِ قُوتِكَ، في بهاءِ القدِّيسينَ. مِنَ البطنِ قبلَ كَوكبِ الصُبحِ ولدتُكَ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            The Lord has sworn and shall not repent: “You are the Priest forever, after the order of Melchizedek.” The Lord is at Your right hand; He shall dash kings in the day of His wrath. He shall judge among the nations. He shall fill them with dead bodies; He shall crush the heads of many on the earth. He shall drink of the brook in the way; therefore He shall lift up the head. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            TUHAN telah bersumpah, dan Ia tidak akan menyesal: "“Engkau adalah imam untuk selama-lamanya, menurut Melkisedek.” TUHAN ada di sebelah kananmu; Ia meremukkan raja-raja pada hari murka-Nya, Ia menghukum bangsa-bangsa, sehingga mayat-mayat bergelimpangan; Ia meremukkan orang-orang yang menjadi kepala di negeri luas. Dari sungaisungai di tepi jalan ia minum, oleh sebab itu ia mengangkat kepala.  ALLELUIA.!         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أقسمَ الربُّ ولن يندمَ أنَّكَ أنتَ هو الكاهِنُ إلى الأبدِ على طقسِ ملكِيصادَقَ. الربُّ عن يمينِكَ، يُحطِّمُ في يومِ رِجزِهِ مُلوكاً، يقضي بينَ الأممِ ويملأُهُم جُثثاً، يسحقُ رؤوسَ كثيرينَ على الأرضِ. وفي الطريقِ يشربُ الماءَ مِنَ الوادي. لذلكَ يرفعُ رأسَهُ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>