<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 110 - I will give thanks to You...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 110 - Aku mau bersyukur kepada TUHAN          </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والعاشرُ - أعترِفُ لكَ ياربُّ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            I will give thanks to You, O Lord, with my whole heart, in the council of the upright, and in their congregation. Great are the works of the Lord; examined are all His wills. Majesty and splendor are His works, and His righteousness endures forever and ever. He has made a remembrance of all His wonders; the Lord is merciful and compassionate. He has given food to those who fear Him; He shall remember His covenant forever. He has declared to His people the power of His works, to give them the inheritance of nations.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Aku mau bersyukur kepada TUHAN dengan segenap hati, dalam lingkungan orang-orang benar dan dalam jemaahjemaah.</div><div>Besar perbuatan-perbuatan TUHAN, layak diselidiki oleh semua orang yang menyukainya. Agung dan bersema rak pekerjaan-Nya, dan keadilan-Nya tetap untuk selamanya.</div><div>Perbuatan-perbuatan-Nya yang ajaibajaib dijadikan-Nya peringatan; TUHAN itu pengasih dan penyayang. Diberikan-Nya rezeki kepada orang-orang yang takut akan Dia.</div><div>Ia ingat untuk selama-lamanya akan perjanjian-Nya. Kekuatan perbuatan-Nya diberitakan-Nya kepada umat-Nya, dengan memberikan kepada mereka milik pusaka bangsa-bangsa.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أعترِفُ لكَ ياربُّ مِنْ كلِّ قلبي. في مجلِسِ المُستقيمينَ وفي مجمعِهِم. عظيمةٌ هي أعمالُ الربِّ، ومشيئاتُهُ كلُّها مفحوصةٌ، جلالٌ وبهاءٌ عملُهُ، وعدلُهُ دائِمٌ إلى أبدِ الأبدِ. صنعَ ذِكراً لجميعِ عجائبِهِ. رحيمٌ هو الربُّ ورؤوفٌ، أعطى طعامَهُ لأتقيائِهِ، يذكُرُ إلى الدهرِ ميثاقَهُ. خبَّرَ شعبَهُ بقوةِ أعمالِهِ، ليُعطيَهُم ميراثَ الأممِ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            The works of His hands are truth and justice; all His commandments are faithful, established forever and ever, made in truth and uprightness. He sent redemption to His people; He commanded His covenant forever; holy and fearful is His name. The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom, and understanding is good to all who do according to it. His praise endures forever and ever. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div><br/></div><div>Perbuatan tangan-Nya ialah kebenaran dan keadilan, segala titah-Nya teguh, kokoh untuk seterusnya dan selamanya, dilakukan dalam kebenaran dan kejujuran. Dikirim-Nya kebebasan kepada umat-Nya, diperintahkan-Nya supaya perjanjian-Nya itu untuk selama-lamanya; nama-Nya kudus dan dahsyat.</div><div>Permulaan hikmat adalah takut akan TUHAN, semua orang yang melakukannya berakal budi yang baik. Puji-pujian kepada-Nya tetap untuk selamanya. ALLELUIA.!</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أعمالُ يدَيهِ حقٌ وعدلٌ. كلُّ وصاياهُ صادِقةٌ، ثابِتةٌ إلى دهرِ الدهورِ، مصنوعةٌ بالحقِّ والاستِقامةِ. أرسلَ خلاصاً لشعبِهِ، أمرَ بعهدِهِ إلى الأبدِ. اسمُهُ قُدُّوسٌ ومرهوبٌ. رأسُ الحكمةِ مخافةُ الربِّ، والفهمُ صالِحٌ لكلِّ مَنْ يعملُ بهِ، وتسبِحتُهُ دائِمةٌ إلى الأبدِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>