<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 111 - Blessed is the man...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 111 - Berbahagialah orang yang takut akan TUHAN         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والحاديَ عشرَ - طوبى للرجلِ الخائفِ الربَّ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Blessed is the man who fears the Lord, and delights greatly in His commandments. His seed shall be mighty in the earth; the generation of the upright shall be blessed. Glory and riches shall be in His house, and His righteousness endures forever. To the upright, light has sprung up in the darkness. The Lord God is compassionate, merciful, and righteous.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Berbahagialah orang yang takut akan TUHAN, yang sangat suka kepada segala perintah-Nya. Anak cucunya akan perkasa di bumi; angkatanangkatan  orang benar akan diberkati. Harta dan kekayaan ada dalam rumahnya, kebajikannya tetap untuk selamanya. Di dalam gelap terbit terang bagi orang benar; pengasih dan penyayang orang yang adil.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            طوبى للرجلِ الخائفِ الربَّ ويَهوى وصاياهُ جداً. يقوى نسلُهُ على الأرضِ. جيلُ المُستقيمينَ يُبارَكُ. مجدٌ وغِنىً في بيتهِ، وبرُّهُ يدومُ إلى الأبدِ. نورٌ أشرقَ في الظُلمةِ للمُستقيمينَ. رحيمٌ هو الربُّ الإلهُ ورؤوفٌ وبارٌ.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            A good man is he who pities and lends; he shall direct his words with truth. For he shall not be moved forever. The righteous shall be in everlasting remembrance. He shall not be afraid of any evil tidings; his heart is ready trusting the Lord. His heart is established, he shall not move, till he shall look upon his enemies. He has dispersed abroad; he has given to the poor; his righteousness endures forever and ever: his horn shall be exalted with honor. The sinner shall see and be angry, he shall gnash his teeth, and consume away; the desire of the sinner shall perish. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mujur orang yang menaruh belas kasihan dan yang memberi pinjaman, yang melakukan urusannya dengan sewajarnya. Sebab ia takkan goyah untuk selama-lamanya; orang benar itu akan diingat selama-lamanya. Ia tidak takut kepada kabar celaka, hatinya tetap, penuh kepercayaan kepada TUHAN. Hatinya teguh, ia tidak takut, sehinggaia memandang rendah para lawannya. Ia membagi-bagikan, ia memberikan kepada orang miskin; kebajikannya tetap untuk selama-lamanya, tanduknya meninggi dalam kemuliaan. Orang fasik melihatnya, lalu sakit hati, ia menggertakkan giginya, lalu hancur; keinginan orang fasik akan menuju kebinasaan. ALLELUIA.!</language>         <language id="Arabic">            صالِحٌ هو الرجلُ الذي يتراءفُ ويُقرِضُ ويُدبِّرُ أقوالَهُ بالحقِّ، لأنَّهُ لا يتزعزعُ إلى الدهرِ. ذِكرُ الصدِّيقِ يدومُ إلى الأبدِ، ولا يخشى مِنْ خبرِ السوءِ. قلبُهُ مُستعِدٌ مُتكِلٌ على الربِّ. قلبُهُ ثابِتٌ لا يتزعزعُ حتى يرى بأعدائِهِ. فرَّقَ وأعطى المساكينَ. برُّهُ دائمٌ إلى دهرِ الدهورِ. يرتفعُ قرنُهُ بالمجدِ. الخاطئُ يُبصِرُ فيغتاظُ ويَصِرُّ بأسنانِهِ ويذوبُ، شهوةُ الخاطئِ تَبيدُ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>