<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 115 - I believed, therefore, I have spoken...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 115 - Aku percaya, sekalipun aku berkata         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والخامسَ عشرَ - آمنتُ لذلِكَ تكلَّمتُ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            I believed, therefore, I have spoken; I was exceedingly humbled. I said in my amazement, “Every man is a liar.” What shall I render to the Lord for everything which He has done unto me? I shall take the cup of salvation, and call upon the name of the Lord. I will pay my vows to the Lord, in the presence of all His people.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Aku percaya, sekalipun aku berkata:"”Aku ini sangat tertindas.” Aku ini berkata dalam kebingunganku:"”Semua manusia pembohong.”</div><div>Bagaimana akan kubalas kepada TUHAN segala kebajikan-Nya kepadaku? Aku akan mengangkat piala keselamatan, dan akan menyerukan nama TUHAN, akan membayar nazarku kepada TUHAN di depan seluruh umat-Nya.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            آمنتُ لذلِكَ تكلَّمتُ. وأنا اتَّضعتُ جِداً. أنا قُلتُ في حَيرَتي: إنَّ كلَّ الناسِ كاذِبونَ. بماذا أُكافئُ الربَّ عن كلِّ ما أعطانِيهِ؟ كأسَ الخلاصِ آخذُ وباسمِ الربِّ أدعو. أُوفي نُذوري للربِّ قُدامَ كلِّ شعبِهِ.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            Precious in the sight of the Lord is the death of His saints. O Lord, I am Your servant; I am Your servant, and the son of Your handmaid. You have broken my bonds; I will sacrifice to You the sacrifice of praise, and will call upon the name of the Lord. I will pay my vows to the Lord in the presence of all His people, in the courts of the Lord's house, in the midst of Jerusalem. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berharga di mata TUHAN kematian semua orang yang dikasihi-Nya. Ya TUHAN, aku hamba-Mu! Aku hamba-Mu, anak dari hamba-Mu perempuanperempuan! </div><div>Engkau telah membuka ikatan-ikatanku! </div><div>Aku akan mempersembahkan korban syukursyukur kepada-Mu, dan akan menyerukan nama TUHAN, akan membayar nazarku kepada TUHAN di depan seluruh umat-Nya, di pelataran rumah TUHAN, di tengahtengah-tengahmu, ya Yerusalem! ALLELUIA.!</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            كريمٌ أمامَ الربِّ موتُ قدِّيسيهِ. ياربُّ أنا عبدُكَ، أنا عبدُكَ وابنُ أمتِكَ. قطّعتَ قُيودي. فلكَ أذبحُ ذبيحةَ التسبيحِ، وباسمِ الربِّ أدعو. أُوفي للربِّ نُذوري في ديارِ بيتِ الربِّ، قُدَّامَ كلِّ شعبِهِ، في وسطِ أورُشَلِيمَ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>