<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 117 - Give thanks to the Lord...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 117 - Bersyukurlah kepada TUHAN         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والسابعَ عشرَ - اعترِفوا للربِّ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Give thanks to the Lord; for He is good, for His mercy endures forever. Let now the house of Israel say that He is good, for His mercy endures forever. Let the house of Aaron say that He is good, for His mercy endures forever. Let now all who fear the Lord say that He is good, for His mercy endures forever.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bersyukurlah kepada TUHAN, sebab Ia baik! Bahwasanya untuk selama-lamanya kasih setia-Nya. Biarlah Israel berkata: "Bahwasanya untuk selama-lamanya kasih setia-Nya!” . Biarlah kaum Harun berkata: "Bahwasanya untuk selama-lamanya kasih setia-Nya!” </div><div>Biarlah orang yang takut akan TUHAN berkata:"Bahwasanya untuk selama-lamanyakasih setia-Nya!</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            اعترِفوا للربِّ لأنَّهُ صالِحٌ وأنَّ إلى الأبدِ رحمتَهُ. ليقُلْ بيتُ إسرائيلَ إنَّهُ صالِحٌ وإنَّ إلى الأبدِ رحمتَهُ. ليقُلْ بيتُ هارونَ إنَّهُ صالِحٌ وإنَّ إلى الأبدِ رحمتَهُ. ليقُلْ أتقياءُ الربِّ إنَّهُ صالِحٌ وإنَّ إلى الأبدِ رحمتَهُ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            I called on the Lord in my affliction, and He answered me, and brought me into a broad place. The Lord is my helper, and I shall not fear what man will do to me. The Lord is my helper, and I shall look down upon my own enemies. It is better to trust in the Lord than to trust in man. It is better to hope in the Lord, than to hope in princes.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>” Dalam kesesakan aku  telah berseru kepada TUHAN. TUHAN telah menjawab aku dengan memberi kelegaan. TUHAN di pihakku.</div><div>Aku tidak akan takut. Apakah yang dapat dilakukan manusia terhadapaku? TUHAN di pihakku, menolong aku; aku akan memandang rendah mereka yang membenci aku. Lebih baik berlindung pada TUHAN dari pada percaya kepada manusia. Lebih baik berlindung pada TUHAN dari pada percaya kepada para bangsawan.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            في ضيقتي صرختُ إلى الربِّ، فاستجابَ لي وأخرجَني إلى الرُّحبِ. الربُّ عوني فلا أخشى ماذا يصنعُ بي الإنسانُ. الربُّ لي مُعينٌ وأنا أرى بأعدائي. الاتكالُ على الربِّ خيرٌ مِنَ الاتكالِ على البشرِ، الرجاءُ بالربِّ خيرٌ مِنَ الرجاءِ بالرؤساءِ.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            All the nations surrounded me, and in the name of the Lord I drove them away. They surrounded me and went around me, and in the name of the Lord I drove them away. They surrounded me as bees around a honeycomb, and they burst as fire among thorns, and in the name of the Lord I drove them away. I was pushed, that I might fall, but the Lord helped me. My strength and my praise is the Lord, and He has become unto me a salvation.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Segala bangsa mengelilingi aku—demi nama TUHAN, sesungguhnya aku pukul mereka mundur. Mereka mengelilingi aku, ya mengelilingi aku—demi nama TUHAN, sesungguhnya aku pukul mereka mundur.</span></div><div>Mereka mengelilingi aku seperti lebah, mereka menyala-nyala seperti api duri,--demi nama TUHAN, sesungguhnya aku pukul mereka mundur. Aku ditolak dengan hebat sampai jatuh, tetapi TUHAN menolong aku. TUHAN itu kekuatanku dan mazmurku; Ia telah menjadi keselamatanku.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            كلُّ الأممِ أحاطوا بي وباسمِ الربِّ انتقمتُ مِنْهُم. أحاطوا بي احتياطاً واكتنَفوني، وباسمِ الربِّ قهرتُهُم. أحاطوا بي مِثلَ النحلِ حولَ الشهدِ، والتهبوا كنارٍ في شوكٍ، وباسمِ الربِّ انتقمتُ مِنْهُم. دُفِعتُ لأسقُطَ والربُّ عضَدَني. قوَّتي وتسبِحتي هو الربُّ وقد صارَ لي خلاصاً.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            The voice of exultation and salvation is in the dwellings of the righteous; the right hand of the Lord has wrought mightily. The right hand of the Lord has exalted me; the right hand of the Lord has wrought powerfully. I shall not die, but live, and recount the works of the Lord. With chastisement the Lord has chastened me, and has not given me up to death.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div> Suara sorak-soraidan kemenangan di kemah orang-orang benar:" </div><div>Tangan kanan TUHAN  melakukan keperkasaan, tangan kanan TUHAN berkuasa meninggikan, tangan kanan TUHAN melakukan keperkasaan!” Aku tidak akan mati, tetapi hidup, dan aku akan menceritakan perbuatan-perbuatan TUHAN.</div><div>TUHAN telah menghajaraku dengan keras, tetapi Ia tidak menyerahkan aku kepada maut</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            صوتُ التهليلِ والخلاصِ في مساكِنِ الأبرارِ. يمينُ الربِّ صنعَتْ قوةً، يمينُ الربِّ رفعَتني، يمينُ الربِّ صنعَتْ قوةً. فلن أموتَ بعدُ، بلْ أحيا وأحدِّثُ بأعمالِ الربِّ. تأديباً أدَّبني الربُّ وإلى الموتِ لمْ يُسْلِمْني.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            Open to me the gates of righteousness, that I will go into them, and praise the Lord. This is the gate of the Lord; the righteous shall enter into it. I will praise You, O Lord, because You have answered me, and have become unto me a salvation. The stone which the builders rejected has become the head of the corner. This has been done by the Lord, and it is wonderful in our eyes.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bukakanlah aku pintu gerbang  kebenaran, aku hendak masuk kedalamnya, hendak mengucap syukur kepada TUHAN.</div><div>Inilah pintu gerbang TUHAN,  orang-orang benarakan masuk ke dalamnya. Aku bersyukur kepada-Mu, sebab Engkau telah menjawab aku dan telah menjadi keselamatanku. Batu yang dibuang oleh tukang-tukang bangunan telah menjadi batu penjuru.</div><div>Hal itu terjadi dari pihak TUHAN, suatu perbuatan ajaib di mata kita.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            افتحوا لي أبوابَ البرِّ لكي أدخُلَ فيها وأعترِفَ للربِّ. هذا هو بابُ الربِّ والصدِّيقونَ يدخلونَ فيهِ. أعترِفُ لكَ ياربُّ لأنَّكَ استجبتَ لي وكُنتَ لي مُخلِّصاً. الحجرُ الذي رذلَهُ البنَّاءونَ هذا صارَ رأساً للزاويةِ. مِنْ قِبَلِ الربِّ كانَ هذا وهو عجيبٌ في أعيُنِنا.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            This is the day which the Lord has made; let us rejoice and be glad in it. O Lord, save us; O Lord, ease our ways. Blessed is He who comes in the name of the Lord; we have blessed you from the house of the Lord. God the Lord has shined upon us; ordain a feast with those that reach the horns of the altar. You are my God, and I will give thanks to You; You are my God, and I will exalt You. I will give thanks to You, O Lord, for You have heard me, and have become unto me a salvation. Give thanks to the Lord for He is good, for His mercy endures forever. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Inilah hari yang dijadikan TUHAN, marilah kita bersorak-sorak dan bersukacita karenanya! Ya TUHAN, berilah kiranya keselamatan!</div><div>Ya TUHAN, berilah kiranya kemujuran! Diberkatilah dia yang dating dalam nama TUHAN!  Kami memberkati kamu dari dalam rumah TUHAN.</div><div>Tuhanlah Allah, Dia menerangi kita. Ikatkanlah korban hari raya itu dengan tali, pada tanduk-tanduk mezbah. Allahku Engkau, aku hendak bersyukur kepada-Mu, Allahku, aku hendak meninggikan Engkau. Bersyukurlah kepada TUHAN, sebab Ia baik! Bahwasanya untuk selama-lamanya kasih setia-Nya. ALLELUIA.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            هذا هو اليومُ الذي صنعَهُ الربُّ. فلنبتهِجْ ونفرحْ فيهِ. ياربُّ خلِّصْنا. ياربُّ سهِّلْ طريقَنا. مباركٌ الآتي باسمِ الربِّ. بارَكناكُم مِنْ بيتِ الربِّ. اللهُ الربُّ أضاءَ علَينا. رتِّبوا عيداً في الواصِلينَ إلى قُرونِ المذبحِ. أنتَ هو إلهي فأشكرُكَ، إلهي أنتَ فأرفعُكَ. أعترِفُ لكَ ياربُّ، لأنَّكَ استجبتَ لي وصِرتَ لي مُخلِّصاً. اشكُروا الربَّ فإنَّهُ صالِحٌ وأنَّ إلى الأبدِ رحمتَهُ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>