<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 119 -  In my own affliction...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 119 -  Dalam kesesakanku ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والتاسعَ عشرَ - إليكَ ياربُّ صرختُ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            In my own affliction I cried to You, O Lord, and You heard me. O Lord, You shall deliver my soul from unjust lips, and from a deceitful tongue. What should be given to you, and what should be added to you, O crafty tongue?! The weapons of the mighty are sharpened with coals of the desert! Woe to me, that my sojourning is prolonged; I have lived among the dwellings of Kedar. My soul has long been a sojourner; I was peaceable among those who hated peace; when I spoke to them, they warred against me without a cause. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dalam kesesakanku aku berseru kepada TUHAN dan Ia menjawab aku: "Ya TUHAN, lepaskanlah aku dari pada bibir dusta, dari pada lidah penipu.” </div><div>Apakah yang diberikan kepadamu dan apakah yang ditambahkan kepadamu, hai lidah penipu? Panah-panah yang tajam dari pahlawan dan bara kayu arar.</div><div>Celakalah aku, karena harus tinggal sebagai orang asing di Mesekh, karena harus diam di antara kemah-kemah Kedar! Cukup lama aku tinggal bersama-sama dengan orang-orang yang membenci perdamaian. Aku ini suka perdamaian, tetapi apabila aku berbicara, maka mereka menghendaki perang. ALLELUIA.!</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            إليكَ ياربُّ صرختُ في حُزني فاستجبتَ لي. ياربُّ نجِّ نفسي مِنَ الشفاهِ الظالِمةِ ومِنَ اللسانِ الغاشِّ. ماذا تُعطَى وماذا تُزادُ مِنَ اللسانِ الغاشِّ. سِهامُ الأقوياءِ مُرهَفةٌ معَ جمرِ البرِّيةِ. ويلٌ لي فإنَّ غُربَتي قد طالتْ عليَّ، وسكنتُ في مساكِنِ قيدارَ. طويلاً سكنَتْ نفسي في الغُربةِ، ومعَ مُبغِضي السلامِ كُنتُ صاحِبَ سلامٍ، وحينَ كُنتُ أكلمُهُم كانوا يقاتِلونني باطِلاً. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>