<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 121 - I was glad for those...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 121 - Aku bersukacita, ketika dikatakan orang ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والحادي والعشرونَ - فرِحتُ بالقائلينَ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            I was glad for those who said to me, “We will go into the house of the Lord.” Our feet stood in the courts of Jerusalem, Jerusalem which is built as a city that is closely compacted together. For there the tribes went up, the tribes of the Lord, as a testimony for Israel, to give thanks to the name of the Lord. For there are set thrones for judgment, even thrones for the house of David.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Aku bersukacita, ketika dikatakan orang kepadaku: "Mari kita pergi ke rumah TUHAN.” Sekarang kaki kami berdiri di pintu gerbangmu, hai Yerusalem. Hai Yerusalem, yang telah didirikan sebagai kota yang bersambung rapat, ke mana suku-suku berziarah, yakni suku-suku TUHAN, untuk bersyukur kepada nama TUHAN sesuai dengan peraturan bagi Israel.</div><div>Sebab di sanalah ditaruh kursi-kursi pengadilan, kursi-kursi milik keluarga raja Daud.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            فرِحتُ بالقائلينَ لي إلى بيتِ الربِّ نذهبُ. وقفَت أرجُلُنا في ديارِ أورُشَليمَ، أورُشَليمُ المبنيَّةُ مِثلُ مدينةٍ مُتَّصِلةٍ بعضِها ببعضٍ. لأنَّ هُناكَ صعِدَتْ القبائلُ، قبائلُ الربِّ، شهادةً لإسرائيلَ، يعترِفونَ لاسمِ الربِّ. هُناكَ نُصِبَتْ كراسيُّ للقضاءِ، كراسيُّ بيتِ داودَ.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            Ask for the things which are for the peace of Jerusalem, and for the prosperity to those who love you. Let peace be within your strength, and prosperity in your heavy towers. For the sake of my brethren and my companions, I have indeed spoken peace concerning you. Because of the house of the Lord our God, I have diligently sought good things for you. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div> Berdoalah untuk kesejahteraan Yerusalem: "Biarlah orang-orang yang mencintaimu mendapat sentosa.</div><div>Biarlah kesejahteraan ada di lingkungan tembokmu, dan sentosa di dalam purimu!” Oleh karena saudara-saudaraku dan teman- temanku aku hendak mengucapkan:"Semoga kesejahteraan ada di dalammu!” Oleh karena rumah TUHAN, Allah kita, aku hendak mencari kebaikan bagimu. ALLELUIA.!</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            اسألوا السلامَ لأورُشَليمَ والخِصبَ لمُحبّيكِ. ليكُنْ السلامُ في حِصنِكِ والخِصبُ في أبراجِكِ الرصينةِ. مِنْ أجلِ إخوتي وأقربائي تكلَّمتُ مِنْ أجلِكِ بالسلامِ، ومِنْ أجلِ بيتِ الربِّ إلهِنا التمستُ لكِ الخيراتِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>