<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 122 - Unto You I have lifted...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 122 - Kepada-Mu aku melayangkan ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والثاني والعشرونَ - إليكَ رفعتُ عينيَّ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Unto You I have lifted up my eyes, O You who dwell in heaven. Behold as the eyes of servants are unto to the hands of their masters, and as the eyes of a maidservant to the hands of her mistress; so our eyes are toward the Lord our God until He has pity on us. Have mercy on us, O Lord, have mercy on us, for we are exceedingly filled with contempt, and our soul has been exceedingly filled. Give the reproach to those who prosper, and contempt to the proud. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kepada-Mu aku melayangkan mataku, ya Engkau yang bersemayam di surga. Lihat, seperti mata para hamba laki-laki memandang kepada tangan tuannya, seperti mata hamba perempuan memandang kepada tangan nyonyanya, demikianlah mata kita memandang kepada TUHAN,  Allah kita, sampai Ia mengasihani kita. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Kasihanilah kami, yaTUHAN, kasihanilah kami, sebab kami sudah cukup kenyang dengan penghinaan; jiwa kami sudah cukup kenyang dengan olok-olok orang-orang yang merasa aman, dengan penghinaan orang-orang yang sombong. ALLELUIA.!</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            إليكَ رفعتُ عينيَّ يا ساكِنَ السماءِ. فها هُما مِثلُ عيونِ العبيدِ إلى أيدي مواليهِم، ومِثلُ عينيِّ الأمَةِ إلى يديِّ سيِّدتِها. كذلِكَ أعيُنُنا نحوَ الربِّ إلهِنا حتى يترأفَ علَينا. ارحمْنا ياربُّ ارحمْنا، فإنَّنا كثيراً ما امتلأنا هواناً، وكثيراً ما امتلأتْ نُفوسُنا، العارُ اردُدهُ على المُخصِبينَ والهوانُ على المُتعَّظمينَ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>