<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 125 - When the Lord brought back...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 125 - Ketika TUHAN memulihkan keadaan Sion         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والخامسُ والعشرونَ - إذا ما ردَّ الربُّ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            When the Lord brought back the captivity of Zion, we became as those who were comforted. Then our mouth was filled with joy, and our tongue with exultation. Then they shall say among the Gentiles, “The Lord has done great things among them.” The Lord has done great things for us, we became joyful. O Lord, You shall bring back our captivity, as the streams in the south. Those who sow in tears shall reap in joy. They went on and wept as they were carrying their seeds, but they shall surely come with exultation, carrying their sheaves. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ketika TUHAN memulihkan keadaan Sion, keadaan kita seperti orang-orang yang bermimpi. Pada waktu itu mulut kita penuh dengan tertawa, dan lidah kita dengan sorak-sorai. </div><div>Pada waktu itu berkatalah orang di antara bangsa-bangsa: "TUHAN telah melakukan perkara besar kepada orang-orang ini!” TUHAN telah melakukan perkara besar kepada kita, maka kita bersukacita. Pulihkanlah keadaan kami, yaTUHAN, seperti memulihkan batang air kering di Tanah Negeb!</div><div>Orang-orang yang menabur dengan mencucurkan air mata, akan menuai dengan bersorak-sorai. Orang yang berjalan maju dengan menangis sambil menabur benih, pasti pulang dengan sorak-sorai sambil membawa berkas-berkasnya. ALLELUIA..</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            إذا ما ردَّ الربُّ سبيَ صِهْيَونَ صِرنا فرِحينَ. حينئذٍ امتلأ فمُنا فرَحاً ولِسانُنا تهليلاً. حينئذٍ يُقالُ في الأممِ إنَّ الربَّ قد عظَّمَ الصنيعَ معهُم. عظَّمَ الربُّ الصنيعَ معنا فصِرنا فرِحينَ. اردُدْ ياربُّ سبيَنا مِثلَ السُيولِ في الجنوبِ. الذينَ يزرعونَ بالدُموعِ يحصُدونَ بالابتهاجِ. سَيراً كانوا يسيرونَ وهُم باكونَ حامِلينَ بِذارَهُم، ويعودونَ بالفرحِ حامِلينَ أغمارَهُم. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>