<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 126 - Unless the Lord builds the house...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 126 - Jikalau bukan TUHAN yang membangun rumah...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والسادسُ والعشرونَ - إنْ لمْ يبنِ الربُّ البيتَ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Unless the Lord builds the house, those who build it have labored in vain. Unless the Lord guards the city, the watchmen have watched in vain. It is vain for you to rise early; rise up after your sitting, you who eat the bread of grief, while He gives sleep to His beloved.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Jikalau bukan TUHAN yang membangun rumah, sia-sialah usaha orang yang membangunnya; jikalau bukan TUHAN yang mengawal kota, sia-sialah pengawal berjaga-jaga. Sia-sialah kamu bangun pagi-pagi dan duduk-duduk sampai jauh malam, dan makan roti yang diperoleh dengan susah payah—sebab Ia memberikannya kepada yang dicintai-Nya pada waktu tidur.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            إنْ لمْ يبنِ الربُّ البيتَ فباطِلاً تعِبَ البنَّاءونَ، وإنْ لمْ يحرُسْ الربُّ المدينةَ فباطِلاً سهِرَ الحُرَّاسُ. باطِلٌ هو لكُمْ التبكيرُ. انهَضوا مِنْ بعدِ جُلوسِكُم يا آكلي الخُبزَ بالهُمومِ، فإنَّهُ يمنحُ أحِباءَهُ نَوماً.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Behold, children are the inheritance of the Lord, the reward of the fruit of the womb. As arrows in the hand of a mighty man, so are the children of one's youth. Blessed is the man who has his quiver full of them; they shall not be ashamed when they speak with their enemies in the gates. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Sesungguhnya, anak-anak lelaki adalah milik pusaka dari pada TUHAN, dan buah kandungan adalah suatu upah. Seperti anak- anak panah di tangan pahlawan, demikianlah anak-anak pada masa muda. Berbahagialah orang yang telah membuat penuh tabung panahnya dengan semuanya itu. Ia tidak akan mendapat malu, apabila ia berbicara dengan musuh- musuh di pintu gerbang. ALLELUIA..         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            البنونُ ميراثٌ مِنَ الربِّ أجرةُ ثمرةِ البطنِ. كالسهامِ بيدِ القويِّ كذلِكَ أبناءِ المُتيَّقِظينَ. مغبوطٌ هو الرجلُ الذي يملأُ جَعبتَهُ مِنْهُم. حينئذٍ لا يَخزَونَ إذا كلَّموا أعداءََََهُم في الأبوابِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>