<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 131 - Lord, remember David...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 131 - Ingatlah, ya TUHAN,  kepada Daud ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والحادي والثلاثونَ - اذكُرْ يا ربُّ داودَ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Lord, remember David and all his meekness; how he swore to the Lord, and vowed to the God of Jacob, saying, “I will not go into the dwelling of my house, or go up to the bed of my couch; I will not give sleep to my eyes, nor slumber to my eyelids, nor rest to my temples, until I find a place for the Lord, and a dwelling place for the God of Jacob.” Behold, we heard of it in Ephratha; we found it in the fields of the wood. Let us enter into His dwelling, and worship at the place where His feet stood.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ingatlah, ya TUHAN,  kepada Daud dan segala penderitaannya, bagaimana ia telah bersumpah kepada TUHAN, telah bernazar kepadaYang Mahakuat dari Yakub: "Sesungguhnya aku tidak akan masuk ke dalam kemah kediamanku, tidak akan berbaring di ranjang petiduranku, sesungguhnya aku tidak akan membiarkan mataku tidur atau membiarkan kelopak mataku terlelap, sampai aku mendapat tempat untuk TUHAN, kediaman untuk Yang Mahakuat dari Yakub. ”Memang kita telah mendengar tentang itu di Efrata, telah mendapatnya di padang Yaar.</div><div>"Mari kita pergi ke kediaman-Nya, sujud menyembah pada tumpuan kaki-Nya.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            اذكُرْ يا ربُّ داودَ وكلَّ دِعَتِهِ. كيفَ أقسَمَ للربِّ ونذرَ لإلهِ يعقوبَ: إنِّي لا أدخُلُ إلى مسكنِ بيتي، ولا أصعدُ على سريرِ فِراشي، ولا أُعطي لعَينيَّ نوماً، ولا لأجفاني نُعاساً، ولا راحةً لصِدغَيَّ، إلى أنْ أجدَ موضِعاً للربِّ ومسكناً لإلهِ يعقوبَ. ها قدْ سَمِعنا بهِ في أفراتةَ ووجدناهُ في موضِعِ الغابةِ. فلندخُلْ إلى مساكنِهِ ونسجُدْ في الموضِعِ الذي فيهِ استقرَّتْ قدَماهُ.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            Arise, O Lord, into Your rest, You, and the ark of Your holy place. Your priests shall clothe themselves with righteousness, and Your righteous shall exult. For the sake of Your servant David, do not turn away Your face from Your anointed.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            ” Bangunlah, ya TUHAN, dan pergilah ke tempat perhentian-Mu, Engkau serta tabut kekuatan-Mu! Biarlah imam-imam-Mu berpakaian kebenaran, dan bersorak-sorai orang-orang yang Kaukasihi! Oleh karena Daud, hamba-Mu,  janganlah Engkau menolak orang yang Kauurapi!         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            قُمْ يا ربُّ إلى راحتِكَ أنتَ وتابوتُ موضِعِ قُدسِكَ. كهنتُكَ يلبَسونَ البِرَّ وأبرارُكَ يبتهِجونَ. مِنْ أجلِ داودَ عبدِكَ لا ترُدَّ وجهَكَ عنْ مسيحِكَ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            The Lord has sworn in truth to David, and He will not turn from it, “Of the fruit of your loins I will set upon your throne. If your children keep My covenant and My testimonies which I will teach them, their children also will sit upon your throne forever.”         </language><language id="Indonesian">            TUHAN telah menyatakan sumpah setia kepada Daud, Ia tidak akan memungkirinya: "Seorang anak kandungmu akan Kududukkan di atas takhtamu;  jika anak-anakmu berpegang pada perjanjian-Ku, dan pada peraturan-peraturan-Ku yang Kuajarkan kepada mereka, maka anak-anak mereka selama-lamanya akan duduk di atas takhtamu.”         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            حلفَ الربُّ لداودَ حقاً ولا يخلِفُ: لأجعَلنَّ مِنْ ثمرةِ بطنِكَ على كُرسيِّكَ. إنْ حفِظَ بنوكَ عهْدي وشهاداتي التي أُعلِّمُهُم إيَّاها، فبنوهُم أيضاً يجلِسونَ إلى الأبدِ على كُرسيِِّّكَ.         </language>      </text>            <text>         <language id="English">            For the Lord has selected Zion, He has chosen her a dwelling for Himself. “This is My resting place forever. Here I will dwell; for I have desired it. In blessing I shall bless her hunting. Her poor I shall satisfy with bread. Her priests I shall clothe with salvation, and her saints with rejoicing shall rejoice. There I shall raise a horn to David. I have prepared a lamp for My anointed. His enemies I shall clothe with shame, and My holiness shall flourish upon Him.” ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sebab TUHAN telah memilih Sion, mengingininya menjadi tempat kedudukan-Nya: "Inilah tempat perhentian-Ku selama-lamanya, di sini Aku hendak diam, sebab Aku mengingininya.</div><div>Perbekalannya akan Kuberkati dengan limpahnya, orang-orangnya yang miskin akan Kukenyangkan dengan  roti, imam-imamnya akan Kukenakan pakaian keselamatan, dan orang-orangnya yang saleh akan bersorak-sorai dengan girang. Di sanalah Aku akan menumbuhkan sebuah tanduk bagi Daud, Aku akan menyediakan sebuah pelita bagi orang yang Kuurapi.</div><div>Musuh-musuhnya akan Kukenakan pakaian penuh malu, tetapi di atas kepalanya akan bersemarak mahkotanya." ALLELUIA..</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            لأنَّ الربَّ اختارَ صِهيَونَ ورضيَها مسْكناً لهُ: هذا هو موضِعُ راحتي إلى أبدِ الأبدِ، ههنا أسكُنُ لأنِّي أردتُهُ. لصيدِها أبارِكُ بركةً، لمساكينِها أُشبِعُ خُبزاً، لكهنتِها أُلبِسُ الخلاصَ وأبرارُها يبتهِجونَ ابتِهاجاً. هناكَ أُقيمُ قرناً لداودَ. هيَّأتُ سِراجاً لمسيحي. لأعدائِهِ أُلبِسُ الخِزيَ وعليهِ يُزهِرُ قُدسي. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>