<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 136 - By the rivers of Babylon...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 136 - Di tepi sungai-sungai Babel...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والسادسُ والثلاثونَ - على أنهارِ بابِلَ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat and wept when we remembered Zion. We hung our harps on the willows in the midst of it. For there those who had taken us captive asked of us the words of a song, and those who had carried us away asked a hymn, saying, “Sing us one of the songs of Zion.”         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Di tepi sungai-sungai Babel, disanalah kita duduk sambil menangis, apabila kita mengingat Sion. Pada pohon-pohon gandarusa di tempat itu kita menggantungkan kecapi kita.</div><div>Sebab di sanalah orang-orang yang menawan kita meminta kepada kita memperdengarkan nyanyian, dan orang-orang yang menyiksa kita meminta nyanyian sukacita: "Nyanyikanlah bagi kami nyanyian dari Sion!”</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            على أنهارِ بابِلَ هناكَ جلسْنا، فبكيْنا عِندما تذكَّرْنا صِهيَونَ. على الصِّفصافِ في وسَطِها علَّقنا قيثاراتِنا، لأنَّهُ هناكَ سألَنا الذينَ سبَوْنا أقوالَ التسبيحِ. والذينَ استاقونا إلى هناكَ قالوا: سبِّحوا لنا تسبِحةً مِنْ تسابيحِ صِهيَونَ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            How will we sing the Lord's song in a strange land? If I forget you, O Jerusalem, I shall forget my right hand. My tongue shall cling to my throat, if I did not remember you; if I did not prefer Jerusalem as the head of my joy.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Bagaimanakah kita menyanyikan nyanyian TUHAN di negeri asing? Jika aku melupakan engkau, hai Yerusalem, biarlah menjadi kering tangan kananku! Biarlah lidahku melekat pada langit-langitku, jika aku tidak  mengingat engkau, jika aku tidak jadikan Yerusalem puncak sukacitaku!         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            كيفَ نُسبِّحُ تسبِحةَ الربِّ في أرضٍ غريبةٍ؟ إنْ نسِيتُكِ يا أورُشليمُ أنسَ يميني، ويلتصِقُ لِساني بحنَكي إنْ لمْ أذكُرْكِ، إنْ لمْ أُفضِّلْ أورُشليمَ في ابتداءِ فرحي.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            Remember, O Lord, the children of Edom in the day of Jerusalem, who said, “Tear it down, tear it down, even to its foundations.” Wretched daughter of Babylon! Blessed is he who will reward you with the reward you have given us. Blessed is he who will seize and bury your infants by the rock. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ingatlah, ya TUHAN, kepada bani Edom,yang pada hari pemusnahan Yerusalem mengatakan: "Runtuhkan, runtuhkan sampai ke dasarnya!” Hai puteri Babel, yang suka melakukan kekerasan, berbahagialah orang yang membalas kepadamu perbuatan-perbuatan yang kaulakukan kepada kami! Berbahagialah orang yang menangkap dan memecahkan anak-anakmu pada bukit batu! ALLELUIA         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            اذكُرْ يا ربُّ بني أدومَ في يومِ أورُشليمَ القائلينَ: انقُضوا، انقُضوا حتَّى الأساسَ مِنْها. يا بِنتَ بابِلَ الشقيَّةَ طوبى لمَنْ يُكافِئُكِ مُكافأتِكِ التي جازيتِنا. طوبى لمَنْ يُمسِكُ أطفالَكِ ويدفِنُهُم عندَ الصخرةِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>