<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 137 - I will give thanks to You...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 137 - Aku hendak bersyukur kepada-Mu ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والسابعُ والثلاثونَ - أعترِفُ لكَ يا...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            I will give thanks to You, O Lord, with my whole heart, for You have heard all the words of my mouth. Before the angels I will chant to You. I will worship toward Your holy temple, and give thanks to Your name, on account of Your mercy and Your truth, for You have magnified Your holy name above all. The day in which I call upon You, hear me speedily; You shall exceedingly look upon my soul with power. Let all the kings of the earth, O Lord, give thanks to You, for they have heard all the words of Your mouth. And let them sing in the ways of the Lord, for great is the glory of the Lord.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Aku hendak bersyukur kepada-Mu dengan segenap hatiku, di hadapan para Allah aku akan bermazmur bagi-Mu. Aku hendak sujud kearah bait-Mu yang kudus dan memuji nama- Mu, oleh karena kasih-Mu dan oleh karena setia-Mu; sebab Kaubuat nama-Mu dan janji-Mu melebihi segala sesuatu.</div><div>Pada hari aku berseru, Engkaupun menjawab aku, Engkau menambahkan kekuatan dalam jiwaku. Semua rajadi bumi akan bersyukur kepada-Mu, yaTUHAN, sebab mereka mendengar janji dari mulut-Mu; mereka akan menyanyi tentang jalan-jalan TUHAN, sebab besar kemuliaan TUHAN.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أعترِفُ لكَ يا ربُّ مِنْ كلِّ قلبي لأنَّكَ استمعْتَ كلَّ كلِماتِ فمي. أمامَ الملائكةِ أُرتِّلُ لكَ وأسجُدُ قُدَّامَ هيكلِكَ المُقدَّسِ، وأعترِفُ لاسمِكَ على رحمتِكَ وحقِّكَ، لأنَّكَ قدْ عظَّمتَ اسمَكَ القُدُّوسَ على الكلِّ. اليومَ الذي أدعوكَ فيهِ أجِبْني بسُرعةٍ. تُكثِرُ التطلُّعَ على نفسي بقوةٍ. فليعترِفْ لكَ يا ربُّ كلُّ ملوكِ الأرضِ. لأنَّهُم قدْ سمِعوا سائرَ كلِماتِ فمِكَ وليُسبِّحوا في طُرُقِ الربِّ. لأنَّ مجدَ الربِّ عظيمٌ،         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            The Lord is high, and He regards the lowly, and He knows the existing things from afar off. If I walk in the midst of affliction, You shall revive me; You have stretched forth Your hands against the wrath of enemies, and Your right hand has saved me. O Lord, You shall reward on my behalf; Your mercy, O Lord, endures forever, do not overlook the works of Your hands. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>TUHAN  itu tinggi, namun Ia melihat orang yang hina, dan mengenal orang yang sombong dari jauh. Jika aku berada dalam kesesakan, Engkau mempertahankan hidupku; terhadap amarah musuhku Engkau mengulurkan tangan-Mu, dan tangan kanan-Mu menyelamatkan aku.</div><div>TUHAN akan menyelesaikannya bagiku! Ya TUHAN,  kasih setia- Mu untuk selama-lamanya; janganlah Kautinggalkan perbuatan tangan-Mu!  ALLELUIA</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            لأنَّ الربَّ عالٍ ويُعاينُ المُتواضِعاتِ والكائناتُ يعرِفُها مِنْ بُعدٍ. إنْ سلكْتُ في وسَطِ الشِدَّةِ فإنَّكَ تُحيِني. على رِجزِ الأعداءِ مددتَ يدَكَ وخلَّصَتْني يمينُكَ. الربُّ يُجازي عنِّي، يا ربُّ رحمتُكَ دائمةٌ إلى الأبدِ. أعمالُ يدَيكَ يا ربُّ لا تترُكْها. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>