<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 14 - O Lord, who shall abide...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Psalm 14 - O Lord, who shall abide...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الرابع عشر - يا ربّ مَنْ يسكن...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O Lord, who shall abide in Your dwelling place? And who can rest upon Your holy mountain? It is he who walks blamelessly, doing righteousness, speaking truth in his heart, he who has not spoken deceitfully with his tongue, neither has done evil to his friend, nor taken up a reproach against his neighbors. The evil worker is disdained before him, but he glorifies those who fear the Lord. He gives oath to his friend and does not turn away from him. He has not given his money on usury, and has not received bribes against the godly. He who does these things shall not stumble forever. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true"><div>Siapa yang boleh menumpang dalam kemah-Mu? Siapa yang boleh diam di gunung-Mu yang kudus?</div><div>Yaitu dia yang berlaku tidak bercela, yang melakukan apa yang adil dan yang mengatakan kebenaran dengan segenap hatinya, yang tidak menyebarkan fitnah dengan lidahnya, yang tidak berbuat jahat terhadap temannya dan yang tidak menimpakan cela kepada tetangganya; yang memandang hina orang yang tersingkir, tetapi memuliakan orang yang takut akan TUHAN; yang berpegang pada sumpah, walaupun rugi; yang tidak meminjamkan uangnya dengan makan riba dan tidak menerima suap melawan orang yang tak bersalah. Siapa yang berlaku demikian, tidak akan goyah selama-lamanya. ALLELUIA.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            ياربُّ مَنْ يسكنُ في مسكنِكَ، ومَنْ يحلُّ في جبلِ قدسِكَ؟ السالكُ بلا عيبٍ والفاعلُ البرَّ، والمتكلمُ بالحقِّ في قلبِهِ، الذي لا يغشُّ بلسانِهِ، ولا يصنعُ بقريبِهِ سوءاً، ولا يقبلُ عاراً على جيرانِهِ. فاعلُ الشرَّ مرذولٌ أمامَهُ، ويمجِّدُّ الذين يتَّقونَ الربَّ. الذي يحلفُ لقريبِهِ ولا يغدرُ بهِ. ولا يُعطي فضَّتَهُ بالرِّبا، ولا يقبلُ الرِّشوةَ على الأبرياءِ. الذي يصنعُ هذا لا يتزعزعُ إلى الأبدِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>