<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 140 - O Lord, I have cried to You...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 140 - Ya TUHAN, aku berseru kepada-Mu...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والأربعونَ - يا ربُّ إليكَ صرختُ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O Lord, I have cried to You; hear me; attend to the voice of my supplication when I cry to You. Let my prayer be set forth before You as incense, and the lifting up of my hands as an evening sacrifice. O Lord, set a watch on my mouth and a strong door for my lips. Do not incline my heart to words of evil, to employ excuses for sins with men who work iniquity, and I shall not agree with their choices. The righteous shall chasten me with mercy, and reprove me, but do not let the oil of the sinner anoint my head, for yet my prayer also is in their pleasures.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya TUHAN, aku berseru kepada-Mu, datanglah segera kepadaku, berilah telinga kepada suaraku, waktu aku berseru kepada-Mu!</div><div><br/></div><div>Biarlah doaku adalah bagi-Mu seperti persembahan ukupan, dan tanganku yang terangkat seperti persembahan korban pada waktu petang. Awasilah mulutku, ya TUHAN,  berjagalah pada pintu bibirku!</div><div>Jangan condongkan hatiku kepada yang jahat, untuk melakukan perbuatan-perbuatan yang fasik bersama-sama dengan orang-orang yang melakukan kejahatan; dan jangan aku mengecap sedap-sedapan mereka. Biarlah orang benar memalu dan menghukum aku, itulah kasih; tetapi janganlah minyak orang fasik menghiasi kepalaku! Sungguh aku terus berdoa menentang kejahatan-kejahatan mereka</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            يا ربُّ إليكَ صرختُ فاستمِعْ لي. أنصِتْ إلى صوتِ تضرُّعي، إذا ما صرخْتُ إليكَ. لِتستقِمْ صلاتي كالبَخورِ قُدَّامَكَ. وليكنْ رفعُ يديَّ كذبيحةٍ مَسائيَّةٍ. ضعْ يا ربُّ حافِظاً لفمي، وباباً حصيناً لشفتيَّ. ولا تُمِلْ قلبي إلى كلامِ الشرِّ، فيتعلَّلُ بعِللٍ في الخطايا معَ أُناسٍ فاعلي الإثمِ، ولا أتفِقُ معَ مُختاريهِم. فليؤدِبْني الصدِّيقُ بِرحمةٍ ويوبِّخْني. أمَّا زيتُ الخاطئِ فلا يدهِنْ رأسي، لأنَّ صلاتي أيضاً بِمسرَّةٍ.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            Their mighty ones have been swallowed up near the rock; they shall hear my words, for they are delightful. As a lump of earth, they are broken upon the ground; their bones have been scattered at Hades. For my eyes are to You, O Lord; O Lord, I have hoped in You; do not take away my soul. Keep me from the snare which they have set for me, and from the stumbling blocks of those who work iniquity. Sinners shall fall by their own net; I am alone until iniquity passes by. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Apabila mereka diserahkan kepada hakim-hakimnya, maka mereka akan mendengar, bahwa perkataan-perkataanku menyenangkan. Seperti batu yang dibelahdan dihancurkan di tanah, demikianlah akan berhamburan tulang-tulang mereka di mulut dunia orang mati.</div><div>Tetapi kepada-Mulah, ya TUHAN, Tuhanku, mataku tertuju; pada- Mulah aku berlindung, jangan campakkan aku! Lindungilah aku terhadap katupan jerat yang mereka pasang terhadap aku, dan dari perangkap orang-orang yang melakukan kejahatan. Orang-orang fasik akan jatuh serentak ke dalam jala mereka, tetapi aku melangkah lalu. ALLELUIA..</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            قدْ ابتُلِعَ أقوياؤهُم عِندَ الصخرةِ، يسمعونَ كلِماتي لأنَّهُم استلذُّوا. مِثلُ شحمِ الأرضِ انشقُّوا على الأرضِ. تبدَّدتْ عِظامُهُم عِندَ الجحيمِ، لأنَّ عُيونَنا إليكَ يا ربُّ، يا ربُّ عليكَ توكَّلتُ فلا تقتُلْ نفسي. احفظْني مِنَ الفخِّ الذي قدْ نصبوهُ لي، ومِنْ شُكوكِ فاعلي الإثمِ. يسقُطُ الخُطاةُ في شبكتِهِم، وأكونُ أنا وحدي حتَّى يجوزَ الإثمُ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>