<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 141 - With my voice to the Lord...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 141 - Dengan nyaring aku berseru-seru kepada TUHAN...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والحادي والأربعونَ - بِصوتي إلى الربِّ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            With my voice to the Lord I cried; with my voice to the Lord I made supplication. I will pour out before Him my supplication. My affliction I will pour out before Him, when my spirit was fainting within me, and You knew my paths. In the way in which I was walking, they hid a snare for me. I looked on my right hand, and beheld, for there was no one who noticed me. Refuge failed me, and there was no one who cared for my soul. I cried unto You, O Lord, and said, “You are my hope, my portion in the land of the living. Attend to my supplication, for I am brought very low; deliver me from those who persecute me, for they are stronger than me. Bring my soul out of prison, that I may give thanks to Your name, O Lord. The righteous wait for me until You reward me.” ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengan nyaring aku berseru-seru kepada TUHAN, dengan nyaring aku memohon kepada TUHAN. Aku mencurahkan keluhanku ke hadapan-Nya,  kesesakanku kuberitahukan ke hadapan-Nya. Ketika semangatku lemah lesu di dalam diriku, Engkaulah yang mengetahui jalanku.</div><div>Di jalan yang harus kutempuh, dengan sembunyi mereka memasang jerat terhadapaku. Pandanglah ke kanan dan lihatlah, tidak ada seorangpunyang menghiraukan aku; tempat pelarian bagiku telah hilang, tidak ada seorangpun yang mencari aku. Aku berseru-seru kepada-Mu , ya TUHAN, kataku:</div><div>"Engkaulah tempat perlindunganku, bagianku dinegeri orang- orang hidup!” Perhatikanlah teriakku, sebab aku telah menjadi sangat lemah.</div><div>Lepaskanlah aku dari pada orang-orang yang mengejar aku, sebab mereka terlalu kuat bagiku. Keluarkanlah aku dari dalam penjara untuk memuji nama-Mu. Orang-orang benar akan mengelilingi aku, apabila Engkau berbuat baik kepadaku. ALLELUIA..</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            بِصوتي إلى الربِّ صرختُ، بِصوتي إلى الربِّ تضرَّعتُ. أسكُبُ أمامَهُ توسُّلي. أبُثُّ لديهِ ضيقي، عِندَ فناءِ رُوحي مِنِّي، وأنتَ علِمتَ سُبُلي. في الطريقِ التي أسلُكُ أخفَوا لي فخَّاً، تأمَّلتُ عنْ اليمينِ وأبصرتُ فلمْ يكنْ مَنْ يعرِفُني. ضاعَ المَهربُ مِنِّي وليسَ مَنْ يسألُ عنْ نفسي. فصرختُ إليكَ يا ربُّ وقُلتُ: أنتَ هو رجائي وحظِّي في أرضِ الأحياءِ. أنصِتْ إلى طِلبتي فإنَّني قدْ تذلَّلتُ جِداً. نجِّني مِنَ الذينَ يضطَّهِدونَني لأنَّهُم قدْ اعتزُّوا أكثرَ مِنِّي. أخرِجْ مِنَ الحبسِ نفسي، لكي أشكُرَ اسمَكَ يا ربُّ. إيَّايَ ينتظِرُ الصدِّيقونَ حتَّى تُجازيني. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>