<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 142 - O Lord, hear my prayer...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 142 - Ya TUHAN, dengarkanlah doaku...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور المائة والثاني والأربعون - يا ربّ اسمعْ صلاتي...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O Lord, hear my prayer; give ear to my supplication in Your truth; hearken to me in Your justice. And do not enter into judgment with Your servant, for in Your sight no one living shall be justified.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya TUHAN, dengarkanlah doaku, berilah telinga kepada permohonanku! Jawablah aku dalam kesetiaan-Mu, demi keadilan- Mu! Janganlah beperkara dengan hamba-Mu ini, sebab di antara yang hidup tidak seorangpun yang benar di hadapan-Mu.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ياربُّ اسمعْ صلاتي. انصِتْ إلى طِلبتي بحقِّكَ. استجِبْ لي بعدلِكَ. ولا تدخُلْ في المُحاكمةِ معَ عبدِكَ، فإنَّهُ لن يتزكَّى قدَّامَكَ كلُّ حيٍ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            For the enemy has persecuted my soul; he has humbled my life down to the ground; he has made me to sit in darkness, as those who have been long dead. Therefore, my spirit grieves in me; my heart is troubled within me. I remembered the days of old, and I meditated on all Your doings; I meditated on the works of Your hands. I spread forth my hands unto You; my soul is toward You as a dry land.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sebab musuh telah mengejar aku dan mencampakkan nyawaku ke tanah, menempatkan aku di dalam gelap seperti orang yang sudah lama mati. Semangatku lemah lesu dalam diriku, hatiku tertegun dalam tubuhku.</div><div>Aku teringat kepada hari-hari dahulu kala, aku merenungkan segala pekerjaan-Mu, aku memikirkan perbuatan tangan-Mu. Aku menadahkan tanganku kepada-Mu, jiwaku haus kepada-Mu seperti tanah yang tandus.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            لأنَّ العدوَّ قد اضطهدَ نفسي، وأذلَّ في الأرضِ حياتي. أجلسَني في الظُلماتِ مثلَ الموتى منذُ الدهرِ، إضجرَ فيَّ رُوحي، اضطربَ فيَّ قلبي. تذكَّرتُ الأيامَ الأولى ولَهجتُ في كلِّ أعمالِكَ، وفي صنائعِ يديكَ كنتُ أتأملُ. بسَطتُ إليكَ يديَّ، صارتْ نَفسي لكَ مثلَ أرضٍ بِلا ماءٍ.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            Hear me quickly, O Lord, for my spirit has failed; do not turn away Your face from me, or I will be like those who go down to the pit. Let me hear Your mercy in the morning, for in You do I hope; make known to me, O Lord, the way in which I should walk, for I have lifted up my soul to You. Deliver me from my enemies, O Lord, for I have fled to You. Teach me to do Your will, for You are my God; Let Your Holy Spirit guide me in the straight way. You shall revive me, O Lord, for Your name's sake; in Your righteousness You shall bring my soul out of affliction. And in Your mercy You will wipe out my enemies, and destroy all who afflict my soul; for I am Your servant. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Jawablah aku dengan segera, ya TUHAN, sudah habis semangatku! Jangan sembunyikan wajah-Mu terhadap aku, sehingga aku seperti mereka yang turun ke liang kubur. </div><div>Perdengarkanlah kasih setia-Mu kepadaku  pada waktu pagi, sebab kepada-Mulah aku percaya! Beritahukanlah aku jalan yang harus kutempuh, sebab kepada-Mulah kuangkat jiwaku.</div><div>Lepaskanlah aku dari pada musuh-musuhku, yaTUHAN, pada- Mulah aku berteduh! Ajarlah aku melakukan kehendak-Mu, sebab Engkaulah Allahku! </div><div>Kiranya Roh-Mu yang baik itu menuntun aku di tanah yang rata! </div><div>Hidupkanlah aku oleh karena nama-Mu, ya TUHAN, keluarkanlah jiwaku dari dalam kesesakan demi keadilan-Mu!</div><div>Binasakanlah musuh-musuhku demi kasih setia-Mu, dan lenyapkanlah semua orang yang mendesak aku, sebab aku ini hamba-Mu! ALLELUIA.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            استجِبْ لي ياربُّ عاجِلاً، فقد فنيَتْ روحي. لا تحجُبْ وجهَكَ عنِّي، فأشابِهُ الهابطينَ في الجُبِّ. فلأسمَعْ في الغدَواتِ رحمَتَكَ، فإنِّي علَيكَ توكَّلتُ. عرِّفْني ياربُّ الطريقَ التي أسلكُ فيها، لأنِّي إليكَ رفعتُ نفسي. انقِذْني مِنْ أعدائي ياربُّ، فإنِّي لجأتُ إليكَ. علِّمْني أن أصنعَ مشيئتَكَ، لأنكَ أنتَ هو إلهي. روحُكَ القُدُّوسُ فليهدِني إلى الاستقامةِ، مِنْ أجلِ اسمِكَ ياربُّ تُحييني. بحقِّكَ تُخرِجُ مِنَ الشدَّةِ نَفسي، وبرحمتِكَ تستأصِلُ أعدائي. وتُهلِكُ جميعَ مُضايقي نَفسي، لأنِّي أنا هو عبدُكَ أنا. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>