<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Psalm 146 - Praise the Lord, for a psalm...         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والسادسُ والأربعونَ - سبِّحوا الربَّ فإنَّ المزمورَ...         </Language>      </Title>                  <Text>         <Language id="English">            Praise the Lord, for a psalm is good; let praise be sweet unto our God. The Lord builds up Jerusalem, and He will gather together the dispersed of Israel. He heals the broken-hearted, and binds up all their fractures. He numbers the multitudes of stars, and calls them all by names. Great is the Lord, and great is His strength; His understanding is infinite. The Lord lifts up the meek, but brings sinners down to the ground.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            سبِّحوا الربَّ فإنَّ المزمورَ جيِّدٌ، ولإلهِنا يلُذُّ التسبيحُ. الربُّ يبني أورُشليمَ. الربُّ يجمعُ مُتفرِّقي إسرائيلَ. الربُّ يشفي المُنكسِري القُلوبِ، ويجبُرُ جميعَ كسرِهِم. المُحصي كثرةَ الكواكِبِ، ولكافَّتِها يُعطي أسماءً. عظيمٌ هو الربُّ وعظيمةٌ هي قوَّتُهُ. ولا إحصاءَ لفهمِهِ. الربُّ يرفعُ الودعاءَ ويُذِلُّ الخُطاةَ إلى الأرضِ.         </Language>      </Text>             <Text>         <Language id="English">            Begin the song to the Lord with thanksgiving; sing praises to our God on the harp, He who covers the heaven with clouds, who prepares rain for the earth, who causes grass to spring up on the mountains, and green herb for the service of men, who gives food to the cattle, and to the young ravens that call upon Him. He will not take pleasure in the strength of a horse, nor will He be well-pleased with the legs of man. The Lord will take pleasure in those who fear Him, and in those who hope in His mercy. ALLELUIA.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ابتدئوا للربِّ بالاعترافِ، رتِّلوا لإلهِنا بالقيثارةِ. الذي يُجلِّلُ السماءَ بالغَمامِ، الذي يُهيئُ للأرضِ المطرَ، الذي يُنبِتُ العُشبَ على الجِبالِ، والخُضرةَ لخِدمةِ البشرِ، ويُعطي البهائمَ طعامَها، ولِفراخِ الغِربانِ التي تدعوهُ. لا يُؤْثِرُ قوَّةَ الفرَسِ ولا يُسرُّ بِساقيِّ الرجُلِ، بلْ يُسَرُّ الربُّ بخائفيهِ وبالراجينَ رحمتَهُ. هَلِّلُويا.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>