<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 147 - Praise the Lord, O Jerusalem...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 147 - Megahkanlah TUHAN,  hai Yerusalem...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ المائةُ والسابعُ والأربعونَ - سبِّحي الربَّ يا أورُشليمُ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Praise the Lord, O Jerusalem; praise your God, O Zion, for He has strengthened the bars of your gates. He has blessed your children within you. He makes your borders peaceful, and fills you with the fatness of wheat. He sends His word to the earth; His word runs swiftly. He gives snow like wool; He scatters the mist like ashes. He casts out His ice like morsels; who will be able to stand before His frost? He will send out His word, and melt them. His wind will blow, and the waters shall flow. He declares His word to Jacob, His ordinances and judgments to Israel. He has not done so with every nation, and He has not revealed to them His judgments. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Megahkanlah TUHAN,  hai Yerusalem, pujilah Allahmu, hai Sion! Sebab Ia meneguhkan palang pintu gerbangmu, dan memberkati anak-anakmu di antaramu.</div><div>Ia memberikan kesejahteraan kepada daerahmu dan mengenyangkan engkau dengan gandum yang terbaik. Ia menyampaikan perintah-Nya kebumi; dengan segera firman- Nya berlari. Ia menurunkan salju seperti bulu domba dan menghamburkan embun beku seperti abu. Ia melemparkan air batu seperti pecahan-pecahan.</div><div>Siapakah yang tahan berdiri menghadapi dingin-Nya? Ia menyampaikan firman-Nya, lalu mencairkan semuanya, Ia meniupkan angin-Nya, maka air mengalir. Ia memberitakan firman-Nya kepada Yakub,  ketetapan-ketetapan- Nya dan hukum-hukum-Nya kepada Israel. Ia tidak berbuat demikian kepada segala bangsa, dan hukum- hukum-Nya tidak mereka kenal.  ALLELUIA</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            سبِّحي الربَّ يا أورُشليمُ، سبِّحي إلهَكِ يا صِهيَونُ. لأنَّهُ قدْ قوَّى مغاليقَ أبوابِكِ وبارَكَ بنيكِ فيكِ. الذي جعلَ تُخومَكِ في سلامٍ، ويملأُكِ مِنْ شحمِ الحِنطةِ. الذي يُرسِلُ كلِمتَهُ إلى الأرضِ فيُسرِعُ قولُهُ عاجِلاً جِداً. المُعطي الثلجَ كالصوفِ، المُذَرِّي الضبابَ كالرمادِ، ويُلقي الجليدَ مِثلَ الفُتاتِ. قُدامَ وجهِ برْدِهِ مَنْ يقومُ؟ يُرسِلُ كلِمتَهُ فتُذيبُهُ. تهُبُّ ريحُهُ فتَسيلُ المِياهُ. المُخبِرُ كلِمتَهُ ليعقوبَ وفرائضَهُ وأحكامَهُ لإسرائيلَ. لمْ يصنعْ هكذا بكلِّ الأممِ، وأحكامُهُ لمْ يوضِّحْها لهُم. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>