<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 15 - Keep me, O Lord...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Psalm 16 - Bahagia orang saleh</language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الخامس عشر - إحفظني يا ربّ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Keep me, O Lord, for I have hoped in You. I said to the Lord, “You are my Lord, and You have no need of my goodness.” He has manifested His wonders to His saints who are in His earth, and He has wrought all His desires in them. Their ailments have been multiplied who hastened after another God. I will not assemble their meetings of blood, nor make mention of their names with my lips. The Lord is the portion of my inheritance and my cup. You are He who brings my inheritance back to me. The measuring lines have fallen to me among the best, and my inheritance is confirmed for me.         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true"><div>Jagalah aku, ya Allah, sebab pada-Mu aku berlindung. Aku berkata kepada TUHAN: "Engkaulah Tuhanku, tidak ada yang baik bagiku selain Engkau". Orang-orang kudus yang ada di tanah ini, merekalah orang mulia yang selalu menjadi kesukaanku.</div><div>Bertambah besar kesedihan orang-orang yang mengikuti Allah lain; aku tidak akan ikut mempersembahkan korban curahan mereka yang dari darah,  juga tidak akan menyebut-nyebut nama merekadi bibirku. Ya TUHAN,  Engkaulah bagian warisanku dan pialaku, Engkau sendirilah yang meneguhkan bagian yang diundikan kepadaku.</div><div>Tali pengukur jatuh bagiku di tempat-tempat yang permai; ya, milik pusakaku menyenangkan hatiku.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            إحفظْني ياربُّ فإنِّي عليكَ توَّكلتُ. قلتُ للربِّ: أنتَ ربِّي، ولا تحتاجُ إلى صلاحي. أظهرَ عجائبَهُ لقديسيهِ الذين في أرضِهِ، وصنعَ فيهِم كلَّ مشيئاتِهِ. كثُرَتْ أمراضُهُم الذين أسرعوا وراءَ آخرٍ. لا أجمعُ مجامِعَهُم مِنَ الدماءِ، ولا أذكرُ أسماءَهُم بشفتيَّ. الربُّ هو نصيبُ مِيراثي وكأسي. أنتَ الذي تردُّ إليَّ مِيراثي. حبالُ المساحةِ وقعتْ لي في أرضٍ خصبةٍ، وإنَّ ميراثي لثابتٌ لي.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            I will bless the Lord who has given me understanding; my reins too have instructed me even till the night. I foresaw the Lord always before me; He is on my right hand, that I should not be moved. Therefore my heart rejoiced and my tongue exulted; moreover also my flesh shall live in hope: because You shall not leave my soul in Hades, neither shall You suffer Your holy One to see corruption. You have made known to me the ways of life; You will fill me with joy with Your face; delight is in Your right hand forever.  ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true"><div>Aku memuji TUHAN, yang telah memberi nasihat kepadaku, ya, pada waktu malam hati nuraniku mengajari aku. </div><div>Aku senantiasa memandang kepada TUHAN;  karena Ia berdiri di sebelah kananku, aku tidak goyah. Sebab itu hatiku bersukacita dan jiwaku bersorak-sorak, bahkan tubuhku akan diam dengan tenteram; sebab Engkau tidak menyerahkan aku kedunia orang mati, dan tidak membiarkan Orang orang Kudus-Mu melihat kebinasaan.</div><div>Engkau memberitahukan kepadaku jalan kehidupan; dihadapan- Mu ada sukacita berlimpah-limpah, di tangan kanan-Mu ada nikmat senantiasa. ALLELUIA.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أبارِكُ الربَّ الذي أفهمَني. وأيضاً إلى الليل تُنذِرُني كليتايَ. تقدمتُ فرأيتُ الربَّ أمامي في كلِّ حينٍ، لأنَّهُ عَن يميني لكي لا أتزعزعَ. مِنْ أجلِ هذا فرِحَ قلبي وتهلَّلَ لساني. وأيضاً جسدي يسكنُ على الرجاءِ. لأنَّكَ لا تتركُ نفسي في الجحيمِ. ولا تدَعُ قدوسَّكَ يرى فساداً. قد عرَّفتَني سُبُلَ الحياةِ. تملأُني فرحاً مع وجهِكَ. البهجةُ في يمينِكَ إلى الانقضاءِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>