<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 18 - The heavens declare...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 19 - The heavens declare...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الثامن عشر - السماواتُ تحدّثُ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            The heavens declare the glory of God, and the firmament proclaims the work of His hands. Day to day utters speech, and night to night proclaims knowledge. There are no speeches or words, in which their voice is not heard. Their sound has gone out upon all the earth, and their words have reached to the ends of the world. In the sun He has set His dwelling, and it comes forth as a bridegroom out of his chamber; it shall exult as a giant running his course. Its going forth is from the extremity of heaven, and its goal is to the other end of heaven, and nothing will be hidden from its heat.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Langit menceritakan kemuliaan Allah, dan cakrawala memberitakan pekerjaan tangan-Nya; hari meneruskan berita itu kepada hari, dan malam menyampaikan pengetahuan itu kepada malam. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Tidak ada berita dan tidak ada kata, suara mereka tidak terdengar; tetapi gema mereka terpencar ke seluruh dunia, dan perkataan  mereka sampai ke ujung bumi. Ia memasang kemah di  langit untuk matahari, yang keluar bagaikan pengantin laki-laki yang keluar dari kamarnya, girang bagaikan pahlawan yang hendak melakukan perjalanannya. Dari ujung langit ia terbit, dan ia beredar sampai keujung yang lain; tidak ada yang terlindung dari panas sinarnya.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            السماواتُ تحدِّثُ بمجدِ اللهِ، والفَلَكُ يخبرُ بعملِ يديهِ. يومٌ إلى يومٍ يُبدي قولاً. وليلٌ إلى ليلٍ يُظهِرُ عِلماً. لا قولَ ولا كلامَ. لا تُسمَعُ أصواتُهُم، في كلِّ الأرضِ خرجَ منطِقُهُم. وإلى أقصى المسكونةِ بلغَتْ أقوالُهُم. جعلَ في الشمسِ مظلَّتَهُ. وهي مثلِ العريسِ الخارجِ مِنْ خدرِهِ. تتهلَّلُ مِثلِ الجبارِ الذي يسرعُ في طريقِهِ. مِنْ أقصى السماءِ خروجُها، ومنتهاها إلى أقصى السماءِ ولا شيءٌ يختفي مِنْ حرارتِها.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            The law of the Lord is pure, converting souls; the testimony of the Lord is faithful, instructing the babes. The ordinances of the Lord are straight, rejoicing the heart; the commandment of the Lord is a light, enlightening the eyes from afar. The fear of the Lord is pure, enduring forever and ever; the judgments of the Lord are true, and justified altogether. The desires of His heart are chosen more than gold and precious stone, and sweeter than honey and the honeycomb. For Your servant keeps them; and in keeping them there is great reward.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Taurat  TUHAN itu sempurna, menyegarkan jiwa; peraturan TUHAN  itu teguh,  memberikan hikmat kepada orang yang tak berpengalaman. Titah TUHAN itu tepat,  menyukakan hati; perintah  TUHAN  itu murni, membuat mata bercahaya. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Takut akan TUHAN itu suci, tetap ada untuk selamanya; hukum- hukum TUHAN itu benar, adil semuanya, lebih indah dari pada emas, bahkan dari pada banyak emas tua; dan lebih manis dari pada madu, bahkan dari pada madu tetesan dari sarang lebah. </span>Lagipula hamba-Mu diperingatkan oleh semuanya itu, dan orang yang berpegang padanya mendapat upah yang besar</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            ناموسُ الربِّ بِلا عيبٍ، يردُّ النفوسَ. شهادةُ الربِّ صادقةٌ، تعلِّمُ الأطفالَ. فرائضُ الربِّ مستقيمةٌ، تفرِّحُ القلبَ. وصيةُ الربِّ مضيئةٌّ، تنيرُ العينينِ عن بُعدٍ. خشيةُ الربِّ زكيةٌ، دائمةٌ إلى أبدِ الأبدِ. أحكامُ الربِّ أحكامُ حقٍّ وعادلةٌ معاً. شهوةُ قلبِهِ مختارةٌ. أفضلَ مِنَ الذهبِ والحجرِ الكثيرِ الثمنِ، وأحلى مِنَ العسلِ والشَّهدِ. عبدُكَ يحفظُها، وفي حفظِها ثوابٌ عظيمٌ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Who can understand transgressions? From my secret sins cleanse me, O Lord, and from the attack of strangers spare Your servant. Let them not have dominion over me, then I shall be blameless, and I shall be cleansed from great sin. All the sayings of my mouth, and the meditation of my heart, shall be pleasing continually before You. O Lord, You are my helper, and my Savior. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Siapakah yang dapat mengetahui kesesatan? Bebaskanlah aku dari apa yang tidak kusadari. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Lindungilah hamba-Mu, juga terhadap orang yang kurang ajar; janganlah mereka menguasai aku! Maka aku menjadi tak bercela dan bebas dari pelanggaran besar. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Mudah-mudahan Engkau berkenan akan ucapan mulutku dan renungan hatiku, ya TUHAN, gunung batuku dan penebusku. ALLELUIA.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            الهفواتُ مَنْ يشعرُ بِها؟ مِنَ الخطايا المُستَتِرةِ ياربُّ طهِّرْني، ومِنَ الغُرباءِ احفظْ عبدَكَ حتَّى لا يتسلَّطوا عليَّ، فحينئذٍ أكونُ بِلا عيبٍ، وأتنقَّى مِنْ خَطيئَةٍ عظيمةٍ. وتكونُ جميعُ أقوالِ فمِي وفكرُ قلبي مرضيَّةً أمامَكَ في كلِّ حينٍ. ياربُّ أنتَ مُعيني ومُخلِّصي. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>