<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 19 - The Lord shall hear you...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 20 - Kiranya TUHAN  menjawab engkau...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور التاسع عشر - يستجيبُ لكَ الربُّ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            The Lord shall hear you in the day of your trouble; the name of the God of Jacob defend you. He shall send you help from His Holy, and uphold you out of Zion. He shall remember all your sacrifices, and enrich your burnt offerings. The Lord shall grant you according to your heart, and fulfill all your counsel. We will confess your salvation, and in the name of our God we shall grow; the Lord shall fulfill all your petitions.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kiranya TUHAN  menjawab engkau pada waktu kesesakan! Kiranya nama Allah Yakub membentengi engkau! Kiranya dikirimkan-Nya bantuan kepadamu dari tempat kudus dan disokong-Nya engkau dari Sion. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Kiranya diingat-Nya segala korban persembahanmu, dan disukai- Nya korban bakaranmu. Kiranya diberikan-Nya kepadamu apa yang kaukehendaki dan dijadikan-Nya berhasil apa yang kaurancangkan. Kami mau bersorak-sorai tentang kemenanganmu dan mengangkat panji-panji demi nama Allah kita; kiranya TUHAN memenuhi segala permintaanmu.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            يستجيبُ لكَ الربُّ في يومِ شدّتِكَ، ينصرُكَ اسمُ إلهِ يعقوبَ. يُرسلُ لكَ عوناً مِنْ قدسهِ، ومِنْ صهيونَ يعضُدُكَ. يذكرُ جميعَ ذبائحِكَ، ويستسمِنُ مُحرقاتِكَ. يُعطيكَ الربُّ حسبَ قلبِكَ، ويُتمِّمُ كلَّ مشورتِكَ. نعترفُ لكَ ياربُّ بخلاصِكَ، وباسمِ إلهِنا ننمو. يُكمِّلُ الربُّ كلَّ سؤلِكَ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Now I know that the Lord has saved His anointed; He shall hear him from His holy heaven; the salvation of His right hand is mighty. These in chariots, and these in horses, but in the name of the Lord our God we will grow. They are overthrown and fallen, but we are risen, and set upright. O Lord, save Your king, and hear us in the day we call upon You. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sekarang aku tahu, bahwa TUHAN memberi kemenangan kepada orang yang diurapi-Nya dan menjawabnya dari surga-Nya yang kudus dengan kemenangan yang gilang-gemilang oleh tangan kanan-Nya. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Orang ini memegahkan kereta dan orang itu memegahkan kuda, tetapi kita bermegah dalam nama TUHAN, Allah kita. Mereka rebah dan jatuh, tetapi kita bangun berdiri dan tetap tegak. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Ya TUHAN, berikanlah kemenangan kepada raja! Jawablah kiranya kami pada waktu kami berseru! ALLELUIA.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            الآنَ علِمتُ أنَّ الربَّ قد خلّصَ مسيحَهُ، واستجابَ لهُ مِنْ سماءِ قدسِهِ بجبروتِ خلاصِ يمينِهِ. هؤلاءِ بمركباتٍ وهؤلاءِ بخيلٍ، ونحنُ باسمِ الربِّ إلهِنا ننمو. هُم عثروا وسقطوا، ونحنُ قُمْنا وانتصبْنا. ياربُّ خلّصْ مَلِكَكَ واستجِبْ لنا يومَ ندعوكَ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>