<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 2 - Why did the nations rage...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Psalm 2 - Raja yang diurapi TUHAN</language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الثاني - لماذا ارتجتْ الأمم...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Why did the nations rage, and the peoples meditate on vain things? The kings of the earth stood up, and the rulers gathered together against the Lord and against His Christ; saying, “Let us break through their bonds, and cast away their yoke from us.”         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true">Mengapa rusuh bangsa-bangsa, mengapa suku-suku bangsa mereka-reka perkara yang sia-sia. Raja-raja dunia bersiap-siap dan para pembesar bermufakat bersama-sama melawan TUHAN dan yang diurapi-Nya: "Marilah kita memutuskan belenggu-belenggu mereka dan membuang tali-tali mereka dari pada kita!”</language>         <language id="Arabic">            لماذا ارتجتْ الأممُ، وتفكرتْ الشعوبُ في الباطلِ. قامَ ملوكُ الأرضِ وتآمرَ الرؤساءُ معاً على الربِّ وعلى مسيحِهِ قائلينَ: لنقطعْ أغلالَهُما، ولنطرحْ عنَّا نيرَهُما.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            He who dwells in the heavens shall laugh at them, and the Lord shall mock them. Then He shall speak to them in His anger, and in His wrath He shall trouble them.         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true">Dia, yang bersemayam di suorga, tertawa; Tuhan mengolok-olok mereka. Maka berkatalah Ia kepada mereka dalam murka-Nya dan mengejutkan mereka dalam kehangatan amarah-Nya</language>         <language id="Arabic">            الساكنُ في السماواتِ يضحكُ بهِم، والربُّ يستهزئُ بهِم. حينئذٍ يكلمُهُم بغضبِهِ، وبرجزِهِ يُرجفهُم.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            “But I have been established king by Him on Zion, His holy mountain, proclaiming the ordinance of the Lord: the Lord said to Me, `You are My Son, today I have begotten You. Ask Me, and I will give You the nations for Your inheritance, and Your authority to the end of the earth. You shall shepherd them with a rod of iron; You shall crush them as a potter's vessel.’”         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true">" Akulah yang telah melantik raja-Ku di Sion, gunung-Ku yang kudus! Aku mau menceritakan tentang ketetapan TUHAN; Ia berkata kepadaku: "Anak-Ku engkau! Engkau telah Kuperanakkan pada hari ini. Mintalah kepada-Ku,  maka bangsa-bangsa akan Kuberikan kepadamu menjadi milik pusakamu, dan ujung bumi menjadi kepunyaanmu. Engkau akan meremukkan mereka dengan gada besi, memecahkan mereka seperti tembikar tukang periuk.”</language>         <language id="Arabic">            أنا أقمتُهُ ملِكاً على صهيونَ جبلِ قدسِهِ، لأكرزَ بأمرِ الربِّ. الربُّ قالَ لي: أنتَ ابني، وأنا اليومَ ولدتُكَ. اسألْني فأعطيكَ الأممَ ميراثَكَ، وسلطانَكَ إلى أقطارِ الأرضِ. لترعاهُم بقضيبٍ مِنْ حديدٍ. ومثلَ آنيةِ الفخارِ تسحقُهُم.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Now, understand, O kings; be instructed, all you who judge the earth, serve the Lord with fear, and rejoice in Him with trembling. Take hold of instruction, lest the Lord be angry, and you perish from the way of righteousness, whenever His wrath shall be suddenly kindled. Blessed are all who trust in Him. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true">Oleh sebab itu, hai raja-raja, bertindaklah bijaksana, terimalah pengajaran, hai para hakim dunia! Beribadahlah kepada TUHAN  dengan takut dan ciumlah kaki-Nya dengan gemetar, supaya Ia jangan murka dan kamu binasa di jalan, sebab mudah sekali murka-Nya menyala. Berbahagialah semua orang yang berlindung pada-Nya! ALLELUIA.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            فالآنَ أيها الملوكُ افهموا، وتأدبوا يا جميعَ قضاةِ الأرضِ اعبدوا الربَّ بخشيةٍ. وهللوا لهُ برعدةٍ. الزموا الأدبَ لئلا يغضبَ الربُّ فتضلُّوا عَن طريقِ الحقِّ. عندما يتَّقدُ غضبُهُ بسرعةٍ، طوبى لجميعِ المتكلينَ عليهِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>