<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 23 - The earth and its fullness...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Psalm 24 - Tuhanlah yang empunya bumi...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الثالث والعشرون - للربِّ الأرضُ ومِلؤها...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            The earth and its fullness are the Lord’s; the world and all that dwell in it. He has founded it upon the seas, and prepared it upon the rivers.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Tuhanlah yang empunya bumi serta segala isinya, dan dunia serta yang diam di dalamnya. Sebab Dialah yang mendasarkannya di atas lautan dan menegakkannya di atas sungai-sungai.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            للربِّ الأرضُ ومِلؤها، المسكونةُ وجميعُ الساكنينَ فيها. هو على البحارِ أسّسَها، وعلى الأنهارِ هيّأها.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Who shall go up to the mountain of the Lord, and who shall stand in His holy place? He that is pure in his hands, and clean in his heart; who has not lifted up his soul in vanity, nor sworn deceitfully to his neighbor. He shall receive a blessing from the Lord, and mercy from God his Savior. This is the generation of those who seek the Lord, who seek the face of the God of Jacob.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>"Siapakah yang boleh naik ke atas gunung TUHAN? Siapakah yang boleh berdiri ditempat-Nya yang kudus?” <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">"Orang yang bersih tangannya dan murni hatinya, yang tidak menyerahkan dirinya kepada penipuan, dan yang tidak bersumpah palsu. Dialah yang akan menerima berkat dari TUHAN dan keadilan dari Allah yang menyelamatkan dia. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Itulah angkatan orang-orang yang menanyakan Dia, yang mencari wajah-Mu, ya Allah Yakub</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            مَنْ يصعدُ إلى جبلِ الربِّ، أو مَنْ يقومُ في موضعِ قدسِهِ؟ الطاهرُ اليدَينِ، النقيُّ القلبِ. الذي لم يحملْ نفسَهُ إلى الباطلِ ولم يحلفْ بالغشِّ. هذا ينالُ بركةً مِنَ الربِّ، ورحمةً مِنَ اللهِ مُخلّصِهِ، هذا هو جيلُ الذينَ يطلبونَ الربَّ ويبتغونَ وجهَ إلهِ يعقوبَ.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            Lift up your gates, you princes, and be lifted up, you everlasting doors, and the King of glory shall come in. Who is this King of glory? The Lord who is strong and mighty, the Lord who is mighty in war. Lift up your gates, you princes, and be lifted up, you everlasting doors, and the King of glory shall come in. Who is this King of glory? The Lord of hosts, He is this King of glory. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Angkatlah kepalamu, hai pintu-pintu gerbang, dan terangkatlah kamu, hai pintu-pintu yang berabad- abad, supaya masuk Raja Kemuliaan! <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">"Siapakah itu Raja Kemuliaan?" "TUHAN,  jaya dan perkasa, TUHAN, perkasa dalam peperangan!” Angkatlah kepalamu, hai pintu-pintu gerbang, dan terangkatlah kamu, hai pintu-pintu yang berabad-abad, supaya masuk Raja Kemuliaan! </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">"Siapakah Dia itu Raja Kemuliaan?" "TUHAN semesta alam, Dialah Raja Kemuliaan!" ALLELUIA</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            ارفعوا أيها الرؤساءُ ابوابَكُم، وارتفعي أيتُها الأبوابُ الدهريّةُ، فيدخلَ مَلكُ المجدِ. مَنْ هو هذا مَلكُ المجدِ؟ الربُّ العزيزُ القديرُ، الربُّ القويُّ في الحروبِ. ارفعوا أيها الرؤساءُ أبوابَكُم، وارتفعي أيتها الأبوابُ الدهريّةُ، فيدخلَ مَلكُ المجدِ. مَنْ هو هذا مَلكُ المجدِ؟ ربُّ القواتِ، هذا هو مَلكُ المجدِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>