<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 24 - To You, O Lord...         </language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur 25 - Kepada-Mu, ya Tuhan, kuangkat jiwaku;...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الرابع والعشرون - إليكَ يا ربّ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            To You, O Lord, I have lifted up my soul. O my God, I have trusted in You; let me not be ashamed forever, nor let my enemies mock me. For all who wait for You shall not be ashamed; let them be ashamed who wrought iniquity in vain. Show me Your ways, O Lord, and teach me Your paths. Lead me to Your truth, and teach me; for You are God my Savior; and for You I have waited the whole day. Remember, O Lord, Your compassions and Your mercies, for they exist from everlasting. The sins of my youth and those of my ignorance do not remember; and according to Your mercy remember me, for the sake of Your goodness, O Lord.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kepada-Mu, ya Tuhan, kuangkat jiwaku; <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Allahku, kepada-Mu aku percaya; </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">janganlah kiranya aku mendapat malu; </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">janganlah musuh-musuhku beria-ria atas aku. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Ya, semua orang yang menantikan Engkau takkan mendapat malu; </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">yang mendapat malu ialah mereka yang berbuat khianat dengan tidak ada alasannya. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Beritahukanlah jalan jalan-Mu kepadaku, ya Tuhan, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">tunjukkanlah itu kepadaku. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Bawalah aku berjalan dalam kebenaran-Mu dan ajarlah aku, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">sebab Engkaulah Allah yang menyelamatkan aku, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Engkau kunanti-nantikan sepanjang hari. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Ingatlah segala rahmat-Mu dan kasih setia-Mu, ya Tuhan, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">sebab semuanya itu sudah ada sejak purbakala. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Dosa-dosaku pada waktu muda </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan pelanggaran pelanggaranku janganlah Kauingat, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">tetapi ingatlah kepadaku sesuai dengan kasih setia-Mu, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">oleh karena kebaikan-Mu, ya Tuhan.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            إليكَ ياربُّ رفعتُ نفسي، يا إلهي عليكَ توَّكلتُ. فلا تُخزِني إلى الأبدِ، ولا تشْمتْ بي أعدائي. لأنَّ جميعَ الذين ينتظرونَكَ لا يُخزَونَ. ليُخزَ الذين يصنعون الإثمَ باطِلاً. أظهِرْ لي ياربُّ طُرقَكَ، وعلِّمْني سُبُلَكَ. اهدِني إلى عدلِكَ وعلِّمْني. لأنَّكَ أنتَ هو اللهُ مُخلِّصي، وإياكَ انتظرتُ النهارَ كلَّهُ. اذكُرْ ياربُّ رأفاتِكَ ومراحِمَكَ، لأنَّها ثابتةٌ مُنذُ الأزلِ. خطايا شبابي وجهالاتي لا تذكُرْ. كرحمَتِكَ اذكُرْني أنتَ مِنْ أجلِ صلاحِكَ ياربُّ.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            For good and upright is the Lord; therefore He shall set a law for those who sin in the way. He shall guide the meek in judgment. He shall teach the meek His ways. All the ways of the Lord are mercy and truth to those who keep His covenant and His testimonies. For the sake of Your name, O Lord, You shall forgive my sin, for it is great.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tuhan itu baik dan benar; <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">sebab itu Ia menunjukkan jalan kepada orang yang sesat. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Ia membimbing orang orang yang rendah hati menurut hukum, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan Ia mengajarkan jalan Nya kepada orang-orang yang rendah hati. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Segala jalan Tuhan adalah kasih setia dan kebenaran </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">bagi orang yang berpegang pada perjanjian-Nya dan peringatan-peringatan-Nya. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Oleh karena nama-Mu, ya Tuhan, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">ampunilah kesalahanku, sebab besar kesalahan itu.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            الربُّ صالِحٌ ومُستقيمٌ، لذلِكَ يُرشِدُ الذين يُخطئونَ في الطريقِ. يَهدي الودعاءَ في الحُكمِ، يُعلِّمُ الودعاءَ طُرُقَهُ. جميعُ طُرُقِ الربِّ رحمةٌ وحقٌ لحافِظي عهدِهِ وشهاداتِهِ. مِنْ أجلِ اسمِكَ ياربُّ اغفِرْ لي خَطيئَتِي لأنَّها كثيرةٌ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Who is the man that fears the Lord? He shall set a law for him in the way which pleases Him. His soul shall dwell in good things, and his seed shall inherit the earth. The Lord is the strength of those who fear Him, and the name of the Lord is for those who revere Him, and His covenant He will manifest to them. My eyes are ever looking towards the Lord, for He will draw my feet out of the snare.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Siapakah orang yang takut akan Tuhan? <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Kepadanya Tuhan menunjukkan jalan yang harus dipilihnya. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Orang itu sendiri akan menetap dalam kebahagiaan </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan anak cucunya akan mewarisi bumi. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Tuhan bergaul karib dengan orang yang takut akan Dia, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan perjanjian-Nya diberitahukan-Nya kepada mereka. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Mataku tetap terarah kepada Tuhan, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">sebab Ia mengeluarkan kakiku dari jaring.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            مَنْ هو الإنسانُ الخائفُ الربَّ، يُرشِدُهُ في الطريقِ التي ارتضاها. نفسُهُ في الخيراتِ تثبتُ، ونسلُهُ يرثُ الأرضَ. الربُّ عِزٌّ لخائفيهِ، واسمُ الربِّ لأتقيائِهِ. ولهُم يُعلنُ عهدَهُ. عينايَ تنظُرانِ إلى الربِّ في كلِّ حينٍ، لأنَّهُ يجتذِبُ مِنَ الفخِّ رِجلِي.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Look upon me, and have mercy on me, for I am an only child and poor. The afflictions of my heart have been multiplied; bring me out of my troubles. Behold my lowliness and my toil, and forgive all my sins. Look upon my enemies, for they have multiplied, and they have hated me with an unjust hatred. Keep my soul, and deliver me. Let me not be put to shame, for I have hoped in You. The harmless and upright joined themselves to me, for I waited for You, O Lord. Deliver Israel, O God, out of all his afflictions. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berpalinglah kepadaku dan kasihanilah aku, <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">sebab aku sebatang kara dan tertindas. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Lapangkanlah hatiku yang sesak </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan keluarkanlah aku dari kesulitanku! </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Tiliklah sengsaraku dan kesukaranku, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan ampunilah segala dosaku. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Lihatlah, betapa banyaknya musuhku, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan bagaimana mereka membenci aku dengan sangat mendalam. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Jagalah kiranya jiwaku dan lepaskanlah aku;</span></div><div>janganlah aku mendapat malu, sebab aku berlindung pada-Mu. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Ketulusan dan kejujuran kiranya mengawal aku, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">sebab aku menanti nantikan Engkau. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Ya Allah, bebaskanlah orang Israel </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dari segala kesesakannya. Alleluia.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            انظُرْ إليَّ وارحَمْني، لأنِّي ابنٌ وحيدٌ وفقيرٌ أنا. أحزانُ قلبي قد كثُرَتْ، أخرِجْني مِنْ شَدائدي. انظُرْ إلى ذُلِّي وتعبي. واغفِرْ لي جميعَ خطايايَ. انظُرْ إلى أعدائي فإنَّهُم قد كثُروا وأبغضوني ظُلْماً. احفظْ نَفسي ونجِّني، لا أُخزى لأنِّي عليكَ توَّكلتُ. الذين لا شرَّ فيهِم والمستقيمونَ لصقوا بي، لأنِّي انتظرتُكَ ياربُّ. يا اللهُ أنقِذْ إسرائيلَ مِنْ جميعِ شدائدِهِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>