<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 28 - Bring to the Lord...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 28 - Kepada TUHAN,  hai penghuni ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الثامن والعشرون - قدِّموا للربِّ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Bring to the Lord, O sons of God, bring to the Lord young rams; bring to the Lord glory and honor. Bring to the Lord glory to His name; worship the Lord in His holy court.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kepada TUHAN,  hai penghuni surgawi, kepada TUHAN sajalah kemuliaan dan kekuatan! Berilah kepada TUHAN kemuliaan nama-Nya, sujudlah kepada TUHAN dengan berhiaskan kekudusan!         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            قدِّموا للربِّ يا أبناءَ اللهِ. قدِّموا للربِّ أبناءَ الكباشِ. قدِّموا للربِّ مجداً وكرامةً. قدِّموا للربِّ مجداً لاسمِهِ. اسجدوا للربِّ في دارِ قدسِهِ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            The voice of the Lord is upon the waters; God of glory has thundered; the Lord is upon the many waters. The voice of the Lord is mighty; the voice of the Lord is in great beauty. The voice of the Lord breaks the cedar; the Lord will break the cedar of Lebanon. And He will beat them small like the calf of Lebanon, and the beloved one like a son of the unicorn. The voice of the Lord cuts a flame of fire. The voice of the Lord shakes the wilderness; the Lord will shake the wilderness of Kadesh. The voice of the Lord strengthens the deer, and will uncover the forests, and in His holy temple every one speaks of glory. The Lord dwells in the flood, and the Lord will sit as a king forever. The Lord will give strength to His people; the Lord will bless His people with peace. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Suara TUHAN di atas air, Allah yang mulia mengguntur, TUHAN di atas air yang besar. Suara TUHAN penuh kekuatan, suara TUHAN penuh semarak. Suara TUHAN mematahkan pohon aras, bahkan, TUHAN menumbangkan pohon aras Libanon. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Ia membuat gunung Libanon melompat-lompat seperti anak lembu, dan gunung Siryon seperti anak banteng. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Suara TUHAN menyemburkan nyala api. Suara TUHAN membuat padang gurun gemetar, TUHAN membuat padang gurun Kadesh gemetar. Suara TUHAN membuat beranak rusa betina yang mengandung, bahkan, hutan digundulinya; dan di dalam bait-Nya setiap orang berseru: “Hormat!" </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">TUHAN bersemayam diatas air bah, TUHAN bersemayam sebagai Raja untuk selama-lamanya. TUHAN kiranya memberikan kekuatan kepada umat-Nya, TUHAN kiranya memberkati umat- Nya dengan sejahtera! ALLELUIA!</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            صوتُ الربِّ على المياهِ. إلهُ المجدِ أرعدَ. الربُّ على المياهِ الكثيرةِ. صوتُ الربِّ بقوةٍ. صوتُ الربِّ بجلالٍ عظيمٍ. صوتُ الربِّ يُحطِّمُ الأرزَ. الربُّ يُكسِّرُ أرزَ لُبنانَ ويسحقُها مِثلَ عِجلٍ. لُبنانَ، وسِريونَ، مِثلَ ابنِ وحيدِ القرنِ. صوتُ الربِّ يقطعُ لهيبَ النارِ. صوتُ الربِّ يُزلزلُ القفرَ. الربُّ يُزلزلُ بريةَ قادِشَ. صوتُ الربِّ يُولِّدُ الأيائلَ ويكشفُ الغاباتِ. وفي هيكلِهِ المُقدَّسِ كلُّ واحدٍ ينطقُ بالمجدِ. الربُّ يسكنُ في الطوفانِ، الربُّ يجلسُ مَلِكاً إلى الأبدِ. الربُّ يُعطي شعبَهُ قوةً، الربُّ يُباركُ شعبَهُ بالسلامِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>