<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 3 - O Lord, why have they...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Psalm 3 - Nyanyian pagi dalam menghadapi musuh</language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الثالث - يا ربّ لماذا كثر...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O Lord, why have they who afflict me multiplied? Many have risen up upon me. Many say unto my soul, “There is no salvation for him in his God.” But You, O Lord, are my supporter, my glory, and the elevation of my head.         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true"><div>Ya TUHAN,  betapa banyaknya lawanku! Banyak orang yang bangkit menyerang aku; banyak orang yang berkata tentang aku: "Baginya tidak ada pertolongan dari pada Allah." <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Tetapi Engkau, TUHAN, adalah perisai yang melindungi aku, Engkaulah kemuliaanku dan yang mengangkat kepalaku.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            ياربُّ لماذا كثُرَ الذينَ يحزنونَني، كثيرونَ قاموا عليَّ. كثيرونَ يقولونَ لنفسي، ليسَ لهُ خلاصٌ بإلهِهِ. أنتَ ياربُّ أنتَ هو ناصري، مجدي ورافعُ رأسي.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            With my voice I cried unto the Lord, and He heard me out of His holy mountain. I laid down and slept; and I arose; for the Lord is He who supports me. I will not be afraid of ten thousands of people, who surround me; who have risen upon me. Rise, O Lord, save me, O my God, for You have smitten all who are enemies to me without cause. The teeth of the sinners You have broken. Salvation is the Lord’s, and His blessing is upon His people. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true"><div>Dengan nyaring aku berseru kepada TUHAN, dan Ia menjawab aku dari gunung-Nya yang kudus. Aku membaringkan diri, lalu tidur; aku bangun, sebab TUHAN  menopang aku. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Aku tidak takut kepada puluhan ribu orang yang siap mengepung aku. Bangkitlah, TUHAN, tolonglah aku, ya Allahku! Ya, Engkau telah memukul rahang semua musuhku, dan mematahkan gigi orang-orang fasik. Dari TUHAN dating pertolongan. Berkat-Mu atas umat-Mu! ALLELUIA.</span></div><div><br/></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            بصَوتي إلى الربِّ صرختُ. فاستجابَ لي مِنْ جبلِ قُدسِهِ. أنا اضطجعتُ ونِمتُ، ثم استيقَظتُ لأنَّ الربَّ ناصري. فلا أخافُ مِنْ ربواتِ الجموعِ المُحيطينَ بي القائمينَ عليَّ. قُمْ ياربُّ خلِّصْني يا إلهي، لأنكَ ضربتَ كلَّ مَنْ يُعاديني باطِلاً. أسنانُ الخطاةِ سحقتَها. للربِّ الخلاصُ وعلى شعبِهِ بركتُهُ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>