<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 45 - Our God is our refuge...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 45 - Allah itu bagi kita tempat ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الخامس والأربعون - إلهُنا ملجأُنا...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Our God is our refuge and our strength; He is our help in the afflictions that have come heavily upon us. Therefore we shall not fear when the earth is troubled, and the mountains are removed into the heart of the seas. The waters have roared and been troubled, the mountains have been troubled by His might. The streams of the river gladden the city of God; the Most High has sanctified His dwelling. God is in the midst of her; she shall not be moved; God shall help her face. The nations were troubled; the kingdoms tottered; He gave forth His voice, the earth shook. The Lord, God of hosts, is with us; the God of Jacob is our helper.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Allah itu bagi kita tempat perlindungan dan kekuatan, sebagai penolong dalam kesesakan sangat terbukti. Sebab itu kita tidak akan takut, sekalipun bumi berubah, sekalipun gunung-gunung goncang di dalam laut; sekalipun ribut dan berbuih airnya, sekalipun gunung-gunung goyang oleh geloranya. Kota Allah, kediaman Yang Mahatinggi, disukakan oleh aliran-aliran sebuah sungai. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Allah ada di dalamnya, kota itu tidak akan goncang; Allah akan menolongnya menjelang pagi. Bangsa-bangsa ribut, kerajaan-kerajaan goncang, Ia memperdengarkan suara-Nya, dan bumipun hancur. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">TUHAN semesta alam menyertai kita, kota benteng kita ialah Allah Yakub.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            إلهُنا ملجأُنا وقوتُنا، ومُعينُنا في شدائدِنا التي أصابتنا جداً. لذلكَ لا نخشى إذا تزعزعتْ الأرضُ، وانقلبتْ الجبالُ إلى قلبِ البحارِ. تعِجُّ المياهُ وتجيشُ، وتتزعزعُ الجبالُ بعزّتِهِ. مجاري الأنهارِ تُفرِّحُ مدينةَ اللهِ. لقد قدَّسَ العليُّ مسكنَهُ، واللهُ في وسطِها فلن تتزعزعَ. يُعينُ اللهُ وجهَها. اضطربتْ الأممُ، وماجتْ الممالكُ. أبدى صوتَهُ، فتزلزلتْ الأرضُ. الربُّ إلهُ القواتِ معَنا، ناصِرُنا هو إلهُ يعقوبَ.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            Come, you, and behold the works of the Lord, the wonders which He has set upon the earth. Putting an end to wars to the ends of the earth; He will crush their bows, and break their weapons, and burn their bucklers in the fire. Be still, and know that I am God; I will be exalted among the nations, I will be exalted upon the earth. The Lord God of hosts is with us; the God of Jacob is our helper. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sela Pergilah, pandanglah pekerjaan TUHAN, yang mengadakan pemusnahan di bumi, yang menghentikan peperangan sampai ke ujung bumi, yang mematahkan busur panah, menumpulkan tombak, membakar kereta-kereta perang dengan api! <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">"Diamlah dan ketahuilah, bahwa Akulah Allah! Aku ditinggikan di antara bangsa-bangsa, ditinggikan di bumi!” TUHAN semesta alam menyertai kita, kota benteng kita ialah Allah Yakub. ALLELUIA.!</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            هلُمَّ فانظروا أعمالَ الربِّ، التي جعلَها آياتٍ على الأرضِ. الذي ينزعُ الحروبَ مِنْ أقاصي الأرضِ. يسحقُ قِسيَّهُم ويكسِرُ سلاحَهُم، ويُحرِقُ أتراسَهُم بالنارِ. ثابِروا واعلموا أنّي أنا هو اللهُ، أرتفِعُ بينَ الأممِ وأتعالى في الأرضِ. الربُّ إلهُ القواتِ معَنا، ناصِرُنا هو إلهُ يعقوبَ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>