<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 46 - Clap your hands...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 47 - Hai segala bangsa, bertepuktanganlah...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور السادس والأربعون - يا جميعَ الأممِ صفِّقوا بأيديكُم...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Clap your hands, all you nations; shout to God with a voice of exultation. For the Lord is most high and fearful; He is a great king over all the earth. He has subdued peoples under us, and nations under our feet. He has chosen us for His inheritance, the beauty of Jacob whom He loved.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Hai segala bangsa, bertepuktanganlah, elu-elukanlah Allah dengan sorak-sorai! Sebab TUHAN, Yang Mahatinggi, adalah dahsyat, Raja yang besar atas seluruh bumi. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Ia menaklukkan bangsa-bangsa ke bawah kuasa kita, suku-suku bangsa ke bawah kaki kita, Ia memilih bagi kita tanah pusaka kita, kebanggaan Yakub yang dikasihi-Nya.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            يا جميعَ الأممِ صفِّقوا بأيديكُم، هلّلوا للهِ بصوتِ الابتهاجِ. لأنَّ الربَّ عالٍ ومرهوبٌ، ملكٌ كبيرٌ على كافّةِ الأرضِ. أخضعَ الشعوبَ لنا، والأممَ تحتَ أقدامِنا، اختارَنا ميراثاً لهُ، جمالَ يعقوبَ الذي أحبَّهُ.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            God has ascended with a shout, and the Lord with a sound of a trumpet. Sing praises to our God, sing praises; sing praises to our King, sing praises; for God is king of all the earth. Sing praises with understanding, for the Lord reigned over all the nations; God sits upon His holy throne. Rulers of the people have assembled with God of Abraham, for God's mighty ones have been greatly exalted upon the earth. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Allah telah naik dengan diiringi sorak-sorai, ya TUHAN itu, dengan diiringi bunyi sangkakala. Bermazmurlah bagi Allah, bermazmurlah, bermazmurlah bagi Raja kita, bermazmurlah! Sebab Allah adalah Raja seluruh bumi, bermazmurlah dengan nyanyian pengajaran! <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Allah memerintah sebagai raja atas bangsa-bangsa, Allah bersemayam di atas takhta-Nya yang kudus. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Para pemuka bangsa-bangsa berkumpul sebagai umat Allah Abraham. Sebab Allah yang empunya perisai-perisai bumi; Ia sangat dimuliakan. ALLELUIA!</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            صعِدَ اللهُ بتهليلٍ، والربُّ بصوتِ البوقِ. رتِّلوا لإلهِنا رتِّلوا، رتِّلوا لمليكِنا رتِّلوا، لأنَّ الربَّ هو ملكُ الأرضِ كلِّها. رتِّلوا بفهمٍ لأنَّ الربَّ قد ملكَ على جميعِ الأممِ. اللهُ جلسَ على كرسيّهِ المُقدَّسِ. رؤساءُ الشعوبِ اجتمعوا معَ إلهِ إبراهيمَ، لأنَّ أعزاءَ اللهِ قد ارتفعوا في الأرضِ جداً. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>