<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 56 - Have mercy upon me...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 57 - Kasihanilah aku, ya Allah ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور السادس والخمسون - ارحمْني يا اللهُ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Have mercy upon me, O God, have mercy upon me; for my soul has trusted in You, and in the shadow of Your wings I will hope, until the iniquity passes away. I will cry to God Most High; God who has benefitted me. He sent from heaven and saved me; He gave over to reproach those who trampled on me. God has sent forth His mercy and His truth, and He has delivered my soul from the midst of young lions; I laid down to sleep, while troubled. As for the sons of men, their teeth are weapons and arrows, and their tongue a sharp sword.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kasihanilah aku, ya Allah, kasihanilah aku, sebab kepada-Mulah jiwaku berlindung; dalam naungan sayap-Mu aku akan berlindung, sampai berlalu penghancuran itu.</div><div>Aku berseru kepada  Allah, Yang Mahatinggi, kepada Allah yang menyelesaikannya bagiku. Kiranya Ia mengirim utusan dari surga dan menyelamatkan aku, mencela orang-orang yang menginjak-injak aku.</div><div> Sela Kiranya Allah mengirim kasih setia dan kebenaran-Nya. Aku terbaring di tengah-tengah singa yang suka menerkam anak-anak manusia, yang giginya laksana tombak dan panah, dan lidahnya laksana pedang tajam.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            ارحمْني يا اللهُ ارحمْني، فإنَّهُ عليكَ توكلَتْ نفسي. وبظلِّ جناحَيكَ أعتصِمُ، إلى أن يعبرَ الإثمُ. أصرخُ إلى اللهِ العليِّ، الإلهِ المُحسنِ إليَّ. أرسلَ مِنَ السماءِ فخلَّصَني، وجعلَ العارَ على الذينَ يطأونَني. أرسلَ اللهُ رحمتَهُ وحقَّهُ، وخلَّصَ نفسي مِنْ بينِ الأشبالِ إذ نمتُ مُضطرباً. أسنانُ أبناءِ البشرِ سلاحٌ وسهامٌ، ولسانُهُم سيفٌ مرهفٌ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Be You exalted, O God, above the heavens, and Your glory above all the earth. They have prepared snares for my feet, and have bowed down my soul; they have dug a pit before me, and fallen into it.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Tinggikanlah diri-Mu mengatasi langit, ya Allah! Biarlah kemuliaan-Mu mengatasi seluruh bumi! Mereka memasang jaring terhadap langkah-langkahku, ditundukkannya jiwaku, mereka menggali lobang di depanku, tetapi mereka sendiri jatuh ke dalamnya.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            اللهُمَّ ارتفعْ على السماواتِ، وليرتفعْ مجدُكَ على سائرِ الأرضِ. نصبوا لرجليَّ فِخاخاً وأحنوا نفسي، حفروا قُدامَ وجهي حُفرةً فسقطوا فيها.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            My heart, O God, is ready, my heart is ready; I will sing, and chant in my glory. Arise, my glory; arise, psaltery and harp; I will rise early. O Lord, I will give thanks to You among the peoples; I will sing to You among the nations. For Your mercy has been magnified up to the heavens, and Your truth up to the clouds. Be You exalted, O God, above the heavens, and Your glory above all the earth. ALLELUIA         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Hatiku siap, ya Allah, hatiku siap; aku mau menyanyi, aku mau bermazmur. Bangunlah, haijiwaku, bangunlah, hai gambus dan kecapi, aku mau membangunkan fajar!</div><div>Aku mau bersyukur kepada-Mu di antara bangsa-bangsa, ya Tuhan, aku mau bermazmur bagi-Mu di antara suku- suku bangsa; sebab kasih setia-Mu besar sampai ke langit, dan kebenaran-Mu sampai ke awan-awan. Tinggikanlah diri-Mu mengatasi langit, ya Allah! Biarlah kemuliaan-Mu mengatasi seluruh bumi! ALLELUIA.!</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            مُستعِدٌ قلبي يا اللهُ، مُستعِدٌ قلبي، أسبِّحُ وأرتِّلُ في تمجيدي. استيقظْ يا مجدي، استيقظْ أيها المِزمارُ والقيثارةُ. أنا أستيقظُ مُبكراً. أعترفُ لكَ في الشعوبِ ياربُّ، وأرتِّلُ لكَ في الأممِ. لأنَّ رحمتَكَ قد عظُمَتْ إلى السماواتِ، وإلى السحابِ عدلُكَ. اللهُمَّ ارتفعْ على السماواتِ، وليرتفعْ مجدُكَ على سائرِ الأرضِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>