<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 6 - O Lord, do not rebuke me...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Psalm 6 - Doa dalam pergumulan</language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور السادس - يا ربّ لا تُبكّتني...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O Lord, do not rebuke me in Your anger, nor chasten me in Your wrath. Have mercy on me, O Lord, for I am weak; heal me, O Lord, for my bones are troubled, and my soul is grievously troubled. But You, O Lord, how long? Return, deliver my soul; revive me for the sake of Your mercy. For in death there is no one who is remembering You; and in Hades who is able to give thanks to You? I became wearied in my groaning; I shall wash my bed every night; I shall wet my couch with my tears. My eye is troubled because of anger; I have grown old because of all my enemies.         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true"><div>Ya TUHAN,  janganlah menghukum aku dalam murka-Mu, dan janganlah menghajar aku dalam kepanasan amarah-Mu. Kasihanilah aku, TUHAN, sebab aku merana; sembuhkanlah aku, TUHAN, sebab tulang-tulangku gemetar, dan jiwaku pun sangat terkejut; tetapi Engkau, TUHAN, berapa lama lagi?</div><div>Kembalilah pula, TUHAN, luputkanlah jiwaku, selamatkanlah aku oleh karena kasih setia-Mu. Sebab di dalam maut tidaklah orang ingat kepada-Mu; siapakah yang akan bersyukur kepada-Mu di dalam dunia orang mati.</div><div>Lesu aku karena mengeluh; setiap malam aku menggenangi tempat tidurku, dengan air mataku aku membanjiri ranjangku. Mataku mengidap karena saki thati, rabun karena semua lawanku.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            ياربُّ لا تُبكِّتْني بغضبِكَ، ولا تؤدِّبْني بسخطِكَ. ارحَمْني ياربُّ فإنِّي ضعيفٌ، اشفِني ياربُّ فإنَّ عظامي قد اضطربَتْ ونفسي قد انزعجَتْ جداً. وأنتَ ياربُّ فإلى متى؟ عُدْ ونجِّ نفسي، وأحيني مِنْ أجلِ رحمتِكَ. لأنَّه ليسَ في الموتِ مَنْ يذكرُكَ ولا في الجحيمِ مَنْ يعترفُ لكَ. تعبتُ في تنهُّدي. أعوِّمُ كلَّ ليلةٍ سَريري، وبدموعي أبِلُّ فِراشي. تعكَّرتْ مِنَ الغضبِ عينايَ. شاخَتْ مِنْ سائرِ أعدائي.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Depart away from me, all who do iniquity, for the Lord has heard the voice of my weeping. The Lord has heard my petition; the Lord has accepted my prayer. All my enemies shall be put to shame and greatly troubled; they shall be turned back and put to shame speedily. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true">Menjauhlah dari padaku, kamu sekalian yang melakukan kejahatan, sebab TUHAN telah mendengar tangisku; TUHAN  telah mendengar permohonanku, TUHAN menerima doaku. Semua musuhku mendapat malu dan sangat terkejut; mereka mundur dan mendapat malu dalam sekejap mata. ALLELUIA.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            ابعدوا عنِّي يا جميعَ فاعلي الإثمِ. لأنَّ الربَّ قد سمعَ صوتَ بُكائي. الربُّ سمعَ تضرُّعي، الربُّ لصلاتي قبِلَ، فليخزَ وليضطرِبْ جداً جميعُ أعدائي، وليرتدُّوا إلى ورائهِم بالخزي سريعاً جِداً. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>