<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 62 - O God, my God...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 63 - Ya Allah, Engkaulah Allahku ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الثاني والستون - يا اللهُ إلهي...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O God, my God, I will rise up early unto You; for my soul has thirsted for You, to make my flesh blossom for You, in a barren land and a trackless and dry place. So I have appeared before You in the Holy, to see Your power and Your glory. For Your mercy is chosen more than life; my lips shall praise You. So I will bless You during my life; I will lift up my hands in Your name. My soul shall be filled as with marrow and fatness; and my lips of joy shall praise Your name.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Allah, Engkaulah Allahku, aku mencari Engkau, jiwaku haus kepada-Mu, tubuhku rindu kepada-Mu, seperti tanah yang kering dan tandus, tiada berair.</div><div>Demikianlah aku memandang kepada-Mu di tempat kudus, sambil melihat kekuatan-Mu dan kemuliaan-Mu. Sebab kasih setia-Mu lebih baik dari pada hidup; bibirku akan memegahkan Engkau.</div><div>Demikianlah aku mau memuji Engkau seumur hidupku dan menaikkan tanganku demi nama-Mu. Seperti dengan lemak dan sumsum jiwaku dikenyangkan, dan dengan bibir yang bersorak- sorai mulutku memuji-muji.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            يا اللهُ إلهي إليكَ أبكِّرُ، عطِشتْ إليكَ نفسي. يشتاقُ إليكَ جسدي، في أرضٍ مقفرةٍ وموضعٍ غيرِ مسلوكٍ ومكانٍ بِلا ماءٍ. هكذا ظهرتُ لكَ في القُدْسِ، لأرى قوّتَكَ ومجدَكَ. لأنَّ رحمتَكَ أفضلَ مِنَ الحياةِ. شفتايَ تُسبِّحانِكَ. لذلكَ أبارِكُكَ في حياتي، وباسمِكَ أرفعُ يديَّ. فتشبعُ نفسي كما مِنْ شحمٍ ودسمٍ. بشفاهِ الابتهاجِ نبارِكُ اسمَكَ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            I have remembered You on my bed; in the time of early morning I have usually meditated on You. For You have become unto me a helper, and under the shadow of Your wings I shall rejoice. My soul has kept very close behind You; Your right hand has upheld me. But those who seek to destroy my soul, shall go into the lowest parts of the earth. They shall be delivered up to the hand of the sword; they shall be portions for foxes. But the king shall rejoice in God; everyone who swears by him shall be proud; for the mouths of those who speak unjust things shall be shut. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Apabila aku ingat kepada-Mu di tempat tidurku, merenungkan Engkau sepanjang kawal malam, sungguh Engkau telah menjadi pertolonganku, dan dalam naungan sayap-Mu aku bersorak-sorai. Jiwaku melekat kepada-Mu, tangan kanan-Mu menopang aku.</div><div>Tetapi orang-orang yang berikhtiar mencabut nyawaku, akan masuk kebagian-bagian bumi yang paling bawah. Mereka akan diserahkan kepada kuasa pedang, mereka akan menjadi makanan anjing hutan.</div><div>Tetapi raja akan bersukacita di dalam Allah; setiap orang, yang bersumpah demi Dia, akan bermegah, karena mulut orang-orang yang mengatakan dusta akan disumbat. ALLELUIA.! </div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            كنتُ أذكرُكَ على فِراشي، وفي أوقاتِ الأسحارِ كنتُ أرتِّلُ لكَ. لأنَّكَ صِرتَ لي عَوناً، وبظلِّ جناحيكَ أبتهِجُ. التحقتْ نفسي وراءَكَ، ويمينُكَ عضَّدَتْني. أمَّا الذين طلبوا نفسي للهلاكِ، فيدخلونَ في أسافلِ الأرضِ. ويُدفعون إلى يدِّ السيفِ، ويكونون أنصِبةً للثعالبِ. أمَّا الملِكُ فيفرحُ باللهِ، ويفتخِرُ كلُّ مَنْ يحلفُ بِهِ. لأنَّ أفواهَ المتكلِّمين بالظلمِ تُسَدُّ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>