<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 69 - O God, be mindful...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 70 - Ya Allah, bersegeralah melepaskan aku ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور التاسع والستون - اللهُمّ التفِتْ إلى معونَتي...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O God, be mindful to my help; make haste, O Lord, to help me. Let them be ashamed and be scorned, those who seek my soul; let them be turned backward and put to shame, those who wish to do evil unto me. Let those who say to me, “Aha, aha,” be turned back in shame immediately. Let all who seek You exult and be glad in You, and let those who love Your salvation say continually, “Let the Lord be magnified.” But I am poor and weak, O God, help me. You are my Helper and Savior, O Lord, do not delay. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Allah, bersegeralah melepaskan aku, menolong aku, ya TUHAN Biarlah mendapat malu dan tersipu-sipu mereka yang ingin mencabut nyawaku; biarlah mundur dan kena noda mereka yang mengingini kecelakaanku; biarlah berbalik karena malu mereka yang mengatakan: "Syukur, syukur!” </div><div>Biarlah bergirang dan bersukacita karena Engkau semua orang yang mencari Engkau; biarlah merekayangmencintai keselamatan dari pada-Mu selalu berkata: "Allah itu besar!” Tetapi aku ini sengsara dan miskin--ya Allah, segeralah datang! Engkaulah yang menolong aku dan meluputkan aku; ya TUHAN, janganlah lambat datang!    ALLELUIA.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            اللهُمَّ التفِتْ إلى معونَتي، ياربُّ أسرعْ وأعِنِّي. ليُخزَ ويخجلْ طالِبو نفسي، وليرتدّْ إلى خلفٍ ويخجلْ الذين يبتغونَ ليَ الشرَّ. وليرجعْ بالخزي سريعاً القائلونَ لي: نَعِمَّاً نَعِمَّاً. وليبتهِجْ ويفرحْ بكَ جميعُ الذين يلتمِسونَكَ، وليقُلْ في كلِّ حينٍ مُحِبُّو خلاصِكَ: فليتعظمْ الربُّ. وأمَّا أنا فمسكينٌ وفقيرٌ، اللهُمَّ أعِنِّي. أنتَ مُعيني ومُخلِّصي ياربُّ فلا تُبطئْ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>