<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 8 - O Lord, our Lord...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Psalm 8 - Manusia hina sebagai mahluk mulia</language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الثامن - أيها الربّ ربّنا...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O Lord, our Lord, how wonderful Your name became in all the earth! For the greatness of Your splendor has been exalted above the heavens. Out of the mouth of babes and sucklings You have prepared praise, because of Your enemies, that You might put down an enemy and avenger.         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true"><div>Ya TUHAN, Tuhan kami, betapa mulianya nama-Mu di seluruh bumi! Keagungan-Mu yang mengatasi langit dinyanyikan.</div><div>Dari mulut bayi-bayi dan anak-anak yang menyusu telah Kauletakkan dasar kekuatan karena lawan-Mu, untuk membungkamkan musuh dan pendendam.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أيها الربُّ ربُّنا، ما أعجبَ اسمَكَ في الأرضِ كلِّها! لأنهُ قد ارتفعَ عظمُ جلالِكَ فوقَ السماواتِ. مِنْ أفواهِ الأطفالِ والرُضعانِ هيأتَ سُبْحاً، مِنْ أجلِ أعدائكَ، لتُسكِتَ عدواً ومُنتقماً.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            For I will regard the heavens, the work of Your fingers; the moon and stars You have established. What is man, that You have been mindful of him? Or the son of man, that You have visited him? You made him a little less than angels; You have crowned him with glory and honor; and You have set him upon the works of Your hands. You have put everything under his feet; all the sheep and oxen, and the beasts of the field, and the birds of the sky, and the fish of the sea that pass through the paths of the seas. O Lord our Lord, how wonderful Your name became in all the earth! ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian" spellcheck="true"><div>Jika aku melihat langit- Mu, buatan jari-Mu, bulan dan bintang-bintang yang Kautempatkan: apakah manusia, sehingga Engkau mengingatnya?  Apakah anak manusia, sehingga Engkau mengindahkannya?</div><div>Namun Engkau telah membuatnya hampir sama seperti Allah, dan telah memahkotainya dengan kemuliaan dan hormat.</div><div>Engkau membuat dia berkuasa atas buatan tangan-Mu; segala- galanya telah Kauletakkan di bawah kakinya: kambing domba dan lembu sapi sekalian, juga binatang-binatang di padang;  burung-burung di udara dan ikan-ikan di laut, dan apa yang melintasi arus lautan.</div><div>Ya TUHAN, Tuhan kami, betapa mulianya nama-Mu di seluruh bumi! ALLELUIA.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            لأنِّي أرى السماواتِ أعمالَ أصابعِكَ. القمرُ والنجومُ أنتَ أسستَها. مَنْ هو الإنسانُ حتى تذكُرَه، أو ابنُ الإنسانِ حتى تفتقِدَه؟! أنقصتَهُ قليلاً عن الملائكةِ. بالمجدِ والكرامةِ توَّجتَهُ، وعلى أعمالِ يديكَ أقمتَهُ. كلَّ شيءٍ أخضعتَ تحتَ قدميهِ، الغنمَ والبقرَ جميعاً وأيضاً بهائمَ الحقلِ، وطيورَ السماءِ وأسماكَ البحرِ السالكةَ في البحارِ. أيها الربُّ ربُّنا. ما أعجبَ اسمَكَ في الأرضِ كلِّها. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>