<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 83 - How beloved are Your dwellings...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 84 - Betapa disenangi tempat kediaman-Mu ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الثالث والثمانون - مساكنُكَ محبوبةٌ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            How beloved are Your dwellings, O Lord, God of hosts! My soul longs, and faints for the courts of the Lord; my heart and my flesh have exulted in the living God. For, the sparrow has found for himself a home, and the turtledove for herself a nest, where she may lay her young; Your altars, O Lord, God of hosts, my King, and my God.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Betapa disenangi tempat kediaman-Mu, ya TUHAN semesta alam Jiwaku hancur karena merindukan pelataran-pelataran TUHAN;  hatiku dan dagingku bersorak-sorai kepada Allah yang hidup. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Bahkan burung pipit telah mendapat sebuah rumah, dan burung layang-layang sebuah sarang, tempat menaruh anak-anaknya, pada mezbah-mezbah-Mu, ya TUHAN semesta alam, ya Rajaku dan Allahku!</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            مساكنُكَ محبوبةٌ ياربُّ إلهُ القواتِ. تشتاقُ وتذوبُ نفسي للدخولِ إلى ديارِ الربِّ. قلبي وجسمي قد ابتهجا بالإلهِ الحيِّ. لأنَّ العصفورَ وجدَ لهُ بيتاً، واليمامةَ عُشاً لتضعَ فيهِ أفراخَها. مذابحَكَ ياربُّ الهُ القواتِ، ملكي وإلهي.         </language>      </text>             <text>         <language id="English">            Blessed are all who dwell in Your house; they will praise You forever and ever. Blessed is the man whose help is from You, O Lord; he sets paths upward in his heart in the valley of weeping, in the place which he has appointed, for there the Law-Giver will grant blessings. They shall go from strength to strength; the God of gods shall be revealed in Zion.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berbahagialah orang-orang yang diam di rumah-Mu, yang terus-menerus memuji-muji Engkau. Berbahagialah manusia yang kekuatannya di dalam Engkau, yang berhasrat mengadakan ziarah! <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Apabila melintasi lembah Baka, mereka membuatnya menjadi tempat yang bermata air; bahkan hujan pada awal musim menyelubunginya dengan berkat. Mereka berjalan makin lama makin kuat, hendak menghadap Allah di Sion.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            طوبى لكلِّ الساكنينَ في بيتِكَ، يباركونَكَ إلى الأبدِ. طوبى للرجلِ الذي نُصرتُهُ مِنْ عِندِكَ ياربُّ، رتِّبْ مصاعِدَ في قلبِهِ. في وادي البُكاءِ، في المكانِ الذي قرّرَهُ. لأنَّ البركاتِ يُعطيها واضعُ الناموسِ. يسيرونَ مِنْ قوةٍ إلى قوةٍ، يتجلّى إلهُ الآلهةِ في صِهيَونَ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O Lord, God of hosts, hear my prayer; hearken, O God of Jacob. Behold, O God our defender, and look upon the face of Your anointed. For one day in Your courts is better than thousands. I chose to throw myself down in the house of God, more than to dwell in the tents of the sinners. For the Lord God loves mercy and truth; He shall give grace and glory; the Lord shall not withhold good things from those who walk in innocence. O Lord God of hosts, blessed is the man who hopes in You. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya TUHAN,  Allah semesta alam, dengarkanlah doaku, pasanglah telinga, ya Allah Yakub.  Sela. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Lihatlah perisai kami, ya Allah, pandanglah wajah orang yang Kauurapi! Sebab lebih baik satu hari di pelataran-Mu dari pada seribu hari di tempat lain; lebih baik berdiri di ambang pintu rumah Allahku dari pada diam di kemah-kemah orang fasik. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Sebab TUHAN Allah adalah matahari dan perisai; kasih dan kemuliaan Ia berikan; Ia tidak menahan kebaikan dari orang yang hidup tidak bercela. Ya TUHAN semesta alam, berbahagialah manusia yang percaya kepada-Mu! ALLELUIA.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أيها الربُّ إلهُ القواتِ استمِعْ لصلاتي، أنصِتْ يا إلهَ يعقوبَ. وانظرْ أيها الإلهُ ناصِرُنا، واطّلِعْ إلى وجهِ مسيحِكَ. لأنَّ يوماً صالحاً في ديارِكَ خيرٌ مِنْ آلافٍ. اخترتُ لنفسي أن أُطرَحَ على بابِ بيتِ اللهِ، أفضلَ مِنْ أن أسكنَ في مظالِّ الخطاةِ. لأنَّ الربَّ الإلهَ يُحبُّ الرحمةَ والحقَّ، ويُعطي مجداً ونِعمةً. الربُّ لا يمنعُ الخيراتِ عن السالكينَ بالدعةِ. ياربُّ إلهُ القواتِ، طوبى للإنسانِ المتكلِ عليكَ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>