<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 84 - O Lord, You have taken pleasure...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 85- Engkau telah berkenan kepada tanah-Mu, ya TUHAN ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الرابع والثمانون - رضيتَ ياربُّ عن...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O Lord, You have taken pleasure in Your land; You have turned back the captivity of Jacob. You have forgiven the transgressions of Your people; You have covered all their sins. You have dissolved all Your wrath; You have turned from the wrath of Your anger. Turn us, O God of our salvation, and turn Your anger away from us. Would You be angry with us forever? Or will You extend Your wrath from generation to generation? O God, You shall turn back and revive us, and Your people shall rejoice in You. Show us Your mercy, O Lord, and grant us Your salvation. I will hear what the Lord God will speak in me, for He shall speak peace to His people, and to His saints, and to those who turned back to Him with all their heart. Moreover His salvation is near to all who fear Him, to make glory dwell in our land. Mercy and truth have met together, righteousness and peace have greeted each other. Truth has sprung out of the earth, and righteousness has looked down from heaven. For the Lord shall give goodness, and our land shall yield its fruit. Righteousness shall go first before Him, and shall set His steps in the way. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Engkau telah berkenan kepada tanah-Mu, ya TUHAN, telah memulihkan keadaan Yakub. Engkau telah mengampuni kesalahan umat-Mu, telah menutupi segala dosa mereka. Engkau telah menyurutkan segala gemas-Mu, telah meredakan murka-Mu yang menyala-nyala.</div><div>Pulihkanlah kami, ya Allah penyelamat kami, dan tiadakanlah sakit hati-Mu kepada kami. Untuk selamanyakah Engkau murka atas kami dan melanjutkan murka-Mu turun-temurun?</div><div>Apakah Engkau tidak mau menghidupkan kami kembali, sehingga umat-Mu bersukacita karena Engkau? Perlihatkanlah kepada kami kasih setia-Mu, ya TUHAN, dan berikanlah kepada kami keselamatan dari pada-Mu! </div><div>Aku mau mendengar apa yang hendak difirmankan Allah, TUHAN.</div><div>nBukankah Ia hendak berbicara tentang damai kepada umat-Nya dan kepada orang-orang yang dikasihi-Nya, supaya jangan mereka kembali kepada kebodohan? Sesungguhnya keselamatan dari pada-Nya dekat pada orang-orang yang takut akan Dia, sehingga kemuliaan diam di negeri kita. </div><div>Kasih dan kesetiaan akan bertemu, keadilan dan damai sejahtera akan bercium-ciuman. Kesetiaan akan tumbuh dari bumi, dan keadilan akan menjenguk dari langit. Bahkan TUHAN akan memberikan kebaikan, dan negeri kita akan memberihasilnya. Keadilan akan berjalan di hadapan-Nya, dan akan membuat jejak kaki-Nya menjadi jalan. ALLELUIA.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            رضِيتَ ياربُّ عن أرضِكَ، رددتَ سبيَ يعقوبَ. غفرتَ آثامَ شعبِكَ، سترتَ جميعَ خطاياهُم. حللتَ كلَّ رِجزِكَ، رجِعتَ عن سَخَطِ غضبِكَ. ردِّنا يا إلهَ خلاصِنا، واصرفْ غضبَكَ عنّا. هل إلى الأبدِ تغضبُ علينا، أو تُواصِلُ رِجزَكَ مِنْ جيلٍ إلى جيلٍ؟ أنتَ يا اللهُ تعودُ فتُحيينا، وشعبُكَ يفرحُ بكَ. أرِنا ياربُّ رحمتَكَ، وأعطِنا خلاصَكَ. إنِّي أسمعُ ما يتكلمُ بهِ الربُّ الإلهُ، لأنَّهُ يتكلمُ بالسلامِ لشعبِهِ ولقديسيهِ، وللذينَ رجَعوا إليهِ بكلِّ قلوبِهِم. لأنَّ خلاصَهُ قريبٌ مِنْ جميعِ خائفيهِ، ليسكنْ المجدُ في أرضِنا. الرحمةُ والحقُّ تلاقيا، البرُّ والسلامُ تلاثما. الحقُّ مِنَ الأرضِ أشرقَ، والبرُّ مِنَ السماءِ تطلّعَ. لأنَّ الربَّ يُعطي الخيراتِ، وأرضَنا تُعطي ثمرَها. البرُّ أمامَهُ يسلكُ ويطأُ في طريقِ خطواتِهِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>