<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 86 - His foundations...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Psalm 87 - Di gunung-gunung yang kudus ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور السادس والثمانون - أساساتُهُ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            His foundations are in the holy mountains. The Lord loves the gates of Zion, more than all the dwellings of Jacob. Glorious things have been spoken of You, O city of God.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Di gunung-gunung yang kudus ada kota yang dibangunkan-Nya: TUHAN lebih mencintai pintu-pintu gerbang Sion dari pada segala tempat kediaman Yakub. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Hal-hal yang mulia dikatakan tentang engkau, ya kota Allah.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أساساتُهُ في الجبالِ المُقدسةِ. يُحبُّ الربُّ أبوابَ صِهيَونَ، أفضلَ مِنْ جميعِ مساكنِ يعقوبَ. أعمالٌ مجيدةٌ قد قيلَتْ عنكِ يا مدينةَ اللهِ.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            I shall make mention of Rahab and Babylon, those who know me; behold the foreigners, and Tyre, and the people of Ethiopia, these were there. “My mother Zion,” a man will say; and a man was living in her, and the Most High Himself has founded her forever. The Lord shall tell it in the writings of peoples and princes, these who were in her. The dwelling of all who rejoice is within you. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Aku menyebut Rahab dan Babel di antara orang-orang yang mengenal Aku, bahkan Filistea, Tirus dan Etiopia: "Ini dilahirkan di sana.”  Tetapi tentang Sion dikatakan: "Seorang demi seorang dilahirkan di dalamnya," dan Dia, Yang Mahatinggi, menegakkannya. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">TUHAN menghitung pada waktu mencatat bangsa-bangsa: "Ini dilahirkan di sana.” Dan orang menyanyi-nyanyi sambil menari beramai-ramai: " Segala mata airku ada di dalammu." ALLELUIA.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أذكرُ رَهَبَ وبابلَ اللتينِ تعرِفانَني. هوذا القبائلُ الغريبةُ وصورُ وشعبُ الحبشةِ، هؤلاءِ كانوا هناكَ. صِهيَونُ الأمُّ تقولُ إنَّ إنساناً وإنساناً وُلِدَ فيها، وهو العليُّ الذي أسَّسَها إلى الأبدِ. الربُّ يُحدِّثُ في كتبِ الشعوبِ والرؤساءِ، أولئِكَ الذينَ وُلِدوا فيها. لأنَّ سُكنَى الفرحينَ جميعِهِم فيكِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>