<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 92 - The Lord has reigned; He has clothed...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 93 - TUHAN adalah Raja, Ia berpakaian ...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمور الثاني والتسعون - الربُّ قد ملكَ، ولبسَ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            The Lord has reigned; He has clothed Himself with beauty. The Lord has clothed and girded Himself with strength; for He has established the world, which shall not be moved. Your throne is prepared from the beginning; You are from everlasting. The rivers have lifted up, O Lord; the rivers have lifted up their voices; the rivers shall lift up their voices, from the voices of many waters. The billows of the waves of the sea are wonderful; the Lord is wonderful in the highest. His testimonies are very sure; holiness is worthy of Your house, O Lord, unto length of days. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            TUHAN adalah Raja, Ia berpakaian kemegahan, TUHAN berpakaian, berikat pinggang kekuatan. Sungguh, telah tegak dunia, tidak bergoyang; takhta-Mu tegak sejak dahulu  kala, dari kekal Engkau ada. Sungai-sungai telah mengangkat, ya TUHAN, sungai-sungai telah mengangkat suaranya, sungai-sungai mengangkat bunyi hempasannya. Dari pada suara air yang besar, dari pada pecahan ombak laut yang hebat, lebih hebat TUHAN di tempat tinggi. Peraturan-Mu sangat teguh; bait-Mu layak kudus, ya TUHAN, untuk sepanjang masa. ALLELUIA.!          </language>         <language id="Arabic">            الربُّ قد ملَكَ، ولبِسَ الجلالَ. لبِسَ الربُّ القوةَ، وتمنطقَ بها. لأنَّهُ ثبَّتَ المسكونةَ فلن تتزعزعَ. كرسيُّكَ ثابتٌ مُنذُ البدءِ، وأنتَ هو مُنذُ الأزلِ. رفعتِ الأنهارُ ياربُّ، رفعتِ الأنهارُ صوتَها. ترفعُ الأنهارُ صوتَها، مِنْ صوتِ مياهٍ كثيرةٍ. عجيبةٌ هي أهوالُ البحرِ، وعجيبٌ هو الربُّ في الأعالي. شهاداتُهُ صادقةٌ جداً، لبيتِكَ ينبغي التقديسُ ياربُّ طولَ الأيامِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>