<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Psalm 95 - Sing to the Lord a new song; sing to the Lord...         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ الخامسُ والتسعونَ - سبِّحُوا الربَّ تسبيحاً جديداً، سبِّحِي الربَّ...         </Language>      </Title>                  <Text>         <Language id="English">            Sing to the Lord a new song; sing to the Lord, all the earth. Sing to the Lord, bless His name; proclaim His salvation day to day. Declare His glory among the Gentiles, and His wonders among all peoples. For the Lord is great, and greatly praised; He is fearsome above all the gods. For all the gods of the nations are devils, but the Lord made the heavens. Majesty and splendor are before Him; holiness and great beauty are in His Holy.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            سبِّحُوا الربَّ تسبيحاً جديداً، سبِّحِي الربَّ يا كلَّ الأرضِ، سبِّحُوا الربَّ وبارِكوا اسمَهُ. بشِّروا مِنْ يومٍ إلى يومٍ بخلاصِهِ. حدِّثوا في الأممِ بمجدِهِ وبينَ جميعِ الشُعوبِ بعجائبِهِ، لأنَّ الربَّ عظيمٌ هو ومُسبَّحٌ جداً. مرهوبٌ على كلِّ الآلِهةِ لأنَّ كلَّ آلِهةِ الأممِ شَيَاطينُ، أما الربُّ فصنعَ السماواتِ. الجلالُ والبهاءُ قُدَّامَهُ، الطهرُ والجمالُ العظيمُ في قُدسِهِ.         </Language>      </Text>                  <Text>         <Language id="English">            Bring to the Lord, O the families of the Gentiles, bring to the Lord glory and honor. Bring to the Lord the glory to His name; carry offerings, and go into His court. Worship the Lord in His holy court; let all the earth tremble before His face. Say among the nations, “The Lord reigned on a wood; for He has established the world that it shall not be moved; He will judge the peoples in righteousness.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قدِّموا للربِّ يا جميعَ قبائلِ الأممِ، قدِّموا للربِّ مجداً وكرامةً، قدِّموا للربِّ مجداً لاسمهِ. احمِلوا الذبائحَ وادخلوا دِيارَهُ، اسجُدوا للربِّ في ديارِهِ المُقدَّسةِ. فلتتزلزلْ الأرضُ كلُّها مِنْ أمامِ وجهِهِ. قولوا بينَ الأممِ إنَّ الربَّ قدْ ملكَ على خشبةٍ، وأيضاً ثبَّتَ المسكونةَ فلن تتزعزعَ. يَدينُ الشُعوبَ بالاستِقامةِ.         </Language>      </Text>                  <Text>         <Language id="English">            Let the heavens rejoice, and the earth exult; let the sea roar, and its fullness. The plains shall rejoice, and all things in them. Then all the trees of the forest shall exult before the face of the Lord, for He is coming to judge the earth; He will judge the world in justice, and the peoples with His truth. ALLELUIA.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فلتفرحِ السماواتُ ولتبتهجِ الأرضُ وليعِجِّ البحرُ وجميعُ ملئِهِ، تفرحُ الوِديانُ وكلُّ ما فيها، حينئذٍ يبتهجُ كلُّ شجرِ الغابِ أمامَ وجهِ الربِّ، لأنَّهُ يأتي ليَدينَ الأرضَ، يَدينَ المسكونةَ بالعدلِ والشُعوبَ بالاستِقامةِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>