<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 97 - Sing to the Lord a new song, for the Lord...         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Mazmur 98 - Nyanyikanlah nyanyian baru bagi TUHAN...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ السابعُ والتسعونَ - سبِّحُوا الربَّ تسبيحاً جديداً لأنَّ الربَّ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Sing to the Lord a new song, for the Lord has wrought wonderful works; His right hand and His holy arm, have wrought salvation for Him. The Lord has made known His salvation; before the nations He has revealed his righteousness. He has remembered His mercy to Jacob, and His truth to the house of Israel; the ends of all the earth have seen the salvation of our God.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Nyanyikanlah nyanyian baru bagi TUHAN, sebab Ia telah melakukan perbuatan-perbuatan yang ajaibajaib; keselamatan telah dikerjakan kepada-Nya oleh tangan kanan-Nya, oleh lengan-Nya yang kudus. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">TUHAN telah memperkenalkan keselamatan yang dari pada-Nya, telah menyatakan keadilan-Nya di depan mata bangsa-bangsa. Ia mengingat kasih setia dan kesetiaan-Nya terhadap kaum Israel, segala ujung bumi telah melihat keselamatan yang dari pada Allah kita.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            سبِّحُوا الربَّ تسبيحاً جديداً لأنَّ الربَّ قدْ صنعَ أعمالاً عجيبةً، خلَّصتْ لهُ يمينُهُ وذراعُهُ القُدُّوسةُ، أعلنَ الربُّ خلاصَهُ وكشفَ قدامَ الأممِ عدلَهُ. ذكرَ رحمتَهُ ليعقوبَ وحقَّهُ لبيتِ إسرائيلَ. نظرتْ أقاصي الأرضِ جميعاً خلاصَ إلهِنا.         </language>      </text>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Shout to the Lord, all the earth; sing and exult, and sing psalms. Sing to the Lord with a harp, with a harp and a voice of psalm, with directed trumpets, and a sound of a trumpet of horn. Shout joyfully before the Lord King. Let the sea roar, and its fullness, the world and all who dwell in it. The rivers shall clap their hands together, and the mountains shall exult before the Lord. For He comes to judge the earth; He will judge the world with righteousness, and the nations with uprightness. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bersorak-soraklah bagi TUHAN, hai seluruh bumi, bergembiralah, bersorak-sorailah dan bermazmurlah! Bermazmurlah bagi TUHAN dengan kecapi, dengan kecapi dan lagu yang nyaring, dengan nafiri dan sangkakala yang nyaring bersorak-soraklah di hadapan Raja, yakni TUHAN! <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Biarlah gemuruh laut serta isinya, dunia serta yang diam di dalamnya! Biarlah sungai-sungai bertepuk tangan,dan gunung- gunung bersorak-sorai bersama-sama di hadapan TUHAN, sebab Ia datang untuk menghakimi bumi. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Ia akan menghakimi dunia dengan keadilan, dan bangsa-bangsa dengan kebenaran. ALLELUIA.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            هلِّلوا للربِّ يا كلَّ الأرضِ، سبِّحُوا وهلِّلوا ورتِّلوا. رتِّلوا للربِّ بالقيثارةِ، بالقيثارةِ وصوتِ المِزمارِ. بأبواقٍ خافِقةٍ وصوتِ بوقِ القرنِ، هلِّلوا أمامَ الربِّ الملكِ. فليعجِّ البحرُ وكلُّ ملئِهِ، المسكونةُ وكلُّ الساكنينَ فيها. تُصفِّقُ جميعُ الأنهارِ، الجبالُ تبتهِجُ أمامَ وجهِ الربِّ، لأنَّهُ أتى ليَدينَ الأرضَ، يَدينَ المسكونةَ بالعدلِ والشُعوبَ بالاستِقامةِ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>