<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Psalm 98 - The Lord reigned; let the people rage...         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ الثامِنُ والتسعونَ - الربُّ قدْ ملَكَ فلترتعِدْ الشُعوبُ...         </Language>      </Title>                  <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord reigned; let the people rage; He who sits upon the cherubim, let the earth be shaken. The Lord is great in Zion, and is high over all peoples. Let them confess His great name, for it is fearsome and holy, and the King's honor loves the judgment. You have prepared uprightness; You have made judgment and justice in Jacob. Exalt the Lord our God, and worship at His footstool; for He is holy.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الربُّ قدْ ملَكَ فلترتعِدْ الشُعوبُ. الجالِسُ على الشاروبيمِ فلتتزلزلْ الأرضُ. عظيمٌ هو الربُّ في صِهيَونَ ومُتعالٍ على كلِّ الشُعوبِ. فليعترِفوا لاسمِهِ العظيمِ لأنَّهُ مرهوبٌ وقُدُّوسٌ وكرامةُ الملِكِ أن يُحبَّ العدلَ أنتَ هيأتَ الاستِقامةَ أنتَ أجريتَ القضاءَ والعدلَ في يعقوبَ. ارفعوا الربَّ إلهَنا واسجُدوا لموطِئِ قدميهِ فإنَّهُ قُدُّوسٌ هو.         </Language>      </Text>             <Text>         <Language id="English">            Moses and Aaron among His priests, and Samuel among those who call upon His name; they called upon the Lord, and He heard them. He spoke to them in a pillar of cloud, for they kept His testimonies and the ordinances which He gave them. O Lord our God, You answered them; O God, You became for them a forgiver and an avenger over all their deeds. Exalt you the Lord our God, and worship at His holy mountain, for the Lord our God is holy. ALLELUIA.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            موسى وهرونُ بينَ كهنتِهِ وصموئيلُ بينَ الذينَ يدْعونَ باسمِهِ، كانوا يدْعونَ الربَّ فيستجيبُ لهُم، بعمودِ الغَمامِ كانَ يُكلمُهُم. لأنَّهُم حفِظوا شهاداتِهِ، والأوامِرَ التي أعطاهُم. أيها الربُّ إلهُنا، أنتَ استجبتَ لهُم. صِرتَ لهُم يا اللهُ غفوراً، ومُنتقِماً على جميعِ أعمالِهِم. ارفعوا الربَّ إلهَنا، واسجُدوا في جبلِهِ المُقدَّسِ، فإنَّ الربَّ إلهَنا قُدُّوسٌ. هَلِّلُويا.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>