<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Psalm 99 - Shout joyfully to the Lord...         </language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur 100 - Bersorak-soraklah bagi TUHAN...         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            المزمورُ التاسعُ والتسعونَ - هلِّلوا للربِّ يا كلَّ الأرضِ...         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            Shout joyfully to the Lord, all the earth. Serve the Lord with gladness; come into His presence with exultation. Know that the Lord Himself is our God; He made us, and not we ourselves; we are His people, and the sheep of His pasture. Enter into His gates with thanksgiving, and His courts with praise; give thanks to Him, praise His name. For the Lord is good; His mercy is forever, and His truth is from generation to generation. ALLELUIA.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bersorak-soraklah bagi TUHAN, hai seluruh bumi! Beribadahlah kepada TUHAN dengan sukacita, datanglah kehadapan-Nya dengan sorak-sorai! <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Ketahuilah, bahwa Tuhanlah Allah; Dialah yang menjadikan kita dan punya Dialah kita, umat-Nya dan kawanan domba gembalaan-Nya. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Masuklah melalui pintu gerbang-Nya dengan nyanyian syukursyukur, ke dalam pelataran-Nya dengan puji-pujian, bersyukurlah kepada-Nya dan pujilah nama-Nya! Sebab TUHAN itu baik, kasih setia-Nya untuk selama-lamanya, dan kesetiaan-Nya tetap turun-temurun. ALLELUIA.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            هلِّلوا للربِّ يا كلَّ الأرضِ. اعبُدوا الربَّ بالفرحِ، ادخُلوا أمامَهُ بالتهليلِ. اعلموا أنَّ الربَّ هو إلهُنا، هو صنعَنا وليسَ نحنُ، ونحنُ شعبُهُ وغنمُ رعيَّتِهِ. ادخُلوا أبوابَهُ بالاعترافِ، ودِيارَهُ بالتسابيحِ. اعترِفوا لهُ، وبارِكوا اسمَهُ. فإنَّ الربَّ صالِحٌ هو، والى الأبدِ رحمتُهُ، وإلى جيلٍ فجيلٍ حقُّهُ. هَلِّلُويا.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>