<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Daytime Litanies</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Litani Pagi</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">طلبة النهار</language>      </Title>            <group>         <season id="!SundayPascha ^ !CovenantThursday11thHour">            <comment>               <language id="English">                  The Litanies are prayed with prostration in the morning.                     </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Litani didoakan sambil bersujud di pagi hari.                     </language>            </comment>                        <insertdocument path="include/LetUsBow"/>         </season>      </group>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray that God may have mercy and compassion on us, hear us, help us, and accept the supplications and prayers of His saints for that which is good on our behalf at all times, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mintalah kepada Allah agar berbelas kasihan dan mengasihani kita, mendengarkan kita dan mendukung kita dan menerima syafaat dan doa-doa para kudus-Nya untuk kita di setiap waktu, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               اطلبوا لكى يرحمنا الله ويتراءف علينا ويسمعنا ويعيننا ويقبل سؤالآتٍ وطلبات قديسيه منهم بالصلاح عنا فى كل حين. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray for the peace of the one, holy, catholic, and apostolic church, and for God’s salvation and comfort to abide in all places, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mintalah kepada Allah untuk kedamaian dari Gereja yang satu, kudus dan Apostolik, dan untuk keselamatan dari Allah di antara bangsa-bangsa dan penghiburan di semua tempat dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               اطلبوا عن سلام الواحدة الوحيدة المقدسة الجامعة الرسولية الكنيسة. وخلاص الله فى الشعوب والطمأنينة بكل موضع. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray for our fathers and brethren who are sick with any sickness, whether in this place or in any place, that the Lord our God may grant us, with them health and healing, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mintalah kepada Allah bagi para bapa dan saudara-saudara kita yang sakit apapun, baik di sini atau dimanapun, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita memberikan mereka dan kita kesehatan dan kesembuhan, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               اطلبوا عن أبائنا وأخوتنا المرضى بكل الأمراض فى هذا الموضع وكل مكان لكى ينعم لنا الرب إلهنا وإياهم بالعافية والشفاء. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for our fathers and brethren in all places who are traveling or planning to travel, that God may ease their ways, whether by seas, rivers, lakes, roads, [air] or other means, and may the Lord our God guide them, return them in safety, and forgive us our sins.             </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi para bapa dan saudara-saudara yang berpergian dan mereka yang berencana untuk mengadakan perjalanan di semua tempat. Kiranya Allah menolong jalan mereka, Mereka yang berpergian melalui laut, sungai, danau, jalan raya atau yang lainnya, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita memimpin mereka dan membawa mereka kembali ke rumah mereka dalam dami, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن أبائنا واخوتنا المسافرين والذين أضمروا السفر بكل مكان٬ ليسهل طرقهم جميعاً إن كانوا فى البحار أو الأنهار أو الينابيع أو الطرق المسلوكة (أو الجو) والذين جعلوا سفرهم بكل نوع٬ لكى يرشدهم الرب إلهنا ويرجعهم إلى مساكنهم بسلام ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for the air of heaven, the fruits of the earth, the trees and vineyards, and all fruit-bearing trees everywhere, that Christ our God may bless them, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon agar angin dari langit, tumbuh-tumbuhan dari bumi, semua pepohonan dan semua kebun anggur dan semua pohon-pohon yang menghasilkan buah di dalam dunia, kiranya Kristus Allah kita memberkati mereka, <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">membuatnya hingga selesai dalam damai, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </span></div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن أهوية السماء وثمرات الأرض وكل الأشجار والكروم وكل شجرة مثمرة فى جميع المسكونة٬ لكى يباركها الرب إلهنا ويكملها بسلام. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask that God may grant us mercy before leading authorities, incline their hearts with goodwill towards us always, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon kepada Allah agar memberikan kita kemurahan dan belas kasihan di hadapan pemerintah yang berkuasa dan agar mereka mencondongkan hati mereka dengan kebaikan terhadap kami setiap waktu, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا لكى يعطينا الله رحمة ورأفة أمام السلاطين الأعزاء ويعطف قلوب المتولين علينا بالصلاح فى كل حين. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for our fathers and brethren who have fallen asleep and reposed in the faith of Christ since the beginning, our holy fathers the patriarchs, metropolitans, bishops, hegumens, priests, our brethren the deacons, our fathers the monks and our brethren the laymen, and for the rest of all departed Christians, that the Lord our God may repose all their souls, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi para bapa dan saudara-saudara yang telah tertidur dan beristirahat dalam iman kepada Kristus sejak mulanya, para patriark bapa kudus kami, para metropolitan bapa kami, para uskup bapa kami, para hegumen bapa kami, para imam bapa kami, para saudara kami diakon, para bapa kami biarawan, para saudara kami orang awam, dan istirahatkanlah semua umat Kristen yang telah tertidur, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita membaringkan jiwa mereka, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن آبائنا واخوتنا الذين رقدوا وتنيحوا فى الإيمان بالمسيح منذ البدء٬ آبائنا البطاركة وآبائنا المطارنة وآبائنا الأساقفة وآبائنا القمامصة وآبائنا القسوس واخوتنا الشمامسة وآبائنا الرهبان واخوتنا العلمانيين٬ وعن كل الذين تنيحوا من المسيحين لكى ينيح الرب إلهنا نفوسهم أجمعين. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for those who care for the sacrifices, offerings, wine, oil, incense, coverings, reading books, and all the altar vessels, that the Lord our God may reward their labors in the heavenly Jerusalem, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi mereka yang mengurus persembahan, korban, anggur, minyak, dupa, kain penutup, buku-buku doa, peralatan altar, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita membalas mereka di Yerusalem sorgawi, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن المهتمين بالصعائد والقرابين والخمر والزيت والبخور والستور وكتب القراءة وكل أوانى المذبح٬ لكى يعوضهم الرب إلهنا عن أتعابهم فى أورشليم السمائية. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for the catechumens of our people, that our Lord may bless them, open the eyes of their hearts, and confirm them in the Orthodox faith until their last breath, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi para katekumen, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita memberkati mereka, menerangi hati mereka, meyakinkan mereka dalam iman Ortodoks hingga nafas terakhir, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن موعوظى شعبنا لكى يباركهم الرب الهنا ويفتح عيون قلوبهم ويثبتهم على الإيمان الأرثوذكسى إلى النفس الأخير. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for this church and for all churches of the Orthodox people, for the desert monasteries and their elders, and for the peace of the whole world, that the Lord our God may protect both us and them from all evil, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi gereja ini, dan semua gereja-gereja Orthodoks, biara-biara di padang gurun, dan para tua-tua yang tinggal di dalamnya, dan bagi kedamaian seluruh dunia, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita melindungi kita dan mereka dari semua kejahatan dan kedengkian, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن هذه الكنيسة وكل الكنائس وديارات الشعوب الأرثوذكسيين فى البرارى والشيوخ السكان فيها وعن طمأنينة كل العالم معاً. لكى يحفظنا الرب إلهنا وإياهم من كل سوء ومن كل شر. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for the life and standing of our honorable father, the Patriarch and Archbishop Pope Abba (...), [and his partner in the apostolic liturgy, our father the bishop (metropolitan), Abba (...),] that the Lord may preserve his life, and confirm him in his see for many years and peaceful times, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi kehidupan dari para bapa yang kita hormati, para uskup utama, patriark kita Abba Tawadros dan Uskup kita anba Rewis kiranya Tuhan Allah menjaga dan meneguhkan dia di atas tahtanya bertahun-tahun dan waktu damai yang panjang, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن حياة وقيام أبينا المكرم رئيس الأساقفة الآب البطريرك البابا أنبا__، (وشريكه في الخدمة أبينا الأسقف (المطران) المكرم الآنبا __،) لكى يحفظ الرب لنا حياته ويثبته على كرسيه سنين عديدة وأزمنه سلامية هادئة مديدة. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for our Orthodox fathers everywhere, the metropolitans, bishops, hegumens, priests, deacons, and all the orders of the Church, that Christ our God may preserve and strengthen them, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi para bapa kita, para uskup dan metropolitan Orthodoks di semua tempat, para hegumen, para imam, para diakon, dan semua susunan Gereja, kiranya Kristus Allah kita menjaga mereka, menguatkan mereka, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن آبائنا المطارنة والأساقفة الأرثوذكسيين بكل مكان والقمامصة والقسوس والشمامسة وكل طغمات الكنيسة لكى يحفظهم المسيح إلهنا ويقويهم. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for this assembly of ours and for all assemblies of the Orthodox people, that the Lord our God may bless them and fulfill them in peace, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi perkumpulan ini dan semua umat Ortodoks, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita memberkati dan memenuhi mereka dalam damai, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن إجتماعنا هذا وكل إجتماع الشعوب الأرثوذكسيين لكى يباركهم الرب إلهنا ويكملهم بسلام. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for the hierarchs of the holy Church, and for all the orders of the clergy, that the Lord our God may bless and strengthen them, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi semua hirarki dari Gereja yang Kudus, dan susunan para klerus, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita memberkati dan menguatkan mereka, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن مدبرى الكنيسة المقدسة وكل رتب الكهنوت لكى يباركهم الرب إلهنا ويقويهم. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for those who toil in the holy Church and for the Orthodox people, that the Lord our God may have mercy on them, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi mereka yang bekerja di dalam Gereja Yang Kudus dan bersama umat Ortodoks, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita mengasihani mereka, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن كل نفس لها تعب فى الكنيسة المقدسة ومع الشعب الأرثوذكسى لكى يصنع الرب إلهنا معهم رحمة. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for all Christ-loving rulers who asked us to pray for them by name, that the Lord our God may remember them in His mercy and grant them favor before powerful rulers, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi semua penguasa yang mengasihi Kristus yang memohon agar namanya disebutkan dalam doa-doa kita, kiranya Tuhan Allah memberkati dan mengingat mereka sejalan dengan kemurahan-Nya memberikan mereka anugerah di hadapan pemimpin yang berkuasa, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن محبى المسيح الرؤساء الذين أمرونا أن نذكرهم بأسمائهم لكى يباركهم الرب إلهنا ويذكرهم بالرحمة ويعطيهم النعمة أمام السلاطين الأعزاء. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for the poor, the weak, the farmers, and for every soul in any type of hardship, that the Lord our God may have compassion on them and on us, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi mereka yang miskin, yang lemah, para petani, dan semua yang berada dalam berbagai macam kesukaran, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita berbaik hati kepada mereka dan kita, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن المساكين والفلاحين والضعفاء وعن كل نفس متضايقة بكل نوع لكى يتراءف علينا الرب إلهنا وإياهم. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for those in the distress of jails, prisons, captivity, or exile, and for those bound by devils, that the Lord our God may free them from their hardships, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi mereka yang di dalam kesusahan penjara dan tempat kegelapan, dan mereka yang berada dalam tawanan atau pembuangan, dan mereka yang diganggu iblis, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita membebaskan mereka dari kesukaran, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن كل المتضايقين الذين فى السجون وفى المطابق والذين فى النفى أو فى السبى والمربوطين من جهة رباطات الشياطين لكى يعتقهم الرب إلهنا من متاعبهم. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for all those gathered with us today in this place, seeking mercy for their souls, that the Lord’s mercy may encompass both us and them, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi semua jiwa yang berkumpul bersama kita hari ini, di tempat ini, yang mencari belas kasihan bagi jiwa mereka, kiranya belas kasihan dari Tuhan Allah kita turun ke atas mereka dan kita, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن كل النفوس المجتمعة معنا اليوم فى هذا الموضع يطلبون الرحمة لنفوسهم لكى تدركنا مراحم الرب إلهنا وإياهم. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for each person by name who asked us to remember them in our prayers, that the Lord our God may always remember them in His goodness, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi mereka yang meminta namanya untuk diingat di dalam doa-doa kita, kiranya Tuhan Allah kita mengingat mereka seturut kebaikan-Nya setiap waktu, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن الذين أوصونا أن نذكرهم كل واحد واحد بإسمه لكى يذكرهم الرب إلهنا بالصلاح فى حين. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for the rising of the waters of the rivers this year, that Christ our God may bless them and raise them according to their measure, give joy to all the earth with the Nile, sustain us and deliver man and animal, and spare the world from death, scarcity, plagues, devastation, the sword of the enemies, and that He may grant calm, peace, and security to the holy Church, and raise the state of Christians in every place on earth until the last breath, and forgive us our sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi melimpahnya air dari sungai pada tahun ini, kiranya Kristus Tuhan kita memberkati dan menaikkannya sesuai ukurannya, berilah sukacita di permukaan bumi, menopang kami, membebaskan manusia dan binatang buas, dan mengangkat dari dunia ini kematian, inflasi, wabah, kematian, evakuasi dan pedang dari musuh. Berikan damai dan ketenangan di dalam gereja kami yang kudus dan naikkanlah keadaan umat Kristen di setiap tempat dan di seluruh dunia sampai nafas terakhir, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن صعود مياه الآنهار فى هذه السنة لكى يباركها المسيح إلهنا ويصعدها كمقدارها ويفرح وجه الأرض بالنيل ويعولنا نحن البشر ويعطى النجاة لشعبه والبهائم ويرفع عن العالم الموت والغلاء والوباء والفناء والجلاء وسيف الأعداء ويجعل الهدوء والسلام والطمأنينة فى البيعة المقدسة ويرفع شأن المسيحيين فى كل مكان وفى كل المسكونة إلى النفس الأخير. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               Let us pray and ask for this holy Pascha of our good Savior, that He may complete it for us in peace and bring us the joy of His holy Resurrection in safety, and forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoa dan memohon bagi Minggu Kudus Paskah dari Juruselamat kita yang Baik, kiranya Dia menyelesaikannya untuk kita di dalam damai dan menunjukkan kita sukacita dari kebangkitan kudus-Nya dalam keamanan, dan ampunilah dosa-dosa kami. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صلوا واطلبوا عن هذه البصخة المقدسة التى لمخلصنا الصالح لكى يكملها لنا بسلام ويرينا بهجة قيامته المقدسة ونحن جميعاً سالمين. ويغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>   </section></document>