<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">    <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Proverbs 9:1-11</language><language id="Indonesian">Amsal 9:1-11</language>         <language id="Arabic">أمثال 9: 1-11</language>      </Title>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/prophecyIntro/Proverbs"/>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            A~]covia~ n~ou/i: ouoh actajro n~sasf n~c~tulloc qarof: Acqolqel n~necswt: acywt m~pec/rp qenoumoki: ouoh accob] n~tect~rapeza:         </language>         <language id="English">            Wisdom built her house, and she supported it with seven pillars. She offered her sacrifices; she mixed her wine in a bowl And prepared her table.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Hikmat telah mendirikan rumahnya, <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">menegakkan ketujuh tiangnya, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">memotong ternak sembelihannya, mencampur anggurnya, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan menyediakan hidangannya.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            الحكمة بنت لها بيتاً ونصبت فيه سبعة أعمدة. ذبحت ذبائحها ومزجت خمرها في البواطي (الأواني) وهيأت مائدتها.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Acouwrp n~nece~biaik e~ywhem qen ounis] n~q~rwou e~ouk~rater ecjwm~moc: Je v/etoi n~ath/t qen y/nou marefi~ haroi:         </language>         <language id="English">            She sent her servants, inviting people to the bowl with a lofty proclamation, saying, "he who is without discernment, let him turn aside to me";         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Pelayan-pelayan perempuan telah disuruhnya berseru-seru di atas tempat-tempat yang tinggi di kota: "Siapa yang tak berpengalaman, singgahlah ke mari"; </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أرسلت عبيدها لينادوا بصوت عال علي الزوايا قائلين: من كان منكم جاهلاً فليأت إلي،         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ouoh nietsat n~c~bw ajoc nwou: Je a~mwini ouwm e~bol qen pawik: ouoh cw e~bolqen pi/rp e~tai yotf nwten: &lt;w n~]metath/t n~cay/nou hina n~tetenwnq kw] n~ca ]metcabe hina n~tetenerneba~hi: ouoh mataho m~petenka] e~ratf qen ougnwcic          </language>         <language id="English">            and to those in need of discernment, she says, "come, eat my bread and drink the wine I mixed for you; forsake lack of discernment, and you shall live; seek discernment so you may live, and keep straight your understanding with knowledge."         </language><language id="Indonesian">dan kepada yang tidak berakal budi katanya: "Marilah, makanlah rotiku, dan minumlah anggur yang telah kucampur;  buanglah kebodohan, maka kamu akan hidup, dan ikutilah jalan pengertian."</language>         <language id="Arabic">            وناقصي الفهم قولوا لهم هلموا كلوا من خبزي وإشربوا من الخمر التي مزجتها لكم  أتركوا عنكم الجهل لتحيوا  أطلبوا الحكمة لتعمروا  وقوموا فهمكم بمعرفة.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            V/e~]c~bw n~hanpethwou efe~[i n~ousws naf: v/etcohi m~pia~ceb/c ef e~hia[ni erof m~minm~mof:         </language>         <language id="English">            He who chastises evil men shall receive dishonor to himself, and he who reproves the ungodly man shall be blamed himself.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Siapa mendidik seorang pencemooh, mendatangkan cemooh kepada dirinya sendiri, dan siapa mengecam orang fasik, mendapat cela.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            من يؤدب الأشرار يلحق بنفسه هواناً ومن يبكت المنافق يكسب عيباً لذاته.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Mpercohi n~han pethwou hina n~tous~temmectwk: cohi de n~oucabe ouoh efe~menritk:          </language>         <language id="English">            Do not reprove evil men, so they may not hate you; reprove a wise man, and he will love you.          </language><language id="Indonesian">            Janganlah mengecam seorang pencemooh, supaya engkau jangan dibencinya, </language>         <language id="Arabic">            لا توبخ الأشرار لئلا يبغضوك. وبخ حكيماً فيحبك.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Cohi de n~ouatc~bw ouoh efe~mectwk: moi n~ou lwiji m~picabe ouoh efe~ercabe n~houo: matame piy~m/i ouoh f~naouah totf e~[i.          </language>         <language id="English">            Give the opportunity to a wise man, and he will be wiser; instruct a righteous man, and he shall continue to receive it.         </language><language id="Indonesian">kecamlah orang bijak, maka engkau akan dikasihinya, berilah orang bijak nasihat, maka ia akan menjadi lebih bijak, ajarilah orang benar, maka pengetahuannya akan bertambah</language>         <language id="Arabic">            وبخ جاهلاً فيبغضك. أعط الحكيم سبباً فيزداد حكمة وعلم البار فيزداد براً           </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Tar,/ n~]covia~ ]ho] n~te P[oic te: ouoh p~co[ni n~te n/eyu ouka] pe.Pcouen pinomoc de vai oumeui~ n~a~gayoc pe: qen pai t~ropoc vai eke~wnq n~ounis] n~,ronoc: ouoh hanrompi n~te p~wnq eue~oua~hou erok.         </language>         <language id="English">            The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom, and the counsel of saints is understanding; for to know the law is characteristic of a good mind. For in this manner you will live a long time, and the years of your life shall be increased.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Permulaan hikmat adalah takut akan TUHAN, dan mengenal Yang Mahakudus adalah pengertian. Karena oleh aku umurmu diperpanjang, dan tahun-tahun hidupmu ditambah.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            راس الحكمة مخافة الرب ومشورة القديسين فهم ومعرفة للناموس هي الفكر الصالح  بهذا المثال تعيش زماناً طويلاً وتزداد لك سنو الحياة.         </language>      </text>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ProphecyConclusion"/>   </section></document>