<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <role id="Deacon">      <insertdocument path="include/litanies/AssembliesDeacon"/>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>      <role id="Priest">      <group>         <season id="Liturgy">            <comment>               <language id="English">                  The priest takes the censer.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Imam mengambil pedupaan itu dari diakon. </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يأخذ الكاهن المجمرة.               </language>            </comment>         </season>      </group>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            M/ic eyrouswpi nan n~aterkwlin n~attahno: eyrenaitou kata pekouws eyouab ouoh m~makarion.         </language>                     <language id="English">            Grant that they may be to us without obstacle or hindrance, that we may hold them according to Your holy and blessed will:         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Berikanlah  kami tanpa halangan atau gangguan, supaya kami dapat melakukannya menurut kehendak-Mu yang kudus dan diberkati.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أعطِ أن تكون لنا بغير مانعٍ ولا عائقٍ، لنصنَعها كمشيئتِكَ المقدسةِ الطوباويةِ.         </language>      </text>            <group>         <season id="Liturgy">            <comment>               <language id="English">                  The priest stretches forth his hand with the censer over the altar toward the four corners, first to the east, then the west, the north, and the south, while saying:               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Imam mengulurkan tangannya dengan pedupaan di atas altar ke arah keempat penjuru, pertama ke timur, kemudian barat, utara, dan selatan,  dengan bentuk salib sambil berkata:</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يمد الكاهن يده بالمجمرة فوق المذبح إلى الجهات الأربع بمثال الصليب أي إلى الشرقِ ثم الغرب ثم الشمال ثم الجنوب وهو يقول:               </language>            </comment>         </season>      </group>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            han/i n~eu,/: han/i n~toubo: han/i n~c~mou: a~ri,arizecye m~mwou nan P[oic nem neke~biaik eyn/ou menencwn sa e~neh.         </language>                     <language id="English">            houses of prayer, houses of purity, houses of blessing. Grant them to us, O Lord, and to Your servants who will come after us, forever.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Berikanlah kami ya Tuhan, rumah doa, rumah kemurnian dan rumah berkat, dan kepada para hamba-Mu yang akan menggantikan kami, seterusnya.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            بيوتُ صلاةٍ، بيوتُ طهارةٍ، بيوتُ بركةٍ، أنعم بها لنا ياربُّ، ولعبيدِك الآتينَ بعدَنا إلى الابد.         </language>      </text>            <comment>         <language id="English">            The following may be said.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Hal berikut mungkin diucapkan atau tidak.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            هنا تقال هذه الأوشية أو تترك:         </language>      </comment>            <insertdocument path="include/TheWorshipOfIdols"/>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            P[oic a~ritou t/rou n~aprakton: ouoh jwr e~bol m~pouco[ni: Vnou] v/e~tafjwr e~bol m~p~co[ni n~A,itovel.         </language>                     <language id="English">            O Lord, bring them all to no avail. Disperse their counsel, O God, who dispersed the counsel of Ahithophel.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Tuhan, buatlah mereka tidak berguna, bubarkan nasihat mereka, ya Allah, seperti Engkau telah membubarkan nasihat Ahitofel.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ياربُّ إجعلْهم كلَّهم كلا شيءٍ، وبدِّد مشورَتَهم يا الله الذي بدَّد مشورةَ أخيتوفل.         </language>      </text>               </role>   <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>      <role id="Priest">      <comment>         <language id="English">            The priest censes toward the East three times above the altar, saying:         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kemudian imam mengangkat dupa ke arah timur tiga kali, sementara mengucapkan Litani Jemaat,  yaitu:         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ثم يرفع الكاهن يده ويبخر شرقاً فوق المذبح ثلاث مرات وهو يقول بقية أوشيه الاجتماعات وهي هذه:         </language>      </comment>            <insertdocument path="include/AriseOLordGod"/>   </role>      <role id="Priest" silent="true">      <comment>         <language id="English">            The priest turns to the East and censes three times, saying inaudibly:         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Imam menghadap ke arah Timur dan mempersembahkan dupa sebanyak tiga kali, sambil berkata dengan lirih:         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ثم يبخر شرقا ثلاث أياد وهو يقول سراً:         </language>      </comment>            <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusion"/>            <group>         <season id="Unction | Baptism | Liturgy">            <comment>               <language id="English">                  At the words “Through whom” (<span class="Coptic">Vai e~te</span>), the priest again censes three times toward the East, then gives the censer to the deacon.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Pada kata-kata “Melalui-Nya” (<span class="Coptic">Vai e~te</span>), the priest again mempersembahkan dupa sebanyak tiga kali ke arah timur, tlalu memberikan pedupaan kepada diakon.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وعند ما يقول  <span class="Coptic">Vai e~te</span> يعطي البخور إلى الشرقِ ثلاث مرات. ثم يعطي المجمرة للشماس.               </language>            </comment>         </season>      </group>   </role> </document>