<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">     <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Eujwk e~bol n~y/eyouab e~taktenhoutou e~roc e~bolhitotk m~metar,ie~reuc: kata pekouws eyouab ouoh m~makarion.      </language>      <language id="English">         fulfilling that holy archpriesthood with which You have entrusted them for Yourself, according to Your holy and blessed will,      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>memenuhi jawatan keimamatan yang Engkau percayakan kepadanya dalam damai dan menurut kehendak-Mu yang kudus, </div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         مكمِّلين رئاسةَ الكهنوتِ المقدسةِ التي ائتمنتَهم عليها من قِبَلِكَ، كإرادتِكَ المقدسةِ الطوباويةِ.      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Euswt e~bol m~p~caji n~te ]meym/i qen oucwouten: eua~moni m~peklaoc qen outoubo nem oumeym/i.      </language>      <language id="English">         rightly handling the word of truth, shepherding Your people in purity and righteousness,      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>menyampaikan firman Kebenaran; dan menggembalakan umat-Mu dalam kesucian dan keadilan. </div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         مفصِّلينَ كلمةَ الحقِّ باستقامةٍ، راعِينَ شعبَك بطهارةٍ وبرٍّ.      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Nem nie~pickopoc t/rou n~oryodoxoc: nem nih/gomenoc nem nip~recbuteroc: nem nidiakwn: nem v~moh t/rf n~te tekoui m~mauatc eyouab n~kayolik/ n~a~poctolik/ n~ekk~l/cia.      </language>      <language id="English">         and all the orthodox bishops, hegumens, priests, and deacons, and all the fullness of Your one, only, holy, catholic, and apostolic Church.      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami juga mohon supaya Engkau melindungi kami bersama uskup ortodoks dan imam agung, para imam dan para diaken dan dalam kepenuhan gereja yang satu, satu-satunya, katolik dan apostolik. </div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         وجميعَ الأساقفةِ الأرثوذكسيين، والقمامصةِ والقسوسِ والشمامسةِ، وكلَّ امتلاءِ كنيستِكَ الواحدةِ الوحيدةِ المقدسةِ الجامعةِ الرسوليةِ.      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Eke~er,arizecye nwou neman n~ouhir/n/ nem ououjai e~bolqen mai niben.      </language>      <language id="English">         Grant them and us peace and safety in every place.      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berikan mereka dan kita damai dan keamanan di setiap tempat. </div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         أنعمْ عليهِم وعلينا بالسلامِ والعافيةِ في كلِّ موضعٍ.      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Noup~roceu,/ de e~toui~ri m~mwou e~h~r/i e~jwn: (nem e~jen peklaoc t/rf:)+ nem noun hwn e~h~r/i e~jwou.      </language>      <language id="English">         Their prayers which they offer on our behalf, (and on behalf of all Your people,)+ as well as ours on their behalf,      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Terimalah doa yang mereka persembahkan bagi kami dan bagi seluruh umat-Mu, dan demikian pula doa kami demi mereka.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         وصلواتَهم التي يقدمونها عنا، (وعن كلِّ شعبِك،)+ وصلواتَنا نحنُ أيضاً عنهم.      </language>            </text>      <comment>      <language id="English">         +Said by the Pope, a metropolitan, or a bishop, if present.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         +Diucapkan oleh Paus, seorang metropolitan, atau seorang uskup, jika hadir.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         +يقولها الأب البابا أو المطران أو الأسقف إذا كان حاضراً.      </language>   </comment>      <comment>      <language id="English">         The deacon presents the censer to the priest, who puts a spoonful of incense into it, while saying:      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Diakon memberikan ukupan kepada Imam, kemudian abouna menaruh satu sendok dupa ke dalamnya dan berkata:      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         ههنا يقدم الشماس المجمرة إلى الكاهن فيضع فيها البخور يداً واحدة وهو يقول:      </language>   </comment>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Sopou e~rok e~jen pekyuciact/rion eyouab n~ellogimon n~te t~ve: e~ouc~yoi n~c~yoinoufi.      </language>      <language id="English">         receive them upon Your holy, rational altar in heaven, as a sweet savor of incense.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Terimalah mereka di atas altar surga-Mu yang suci yang rasional, sebagai wangian yang berbau harum      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         اقبلْها إليكَ على مذبَحِكَ المقدسِ الناطقِ السمائِيّ رائحةَ بَخُورٍ.      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Noujaji men t/rou n/e~tounau e~rwou: nem n/e~te n~cenau e~rwou an qemqwmou ouoh mayebiwou capec/t n~nou[alauj n~,wlem.      </language>      <language id="English">         All their enemies, visible and invisible, trample and humiliate under their feet speedily.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Musuh-musuh-Mu, baik yang kelihatan maupun tidak kelihatan, taklukkan semua musuh di bawah kaki mereka. </language>      <language id="Arabic">         فسائر أعدائِهم الذين يُرَوْن والذين لا يُرَوْن، اسحقهُم وأَذِلَّهم تحت أرجلِهم سريعاً.      </language>            </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Nywou de a~reh e~rwou qen ouhir/n/ nem oudikeo~cun/: qen tekekk~l/cia eyouab.      </language>      <language id="English">         As for them, keep them in peace and righteousness in Your holy Church.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Untuk mereka, peliharalah mereka dalam damai dan kebenaran dalam Gereja-Mu yang kudus.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         وأما هم فاحفظْهُم في سلامٍ وعدلٍ في كنيستِك المقدسةِ.      </language>            </text></document>