<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">      <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Litany of Peace</language><language id="Indonesian">Litani Perdamaian</language>         <language id="Arabic">أوشية السلام</language>      </Title>            <insertdocument path="include/litanies/PeaceShort"/>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nilaoc t/rou nem nio~hi t/rou c~mou e~rwou: ]hir/n/ ]e~bol qen niv/oui: m/ic e~q~r/i e~nenh/t t/rou.            </language>            <language id="English">               All peoples and all flocks, bless. The heavenly peace, send down into all our hearts;            </language><language id="Indonesian">               semua orang dan semua kawanan berkatilah. Damai surgawi, turunkanlah ke dalam hati kita, </language>            <language id="Arabic">               كلَّ الشعوبِ وكلَّ القُطعانِ. باركْهم. السلامَ الذي من السمواتِ أنزلْهُ على قلوبِنا جميعاً.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Alla nem ]kehir/n/ n~te paibioc vai: a~ri,arizecye m~moc nan n~h~mot.            </language>            <language id="English">               even the peace of this life, graciously grant to us.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               bahkan kedamaian dari hidup ini, dengan penuh rahmat berikanlah kepada kami.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               بل وسلامَ هذا العمرِ أَنْعِمْ بِه علينا إنعاماً.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Piouro (Pip~roedroc) nimetmatoi niar,wn nico[ni nim/s nenyeseu nenjinmosi e~qoun nem nenjinmosi e~bol: celcwlou qen hir/n/ niben.            </language>            <language id="English">               The king (leader), the armies, the rulers, the counselors, the multitudes, our neighbors, our coming in and our going out, adorn them with all peace.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Sang Raja (Penguasa) bala tentara, Pemimpin dan Penasehat, yang berkembang, dari sesama kita, yang datang dan pergi, semuanya diberkati dengan segala perdamaian.</span></div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الملكَ (الرئيسَ) والجندَ والأراخنةَ والمشيرينَ والجموعَ وجيرانَنا ومداخلَنا ومخارجَنا، زَيِّنْهُم بكلِ سلامٍ.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pouro n~te ]hir/n/ moi nan n~tekhir/n/: hwb gar niben akt/itou nan.            </language>            <language id="English">               O King of peace, grant us Your peace, for You have given us all things.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Raja Damai, berikanlah damai-Mu, karena telah diberikan kepada kita semua itu. </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               يا ملكَ السلام، أعطِنا سلامَكَ، لأن كلَّ شيءٍ قد أعطيتنا.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Jvon nak Vnou] pencwt/r: je tencwoun n~keouai an e~b/l e~rok: pekran eyouab petenjw m~mof.            </language>            <language id="English">               Acquire us to Yourself, O God our Savior, for we know none other but You. Your holy name we  utter.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Datanglah kepada kami, ya Allah, Juruselamat kami, karena kami tahu bahwa tidak ada selain Engkau. Nama-Mu yang kudus kami ucapkan, </div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               اقتننا لكَ يا الله مخلِّصُنا لأننا لا نعرفُ آخرَ سواك، اسمَكَ القدوس هو الذي نقوله.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Marouwnq n~je n/e~te noun m~'u,/ hiten Pekp~neuma eyouab.            </language>            <language id="English">               May our souls live by Your Holy Spirit,            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>kiranya jiwa kami hidup dengan Roh Kudus-Mu.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فلتحيَ نفوسُنا بروحِكَ القدوس.            </language>                  </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh m~peny~refjemjom e~ron a~non qa neke~biaik: n~je v~mou n~te hannobi: (oude qa peklaoc t/rf.)+            </language>            <language id="English">               and let not the death of sins have dominion over us, we Your servants, (nor over all Your people.)+            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Janganlah biarkan dosa kematian berkuasa atas kami, kami hamba-Mu, (tidak pula atas seluruh umat milik-Mu.)+</language>            <language id="Arabic">               ولا تَدَعْ موتَ الخطايا يقوَى علينا، نحنُ عبيدَك، (ولا على كلِّ شعبِك.)+            </language>                  </text>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               +Said by the Pope, a metropolitan, or a bishop, if present.                           </language><language id="Indonesian">               +Diucapkan oleh Paus, Metropolitan atau Uskup jika hadir.</language>            <language id="Arabic">               +يقولها الأب البابا أو المطران أو الأسقف إذا كان حاضراً.            </language>         </comment>      </role>                  <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>   </section></document>