<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Comment>      <Language id="English">         These verses from the Psalms shall be recited with the response “Alleluia” in its known tune.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         ثم تقال هذه القطع من المزامير مع مرد هلليلويا بلحنه المعروف      </Language>   </Comment>      <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">Psalms</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">مزامير</Language>      </Title>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            Psalm 34:11-15         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            مزمور 34: 11-15         </Language>      </Comment>         <Text>         <Language id="English">            Come, you children, hear me: I will teach you the fear of the Lord. Who is the man that desires life, and is thinking to see good days? Keep your tongue from evil, and your lips from speaking guile. Turn away from evil, and do good; seek peace, and pursue it. For the eyes of the Lord are over the righteous, and His ears are bent to their prayer: Alleluia.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تعالوا أيها الأبناء وإسمعونى لأعلمكم خشية الرب. من هو الإنسان الذي يهوى الحياة، ويظن أن يرى أياما صالحة؟ أكفف لسانك عن الشر، وشفتيك عن أن يتكلما بالغدر. حد عن الشر واصنع الخير، اطلب السلامة واتبعها. فإن عيني الرب على الأبرار، وأذنيه تنصتان إلى طلبتهم. الليلويا         </Language>      </Text>                 <Comment>         <Language id="English">            Psalm 119:121-128         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            مزمور 119: 121-128         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            I have done judgment and justice; do not deliver me to the hands of those who injure me. Accept Your servant unto You for good: do not let the proud say falsehood against me. My eyes have failed for Your salvation, and for the word of Your righteousness. Deal with Your servant according to Your mercy, and teach me Your ordinances. I am Your servant; instruct me, and I will know Your testimonies. It is the time to work for the Lord: they have utterly broken Your law. Therefore I have loved Your commandments more than gold and topaz. Therefore I stood for all Your commandments: I have hated every unjust way. Alleluia.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قد صنعت حكما وعدلا فلا تسلمني إلى الذين يظلمونني. إقبل عبدك إليك في الخير، لئلا يكذب عليّ المستكبرون. عيناي قد فنيتا من انتظار خلاصك وقول عدلك. اصنع مع عبدك حسب رحمتك، وحقوقك علمني. عبدك أنا، فهمني فأعرف شهاداتك. إنه وقتٌ يُعمل فيه للرب، و قد نقضوا ناموسك. لأجل هذا أحببتُ وصاياك أفضل من الذهب والجوهر، ولأجل هذا بازاء كل وصاياك تقومتُ، وكل طريق ظلم أبغضتُ. الليلويا.         </Language>      </Text>                 <Comment>         <Language id="English">            Psalm 55:4-8         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            مزمور 55: 4-8         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            My heart is severely pained within me, and the terrors of death have fallen upon me. Fearfulness and trembling have come upon me, and horror has overwhelmed me. So I said, "Oh, that I had wings like a dove! I would fly away and be at rest. Indeed, I would wander far off, and remain in the wilderness. I would hasten my escape from the windy storm and tempest". Alleluia.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إضطرب قلبى فىّ ، وجزع الموت أتى علىّ. خوف ورعدة أتيا علىّ وغشيتنى الظلمة. فقلت من يعطينى جناحين كالحمامة فأطير وأستريح. هأنذا قد إبتعدت هارباً وسكنت البرية. كنت منتظراً الذى يخلصنى من صغر النفس و من الزوبعة. هلليلويا.         </Language>      </Text>      </Section></Document>