<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Gospels         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير الأناجيل         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            God has created the angels and the principalities in Heaven to praise and glorify Him and do His will. Satan was one of the principalities of heaven but when he overstepped his boundaries and rejected the truth, he fell from his leadership position and from heaven to earth where he thought he would have no master. Hence, God created Adam to punish him, and made Adam ruler of the earth and what is upon it. When Satan witnessed this, he became jealous and envied man’s leadership and the pleasures of paradise. He realized that, with the will of God, Adam would reach the heavenly status that he and his demons will not be able to achieve. Therefore, he trapped Adam and made him to fall. Adam was no longer the ruler of the earth but fell under Satan’s leadership. The devil entered into the serpent and spoke to Eve, so she sinned, and so did her husband. And both lost their roles as rulers of the earth and became, along with their offspring, subservient to Satan. Satan now boasts of his evil council and claims victory over the Lord.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إن الله تعالى قد خلق الملائكة والرؤساء في السماء للتسبيح والتقديس ولنفاذ مشيئته وكان إبليس أحد الرؤساء الكبار في السماء، ولكنه لما تعدى طوره، ومال بإثاره عن الحق، وتعظم على باريه، وخرج عن الحد المرسوم له. سقط من رياسته ونزل من السماء إلى الأرض، وظن أنه يكون فيها بلا رئيس يترأس عليها. حينئذ خلق الله آدم تبكيتاً له وجعله رئيساً على الأرض وما عليها، فلما شاهده إبليس اشتدت غيرته وحسده على الرئاسة وعلى نعيم الفردوس وتحقق عنده أنه بإرادة الله يصير إلى المرتبة السمائية التي خلت منه ومن شياطينه الذين وافقوه على رأيه الفاسد، فنصب فخاً أوقع فيه آدم. وأخرجه من رئاسة العالم وجعله تحت رئاسته وذلك أنه استتر في الحية وكلم حواء بما به طغت وأطغت آدم معها. وبذلك أخرجهما من رئاستهما وصارا بطغيانهما تحت سلطانه هما ونسلهما جيلاً بعد جيل، والشيطان يفتخر على الباري بحكمته الشريرة مدعياً الغلبة على حكمة الله.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            God’s justice does not permit the saving of Adam from Satan’s captivity by force. He therefore delivered him by the greatest mystery of all when He delivered His only Son to die on the cross and save Adam judiciously. Pride and vanity brought the devil down to earth whereas the love and humbleness brought the Son of God to our world where He dwelled among us. When the devil saw Adam as ruler, he was cruel to him; whereas when the Son of God saw Adam in captivity and disgrace, He had mercy on him and sacrificed Himself for him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما كان عدل الله يقتضي بأن لا يخلص آدم ونسله من أسر إبليس اغتصاباً. أحسن التدبير في خلاصهم بالسر الذي يفوق حكمة الحكماء وعقول البلغاء والعلماء. وذلك أنه أسلم ابنه الوحيد إلى الموت الذي لحق بآدم ونسله ليخلصه بعدل، فالكبرياء والتعاظم أسقطا الشيطان إلى الأرض والتواضع والحب أهبطا ابن الله إلى عالمنا وعاش بيننا بالمسكنة. الشيطان لما رأى آدم في الرئاسة والنعيم صار قاسياً عليه. وابن الله لما رأى آدم في الأسر والهوان رحمه حتى أنه فداه بنفسه.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The devil hid in the serpent to trap Adam and his offspring and to hold them captive whereas the Son of God hid in the body of a human, concealing His divinity from the devil, until He delivered the human race from Satan’s captivity. God conquered Satan’s evil council with His mercy, humility and His acceptance of pain. God’s plan was to deliver man using good wisdom rather than Satan’s evil council. When Jesus hid His divinity from Satan, Satan thought Jesus was a man, and made others kill Him. Jesus then asked Satan for the price of His death and in return freed the entire human race from his grasp.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الشيطان استتر في جسم الحية حتى أطغى آدم وأسره وجميع نسله وابن الله استتر في جسم آدم وأخفى سر لاهوته عن الشيطان حتى خلص الناس أجمع من أسره. فالحكمة الشريرة التي افتخر بها إبليس، أبطلها الله بحكمته الصالحة التي هو التواضع والرحمة واحتمال الأذى، وكان قصد الباري أن يأخذ الناس منه بحكمة صالحة، كما أخذهم إبليس بحكمة شريرة، فلما أخفى السيد المسيح لاهوته عن إبليس ظنه إنساناً وحرك عليه من قتله، فطالبه الله بفدية قتله وأخذ منه كل الناس في فدية قتله.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            We read in the gospels how God hid His divinity from Satan and how every divine work He did, He coupled with a display of human weakness. When He gave the disciples His Holy body and Blood and told them that His blood will be shed to save the world, Satan could see His divinity especially after the long speech He gave to the disciples. In this speech, He showed them His divinity and that He is a true God from a true God equal to the Father in principle and that He is in the Father and the Father is in Him and that He is one with the Father and the Holy Spirit. He promised that He would send them a Comforter who would teach them everything. He then spoke to the Father, again clearly showing His divinity. Thus, when the devil was assured of His divinity and that He had taken human form to deliver the human race from his captivity, He sped to destroy His work by enticing the Jews to kill Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ونعلم من الأناجيل كيف كان الرب يخفي لاهوته عن إبليس فكان إذا فعل آية يظهر لاهوته يقرنها بعمل يظهر به الضعف فمن ذلك أنه لما أعطى تلاميذه جسده ودمه الأقدسين وحقق لهم أن دمه يُهرق عن خلاص العالم وظهرت لإبليس ألوهيته لاسيما من الخطاب الطويل الذي قاله لهم وأظهر لهم فيه لاهوته ، وأنه إله حق من إله حق، مساو للآب في الجوهر ، وأنه في الآب والآب فيه، وأنه واحد مع الآب والروح القدس، وقد وعدهم أنه يرسل لهم المعزي فيعلمهم بكل شيء وخاطب أباه خطاباً أوضح فيه لاهوته بأجلى بيان، فلما تحقق أنه إله وإنه تجسد لكي ينقذ الناس من أسره أسرع بكل همته أن يبطل ما قد عمله من إغراء اليهود على قتله، فأظهر ربنا من الضعف ما به جعل الشيطان يظنه إنساناً كبقية الناس.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Our Lord then showed enough human weakness to convince the devil that He is a human by demonstrating His fear of death. The devil then decided to kill Him at the hands of the Jewish priests. The weakness that our Lord showed was that, “He began to be sorrowful and deeply distressed,” and “Then He said to them, "My soul is exceedingly sorrowful, even to death. Stay here and watch with Me. He blamed them when He returned and found them asleep, and said to them, “Watch and pray, lest you enter into temptation.” He prayed earnestly showing that He did not want to die and asked His father to spare Him the cup of death – if possible. “Then an angel appeared to Him from heaven, strengthening Him.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وذلك أنه أظهر التخوف من الموت حينئذ عزم إبليس على تنفيذ الحكم عليه بالموت على يد كهنة اليهود والضعف الذي أظهره ربنا هو أنه "ابتداء يحزن ويكتئب" وكان يقول "نفسي حزينة جداً حتى الموت"، وقال لتلاميذه أن يسهروا معه وقد لامهم لما رجع من صلاته ووجدهم نياماً، فقال لهم: "اسهروا وصلوا لئلا تدخلوا في تجربة". وكان يصلي بحرارة شديدة يظهر فيها أنه لا يشاء الموت. ويسأل أباه أن يعبر عنه شرب كأس الموت إن أمكن "وظهر له ملاك من السماء ليقويه"         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The appearance of the angel had three meanings. First, to teach His disciples that His power is endless, and His will is obeyed by those who live in heaven and on earth. Second, to show the devil that He is like the rest of the people: in need of the support of the angels when in distress. Third, to show us that God sends His angels from heaven to comfort and strengthen the patience and determination of the righteous when they are in distress...         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولظهور الملاك ثلاثة معانٍ: الأول ليعلم تلاميذه أن قدرته واسعة وأن أمره نافذ في السمائيين والأرضيين. والثاني ليظهر لإبليس أنه مثل الناس المحتاجين إلى تقوية الملائكة في حين الشدائد. والثالث ليدلنا على أن الصديقين إذا وقعوا في الشدائد يرسل الله لهم ملائكة من السماء ليعزوهم ويقووا صبرهم وعزمهم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            To show the devil that He is like all people who worry when they fall in trouble that could lead to death, “He prayed more earnestly” showing us that we must hold on to prayers at the time of need. “Then His sweat became like great drops of blood falling down to the ground.” Sweat is a light water vapor coming from the blood and seeping through the skin pores. Many physicians have testified that during time of extreme pain and suffering the human body can secrete sweat and blood. The physicians said that such an occurrence is not impossible and has been witnessed a number of times... Luke, who was a physician, is the only evangelist who mentioned this occurrence.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولكي يظهر لإبليس أنه مثل كل الناس الذين يقلقون عن التعب ووقوعهم في الشدائد التي تقضي إلى الموت "كان يصلي بلجاجة" ليعلمنا الاعتصام بالصلاة وقت الشدائد. "وصار عرقه كقطرات دم نازلة على الأرض" والعرق هو بخار رقيق مائي يتصاعد من الدم ويخرج من منافذ الجلد المعروفة بالمسام إلى سطح الجسد. وقد ثبت من شهادة أطباء عديدين أن سيلان العرق ممزوجاً بدم من جسد الإنسان في وقت الغم الشديد، والضيق العظيم، ليس بأمر مستحيل، بل قد شوهد مراراً.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Others have said that Luke’s words did not necessarily mean that our Lord sweated blood but that His sweat drops were as large as blood drops and that He sweated so much that drops of sweat fell on the floor like blood from an open wound. In His prayer, the Lord said, “My soul is exceedingly sorrowful.” As He desired to hide His divinity from the devil, He was truly sad because as He said, “there will be more joy in heaven over one sinner who repents,” there is also a lot of sadness in heaven when a believer sins.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد امتاز لوقا بإيراد هذا الخبر ولا يخفي أنه كان طبيباً. وقيل لا يلزم من كلام لوقا أن العرق كان ممزوجاً بدم بل كلامه يفيد أن قطرات العرق كانت كبيرة كقطرات الدم، وأنها خرجت من جسده بكثرة حتى وقعت على الأرض كدم من جرح، وفي صلاته كان يقول: "نفسي حزينة جداً حتى الموت".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He was very sad because Judas, His disciple, had fallen into sin. He was also sad for us because the devil had overcome us and made us sin so that He had to die for us in the body that He had taken from the Virgin Mary. He became a real person who feels sadness and unhappiness not an illusion. For illusions do not feel.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فهو إن كان يريد ذلك كان يريد بذلك إخفاء لاهوته عن إبليس. ولأنه كان بحق حزيناً لأنه كما قال: "يكون فرح في السماء بخاطئ واحد يتوب". هكذا يكون حزن عظيم على صديق واحد يخطئ، وعليه فإنه كان حزيناً حزناً حقيقياً على سقوط يهوذا تلميذه في الخطية. وكان حزيناً علينا حيث قد تغلب علينا الشيطان وأوقعنا في الخطية التي جعلته يحمل الموت عنا بجسده الذي أخذه من السيدة العذراء. وصار إنساناً حقيقياً لا خيالاً. لأن الخيال لا يحزن ولا يكتئب.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He was also truthful when He asked to be spared the cup of death. As human, He had no wish to die and as a human, He suffered and died. As God, His divinity does not suffer pain or death. His divine and human natures are one. As human, He suffered for us, Christians; but as God He is not subject to pain. When He told His disciples, “Rise and pray, lest you enter into temptation,” He taught us to ask God to spare us trials of evil and not to rely upon ourselves. “The spirit indeed is willing, but the flesh is weak," which means that if your spirit is capable of handling trials, your body is weak.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد كان في قوله الصدق عندما سأل أن تعبر عنه كأس الموت. لأنه من حيث هو إنسان تألم ومات. فأما من حيث هو إله فلا يلحق لاهوته ألم ولا موت. ولأنه تبارك اسمه واحد بلاهوته وناسوته، فقد تألم هذا الواحد بناسوته ألماً حقيقياً عنا نحن المسيحيين. وهو بلاهوته غير قابل الآلام، وأما قوله لتلاميذه: "اسهروا وصلوا لئلا تدخلوا في تجربة" فيعلمنا أن نسأل في الصلاة ألا نمتحن في الشرور، ولا نتكل على نفوسنا. "أما الروح فنشيط وأما الجسد فضعيف". فإنه وإن كانت أرواحكم قوية على احتمال الشدائد، إلا أن أجسادكم عن ذلك ضعيفة.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Sleep now, and rest,” because I no longer need your help. The situation had reached its end. He said, “The hour has come” to show His disciples that He knows the future and hidden things, as John said, “Jesus therefore, knowing all things that would come upon Him, went forward,” and         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "ناموا الآن واستريحوا" لأني غير محتاج إلى معونتكم، لأن الأمر قد بلغ النهاية. قال: "هوذا الساعة قد اقتربت" ليدل تلاميذه على أنه عالم بالخفايا والمزمعات كما قال يوحنا: "فخرج يسوع وهو عالم بكل ما يأتي عليه".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “the Son of Man is being betrayed into the hands of sinners,” showing that Jesus did not deserve to die. Only the malicious intents of the Jews made them do what they did. He said, “Rise, let us be going,” to the place that Judas knew.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبقوله: "وابن الإنسان يُسلم نفسه إلى يد الخطاة". دل على أنه لم يستحق الموت ولكن بالنسبة لخبث نيات يهوذا فعلوا به ما فعلوا. قال: "قوموا ننطلق" إلى المكان الذي كان يهوذا يعرفه.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He also said, “See, My betrayer is at hand,” showing that He knew the future and that Judas was alert and working hard on delivering his master while his eleven friends were asleep.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبقوله: "هوذا من يسلمني قد اقترب". دل على علمه بالغيب وأن يهوذا كان مجتهداً ومتيقظاً في تسليم سيده بينما كان أصحابه الإحدى عشر نياماً.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Glory be to God Forever, Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>