<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Gospels         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير الأناجيل         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Matthew the evangelist says that Jesus gave His disciples His holy body and Blood on the eve of His crucifixion, “And when they had sung a hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.” We learn from this that we should never cease worshipping the Lord and that we should praise God after receiving the Holy Communion.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يقول متى البشير أن السيد المسيح قد أعطى تلاميذه جسده ودمه الأقدسين، وكان ذلك في الليلة التي يليها يوم صلبه "ثم سبحوا وخرجوا إلى جبل الزيتون" ونتعلم من ذلك ألا نفتر من ذكر الله تبارك اسمه في كل حال وأن نسبح الله بقلوب نقية بعد تناولنا القربان المقدس.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Therefore, after partaking of the holy mysteries, when we face trials, and before we move from one place to another, because praising God and thanking Him remove every evil fear from the heart and affirms every God-fearing trait.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهكذا يجب علينا بعد تناولنا الطعام، وكذلك عند ملاقاة الشدائد وقبل انتقالنا من مكان إلى غيره، لأن تسبيح الله وشكره يزيل من القلب كل خوف رديء ويثبت فيه كل خشية صالحة.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            People may wonder why Jesus took the disciples to the Mount of Olives at that time. There are several reasons for this. First, Jesus wanted to spare the owners of the house where He had the Paschal Supper with His disciples, the evil of the soldiers who came with Judas from the Sanhedrin and the High Priests. Second, He did not want to be in a confined space so that people would know that nothing would prevent Him from running away, if He so chooses. Third, He wanted to show Himself in an open place where no man can hide. Fourth, Judas knew of this place because the Lord used to go there often to teach.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولسائل أن يسأل: ما هو السبب في خروجهم إلى جبل الزيتون في ذلك الوقت؟ فيقال: أنه أراد بذلك عدة أنواع: الأول أنه أراد أن يصوم أهل المنزل الذي عمل فيه الفصح من شر الجند والشرطة الذين يحضرهم يهوذا من عند رؤساء الكهنة ومشايخ شعب اليهود. والثاني أنه أراد ألا يكون في موضع محصور حتى يعلم أنه لو أراد الهرب لما كان مانع من ذلك. والثالث أراد أن يشهر نفسه في موضع مكشوف لا يمكن لأحد أن يستر فيه. والرابع لأجل أن يهوذا كان يعرف الموضع حيث كان السيد يُعلم فيه ويتردد إليه.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            John writes, “He went out with His disciples over the Brook Kidron, where there was a garden, which He and His disciples entered. And Judas, who betrayed Him, also knew the place; for Jesus often met there with His disciples,” which shows that after leaving the place where they had the Paschal Supper, He went to the Mount of Olives then went to the Brook Kidron and this was the place where they crossed from one side to the other. Judas knew all these places because Jesus met them there to pray and teach.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويقول يوحنا أنه خرج مع تلاميذه إلى عبر وادي قدرون حيث كان بستان دخله هو وتلاميذه. وكان يهوذا يعرف الموضع لأن يسوع اجتمع هناك كثيراً مع تلاميذه. ومن هذا يتضح أنه من بعد الخروج من العلية جاء إلى جبل الزيتون ثم مضى منه إلى عبر وادي قدرون والعبر هو الموضع الذي يعبر منه من هذا الجانب إلى الجانب الآخر. وهذه المواضع بأسرها كان يهوذا يعرفها لأنه كان يجتمع معهم فيها للصلاة والتعليم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Jesus wanted His disciples to be aware of the doubts they will have upon His arrest and of His knowledge of what is to happen so He told them, "All of you will be made to stumble because of Me this night, for it is written: 'I will strike the Shepherd, And the sheep will be scattered.” The shepherd is none other than Jesus and the sheep are none other than the disciples, revealing God’s unparalleled love for us for He has delivered His only Son to be beaten and killed.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأراد الرب أن يعلم تلاميذه بما سيخامرهم من الشك حين القبض عليه وأنه عالم بما سيكون. فقال لهم: "كلكم تشكون فيَّ في هذه الليلة لأنه مكتوب أني أضرب الراعي فتتبدد خراف الرعية" والراعي هو السيد المسيح ورعيته تلاميذه. وبهذا قد أوضح حب الآب لنا الذي لا يعادله حب. إذ أسلم ابنه إلى الضرب والموت، لأنه نسب ضربه إليه.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Zechariah the prophet had prophesied the events of this night when he said that all of them would doubt Him that night. Because Peter loved Him most, He was quick to blunder saying, "Even if all are made to stumble, yet I will not be." Jesus wanted to put an end to his boasting and pride amidst his brethren, and answered him, “I say to you that today, even this night, before the rooster crows twice, you will deny Me three times." He came to know his weakness and was no longer full of self-confidence and pride. Peter was not the only one to sin but encouraged all the other disciples to say as he did which shows us that self-reliance is the beginning of downfall.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد سبق فقال هذه النبوة على لسان زكريا النبي. ولما قال لهم أنهم سيشكون فيه كلهم في هذه الليلة، ولأن بطرس كان أكثر حباً له: تسرع كعادته في الكلام وقال له: "وإن شك فيك الجميع فأنا لا أشك أبداً". فأراد الرب أن يمنع عنه الافتخار والتعظيم على إخوته، وقال له: "إنك في هذه الليلة قبل أن يصيح ديك تنكرني ثلاث مرات". ولكن بطرس كان كثير الثقة بنفسه. ولذلك لم يسأل من السيد أن ينحيه من ذلك. بل أجاب بعجرفة وكبرياء وتكذيب لكلام السيد وقال: "ولو اضطررت أن أموت معك لا أنكرك". وعلى هذا قد استحق أن تتخلى العناية الإلهية عنه حتى جحد سيده. وليعرف ضعفه ولا يعود إلى التكبر والثقة بنفسه ولم يخطئ بطرس وحده في تكذيبه لمعلمه، بل جعل إخوته التلاميذ أن يقولوا مثله. ومن هذا نتعلم أن الاتكال على النفس مقدمة السقوط.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Jesus wanted to show them how strong or rather how weak they are. He said, as stated in Luke, “And the Lord said, "Simon, Simon! Indeed, Satan has asked for you, that he may sift you as wheat,” which means that the devil thinks that you are like the rest of the Jews and will think evil of Me. He will try to make you lose your faith in Me and then betray Me. He will ask Me to forsake you and I will do so for a little while, so that he may know that what you do is because of the human weakness and not out of hatred for Me.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما أحب المسيح أن يريهم مقدار قوتهم وبالحري ضعفهم وأنه مع تخليته لهم لحظة يتركونه ويهربون: قال: ما هو مسطور في لوقا "وقال الرب: سمعان سمعان هوذا الشيطان طلبكم لكي يغربلكم كالحنطة". ومعنى هذا أن الشيطان يظن بكم أنكم كباقي اليهود في اعتقاد الشر فيَّ فيحاول أن يكفركم ويطمع في انحرافكم عني ويعذر بكم كالأجراء معي ويسألني تخليتي إياكم وأنا أفعل ذلك قليلاً أي أتخلى عنكم زماناً يسيراً ليعلم أن ما تفعلونه هو من ضعف البشرية. وليس هو عن بُغض لي.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            This is not the first time that the devil makes a request of the Lord. The devil had asked Him to allow him to enter into a herd of pigs, along with a great number of his servants. “So the demons begged Him, saying, "If You cast us out, permit us to go away into the herd of swine." However, He says to Peter, “But I have prayed for you, that your faith should not fail” for Peter was in extreme danger due to his self-reliance. This shows that the devil’s request for evil to be inflicted upon people is strong, but Jesus’ request is far stronger when addressing the Father. He says, “And I know that You always hear Me.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وليس هذا هو أول سؤال الشيطان لسيدنا بل سأله أيضا أن يدخل مع جيش كبير من أجناده في قطيع من الخنازير. أما العلة التي من أجلها قال لسمعان ولكنني طلبت من أجلك لكيلا يفنى إيمانك هي لأنه كان في أشد الخطر من فرط اتكاله على نفسه، فعلم أن طلب الشيطان ضرر الناس قوي ولكن طلب يسوع أقوى إذ يقول هو نفسه مخاطباً الآب: "وإن علمت أنك في كل حين تسمع لي".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            And Luke says that our Lord told His disciples, “When I sent you without a money bag, knapsack, and sandals, did you lack anything?" Therefore, they said, "Nothing." This means that when I sent you the first time to call the Israelites, I granted you my power and protection but now you must take care of yourselves because I am going to leave you. He did this to show them that if His power and care should leave them, they will meet their doom.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويقول لوقا إن سيدنا قال لتلاميذه: "حين أرسلتكم بلا كيس ولا مزود ولا أحذية هل أعوزكم شيء فقالوا لا" ومعنى ذلك هو أنني حين بعثتكم لولا لدعوة بني إسرائيل أصحبتكم قوتي وراعيتكم حتى جرت أموركم على السداد، والآن فينبغي أن تأخذوا الحذر لنفوسكم لأني مفارقكم وهذا فعله ليشعرهم بمقدار قوته وأن عنايته إن لم تكن معهم هلكوا.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            When He said, “that who does not have a sword let him sell his garment and buy one” He did not want them to fight but to alert them and teach them that the power they have and which will be for their successors is from Him. As the disciple says, “Not that we are sufficient of ourselves to think of anything as being from ourselves, but our sufficiency is from God.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله: "من لم يكن له سيف فليبيع ثوبه وليبتع له سيف". لم يرد به المقاتلة لكن لإشعارهم بأنهم يحتاجون أن يتيقظوا ويتنبهوا مع تخليته إلى حد لا شيء بعده. ويعلموا أن القوة التي كانت لهم أولاً والتي تكون مع خلفائهم من بعدهم هي من جهته كما يقول الرسول: "لسنا أننا كفاة من أنفسنا، بل كفايتنا من الله".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And He was numbered with the transgressors,” which means with the thieves. However, the disciples did not understand His purpose when He said, “let him sell his garment and buy one. Therefore, they said, "Lord, look, here are two swords." And He said to them, "It is enough." He did not mean that two swords are enough but that it is enough talking about this subject because He realized that they were unable to understand. He also said enough so that in the future they will be able to understand. Those who doubt ask, where would the disciples get swords? St. John replies that these were the knives prepared for the Pascha and when the disciples realized the danger that our Lord was in, they took the knives to protect Him. Others have said that the people of Galilee used to wear swords at the time because the country was full of beasts and thieves, hence the disciples wore swords.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله "وأحصي مع أثمة" يريد مع اللصوص. أما التلاميذ فلكونهم لم يعرفوا أغراضه من قوله "ويشتر سيفاً" قالوا عندنا سيفان. فقال لهم يكفي. وليس معنى كلامه أنه يكفي سيفان بل إنه يكفي أن يتكلموا في ذلك الموضوع إذ غير قادرين على إدراك معناه وأن الذي قاله كاف لإدراك المعنى فيما يعد ويتشكك المتشكك ويقول من أين كان للتلاميذ سيوف ويقول يوحنا فم الذهب إنها السكاكين المعدة للفصح. ولما علم التلاميذ بصورة ما يحل بالسيد أخذوها معهم ليدافعوا عنه. وقال غيره أن أكثر الجليليين كانوا يتقلدون السيوف في ذلك الوقت لأن البلاد يومئذ كانت كثيرة الوحوش واللصوص فجرى بعض التلاميذ على عادة أهل وطنهم         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Glory be to Our God Forever, Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولربنا المجد دائماً أبداً. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>