<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Text>      <Language id="English">         In the Church of the firstborn: in the pure assembly: living in all piety: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         في كنيسة الأبكار: في مـجـمـع الأطهار: قائـــم بـكــل وقــــار: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         He was an idol worshipper: a highway robber: he inquired about the Judge: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         كان أصله عابد أوثان: قاطع طريق لزمـان: وســـأل عن الديـــــان: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Moses was a barbarian: his life was full of sin: he yearned to be purified: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         كان موسى من البربر: حياته مليئة بالشر: وطـــلــب إنــه يـتـبـرر: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         A thief, murderer, and adulterer: lover of this passing world: the precious Blood washed him: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         ســـارق قـــاتــل زاني: حب العالم الفاني: غـســلـه الـدم الـقانـي: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Moses the thirsty: heard of the fathers the monks: the dwellers of Shiheet: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         سمع موسى العطشان: عن الآباء الرهبان: بشـيـهيت كانوا سـكان: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         He asked, “Is there a God: Great and Awesome: my heart yearns for Him”: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         ســـأل هــل فيه إلـــه: له العظمة والجاه: قلبي مشتاق لســمـاه: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Abba Isidore answered: “Our God is Strong and Holy: all heads bow to Him” : the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         أجابه آڤا إيسيذورس: إلهنا قوي قدوس: تنـحنــي لــه الرؤوس: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Our God is merciful: He took the form of man: through His love He accepted shame: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         إلهنا رؤوف حنّـان: أخذ شـكـل الإنســـــان: من محبته رضي بالهوان: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Our God’s promise is faithful: He accepts all the repentant: and loves the humble ones: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         إلـــهـنا وعـده أميـن: يـقـبـل كـل التـائـبين: ويـحـب المنسـحقين: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Give your life to Him: abandon your past with Him: with His grace repent to Him: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         سلِّم نفسك في إيديه: وأترك ماضيك عليه: بالنعمة تتـوب إليه: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Moses stood and said: “Receive me like a lost son: help me to repent now!” : the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         وقف موسى وقال: إقبلني كإبن ضال: توبني أتوب في الحـال: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         With tears and joy: with groaning and delight: he repented of his past: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         بـــدمـوع وإبـتـهـالات: بـتــنـهــد وبــزفــرات: ونـدم على كل ما فات: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         He approached Christ with love: heartbroken and wounded: he wished to gain rest: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         تَقَدم للمسـيح: بفؤاد محزون وجريح: وأراد أن يـستريح: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         He offered a true repentance: openly without return: revealing all his sins: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         قدم توبة ورعة: علناً وبلا رجعة: تفاصــيلـها مـتـســعة: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Lo an angel of light: wiped away his black sins: the tablet became pure white: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         وإذا بملاك موجود: يمسح خطاياه السود: بيَّض لوحه الـمشـهود: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Abba Macarius witnessed: that his Lord forgave and saved him: a new life was granted to him: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         أنبا مكاريوس رآه: رَبُه سامحه ونجاه: وإنكتبت له الحيـاة: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         He received the first Mystery: by water, Spirit and fire: removing all impurities: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         نـــــال أول الأســرار: بالماء والروح والنار: وأزال كــــــل الأوزار: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Repentance is amazing: kindling fire in the heart: the stranger becomes a companion: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         دي التوبة أثرها عجيب: تشعل في القلب لهيب: والشــارد يبقى قريب: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         The murderer became righteous: the sinner a chosen vessel: the robber among the chosen ones: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         القاتل أصبح بار: والخاطئ إناء مختار: والسارق من الأخيار: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Repentance is powerful: making the adulterous a virgin: and the doubtful accepted: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         والتوبة لها مفعول: تجعل الزاني بتول: والمتمرد مـقـبول: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         A servant of desires and shame: received dignity through grace: becoming the strongest of the free: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         عبد الشهوات والعار: النعمة أعطت له فخار: واصبح أقـوى الأحرار: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         The Spirit guided the tyrant: from darkness to light: producing fruits for His beloved: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         والروح قاد الجبار: من الظلمة للأنوار: ووهب لحبيبـه ثـمار: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         He longed for monasticism: and vowed to walk in goodness: God showed him the way: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         إشــتــاق لـحـياة الدير: وعزم يسلك في الخير: فرســم له خط الســير: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         His asceticism surpassed others: he served the other monks: with humility and vigils: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         في نسكه فاق الأقران: كان يخدم الرهبان: بـتواضــع الســـهــران: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         With perseverance he exhausted himself: walking thousands of meters: to fill their water jars: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         يتعب نفسه بإصرار: يمشي آلاف الأمتار: يـملأ لـهـــم الـجـرار: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         He was advancing in the way: in steadfastness and diligence: and growth in righteousness: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         صار يقطع الطريق: في ثبات مع تدقيق: وتقـدم فيـما يليــق: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         In virtues and prayers: in fasting and asceticism: in reverence and prostrations: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         في فضائل في صلوات: في صوم في نسكيات: بتخشـع ومــطــانـيــات: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         An ascetic faithful worshiper: with strong steadfast faith: terrifying the demons: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         عابد زاهد وأمين: وإيمانه أساسه متين: يـــرعــب الشـياطين: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         He loved the brothers: they chose him for the priesthood: they made known their desire: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         حب الأخوة وحبوه: للكهنوت إنتخبوه: رفعوا الرغبة وطلبـوه: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         When they tested him: the priests roused and expelled him: he submitted to their command: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         لكن حين إمتحنوه: ثاروا الكهنة وطردوه: وخضع لما أرادوه: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         He said, “I am not worthy: they banished you O black one: O you dark-skinned man!”: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         قال إستحقاقي يكون: نبذوك يا أسود اللون: يا رمادي الجلد تهـون: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         The patriarch heard his sayings: he learned of his righteous acts: his humble and perfect soul: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         سمع البطرك أقواله: وعرف تقوى أحواله: وإتضاع روحه وكماله: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         He ordained him in the Holy Name: a voice said “Worthy”: all the souls heard it: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         رسمه بأمر القدوس: وصوت قال أكسيوس: ســمعته كل النفوس: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Blessed are you O Moses: you received your King’s praise: the Lord of the vine empowered you: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         طوباك يا موسى طوباك: قد نلت رضا مولاك: رب الكـرمـة قـوّاك: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Once they requested you: for the case of a sinful monk: in the assembly they would judge him: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         وفي مرة جم طلبوه: لراهب إستذنبوه: في المجمع هايحاكموه: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Saint Moses came to them: a bag of sand on his back: he entered sad and sorrowful: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         جالهم موسى القديس: على ظهره الرمل في كيس: ودخل مهموم وتعيـس: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         They asked him what he carried: what was it that he brought in: he said he is carrying his sins: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         سألوه إيه جاب وياه: وإيه الحمل اللي معاه: قال إنه شـايل خطاياه: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         A famous helpful lesson: the monks accepted joyfully: they forgave the poor sinner: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         كان درس مفيد مشهور: قبله الرهبان بسرور: سامحو الخاطئ المكسور: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         We wish to live your life: we wish to be like you: remember us in your prayers: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         ياريت نحيا حياتك: ياريتنا في صفاتك: أذكـرنا في صـــــلاتك: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Before the exalted throne: before God the Great: remember us our beloved father: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         قدام العرش العالي: وأمام الرب الوالي: أذكــــرنا يا أبــانا الغالي: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Abba (….) the great: may He grant him long life: to preach the Gospel: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         أنبا(....) الجليل: يعطي له عمر طويل: لــيــكــــرز بــالإنـجـيـل: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Abba (….) our bishop: keep him and us O Lord: with his prayers protect us: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         وأنبا (....) أسقفنا: إحفظه يارب وإحفظنا: وبــصــلاتـه أحـرسـنا: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         The bishops and clergy: guard them O Holy: with the ranks of the angels: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         والأساقفة والإكليروس: إحـــمــــيــهــم يـــــا قــــدوس: حوطهم بعساكر ني أنجيلوس: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         The deacons and monks: the servants in every place: O Lord fill them with faith: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         والشمامسة والرهبان: والخدام في كل مكان: يــارب إمــلأهـم بالإيـمـان: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         Abba Moses blessed are you: you received your King’s praise: the Lord of the vine protected you: the strong Abba Moses.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         أنبا موسى طوباك: قد نلت رضا مولاك: رب الكـرمـة صانك وحَماك: بي جوري اڤا موسي.      </Language>   </Text>   <Text>      <Language id="English">         The mention of your name: is in all the believers’ mouths: they all say “O God of Abba Moses: help all of us!”      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         تفسير إسمك في أفواه: كـــــل الــمـــؤمــنـيــن: الــكـل يقولون يا إلــه: أنبا موسى أعنا أجمعــين.      </Language>   </Text></Document>