<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Gospels         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير الأناجيل         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Due to Adam’s sin, his eating from the forbidden tree, we came to reside in three houses. When man was thrown out of Eden, his body and soul resided on earth. Upon death, the body resides in a house and the soul in another. The body resides in a grave and the soul resides in Hades; but our God visited man in all three. In each visit, he took our form. He visited those living on earth in a human body and with a soul like them. He visited the dead bodies in a dead body in a grave, like them. As for those who were in Hades, He appeared to them as a human being and delivered them.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إننا بمعصية آدم وأكله من الشجرة صرنا ننزل ثلاثة منازل. لما خرجنا من الفردوس نزلنا بالجسد والنفس أحياء إلى الأرض. وفي حين الموت ينزل جسدنا في منزل ونفسنا في آخر. أي ينزل جسدنا إلى القبر ونفسنا إلى الجحيم فأنعم علينا إلهنا بافتقادنا في هذه المنازل الثلاثة. وفى كل منزل ظَهر بها كشبهنا. الأحياء على الأرض ظهر لهم حياً بجسد ونفس مثلهم. والأجساد الميتة ظهر لها مثلها بجسد ميت في قبر. والأنفس التي في الجحيم أشرق عليها بنفس ناسوته وأصعدها من الجحيم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            When Adam left Eden to earth and started to multiply, the devil drew humankind to sin until they became evil. They corrupted the earth and made it vile. God sent them the prophets to guide them back to the virtuous path and to urge them to avoid sin and wickedness but the prophets failed in doing so. They only managed to save themselves from sin and that is why the Son of God and the second Person of the Holy Trinity came to earth in the body of a man. He resembled us in every aspect except sin. He lived on earth a holy and a perfect life showing us the plan that had been set but that we had not followed and demonstrating that it is possible for those who chose to please their Creator to live in perfection in this life.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وذلك أن آدم لما خرج من الفردوس إلى الأرض وتناسل منه الجنس البشري. صار الشيطان يحسن إلى الناس الخطيئة حتى توغلوا في الشرور وقد عم الفساد الأرض وتنجست من آثامهم. فأرسل الرب إليهم الأنبياء يرشدونهم إلى الطريق المستقيم ويحثونهم على مجانبة الشرور ومباينة الآثام. وقد عجز الأنبياء في مهمتهم هذه. ولم يقدروا إلا على تخليص نفوسهم فقط من الخطيئة الفعلية لا الجدية. ولذا نزل ابن الله الأقنوم الثاني من الثالوث وأخذ جسداً منا وتشبه بنا في كل شيء ماخلا الخطيئة وسار على الأرض سيرة القداسة وبالإجمال على غاية ما يكون من الكمال وهو يقصد بذلك أن يرسم لنا خطة قد عجزنا عن سلوكها. ليُعَلِمنا أن السلوك بالكمال في هذه الحياة الدنيا ممكن لمن يرغب رضا باريه.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Because of their sinful life, the Jews refused to accept His teachings. Overpowered by their desires, they sentenced Him to death because His ways did not agree with their works. He tolerated unbelievable humiliations and tortures demonstrating for us forgiveness, even to those who wrong us. He asked God to forgive those who crucified Him while He was on the cross and they were mocking Him. When the hour came and He gave His spirit, He descended into Hades with His divine nature and delivered those captured there.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولكن اليهود لتوغلهم في الآثام لم يقبلوا منه الوعظ والإرشاد لتغلب الأهواء عليهم. وحكموا عليه بالموت حسداً لمغايرة أعماله لأعمالهم. وقد احتمل منهم من الإهانات الفادحة والآلام المبرحة ما يعجز اللسان عن وصفها. تاركاً لنا بذلك نموذج الصفح عمَّن يسيء إلينا كما طلب هو الغفران لصالبيه في الوقت الذي كان فيه مُعلقاً على الصليب وهم يفترون عليه ويستهزئون به حتى أتت الساعة المعيَّنة التي فيها أسلَم الروح حيث نزلت إلى الجحيم متحدة باللاهوت وخلصت المسبيين الذين ماتوا على رجاء.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            When the Lord gave up His spirit, “Then, behold, the veil of the temple was torn in two from top to bottom”; all the heavenly powers and authorities surrounded the cross disturbed by the horror of the crucifixion. When the Lord gave up His spirit, the chief of the angels wanted to strike the city with his sword and divide it in two to swallow all those who conspired against Jesus but God had mercy on them and asked the angel to tear the veil of the altar.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما أسلم الرب الروح "وإذا حجاب الهيكل انشق إلى أثنين من فوق إلى أسفل" ويجب أن نعلم أن السيد لما كان على الصليب كانت جميع القوات السمائية محيطة بالصليب المقدس منزعجة من هول ذلك الأمر. فلما أسلم السيد الروح أراد رئيس الملائكة أن يضرب بسيفه وسط المدينة فيقسمها شطرين لتبتلع جميع الذين اتفقت مؤامرتهم على صلب الرب. فرحمهم الرب إلا أنه لم يعطل حميته وأشار إليه أن يضرب بسيفه حجاب الهيكل فانشق إلى أثنين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            This was a sign of the destruction of the temple at the hands of the Romans, and a sign of the end of the priesthood of the Jews, their offerings, their laws and it indicated the taking away of their blessing. The Lord Christ died at the ninth hour, which was the time the Jews made their evening offering in the temple and the priest offered incense in the Holy of Holies while the people prayed outside. Behold the veil was torn in two, as a sign of the destruction of the temple and the laws of Moses. It also indicated they blasphemed against their God. The Jews used to tear their garment when they heard a blasphemy. “And the earth quaked, and the rocks were split,” because of the danger and the immense horror of the crucifixion. Its danger disturbed even the inanimate objects. The sun covered its light so as not to see the sufferings of the Lord Christ and the earth trembled at the grave sin of its inhabitants. The quaking of the earth was like the shaking of vessel at sea; threatening the hypocrite. “The rocks were split” indicating that the crucified was the Creator and that the inanimate grieved His suffering while the hearts of His tormentors were still hard and cruel. Since the tongues that were supposed to praise and glorify Him became dumb and silent, the inanimate rocks screamed, praising and glorifying the Lord. Our Lord Jesus Christ referred to this saying, “I tell you that if these should keep silent, the stones would immediately cry out.” In several cases, God had rebuked the speaking using the dumb as Balaam’s donkey rebuked him and the splitting of the altar and the pouring out of the ashes rebuked Jeroboam.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان ذلك لنوعين: الأول علامة على خرابه فيما يأتي من الأيام على أيدي الرومان والثاني دلاله على إبطال كهنوت اليهود وقرابينهم ونواميسهم وانتزاع نعمة الله منهم. وذلك أنه لما كان موت السيد المسيح في الساعة التاسعة من النهار أي في الوقت الذي تُقدَّم فيه ذبيحة المساء في الهيكل وكان الكاهن يقدم البخور حينئذ في القدس والشعب يصلي خارجاً. وإذا حجاب الهيكل قد انشق إلى أثنين علامة على خرابه ونسخ النظام الموسوي وليدل على أنهم قد جدفوا على إلههم وذلك أنهم كانوا يشقون ثيابهم عند سماعهم التجديف "والأرض تزلزلت" لأن حادث الصلب كان خطره عظيماً وهوله شديداً. ومن خطورته اضطربت الجمادات. فكما أن الشمس حجبت نورها حتى لا تعاين آلام السيد المسيح. كذلك الأرض قد ارتجفت من فظاعة إثم سكانها بصلبهم رب المجد. وتزلزُل الأرض كان كاهتزاز المهد أو كاهتزاز الإناء في الماء وكان ذلك تهديداً للمنافقين "والصخور تشققت" دلالة على أن المصلوب هو الخالق وأن الجماد قد لان مُظهراً التألم على آلام مبدع الكون وقلوب صالبي الرب لم تزل على ما هي عليه من الصلابة والقساوة. وبما إن الألسنة الناطقة التي كان لائقاً بها أن تميز من المصلوب لتسبحه قد أُعدمت النطق وأبكمت. فقد صرخت الحجارة بالتمجيد والتسبيح. وإلى هذه المعنى يشير ربنا يسوع المسيح بقوله: "إن سكت هؤلاء فالحجارة تصرخ". وكثيراً ما يردع الله أحيانا الناطقين بواسطة غير الناطقين كما ردع بلعام بأتانه. ويوريعام بانشقاق المذبح وتذرية الرماد.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The evangelist said, “and the graves were opened; and many bodies of the saints who had fallen asleep were raised” referring to the raising of the residents of the graves upon the Lord’s command in the second coming because He said, “the hour is coming, and now is, when the dead will hear the voice of the Son of God; and those who hear will live.” Then he said, “Do not marvel at this; for the hour is coming in which all who are in the graves will hear His voice and come forth--those who have done good, to the resurrection of life, and those who have done evil, to the resurrection of condemnation”, meaning: do not be surprised that some of the dead will be resurrected upon hearing My voice, because there will come another hour when all those residing in the graves will hear His voice.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال البشير: "والقبور تفتحت وقام كثير من أجساد القديسين الراقدين" وهذا إشارة إلى قيام سائر من في القبور بأمره في مجيئه الثاني لأنه القائل: "أنه تأتى ساعة وهي الآن حين يسمع الأموات صوت ابن الله والسامعون يحيون". ثم قال: "لا تتعجبوا من هذا. فأنه تأتي ساعة فيها يسمع جميع الذين في القبور صوته. فيخرج الذين فعلوا الصالحات إلى قيامة الحيوة والذين عملوا السيئات إلى قيامة الدينونة"، تقديره لا تتعجبوا من إنهاض بعض الموتى قريباً بصوتي لأنه ستأتي ساعة غير هذه يسمع فيها جميع الذين في القبور.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            When He says the resurrection of life and the resurrection of condemnation, He refers to the difference between those He resurrected when He gave up His soul and those He will resurrect upon His second coming. Both signify His general and specific power to resurrect the dead. When He said, “they are saints,” He meant that their testimony was valid. He said, “and coming out of the graves after His resurrection, they went into the holy city and appeared to many” showing that their graves were opened when He gave up the spirit and they were resurrected after His resurrection to announce His resurrection among their families. After those saints had accomplished their mission, they returned to their graves because the time for the general resurrection had not come except for Jesus Christ as St. Paul said, “the firstborn from the dead, that in all things He may have the preeminence.” Note that when Jesus screamed and gave up the spirit four wonders took place: the veil was torn, the earth quaked, the rocks were split, and the dead were raised. If we add darkness at six, then we have five wonders.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله عن هؤلاء خاصة أن قوماً إلى حياة الأبد وقوماً إلى عذاب مؤبد يدل على الفرق بين من أقامهم وقت إسلامه روحه وبين من سيقيمهم عند إتيانه الثاني. وكلا الاثنين يدلان على حصول المقدرة له بطريق التعميم والتخصيص ويقصد بقوله أنهم قديسون لتكون شهادتهم أقرب إلى التصديق. وبقوله : "وخرجوا من القبور بعد قيامته ودخلوا المدينة المقدسة وظهروا لكثيرين" يدل على أن قبورهم تفتحت وقت إسلامه روحه وقيامتهم كانت بعد قيامته ليذيعوا بقيامته بين ذويهم. ومن بعد ما أكمل هؤلاء المراد بقيامتهم عادوا إلى قبورهم لأنه لم يجز أن يقوم القيامة العامة في المقدمة إلا سيدنا المسيح وحده كقول بولس الرسول: "الذي هو البداءة بكر من الأموات". واعلم أنه عندما صرخ السيد المسيح واسلم الروح قد صدرت أربع آيات: انشقاق حجاب الهيكل. وتزلزل الأرض. وتشقق الصخور. وقيام الموتى من القبور. وبإضافة حدوث الظلمة وقت السادسة تكون الآيات خمساً.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “So when the centurion and those with him, who were guarding Jesus, saw the earthquake and the things that had happened, they feared greatly, saying, "Truly this was the Son of God!"” May be the centurion described Jesus as the Son of God because he heard it from Jesus or because he heard the passers by say, “let Him deliver Him now if He will have Him; for He said, 'I am the Son of God.'" Those who guarded Jesus were soldiers sent by the Roman governor Pilate. When they saw these marvels, they were scared because of what they had done along with the Jews. They did not say, “Truly this was the Son of God” out of belief in Him but because they testified for the truth.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "وأما قائد المائة والذين معه يحرسون يسوع فلما رأوا الزلزلة وما كان خافوا جدا وقالوا حقا كان هذا ابن الله" وقول القائد عن الرب أنه "ابن الله" ربما يكون قد سمع منه هذا القول أو علمه من قول المجتازين به "إن كنت ابن الله فخلِّص نفسك" والذين معه يحرسون يسوع هم الجند المرسلون من قبل بيلاطس الوالي الروماني الذين لما رأوا الآيات اشتد خوفهم لأجل ما كان منهم وما أقدموا عليه مع اليهود. وقولهم "حقا كان هذا ابن الله" لم يكن على حكم الإيمان به بل على سبيل الشهادة له بالحق.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And many women who followed Jesus from Galilee, ministering to Him, were there looking on from afar.” The Jews did not realize that these women were disciples. They stood from afar waiting to know what will happen to Jesus so they could notify the disciples. One of them was Mary Magdalene whom Jesus had delivered from seven devils and Mary, mother of James who is the virgin Mary. James is the son of Joseph, the carpenter. Because the virgin Mary was betrothed to Joseph, she considered his children hers. The Mother of Zebedee’s sons, the mother of John and James who are counted among the twelve disciples, was also there. Mark adds, “Salome” and she is a relative of Joseph, the carpenter. She lived near Bethlehem during Jesus’ birth and she attended his birth.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "وكانت هناك نساء كثيرات ينظرن من بعيد وهن كن قد تبعن يسوع من الجليل يخدمنه" أما النساء فلأنهن غير معروفات عند اليهود أنهن من تلاميذه. فكن واقفات من بعيد ينظرن ما سيكون من أمر السيد، فيخبرن به الرسل على جليته. فمنهن مريم المجدلية التي أخرج منها سبعة شياطين "ومريم أم يعقوب" وهى السيدة البتول. ولأن يعقوب هو ابن يوسف النجار ولتعلق البتول بيوسف خطيبها صارت أولاده أولادها بالاستعارة لا على الحقيقة "وأم ابنيَّ زبدي" وهى أم يعقوب ويوحنا المعدودين ضمن الإثني عشر رسولا. ويقول مرقس "وسالومة" وهى من أقارب يوسف النجار وكانت مقيمة في بيت لحم وقت ميلاد الرب بها وحضرت ميلاده.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Therefore, because it was the Preparation Day, the bodies should not remain on the cross on the Sabbath, for that Sabbath was a great day, the Jews asked Pilate that their legs might be broken, and that they might be taken away.” What an absurd excuse! It indicates the evil of its doers who tortured and killed the Savior under the pretext of preserving the Sabbath when they had wronged the Lord of the Sabbath. “Then the soldiers came and broke the legs of the first and of the other who was crucified with Him. But when they came to Jesus and saw that He was already dead, they did not break His legs” to fulfill the prophecy, “He guards all his bones; Not one of them is broken.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "ثم إذ كان استعداد فلِكَي لا تبقى الأجساد على الصليب في السبت لأن يوم ذلك السبت كان عظيماً. سأل اليهود بيلاطس أن تكسر سيقانهم ويُرفعوا" وما أسخف هذا الاحتجاج الذي يدل على فظاعة شر مقدميه إذ أنهم يقتلون المُخلص ويأتون معه من أنواع التعذيب ما يكل اللسان عن وصفها ثم يسترون شناعة عملهم بحجة حفظ السبت بينما أنهم قد أساءوا إلى رب السبت "فأتى العسكر وكسروا ساقي الأول والآخر المصلوب معه. وأما يسوع فلما جاءوا إليه لم يكسروا ساقيه لأنهم راؤه قد مات" لتتم النبوة القائلة: "يحفظ جميع عظامه. واحد منها لا ينكسر".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            It was the Roman custom to leave the crucified on the cross until they die; rot or their bodies are eaten by the birds. The Jews considered leaving the bodies on the crosses defilement to their land, especially after sunset and because Saturday was most holy, so they asked Pilate to remove them.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولأن العادة كانت عند الرومانيين أنهم يتركون المصلوبين على الصلبان حتى يموتوا ويفسدوا وتأكل أجسادهم طيور السماء. أما اليهود فقد حسبوا إبقاء الأجساد على الصلبان تنجيسا لأرضهم. لاسيما بعد غروب الشمس. ولما كان السبت عندهم من أقدس الأيام سألوا بيلاطس ذلك السؤال.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “But one of the soldiers pierced His side with a spear,” to confirm his death “and immediately blood and water came out,” indicating that he did not die defeated and to fulfill Zechariah prophecy, “then they will look on Me whom they pierced.” He was not pierced except in his side because as sin was from the woman who was created from a rib taken from the side of the first Adam so came salvation and purification from the side of the second Adam. Blood saved us and water purified us. His holy Blood was spilt on the earth to keep it and its inhabitants. His Body was raised on the cross to save the severed. His soul went to Hades to save those who were there because He is the Pantocrator. Glory be to Him forever, Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "لكن واحداً من العسكر طعن جنبه بحربة" ليتأكد من موته "وللوقت خرج دم وماء" دلالة على أنه لم يمت مقبوراً. ولتتم نبوة زكريا القائلة: "فينظرون إلى الذي طعنوه" ولم يُطعن في موضع غير جنبه لكي كما أن الخطيئة كانت أولا من المرأة التي خُلقت من الضلع المأخوذ من جنب آدم الأول. كذلك كان الخلاص والتطهير من جنب آدم الثاني. لأن بالدم كان الخلاص. وبالماء التطهير. هذا وأن دمه الأقدس قد أهرق على الأرض ليحفظها ومن عليها. وجسده كان مرفوعا على الصليب ليحفظ الاستقصاءات: ونفسه ذهبت إلى الجحيم خلَّصت الذين هناك لأنه ضابط الكل الذي له المجد الدائم إلى الأبد آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>       </Document>