<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Absolution of the Servants</language><language id="Indonesian">Absolusi Pelayan</language>         <language id="Arabic">تحليل الخدام</language>      </Title>            <comment>         <language id="English">                     The priest makes the sign of the cross at each of the following times: (1) eastward on the serving priests; (2) eastward on the deacons; (3) turning northward, on the rest of the servants; (4) turning westward, on the entire congregation; and (5) turning to the East, on himself.         </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Imam membuat tanda salib pada setiap saat berikut ini: (1) ke arah timur pada imam yang sedang melayani; (2) ke arah timur pada diaken; (3) berbalik ke arah utara, pada pelayan lainnya; (4) berbalik ke arah barat, pada seluruh jemaat; dan (5) berbalik ke arah timur, pada dirinya sendiri.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">                     (1) يرشم الكهنة الخدام شرقاً رشماً واحداً بمثال الصليب. (2) يرشم الشمامسة شرقاً رشماً واحداً. (3) يلتفت ويرشم بحرياً باقي الخدام الوقوف في الخورس. (4) يلتفت ويرشم الشعب كله غرباً. (5) يلتفت إلى الشرقِ ويرشم ذاته.         </language>      </comment>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Neke~biaik n~refsemsi n~te paie~hoou vai: pih/goumenoc (pip~recbuteroc:) nem pidiakwn nem pik~l/roc nem pilaoc t/rf nem tametjwb.         </language>         <language id="English">            May Your servants, ministers of this day, the hegumen(s), the priest(s), (1) the deacon(s), (2) the clergy, (3) and all the people, (4) and my weakness, (5)         </language><language id="Indonesian">Kiranya hamba-hamba-Mu, pelayan-pelayan-Mu hari ini, (para) hegomen, (para) imam, (1) (para) diakon, (2) para klerus, (3) dan semua umat-Mu, (4) dan kelemahan diri saya, (5)</language>         <language id="Arabic">            عبيدُكَ خدامُ هذا اليوم، القمص (أو القس1) والشماس (2) والإكليروس (3) وكلُّ الشعبِ، (4) وضعفي.(5)         </language>               </text>                  <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Eue~swpi euoi n~remhe: e~bolqen rwc n~]pana~gia~ Triac: Viwt nem Ps/ri nem Pip~neuma eyouab.         </language>         <language id="English">            be absolved from the mouth of the All Holy Trinity, the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit;         </language><language id="Indonesian">            akan diselamatkan dari mulut Allah Tritunggal Yang Maha Kudus, Bapa, Putra dan Roh Kudus, </language>         <language id="Arabic">            يكونونَ محاللين من فمِ الثالوثِ القدوسِ الآبِ والابنِ والروحِ القدسِ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Nem e~bolqen rwc n~]oui~ m~mauatc eyouab n~kayolik/ n~a~poctoctolik/ n~ekk~l/cia.         </language>         <language id="English">            and from the mouth of the one, only, holy, catholic, and apostolic Church;         </language><language id="Indonesian">dan dari mulut gereja yang satu, satu-satunya kudus, katholik  dan apostolik.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            ومن فمِ الكنيسةِ الواحدةِ الوحيدةِ المقدسةِ الجامعةِ الرسوليةِ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Nem e~bolqen rwou m~pi02 (metc~nau) n~a~poctoloc: nem e~bolqen rwf m~piyew~rimoc n~euaggelict/c Markoc pia~poctoloc eyouab ouoh m~marturoc: nem pipatriar,/c eyouab Ceu/roc: nem pencaq Diockoroc: nem pia~gioc Ayanacioc pia~poctolikoc: nem pia~gioc Petroc ieromarturoc piar,iereuc: nem pia~gioc Iwann/c pi,~rucoctomoc: nem pia~gioc Kurilloc: nem pia~gioc Bacilioc: nem pia~gioc Gr/gorioc.         </language>         <language id="English">            and from the mouths of the twelve apostles; and from the mouth of the Beholder of God, the Evangelist Mark, the holy apostle and martyr; the patriarch Saint Severus; our teacher Dioscorus; Saint Athanasius the Apostolic; Saint Peter the holy martyr and archpriest; Saint John Chrysostom; Saint Cyril; Saint Basil; and Saint Gregory;         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Dan dari mulut kedua belas rasul, dari mulut  Penginjil Santo Markus Rasul dan Martir sang Pelihat Allah, dan dari Patriarkh Santo Severus, dan Santo Dioskorus Guru kami, dari Santo Athanasius yang Rasuli, Santo Petrus meterai Martir Suci yang terakhir dan Imam Agung, Santo Yohanes Krisostomos, Santo Kyrillos, Santo Pasilius, dan Santo Gregorius,         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ومن أفواهِ الاثني عشرَ رسولاً، ومن فم ناظِرِ الإلهِ الانجيلي مَرقُسَ الرسولِ الطاهرِ والشهيد، والبطريركِ القديسِ ساويرس، ومعلمِنا ديسقورس، والقديسِ أَثناسيوسَ الرسولي، والقديسِ بطرسَ الشهيد الطاهر رئيسِ الكهنةِ، والقديسِ يوحنا ذهبيِّ الفمِ، والقديسِ كيرلس، والقديسِ باسيليوس، والقديس اغريغوريوس.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Nem e~bolqen rwou m~pit#i#/# (somt se met s~m/n) e~tauywou] qen Nikea~: nem pir#n# (se tebi) n~te Kwctantinoupolic: nem pic# (c~nau se) n~te Evecoc.         </language>         <language id="English">            and from the mouths of the three hundred and eighteen assembled at Nicea; the one hundred and fifty at Constantinople; and the two hundred at Ephesus;         </language><language id="Indonesian">            dan dari mulut tiga ratus delapanbelas bapa-bapa yang berkumpul di konsili Nikea, dan seratus lima puluh di konsili Konstantinopel, dan dua ratus di konsili Efesus, </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ومن افواهِ الثلثمائةِ والثمانيةِ عشرَ المجتمعين بنيقيه، والمِئَة والخمسين بمدينةِ القسطنطينية، والمِئَتَيْنِ بأفسس.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Nem e~bolqen rwf m~peniwt ettai/out n~ar,ie~reuc abba (...) nem pefkes~v/r n~litourgoc abba (...) pie~pickopoc (pim/tropolit/c): nem e~bolqen rwc n~tamete~la,ictoc.         </language>         <language id="English">            and from the mouth of our honored father, the archpriest, Abba (...); and from the mouth of his partner in the [apostolic] liturgy, our honored father the bishop (metropolitan), Abba (...); and from my own mouth, being the least.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            dan melalui mulut yang kami muliakan Imam Besar dan Baba Anba (..), dan  rekannya dalam Liturgi Apostolik Bapa kita Uskup/Metropolitan Abba (..) dan dari mulut saya yang hina ini.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ومن فمِ أبينا المكرم رئيسِ الكهنةِ أنبا (...) وشريكهِ في الخدمةِ [الرسوليةِ] أبينا الأسقف (المطران) المكرم أنبا (...) ومن فمِ حقارتي.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Je f~c~marwout ouoh f~meh n~w~ou n~je pekran eyouab: Viwt nem Ps/ri nem Pip~neuma eyouab.         </language>         <language id="English">            For blessed and full of glory is Your holy name, O Father and Son and Holy Spirit,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Karena diberkati dan penuh kemuliaan Nama-Mu yang kudus, ya Bapa, Putra dan Roh Kudus, </language>         <language id="Arabic">            لأنه مباركٌ ومملوءٌ مجداً اسمُك القدوسُ، أيها الآبُ والابنُ والروحُ القدسُ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            }nou nem n~c/ou niben nem sa e~neh n~te nie~neh t/rou: a~m/n.         </language>         <language id="English">            now and at all times and unto the age of all ages. Amen.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            sekarang dan selamanya dan dari segala abad hingga segala abad, Amin         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ كلِّها. آمين.         </language>               </text>        </section> </document>