<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <section expanded="true">                  <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">All You Heavenly Orders</language><language id="Indonesian">All You Heavenly Orders</language>         <language id="Arabic">يا كل الصفوف</language>                           </Title>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ni,oroc t/rou n~naniv/oui: a~ri'alin e~Pennou] qen nibwhem n~te nihwc: ounof m~mwten neman m~voou e~retenrasi: qen t~a~nactacic m~v~n/b Pi,~rictoc.         </language>         <language id="English">            All you heavenly orders, sing to our God with the melody of praise. Rejoice with us today with gladness, in the Resurrection of the Lord Christ.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Semua paduan suara surgawi, Bernyanyilah bagi Tuhan kami dengan melodi pujian, Bersukacitalah bersama kami hari ini dengan kesenangan, di dalam Kebangkitan Tuhan Kristus.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            يا كل الصفوف السمائيين، رتلوا لإلهنا بنغمات التسبيح وابتهجوا معنا اليوم فرحين، بقيامة السيد المسيح.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Mvoou a~nip~rov/tia jwk e~bol: ouoh a~nicaji n~te nenio] swpi: eybe t~a~nactacic m~P[oic e~bol qen n/eymwout: efoi n~sorp n~n/etauenkot:         </language>         <language id="English">            Today the prophecies are fulfilled and the sayings of the forefathers are realized by the Resurrection of the Lord from among the dead; He is the firstfruit of those who have fallen asleep.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Hari ini nubuatan digenapi, Dan perkataan nenek moyang diwujudkan, Dengan Kebangkitan Tuhan dari antara orang mati, Dia adalah buah sulung dari mereka yang telah meninggal.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            اليوم قد كملت النبوات ، وقد تمت أقوال الآباء الأولين بقيامة الرب من بين الأموات ، وهو بدء المضطجعين.          </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Aftwnf n~je P[oic m~v~r/] m~v/ e~tenkot: ie ke ouai efyaqi e~bol qen p~/rp: ouoh aferh~mot nan m~piwnq n~e~neh: ouoh afaiten n~remhe e~bol ha ]metbwk n~sasi.         </language>         <language id="English">            The Lord arose as one who sleeps, and as one who is sated with wine, He has granted us the everlasting joy, and freed us from bitter bondage.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tuhan bangkit sebagai orang yang tidur, Dan sebagai orang yang kenyang dengan anggur, Dia telah memberi kita sukacita abadi, Dan membebaskan kita dari perbudakan pahit.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            قد قام الرب مثل النائم ، وكالثمل من الخمرة ، ووهبنا النعيم الدائم ، وعتقنا من العبودية المرة.         </language>               </text>            <text>                        <language id="English">            He led Hades captive and crushed the brass doors. He utterly broke the bars of iron and, for us, exchanged punishment for salvation.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            He led Hades captive and crushed the brass doors. He utterly broke the bars of iron and, for us, exchanged punishment for salvation.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وسبي الجحيم سبياً، وحطم ابوابه النحاس، وكسر متاريسه الحديد كسراً، وأبدل لنا العقوبة بالخلاص.         </language>               </text>            <text>                        <language id="English">            And brought back Adam to Paradise, with joy, gladness, and happiness; he and his sons who were in captivity, to the joy once more.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            And brought back Adam to Paradise, with joy, gladness, and happiness; he and his sons who were in captivity, to the joy once more.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وأعاد آدم إلي الفردوس، بفرح وبهجة ومسرة، هو وبنيه الذين كانوا في الحبس، إلي النعيم دفعة أخري.         </language>               </text>            <text>                        <language id="English">            Today the flags of salvation spread, the bodies and the spirits were renewed, and the believers won the clemency for retribution, and glorified God with praises and joy.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Today the flags of salvation spread, the bodies and the spirits were renewed, and the believers won the clemency for retribution, and glorified God with praises and joy.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            اليوم إنتشرت اعلام الخلاص، وتجددت الأجسام والأرواح، وفاز المؤمنون بالصفح عن القصاص، ومجدوا الله بالتسابيح والأفراح.         </language>               </text>            <text>                        <language id="English">            Today the daughter of David rejoiced, and the hearts of the righteous apostles became glad, when they announced to them the news, and what they heard from the pure angels.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Today the daughter of David rejoiced, and the hearts of the righteous apostles became glad, when they announced to them the news, and what they heard from the pure angels.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            اليوم إبتهجت إبنة داود، وتهللت قلوب الرسل الأبرار، حينما بشرتهم النسوة بتمام الموعود، وما سمعوه من الملائكة الأطهار.         </language>               </text>            <text>                        <language id="English">            That Jesus Christ is risen, “But He is not here as you see.” So the women went to His honored disciples and announced to them, the Resurrection of the Creator of all things.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            That Jesus Christ is risen, “But He is not here as you see.” So the women went to His honored disciples and announced to them, the Resurrection of the Creator of all things.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أن يسوع المسيح قد قام، ليس هو ههنا كما ترون. فذهبت النسوة وبشرت تلاميذه الكرام، بقيامة خالق البرايا أجمعين.         </language>               </text>            <text>                        <language id="English">            And He appeared to His disciples and gave them joy, with delight they saw Him, in the glory of His divinity and they became happy, when they saw Him alive.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            And He appeared to His disciples and gave them joy, with delight they saw Him, in the glory of His divinity and they became happy, when they saw Him alive.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وظهر لتلاميذه وأبهجهم، ببهاء نظره متجلياً، بمجد لاهوته وأسعدهم، لما شاهدوه حيّاً.         </language>               </text>            <text>                        <language id="English">            We praise and increase His exaltation, and confess the glory of His Resurrection, we thank Him for His great grace, for His mercy endures forever.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            We praise and increase His exaltation, and confess the glory of His Resurrection, we thank Him for His great grace, for His mercy endures forever.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            نسبحه ونزيد رفعته، ونعترف بمجد قيامته، ونشكره علي عظيم نعمته، لأن إلي الأبد رحمته..         </language>               </text>   </section>   </document>