<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <role id="Deacon">      <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Exposition Introduction</language><language id="Indonesian">Pendahuluan Komentari</language>         </Title>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Acere~piyumin e~nau: n~je ?lan/ ]ourw: e~pise eyouab n~te pic~tauroc: pise e~taues Pa[oic e~rof.            </language>            <language id="English">               Queen Helen desired to see the holy wood of the cross, on which my Lord was crucified.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ratu Helena ingin melihat kayu salib yang kudus, tempat Tuhan disalibkan di atasnya.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               اشتهت الملكة هيلانة أن تنظر خشبة الصليب المقدس التي صلب السيد عليها.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Mpec,atotc e~bol e~p~t/rf: eckw] n~cwf qen ou[isswou: sa tecjemf qen ouc~pod/: eybe pecnah] e~qoun e~rof…            </language>            <language id="English">               She did not give up at all, seeking after it longingly, until she found it diligently, because of her faith in it…            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ia sama sekali tidak pernah lelah, melainkan senantiasa mencarinya dengan kerinduan dan kesungguhan sampai ia menemukannya karena kesetiaannya...            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               فلم تكل البتة بل كانت تطلبه باشتياقٍ واجتهاد حتي وجدته من أجل أمانتها...            </language>         </text>      </section>            <comment>         <language id="English">            The expositions are continued:         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Komentari dilanjutkan</language>      </comment>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">First Exposition</language><language id="Indonesian">Komentari Pertama</language>            <language id="Arabic">الطرح الأول</language>         </Title>                  <text>            <language id="English">               Queen Helen desired to see the holy wood of the Cross on which the Lord was crucified.  She longed for it diligently and she did not rest.  Because of her faith she found it.                         </language><language id="Indonesian">Ratu Helena ingin melihat kayu salib yang kudus, tempat Tuhan disalibkan di atasnya. Ia sama sekali tidak pernah lelah, melainkan senantiasa mencarinya dengan kerinduan dan kesungguhan sampai ia menemukannya karena kesetiaannya.</language>            <language id="Arabic">                شتهت الملكة هيلانة أن تنظر خشبة الصليب المقدس التي صلب السيد عليها. فلم تكل البتة بل كانت تطلبه باشتياقٍ واجتهاد حتي وجدته من أجل أمانتها.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="English">               This is a day of rejoicing in heaven and on earth for the appearance of the life-giving Cross.  We bow to the Cross, the immortal wood on which Christ was crucified to save us from our sins.                         </language><language id="Indonesian">Hari itu menjadi sukacita di surga dan di bumi karena penampakan salib yang menghidupkan. Kita sujud kepada salib, kayu yang tak dapat binasa, tempat Tuhan disalibkan di atasnya sampai Ia menyelamatkan kita dari dosa-dosa kita.</language>            <language id="Arabic">                كان فرح اليوم في السماء وعلي الأرض من أجل ظهور الصليب المحيي. نسجد للصليب، الخشبة الغير المائتة التي صلب السيد عليها حتى خلصنا من خطايانا.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="English">               Queen Helen went with three thousand soldiers to Jerusalem to ask for the Cross.  The Jews consulted together saying, “We will not show the Cross, even if we have to die.” So Judas prayed, saying “O Lord the Almighty, the Lord of Hosts, who is sitting on the cherubim, show us.  O You, who measured the heavens by the span of Your hands and the earth with Your fist,             </language><language id="Indonesian">Helena sang ratu bangkit, dan membawa bersamanya tiga ribu prajurit, lalu pergi ke Yerusalem untuk mencari salib. Orang-orang Yahudi pun bermusyawarah satu sama lain sambil berkata: “Sekalipun sampai harus mati semuanya, janganlah kita menampakkan salib itu.” Maka Yudas berdoa sambil berkata: “Ya Tuhan Allah Yang Mahakuasa, Tuhan semesta alam, yang bersemayam di atas kerubim, nyatakanlah kepada kami. Engkau yang mengukur langit dengan jengkal, dan bumi dengan genggaman tangan-Mu,<br self-closing="true"> <br/></language>            <language id="Arabic">                قامت هيلانة الملكة، وأخذت معها ثلاثة آلاف جندي، ومضت إلي أورشليم لتطلب الصليب فتشاور اليهود مع بعضهم قائلين: لو وصل الأمر إلي أن نموت كلنا لا نظهر الصليب. فصلي يهوذا قائلاً: أيها الرب الإله الضابط الكل رب الصباؤوت الجالس علي الشاروبيم اظهر لنا. يا من قاس السماء بشبرة والأرض بقبضته            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="English">               show Your Cross for the glory of Your holy name.”  When they dug they found the three Crosses but they could not identify which one belonged to our Savior.  At that hour, some people passed by while carrying a coffin.  Judas ordered them to lay it down.  On the coffin they put the first cross, then the second cross, but the dead person did not rise.  When they put the third cross on the coffin, the dead person sat up.            </language><language id="Indonesian">nyatakanlah salib-Mu, supaya nama kudus-Mu dimuliakan.” Ketika mereka menggali, mereka menemukan tiga salib sekaligus, namun mereka tidak tahu yang mana adalah salib Juruselamat kita. Dan pada saat itu lewatlah sebuah iring-iringan kematian. Maka Yudas memerintahkan agar mereka meletakkan peti jenazah di tanah. Ketika mereka meletakkan salib pertama dan kedua di atasnya, ia tidak bangkit. Namun ketika mereka meletakkan salib yang ketiga, orang mati itu bangkit duduk.</language>            <language id="Arabic">                اظهر صليبك لكي يتمجد اسمك القدوس. وفي تلك الساعة افترقت الأرض إلي ثلاثة طرق. وأعمق طيب رفيع عظيم الكرامة. ولما حفروا وجدوا ثلثة صلبان معاً ولم يعلموا أيها هو صليب مخلصنا . وفي تلك الساعة جازوا بميت. فأمر يهوذا أن يضعوا نعش الميت علي الأرض. ولما وضعوا عليه الصليب الأول والثاني ولم يقم.وضعوا الصليب الثالث فجلس الميّت.            </language>            </text>                  <text>            <language id="English">               Queen Helen kneeled in worship.  The people all together were crying and saying, “Blessed is the Lord Jesus and His life-giving Cross on which He was crucified to save His people.”             </language><language id="Indonesian">Dan seluruh bangsa bersama-sama berseru: “Diberkatilah Tuhan Yesus dan salib-Nya yang menghidupkan, yang di atasnya Ia disalibkan sampai Ia menyelamatkan umat-Nya.”</language>            <language id="Arabic">                وجميع الشعب معاً صارخين قائلين: مبارك الرب يسوع وصليبه المحيي الذي صلب عليه حتى خلص شعبه.            </language>         </text>      </section>      <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Second Exposition</language><language id="Indonesian">Komentari Kedua</language>            <language id="Arabic">الطرح الثاني</language>         </Title>         <text>            <language id="English">               Hail to the Cross, the sign of victory that was given to the Christians for strengthening.  Hail to the Cross the tree, lifted up to the heavens, whose sweet-smelling branches give life to everyone.  Hail to the Cross, the sign of salvation that Constantine saw shining in the heavens.  Hail to the Cross, that was diligently sought by Queen Helen until she found it along with the nails.              </language><language id="Indonesian">Salam bagi salib, tanda kemenangan yang diberikan kepada orang-orang Kristen untuk dikuatkan olehnya. Salam bagi salib, pohon yang ada di Firdaus, yang cabang-cabangnya yang harum menghidupkan setiap orang. Salam bagi salib, tanda keselamatan yang dilihat Konstantinus bersinar di tengah langit. Salam bagimu, hai salib, yang dicari oleh Ratu Helena dengan kesungguhan hingga ia menemukannya bersama paku-pakunya.</language>            <language id="Arabic">                لسلام للصليب علامة الظفر الذي أعطي للمسيحيين ليتقووّا من قبله. السلام للصليب الشجرة التي في الفردوس. التي أغصانها العطرية تحيي كل أحد. السلام للصليب علامة الخلاص الذي رآه قسطنطين يضئ في وسط السماء. السلم لك أيها الصليب الذي طلبته الملكة هيلانة باجتهاد حتي وجدته مع المسامير.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="English">               Hail to the cross that was put in the bitter water, which was rendered sweet to quench the thirst of the faithful.                          </language><language id="Indonesian">               Salam bagi salib yang diletakkan di air pahit lalu menjadi manis, dan darinya orang-orang beriman minum.                          </language>            <language id="Arabic">                لسلام للصليب الذي جعل في المياه المرة فصارت حلوة وشرب منها المؤمنون.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="English">               Hail to the Cross that deserved to be believed in by Isaac the Samaritan and all those who were with him.  Hail to the Cross, the pride of the Christians, on which the Lord was crucified to save his people.  Hail to the Cross, the lampstand of pure gold on which the lamp, Immanuel, was lit.            </language><language id="Indonesian">Salam bagi salib yang membuat Ishak orang Samaria dan semua yang bersamanya layak untuk percaya. Salam bagi salib, kebanggaan Kekristenan, tempat Tuhan disalibkan hingga Ia menyelamatkan umat-Nya. Salam bagi salib, pelita emas yang murni, tempat lampu, yaitu Imanuel, dinyalakan di atasnya.</language>            <language id="Arabic">                لسلام للصليب الذي استحق ان يؤمن به اسحق السامري وكل الذين معة. السلام للصليب فخر المسيحية الذي صلب عليه الرب حتي خلص شعبه. السلام للصليب المنارة الذهب المصفي التي أوقد عليها المصباح الذي هو عمانوئيل.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="English">               Hail to the Cross, the wooden scepter on which the blood of the lamb was shed. Hail to the Cross, the indispensable sign in the hands of the Highest like a decorated crown.            </language><language id="Indonesian">Salam bagi salib, tongkat kayu badam, yang meneteskan darah Anak Domba di atasnya. Salam bagi salib, tanda goresan yang tak terlepas, yang ada di tangan Yang Mahatinggi bagaikan mahkota berhias.</language>            <language id="Arabic">                لسلام للصليب قضيب خشبة اللوز الذي قطر عليه دم الحمل. السلام للصليب الرشم الذي لا يحل الذي في يدي العالي مثل تاج مزخرف.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="English">               Hail to the cross on which the Lord was crucified and He stretched His hands and attracted everyone to Him.  Because of a tree, Adam was chased out of the paradise, and because of the blessed Cross, he returned to his rank once more.  We ask the compassionate Lord to grant us the forgiveness of our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian">Salam bagi salib, tempat Tuhan disalibkan, di mana Ia merentangkan tangan-Nya dan menarik semua orang kepada-Nya. Karena melalui sebatang pohon, Adam diusir keluar dari Firdaus, dan melalui salib, salib yang diberkati, ia dikembalikan lagi ke kedudukannya. Maka kita memohon kepada Tuhan yang penuh belas kasih agar Ia menganugerahkan kepada kita pengampunan dosa-dosa kita.</language>            <language id="Arabic">                السلام للصليب الذي صلب الرب عليه فبسط يديه وجذب كل أحد اليه. من قبل شجرة واحدة نفي آدم إلي خارج الفردوس، ومن قبل الصليب عود الصليب المبارك رد إلي رتبته مرة أخري. فنسأل الرب المتحنن ان ينعم لنا بغفران خطايانا.            </language>         </text>         <text>                     <language id="English">                Glory is due to Him forever. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian">                Bagi-Nya kemuliaan selama-lamanya. Amin.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">                له المجد دائماً آميـن.                                     </language>         </text>                   </section>      </role>        </document>