<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <insertdocument path="include/LitanyOfTheGospelIntro" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <group>      <season id="HosannaSundayFirstLiturgyGospel">         <role id="Reader">               <insertdocument path="include/ChantedPsalmIntro" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>            <insertdocument path="readings/HosannaSundayFirstLiturgyPsalm" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>         </role>      </season>            <season id="!JoyousSaturday">         <linkdocument path="readings/Chanted Psalm">            <language id="English">               Psalm Chant            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Mazmur</language>            <language id="Arabic">               المزمور            </language>         </linkdocument>      </season>   </group>      <group>      <season id="!JoyousSaturday">         <role id="Deacon">            <insertdocument path="include/psalmResponse/PsalmBishop" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>            <insertdocument path="include/psalmTrailer/PsalmTrailer" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>         </role>                  <insertdocument path="include/psalmResponse/PsalmResponse" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>         </season>   </group>      <group>      <season id="RaisingOfIncense | Liturgy">         <role id="Priest" silent="true">            <section>               <Title data-section-header="true">                  <language id="English">Bow down before the Gospel...</language><language id="Indonesian">Bersujudlah di hadapan Injil...</language>                  <language id="Arabic">اسجدوا لإنجيلِ...</language>                  <language id="Coptic">Ouwst m~pieuaggelion...</language>                           </Title>                              <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The priest turns toward the Gospel and censes it, while saying inaudibly:                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Imam itu menoleh ke arah Injil dan mempersembahkan dupa, sambil berkata dengan tidak terdengar:                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     يلتفت الكاهن نحو الإنجيل ويعطي البخور له وهو يقول (سرا(ً:                  </language>               </comment>                                    <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Ouwst m~pieuaggelion n~te I/couc Pi,~rictoc. Hiten nieu,/ n~te piiero'alt/c Dauid pip~rov/t/c: P[oic a~rih~mot nan m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Bow down before the Gospel of Jesus Christ. Through the prayers of the psalmist David the prophet, O Lord, grant us the forgiveness of our sins.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Bersujudlah di hadapan Injil Yesus Kristus. Melalui doa pemazmur Daud sang nabi, Ya Tuhan, berikanlah kami pengampunan atas dosa-dosa kami.                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     اسجدوا لإنجيلِ يسوع المسيح. بصلُّواتِ المرتل داود النبي، ياربُّ انعم لنا بغفرانِ خطايانا.                  </language>               </text>                              <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The priest goes up to the sanctuary and makes the sign of the cross over the incense box and puts a spoonful of incense into the censer, saying “Glory and honor (<span class="Coptic">ouw~ou nem outaio</span>)” to the end. The deacon goes up to the sanctuary with the Gospel, and the priest offers incense to it as they both go around the altar once counterclockwise, while the priest says this Prayer of Simeon the Priest inaudibly.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">Imam naik ke tempat kudus dan membuat tanda salib di atas kotak pedupaan dan menaruh sesendok pedupaan ke dalam pedupaan, sambil berkata “Kemuliaan dan keagungan (<span style="font-family: Coptic;">ouw~ou nem outaio</span>)” di akhir. Diakon naik ke tempat kudus dengan Injil, dan imam mempersembahkan pedupaan kepada Injil itu sambil mereka berdua berjalan mengelilingi altar satu kali berlawanan arah jarum jam, sementara imam mengucapkan Doa Simeon sang Imam tanpa suara.</language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     ثم يصعد إلى الهيكل ويرشم درج البخور رشماً واحداً بمثال الصليب ويضع يد بخور في المجمرة وهو يقول<span class="Coptic">ouw~ou nem outaio</span>  بكاملها. ويصعد الشماس بالإنجيل إلى الهيكل ويعطيه الكاهن البخور وهو دائر حول المذبح دورة واحدة يميناً والشماس حامل الإنجيل  والكاهن يقول صلاة سمعان الكاهن هذه سراً:                  </language>               </comment>                              <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     }nou pan/b ,~na,a pekbwk e~bol qen ouhir/n/ kata pekcaji: je aunau n~je nabal e~peknohem: v/e~takcebtwtf m~pem~yo n~nilaoc t/rou: ououwini eu[wrp e~bol n~te haneynoc: nem ouw~ou n~te peklaoc Pic~ra/l.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Lord, now You are letting Your servant depart in peace, according to Your word; for my eyes have seen Your salvation which You have prepared before the face of all peoples, a light for revelation to the Gentiles, and for glory to Your people Israel.                  </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>"Sekarang, Tuhan, biarkanlah hamba-Mu ini pergi dalam damai sejahtera, sesuai dengan firman-Mu,</div><div>sebab mataku telah melihat keselamatan yang dari pada-Mu, <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">yang telah Engkau sediakan di hadapan segala bangsa, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">yaitu terang yang menjadi penyataan bagi bangsa-bangsa lain dan menjadi kemuliaan bagi umat-Mu, Israel."</span></div></language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     الآن يا سيدي تُطلق عبدَكَ بسلامٍ كقولِكَ، لأن عينَيَّ قد أبصرتا خلاصَكَ الذي أعددتَه قدامَ جميعِ الشعوبِ، نورَ إعلانٍ للأممِ ومجداً لشعبِك إسرائيل.                  </language>               </text>                              <comment>                  <language id="English">                     After encircling the altar, the priest offers incense to the Gospel three times, while saying inaudibly:                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Setelah mengelilingi altar, pendeta membakar dupa kepada Injil sebanyak tiga kali, sambil berkata dengan tidak terdengar:                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     وبعد انتهاء الدورة يعطي الكاهن البخور للإنجيل ثلاث مرات وهو يقول (سرا(ً:                  </language>               </comment>                              <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Ouwst m~pieuaggelion n~te I/couc Pi,~rictoc Ps/ri m~Vnou] etonq: piw~ou naf sa e~neh.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Bow down before the Gospel of Jesus Christ, the Son of the living God; to Him be the glory for ever.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Sujudlah di hadapan Injil Yesus Kristus, Anak Allah yang hidup; bagi-Nya kemuliaan sampai selama-lamanya.                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     اسجدوا لإنجيلِ يسوعَ المسيح ابن الله الحي، له المجد إلى الأبد.                  </language>               </text>                              <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The priest takes the Gospel from the deacon, turns to the west, and offers it to the other priests, while saying,                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Imam mengambil Injil dari diakon, berbalik ke arah barat, dan menawarkannya kepada imam-imam lainnya, sambil berkata,                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     ثم يأخذ الإنجيل من الشماس ويلتفت به إلى الغرب ويعطيه للأباء الكهنة وهو يقول:                  </language>               </comment>                              <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Nywten de w~ouniatou n~netenbal je cenau: nem netenmasj je cecwtem: marenerp~emp~sa n~cwtem ouoh e~i~ri n~nekeuaggelion eyouab: qen nitwbh n~te n/eyouab n~tak.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Blessed are your eyes for they see, and your ears for they hear. May we be worthy to hear and to act according to Your Holy Gospels, through the prayers of Your saints.                  </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Diberkatilah matamu karena dapat melihat, dan telingamu karena dapat mendengar. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Layakkanlah kami untuk mendengar dan melakukan seturut Injil Kudus-Mu melalui permohonan orang-orang Kudus-Mu.</span></div></language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     أما أنتم فطوبى لأعينِكم لأنها تبصر، ولآذانِكم لأنها تسمع، فلنستحق أن نسمعَ ونعملَ بأناجيلِك المقدسةِ بطلباتِ قديسيك.                  </language>               </text>                              <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The priests come forward to kiss the Gospel, saying, “Bow down before the Gospel (<span class="Coptic">ouwst m~pieuaggelion</span>)” to the end. Then the serving priest kisses the Gospel himself and offers the censer to the fellow priest or any non-serving priest to cense the Gospel. He approaches the lectern and reads the Gospel. However, if the Pope, a metropolitan, or a bishop is present, then the one of highest rank reads the Gospel at the sanctuary door facing west, while the serving priest offers incense. After chanting the Psalm, the deacon, while still standing at the door of the sanctary, says:                  </language><language id="Indonesian">Para imam maju untuk mencium Injil, sambil berkata, “Sujudlah di hadapan Injil (<span style="font-family: Coptic;">ouwst m~pieuaggelion</span>)” sampai akhir. Kemudian imam yang melayani mencium Injil sendiri dan mempersembahkan pedupaan kepada sesama imam atau imam yang tidak melayani untuk membakar dupa Injil. Ia mendekati mimbar dan membaca Injil. Namun, jika Paus, seorang metropolitan, atau seorang uskup hadir, maka orang yang berpangkat tertinggi membaca Injil di pintu tempat kudus yang menghadap ke barat, sementara imam yang melayani membakar dupa. Setelah melantunkan Mazmur, diakon, sambil tetap berdiri di pintu tempat kudus, berkata:</language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     ويأتي الكهنة ويقبلون الإنجيل وهم يقولون أيضاً <span class="Coptic">ouwst m~pieuaggelion</span>  بكاملها. ثم يقبله هو بعدهم أيضاً ويسلم المجمرة للكاهن الشريك أو الكاهن غير الخديم ليبخر للإنجيل. وهو يتقدم إلى المنجلية فيقرأ الإنجيل. أما إذا كان البابا أو المطران أو الأسقف حاضراً فهو الذي يقرأ الإنجيل على باب الهيكل ووجهه إلى الغرب، والكاهن الخديم يبخر للإنجيل. وبعد قراءة المزمور يقول الشماس (وهو واقف داخل باب الهيكل):                  </language>               </comment>            </section>               </role>      </season>   </group>         <group>      <season id="!JoyousSaturday">         <role id="Deacon">                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ctay/te meta vobou Yeou: a~koucwmen tou a~giou euaggeliou.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Stand in the fear of God. Let us hear the Holy Gospel.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdirilah dalam takut akan Allah, dan dengarlah Injil Kudus.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  قفوا بخوف الله لسماع الإنجيل المقدس.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               The Gospel is read in Coptic as follows:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Injil dibacha dalam Bahasa Koptik</language>         </comment>                  <role id="Priest">            <text type="GospelIntro">               <language id="Coptic">                  Fc~marwout n~je v/eyn/ou qen v~ran m~P[oic n~te nijwm. Kurie eulog/con ek tou kata [AUTHOR] a~giou euaggeliou to a~nagnwcma.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Blessed is He who comes in the name of the Lord of hosts. Bless, O Lord, the reading of the holy Gospel according to Saint [AUTHOR].               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Terpujilah Dia yang datang dalam nama Tuhan semesta alam. Ya, Tuhan berkatilah pembacaan dari Injil suci menurut Santo [AUTHOR].               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  مبارك الآتي باسم رب القوات. يارب بارك الفصل من الإنجيل المقدس من [AUTHOR]               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Doxa ci Kurie.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Glory to You, O Lord.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kemuliaan bagi-Mu ya Tuhan. (Doksasi Kireye)</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  المجد لك يارب               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <insertdocument path="include/GospelBishopIntro" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>                  <section>            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Coptic Gospel</language><language id="Indonesian">Injil dalam Bahasa Koptik</language>            </Title>                        <role id="Priest">               <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh pencwt/r ouoh penouro t/ren I/couc Pi,~rictoc Ps/ri m~Vnou] etonq piw~ou naf sa e~neh.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Our Lord, God, Savior, and King of us all, Jesus Christ, Son of the Living God, to whom is glory forever.                  </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tuan kita, Tuhan kita, Raja kita dan Juruselamat kita, Yesus Kristus, Anak Allah yang hidup, bagi Dialah kemuliaan untuk selamanya, Amin.</div></language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     ربنا وإلهنا ومخلصنا وملكنا كلنا يسوع المسيح، ابن الله الحي، الذي له المجد للأبد.                  </language>               </text>                              <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The Coptic Gospel is read concluded with the following:                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     The Coptic Gospel is read concluded with the following:                  </language>               </comment>                              <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Piw~ou va Pennou] pe sa e~neh n~te nie~neh t/rou: a~m/n.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Glory is due to our God unto the age of all ages. Amen.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Kemuliaan bagi <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Allah kita sepanjang segala masa. Amin.</span><br/></language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     المجد لإلهنا إلى ابد الآبدين. آمين.                  </language>               </text>            </role>                        <role id="People">               <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Doxa ci Kurie.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Glory to You, O Lord.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Kemuliaan bagi-Mu, ya Tuhan.</language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     المجد لك يارب.                  </language>               </text>            </role>         </section>      </season>   </group>      <insertdocument path="readings/Psalm and Gospel" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>               <role id="Priest">      <section silent="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Silent Gospel Conclusion</language><language id="Indonesian">Silent Gospel Conclusion</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               At the conclusion of the Gospel, the priest censes it three times and says:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               At the conclusion of the Gospel, the priest censes it three times and says:            </language>                     <language id="Arabic">               وعند الإنتهاء من قراءة الإنجيل يبخر الكاهن نحوه ثلاث أياد ويقول:            </language>         </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh n~yok pe e~tecerp~repi nak n~je ]doxologia: qen ouc~m/ n~ouwt n~te ouon niben: piw~ou nem pitaio~ ]metnis] ]p~rockun/cic: nem Pekiwt n~a~gayoc: nem Pip~neuma eyouab n~reftanqo ouoh n~o~mooucioc nemak.            </language>            <language id="English">               You are He to whom praise is due from everyone with one voice, along with glory, honor, majesty, and worship, with Your good Father and the Holy Spirit, the Giver of Life, who is of one essence with You,            </language><language id="Indonesian">               You are He to whom praise is due from everyone with one voice, along with glory, honor, majesty, and worship, with Your good Father and the Holy Spirit, the Giver of Life, who is of one essence with You,            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وأنت الذي ينبغي لكَ التمجيدُ، بصوتٍ واحدٍ من كلِّ أحدٍ، والمجدُ والإكرامُ والعظمةُ والسجودُ، مع أبيك الصالحِ والروحِ القدسِ المحيِي المساوِي لكَ.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               }nou nem n~c/ou niben: nem sa e~neh n~te nie~neh t/rou: a~m/n.            </language>            <language id="English">               now and at all times and unto the age of all ages.  Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               now and at all times and unto the age of all ages.  Amen.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               الآنَ وكل أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ كلِّها. آمين.            </language>         </text>      </section>   </role>      <comment>      <language id="English">         After the Gospel is read, the congregation says:      </language><language id="Indonesian">         After the Gospel is read, the congregation says:      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         يقرأ الإنجيل وفي ختامه يقول الشعب:      </language>   </comment>      <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <section>      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Instructions for Gospel Reading</language><language id="Indonesian">Instructions for Gospel Reading</language>      </Title>            <comment>         <language id="English">            Please note that several churches in the lands of immigration have grown accustomed to reading the Gospel in both English and Arabic without reading it in Coptic. As a result, after the Litany of the Gospel, “Alleluia” is chanted without reading the Psalm. This practice is improper. Therefore, in these instances, we recommend the following order be observed:            <ol>                  <li>After the Litany of the Gospel, the Psalm is read (Arabic or English) followed by “Alleluia” or the response to the Psalm.</li>                <li>The deacon says “Stand in the fear of God (<span class="Coptic">Ctay/te</span>)”</li>               <li>The priest says “Blessed is He (<span class="Coptic">Fc~marwout</span>)”</li>               <li>The reader says, “Stand in the fear of God…”</li>               <li>The Gospel is read (Arabic or English) preceded by the priest saying, “Our Lord (<span class="Coptic">Pen[oic</span>)”</li>               <li>The Psalm is read.</li>               <li>The reader says, “Blessed is He who comes in the name of the Lord...”</li>               <li>The Gospel is read.</li>            </ol>                  </language><language id="Indonesian">            Please note that several churches in the lands of immigration have grown accustomed to reading the Gospel in both English and Arabic without reading it in Coptic. As a result, after the Litany of the Gospel, “Alleluia” is chanted without reading the Psalm. This practice is improper. Therefore, in these instances, we recommend the following order be observed:            <ol>                  <li>After the Litany of the Gospel, the Psalm is read (Arabic or English) followed by “Alleluia” or the response to the Psalm.</li>                <li>The deacon says “Stand in the fear of God (<span class="Coptic">Ctay/te</span>)”</li>               <li>The priest says “Blessed is He (<span class="Coptic">Fc~marwout</span>)”</li>               <li>The reader says, “Stand in the fear of God…”</li>               <li>The Gospel is read (Arabic or English) preceded by the priest saying, “Our Lord (<span class="Coptic">Pen[oic</span>)”</li>               <li>The Psalm is read.</li>               <li>The reader says, “Blessed is He who comes in the name of the Lord...”</li>               <li>The Gospel is read.</li>            </ol>                  </language>      </comment>   </section>      <group>      <season id="Liturgy | ConsecrationOfWaters">         <insertdocument path="include/SilentPrayerGospel" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </season>   </group></document>