<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Group>      <Season id="Theophany">         <Section>            <Title>               <Language id="English">Exposition for the Feast of the Theophany</Language>               <Language id="Arabic">طرح لعيد الغطاس</Language>            </Title>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  In those days Jesus came from Nazareth to Judea, and the crowds saw His glory in the Jordan. As the forerunner and baptizer of the people used to say, “This is indeed the Lamb of God who carries the sins of the world.” The Lamb, the Forgiver of sins, came to the Jordan to be baptized by John, like the rest of those who came to him.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  وفي تلك الأيام جاء يسوع من الناصرة إلى اليهودية، ورأت الجموع مجده في الأردن. إذ كان يقول السابق المُعمِّد للشعب: «هذا بالحقيقة حمل الله الذي يحمل خطايا العالم». وأتى الحمل الغافر الخطايا إلى الأردن ليعتمد من يوحنا مثل بقية الآتين إليه.               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  John refused saying, “I need to come to you, and you come to me?” Our Lord Jesus Christ answered, saying to him, “Why do you prevent me, O John? The will of My Father and the Holy Spirit and My love for mankind brought Me to birth, and also called for me to descend to the baptism.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  فامتنع يوحنا قائلا: «إني أنا المحتاج أن آتى إليك، وأنت أتيت إليَّ». فأجاب ربنا يسوع المسيح قائلا له: «لماذا تمنعني يا يوحنا؟ إرادة أبي والروح القدس ومحبتي للبشر أتتا بي إلى الميلاد، ودعتاني أيضاً إلى أن أنزل إلى العماد.               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  My great power is what attracted Me and made Me a child. It also attracted Me to descend and be baptized by you. The bosom of baptism will not harm Me more than the narrowness of the womb. The waters of the Jordan will not be darker for Me more than the depths.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  وقوتي العظيمة هي التي جذبتني وصيَّرتني طفلاً. وهي أيضاً جذبتني لأنزل وأعتمد منك. فلن يضرني حضن المعمودية أكثر من ضيق البطن. ولن تظلم عليَّ مياه الأردن أكثر من الجوف.               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  If you think that you are honoring Me by preventing my baptism, you should have prevented Me from being conceived and born. Which is more despicable, the narrowness of the womb in the flesh or the glory of baptism?               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  إن كنت تظن أنك تكرمني بإمتناعك عن عمادك لي، فكان ينبغي لك أن تمنعني عن الحمل والميلاد. أيهما أحقر موضع ضيق البطن في الجسد، أم عظمة المعمودية؟               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  If you were able to prevent Me from being wrapped with swaddling clothes, then prevent Me from being baptized. If you were able to prevent Me from sucking the simple milk, then prevent Me from descending to the spring. If you could have prevented Me from dwelling into the womb of the Virgin Mary, you would also be able to prevent Me from the bosom of baptism.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  إن كنت قدرت أن تمنعني عن أن ألتف بأقماط، فامنعني عن العماد. إن كنت قدرت أن تمنعني عن مص الحليب البسيط، فامنعني عن النزول إلى الينبوع. لو كنت تقدر أن تمنعني عن الحلول في بطن مريم العذراء، لكنت أيضاً تقدر أن تمنعنى من حضن المعمودية.               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Now I have come and walked in the path of birth in order to complete it. How then can I return from it? Therefore, it is befitting of Me, as I was sent forth from My Father, to complete the path of righteousness.”               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  والآن سرتُ وأتيت فى طريق الميلاد لكي أكملها. فكيف يمكن أن أرجع عنها فلهذا يليق بي كما إنى أرسلت من عند أبي أن أُكمّل طريق البِر.»               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  When the Lord was finished speaking to John, he was terrified of the King's Son and worshiped Him, and confessed with fear and supplication, saying: “I implore you, O my Lord, because I am unable to approach you. The grass is too weak to touch the flame. For how can the weak hay hold the flames of fire or the flame come close to the ember?! How can I place my hand on your head and baptize you with water, O Baptizer of all?”               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  ولما فرغ السيد من كلامه ليوحنا. إرتعب هذا من ابن الملك وسجد له. واعترف بإرتعاب وتضرع قائلا: «أنا أطلب إليك يا سيدي لأني لا أستطيع أن أتقدم إليك. وضعيفة هي الحلفاء أن تمس اللهيب. إذ كيف يقدر القش الضعيف أن يمسك بلهيب النار؟ أو الشعلة أن تقرب الجمرة؟ وكيف أضع يدي على رأسك، وأعمدك بالماء يا مُعمِّد الكل؟»               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Then the Lord answered, saying to him, “John, refrain your questions, be calm in mind, and say nothing when you baptize Me. But come and place your hand upon My head, for the Father acknowledges this for the sake of His Son. You come to me and place your hand upon me, and without your words, the Spirit testifies of Me with the truth.”               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  حينئذ أجاب السيد قائلا له: «كُفّ يا يوحنا عن السؤال وكن هادىء البال ولا تقل شيئاً عندما تعمدني. تعال وضع يدك فقط على رأسي. فالآب يُقرّ هذا من أجل ابنه. فتعال أنت إليَّ، وابسط يدك علىَّ. وبغير كلامك يشهد الروح علىَّ بالحق.»               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Then John came forward and put his hand on the head of the Flame, and the ranks of the angels were standing, astonished with great fear, and the powers were amazed, by the bewilderment and astonishment that was there. For the hand of flesh was not burned by the Flame from which the seraphim cover their faces from His intensity.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  حينئذ تقدم يوحنا ووضع يده على رأس اللهيب، وصفوف الملائكة واقفون مندهشون بالرعب العظيم. والقوات مبهوتون بما كان هنالك من الحيرة والدهشة. لأن يد اللحم لم تحترق باللهيب الذي حجب السارافيم وجوههم من شدته.               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  On top of the Creator's head, John placed his lactiferous hand that was drowning in mud, and grabbed its Master and touched His head without being burnt. An amazing saying from which the luminaries are ashamed of, and whoever beholds, will see the son of the barren descend to baptize the Invisible One among the angels, Who is carried by the cherubim, and hidden from the ranks, glorified by the thrones, and feared and revered by all the heavenly ranks.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  وفوق رأس الخالق وضع يوحنا يده اللبنيه الغارقة في الطين. فأمسكت بسيدها، ولمست رأسه دون أن تذوب. قول مدهش يستحي منه النورانيون. ومن عاين عين إبن العاقرنزل يُعمد غير المرئي من الملائكة، ومحمولاً من الكاروبيم. ومستوراً من الصفوف. ممجداً من الكراسي. ومخوفاً مهيباً من كل المراتب السمائية.               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Leaving the assumptions of all the races confused; and the powers amazed; and the cavalries shivering; and the doors trembling; and the Flame standing before the terrified one; He descended to be baptized from the hand of the dirt and the creation of His hands.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  تاركاً أوهام جميع الأجناس حائرة. والقوات راهبة، والكراديس فازعة. والابواب راعدة. واللهيب قائم ناحية الترعاب، ونزل يتعمد من يد التراب وجبلة يديه.               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  When our Savior was baptized by the hand of John, the heavens were opened to Him, and the Father cried out to His beloved. The splendid Spirit rose to bear witness to the Only-Begotten, and the voice came out from the kingdom abode, and the hidden word moved without a mouth, to bear witness to the truth of the Divinity, and a Voice thundered from heaven without an embodied tongue, about His Incarnate Beloved.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  ولمـا اعتمد مخلصنا من يد يوحنا، إنفتحت له السموات، وصرخ الآب على حبيبه. قامت الروح البهية تشهد على الوحيد. وخرج الصوت من قيطون المملكة. إذ تحركت الكلمة الخفية بغير فمّ. لتشهد على حقيقة اللاهوت وَرَعد الصوت من السماء من غير لسان متجسم على حبيبه المتجسد.               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  He did not speak, at that time, in the tongue of a king or preach by a spiritual mouth, but rather, He spoke with His eternity about the Son of His mystery, when He ascended from the water and said, “This is My beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased, listen to Him.”               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  ولم يتكلم في ذلك الوقت بلسان ملك. أو يبشر بفم روحانى. بل تكلم مع أزليته عن ابن سرّه. لما صعد من الماء قائلاً: «هذا هو ابني الحبيب الذي به سُررت، فاسمعوا له».               </Language>            </Text>            <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Praise be to God forever.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  والسُبح لله دائماً.               </Language>            </Text>         </Section>      </Season>   </Group></Document>