<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <group>      <season id="StBasilLiturgy">         <Title>            <language id="English">The Divine Liturgy According to Saint Basil</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Misa Kudus Menurut Santo Basilius</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">قداس القديس باسيليوس الكبير</language>            <language id="Coptic">}a~navora n~te Pia~gioc Megalo Bacilioc </language>         </Title>      </season>            <season id="StGregoryLiturgy">         <Title>            <language id="English">The Divine Liturgy According to Saint Gregory the Theologian</language><language id="Indonesian">Misa Kudus Menurut Santo Gregorius Sang Teolog</language>            <language id="Arabic">قداس القديس اغريغوريوس الناطق بالإلهيات</language>            <language id="Coptic">}a~navora n~te Pia~gioc Gr/gorioc Piyeo~logoc</language>         </Title>      </season>            <season id="StCyrilLiturgy">         <Title>            <language id="English">The Divine Liturgy According to Saint Cyril the Great</language><language id="Indonesian">Misa Kudus Menurut Santo Cyril Agung</language>            <language id="Arabic">قداس القديس كيرلس الكبير</language>            <language id="Coptic">}a~navora n~te Pia~gioc Megalo Kurilloc</language>         </Title>                  <comment>            <language id="Coptic">               T~ar,/ n~]a~navora n~te peniwt eyouab Markoc pia~poctoloc: y/etaferbebeon m~moc n~je pit~ricmakarioc pia~gioc Kurilloc pir,/epickopoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               The beginning of the Anaphora of our holy father Mark the Apostle, which the thrice-blessed St. Cyril the Archbishop confirmed.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Awal Anafora dari bapa kami yang kudus, Markus sang Rasul, yang diteguhkan oleh Santo Cyril sang Uskup Agung yang tiga kali diberkati.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               بَدءُ قُدَّاسِ أبينا القديسِ مَرْقُسَ الرسول الذي رتَّبهُ وجَمَعهُ المثلث الطوبَى القديسُ كيرلس رئيسُ الأَساقفةِ.              </language>         </comment>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               The Liturgy that was instituted by our father, Saint Mark the Apostle, the evangelist of the land of Egypt, was translated from Greek into Coptic by Saint Cyril, the 24th Pope, who is called the Pillar of the Faith. The Coptic version of the Liturgy of Saint Mark is known as the Liturgy of Saint Cyril.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Liturgi yang disusun oleh bapa kami, Santo Markus Rasul, penginjil tanah Mesir, diterjemahkan dari bahasa Yunani ke dalam bahasa Koptik oleh Santo Cyril, Paus ke-24, yang disebut Pillar Iman. Versi Koptik dari Liturgi Santo Markus dikenal sebagai Liturgi Santo Cyril.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               هذا القداس وضعه ابينا القديس مرقس الرسول، كاروز الديار المصرية. وقد ترجمه من اللغة اليونانية إلى القبطية القديس كيرلس، وهو البابا الرابع والعشرون في عداد البطاركة الملقب بعمود الدين.            </language>         </comment>      </season>   </group>   <season id="!CovenantThursday ^ !JoyousSaturday">      <comment>         <language id="English">            The sermon may be delivered.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Khotbah dapat disampaikan         </language>      </comment>      <insertdocument path="include/LiturgyExpositions" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   </season>      <insertdocument path="include/PrayerOfTheVeil" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <comment>      <language id="English">                  The response to the Gospel is chanted:      </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tanggapan terhadap Injil dilantunkan:      </language>   </comment>         <insertdocument path="include/gospelResponse/GospelResponse" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <comment>      <language id="English">                  The priest, having made a prostration to the East before the sanctuary door, receives absolution from the Pope, a metropolitan, or a bishop, making a prostration to them, if any of them is present. Then he makes a prostration to his brethren the priests, embraces them, and asks of them absolution and prayer on his behalf. Then he ascends to the sanctuary and kisses the altar. And he focuses his mind that he may be humble of heart. Then he stands at the west side of the altar facing East.      </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Imam, setelah melakukan metania ke arah Timur di depan pintu altar, menerima absolusi dari Paus, metropolitan, atau uskup, dengan bersujud kepada mereka, jika salah seorang dari mereka hadir. Kemudian ia bersujud kepada saudara-saudaranya sesama imam, saling berpelukan dengan mereka, dan meminta absolusi serta doa mereka baginya. Setelah itu ia naik ke altar dan mencium altar. Lalu ia memusatkan pikirannya agar rendah hati dalam hatinya. Kemudian ia berdiri di sisi barat altar sambil menghadap ke Timur.</language>      <language id="Arabic">                  يسجد الكاهن تجاه الشرق أمام باب الهيكل. ويضرب المطانية للبابا أو المطران أو الأسقف إذا كان أحدهم حاضراً، ليتلقَّى منه الحِلَّ. ثم يضرب المطانية لإخوته الكهنة ويُصافحهم ويسألهم الحِلَّ والصلاة من أجله. ثم يصعد إلى الهيكل، ويُقبِّل المذبح بفمه. ويجمع عقله، ويكون متخشع القلب. ويقف غربي المذبح متجها إلى الشرق.      </language>   </comment>      <group>      <season id="!StCyrilLiturgy">                  <comment>            <language id="English">                        Then he says:            </language><language id="Indonesian">                        Kemudian ia berkata:            </language>            <language id="Arabic">                        ثم يقول الكاهن:            </language>         </comment>                  <insertdocument path="include/ThreeGreatLitanies" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>         </season>   </group>               <insertdocument path="include/Ensofia" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   <insertdocument path="include/CreedPeople" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <season id="StBasilLiturgy | StGregoryLiturgy">      <insertdocument path="include/YouShallSprinkle" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   </season>       <role id="Priest">      <comment>         <language id="English">                     Now the priest looks toward the west, shakes the water off his hands before all the people, then dries his hands with a clean towel.         </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Sekarang imam memandang ke arah barat, mengibaskan air dari tangannya di hadapan seluruh umat, lalu mengeringkan tangannya dengan handuk yang bersih.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">                     ثم يلتفت إلى الغرب وينفض يديه أمام جميع الشعب وينشفها في ستر نظيف.         </language>      </comment>   </role>      <season id="!CovenantThursday ^ !JoyousSaturday">      <insertdocument path="include/StandardPrayerIntro" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <insertdocument path="include/PrayerOfReconciliation" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>            <linkdocument path="include/Ordinations">         <language id="English">Ordinations</language><language id="Indonesian">Penahbisan</language>         <language id="Arabic">الرسامات</language>      </linkdocument>   </season>      <insertdocument path="include/adamAspasmos/AdamAspasmos" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   <insertdocument path="include/adamAspasmos/ShortConclusion" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <role id="Priest">      <season id="JoyousSaturday | CovenantThursday">         <comment>            <language id="English">               The Prosvareen is lifted and the service is continued.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Prosfarin diangkat dan ibadah dilanjutkan.            </language>         </comment>      </season>            <comment>                  <language id="English">            The priest transfers to his left hand the veil which he is holding, and he takes in his right hand the veil which is upon the oblation, and with it he makes the following three signs of the cross while keeping the two veils in his hands.          </language><language id="Indonesian">            Imam memindahkan penutup yang dipegangnya ke tangan kiri, lalu mengambil dengan tangan kanannya penutup yang berada di atas persembahan. Dengan kedua penutup tetap berada di tangannya, ia membuat tiga tanda salib berikut.          </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ثم يضع الكاهن اللفافة التي معه على يده اليسرى. ويأخذ بيده اليمنى اللفافة التي على القربانة ويرشم بها الثلاثة الرشوم الآتية. وبعد ذلك يُبقي اللفافتين على يديه.         </language>               </comment>               </role>      <insertdocument path="include/Anaphora" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   <insertdocument path="include/AgiosAgiosAgios" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   <insertdocument path="include/InstitutionNarrative" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>         <group>      <season id="StBasilLiturgy | StGregoryLiturgy">         <insertdocument path="include/ShortLiturgyLitanies" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>         <insertdocument path="include/CommemorationOfTheSaints" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </season>   </group>      <role id="People">          <group>         <season id="StBasilLiturgy">                    <insertdocument path="include/AsItWasBasil" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>                        <section>               <Title data-section-header="true">                  <language id="English">As It Was And Is</language><language id="Indonesian">Seperti Semula dan Sekarang</language>                  <language id="Arabic">كما كانَ فهو كائنٌ</language>                  <language id="Coptic">Wcper /n ke ectin</language>               </Title>                              <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The following response, from the liturgy of St. Gregory, may be said instead.                       </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Respons berikut, dari Liturgi Santo Gregorius, dapat digunakan sebagai gantinya:</language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     أو يقال المرد التالي عوضاً عن السابق:                       </language>               </comment>                              <insertdocument path="include/gregorian/AsItWas" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>            </section>         </season>                  <season id="StGregoryLiturgy | StCyrilLiturgy">                    <insertdocument path="include/gregorian/AsItWas" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>                        <section>               <Title data-section-header="true">                  <language id="English">As It Was And Shall Be</language><language id="Indonesian">Seperti Semula Biarlah</language>                  <language id="Arabic">كما كان وهكذا يكون</language>                  <language id="Coptic">Wcper/n ke ecte ectin</language>               </Title>                              <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The following response, from the liturgy of St. Basil, may be said instead.                       </language><language id="Indonesian">Respons berikut, dari Liturgi Santo Basilius, dapat digunakan sebagai gantinya.                       </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     أو يقال المرد التالي عوضاً وهو من القداس الباسيلي.                       </language>               </comment>                              <insertdocument path="include/AsItWasBasil" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>                        </section>         </season>      </group>   </role>      <role id="Priest">             <group>         <season id="StBasilLiturgy">                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  {imwit qajwn e~qoun e~tekmetouro. Hina nem qen vai kata v~r/] on qen hwb niben n~tef[iw~ou ouoh n~tef[ic~mou ouoh n~tef[ici: n~je peknis] n~ran eyouab: qen hwb niben ettai/out ouoh etc~marwout: nem I/couc Pi,~rictoc pekmenrit n~S/ri: nem Pip~neuma eyouab.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Lead us throughout the way into Your kingdom, that as in this, so also in all things, Your great and holy name may be glorified, blessed, and exalted in everything honored and blessed, with Jesus Christ, Your beloved Son, and the Holy Spirit.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tuntunlah kami masuk ke dalam kerajaan-Mu, supaya nama-Mu yang agung dan kudus dimuliakan, dipuji dan ditinggikan dalam segala sesuatu. Dimuliakan dan diberkati bersama Yesus Kristus,  Putra-Mu yang Kau kasihi dan Roh Kudus.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  واهدنا إلى ملكوتِك لكي وبهذا، كما أيضاً في كلِّ شيءٍ، يتَمَجَّدَ ويتبارَكَ، ويَرتفِعَ اسمُكَ العظيمُ القدوسُ في كلِّ شيءٍ كريمٍ ومباركٍ، مع يسوعَ المسيحِ ابنِكَ الحبيبِ والروحِ القدسِ.               </language>                     </text>         </season>                  <season id="StGregoryLiturgy">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Hina nem qen vai kata v~r/] on qen hwb niben n~tef[iw~ou ouoh n~tef[ic~mou ouoh n~tef[ici: n~je peknis] n~ran eyouab: qen hwb niben ettai/out ouoh etc~marwout: nem Pekiwt n~a~gayoc: nem Pip~neuma eyouab.               </language>               <language id="English">                  That as in this, so also in all things, Your great and holy name may be glorified, blessed, and exalted in everything honored and blessed, with Your good Father and the Holy Spirit.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Supaya dengan ini, sebagaimana juga dalam segala sesuatu, nama-Mu yang agung dan kudus dimuliakan, diberkati, dan ditinggikan dalam segala hal yang mulia dan diberkati, bersama Bapa-Mu yang baik dan Roh Kudus.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  كي وبهذا، كما أيضاً في كلِّ شيءٍ، يتمجدَ ويتباركَ، ويرتفعَ اسمُكَ العظيمُ القدوسُ، في كلِّ شيءٍ كريمٍ ومباركٍ، مع أبيكَ الصالحِ والروحِ القدسِ.               </language>                     </text>         </season>                  <season id="StCyrilLiturgy">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Hina nem qen vai kata v~r/] on qen hwb niben n~tef[iw~ou ouoh n~tef[ic~mou ouoh n~tef[ici: n~je peknis] n~ran eyouab: qen hwb niben ettai/out ouoh etc~marwout: nem I/couc Pi,~rictoc pekmenrit n~S/ri: nem Pip~neuma eyouab.               </language>               <language id="English">                  That as in this, so also in all things, Your great and holy name may be glorified, blessed, and exalted in everything honored and blessed, with Jesus Christ, Your beloved Son, and the Holy Spirit.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Supaya dengan ini, sebagaimana juga dalam segala sesuatu, nama-Mu yang agung dan kudus dimuliakan, diberkati, dan ditinggikan dalam segala hal yang mulia dan diberkati, bersama Yesus Kristus, Putra-Mu yang terkasih, dan Roh Kudus.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لكي وبهذا، كما أيضاً في كلِّ شيءٍ، يتَمَجَّدَ ويتبارَكَ، ويَرتفِعَ اسمُكَ العظيمُ القدوسُ في كلِّ شيءٍ كريمٍ ومباركٍ، مع يسوعَ المسيحِ ابنِكَ الحبيبِ والروحِ القدسِ.               </language>                     </text>         </season>      </group>            <comment>         <language id="English">            The priest bows his head toward the priests and deacons, and without signing them with the sign of the cross, says:         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Imam menundukkan kepalanya kepada para imam dan diakon, dan tanpa membuat tanda salib atas mereka, berkata:         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            يخضع الكاهن يرأسه نحو الكهنة والشمامسة (بلا رشم) ويقول:         </language>      </comment>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ir/n/ paci.         </language>         <language id="English">            Peace be with all.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Salam damai bagi semua.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            السلام للكل         </language>               </text>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/AndWithYourSpirit" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Introduction to the Fraction</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Pendahuluan Fraksi</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">مقدمة القسمة</language>      </Title>            <role id="Priest">                 <group>            <season id="StBasilLiturgy | StCyrilLiturgy">                         <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Palin on marenseph~mot n~totf m~Vnou] pipantokratwr: Viwt m~Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Again, let us give thanks to God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ,                   </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sekali lagi, marilah kita  bersyukur kepada Allah Sang Pantokrator, Bapa dari Tuhan, Allah dan Juruselamat kami, Yesus Kristus </div></language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     وأيضاً فلنشكرْ اللهَ ضابطَ الكلِّ، أبا ربِّنا وإلهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.                  </language>                        </text>                              <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Je afy~renerp~emp~sa on ]nou e~o~hi e~raten qen paima eyouab vai: ouoh e~fai n~nenjij e~p~swi: ouoh e~semsi m~pefran eyouab.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                                 for He also has made us worthy now to stand in this holy place, to lift up our hands, and to serve His holy name.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                                 karena Ia telah melayakkan kita untuk berdiri di tempat kudus ini, mengangkat tangan kita dan melayani nama Kudus-Nya.                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     لأنه جَعَلَنا أهلاً الآنَ أن نقِفَ في هذا الموضعِ المقدَّسِ، ونرفعَ أيدينا إلى فوقُ، ونخدمَ اسمَه القدوسَ.                  </language>                        </text>                              <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Nyof on maren]ho e~rof hopwc n~tefaiten n~emp~sa n~]mets~v/r nem ]meta~l/m'ic n~te nefmuct/rion n~nou] ouoh n~aymou.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Let us also ask Him to make us worthy of the communion and partaking of His divine and immortal Mysteries.                  </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Marilah kita mohon kepada Dia untuk membuat kita layak mengambil bagian  dalam misteri  Ilahi-Nya yang tidak dapat binasa.</div></language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     هو أيضاً فلنسأَلْهُ أن يجعَلَنا مستحِقين لشركةِ وتناولِ أسرارِهِ الإلهيةِ غيرِ المائتةِ.                  </language>                        </text>            </season>                     <season id="StGregoryLiturgy">                         <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Penn/b pencwt/r: pimairwmi n~a~gayoc: pireftanqo n~te nen'u,/.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     O our Master and Savior, the Good One and Lover of Mankind, Life giver to our souls,                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Ya Guru kami dan Juruselamat kami, Yang Baik dan Pengasih umat manusia, Pemberi hidup bagi jiwa kami,                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     يا سيِّدَنا ومخلِّصَنا محبَّ البشرِ الصالحَ مُحيي أنفسِنا.                  </language>                        </text>                              <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Vnou] v/e~taft/if m~min m~mof n~cw] qaron eybe nennobi.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     God, who gave Himself up for our salvation from sin,                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Ya Allah, yang telah menyerahkan diri-Nya demi keselamatan kami dari dosa,                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     يا الله الذي أسلمَ ذاتَهُ عنَّا خلاصاً من أجلِ خطايانا.                  </language>                        </text>                              <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     V/e~te e~bolhiten p~a~sai n~te pefnai: afbwl e~bol n~]metjaji n~te nirwmi.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     who through the multitude of His mercies has loosed the enmity of mankind,                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     yang melalui kelimpahan belas kasihan-Nya telah melepaskan permusuhan manusia,                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     الذي بكثرَةِ  رحمتِهِ حلَّ عداوةَ البشرِ.                  </language>                        </text>                              <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Pimonogen/c n~nou]: v/et,/ qen kenf m~pefiwt.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     the only-begotten God who is in the bosom of His Father,                  </language><language id="Indonesian">Wahai Allah, Sang Putra Tunggal, yang ada di pangkuan Bapa-Nya,                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     أيها الإلهُ الوحيد الذي في حِضْنِ أبيه.                  </language>                        </text>                              <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Kurie eulog/con.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     O Lord, bless us.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Ya Tuhan, berkatilah kami.</language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     ياربُّ بارِكْ.                  </language>                        </text>            </season>         </group>      </role>            <role id="People">                     <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Am/n.            </language>            <language id="English">               Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Amin.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               آمين            </language>                  </text>      </role>            <role id="Priest">            <comment>            <language id="English">               The priest takes the pure Body with his right hand and places It in his left hand, and places the index finger of his right hand on the Body at the side of the Despotikon, at the place of separation, and says:                 </language><language id="Indonesian">               Imam mengambil Tubuh Kudus dengan tangan kanannya dan meletakkan-Nya di tangan kirinya, lalu menempatkan jari telunjuk tangan kanannya pada Tubuh di sisi Despotikon, pada tempat pemisahan, dan berkata:                 </language>            <language id="Arabic">               يأخذ الكاهن الجسد الطاهر بيده اليمنى ويضعه على اليسرى. ويضع إصبعه السبابة اليمنى على الجسد بجانب الأسباديقون من المكان المقسوم، وهو يقول:                 </language>         </comment>      </role>            <group>         <season id="StBasilLiturgy">                     <role id="Priest">                           <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Picwma eyouab...                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     The Holy Body…                   </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Tubuh yang suci ..</language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     الجسد المقدس                  </language>                        </text>            </role>                        <role id="People">                           <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Tenouwst m~pekcwma eyouab...                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     We worship Your Holy Body…                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     kami sujud menyembah tubuh-Mu yang suci.</language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     نسجد لجسدك المقدس                  </language>                        </text>            </role>                        <role id="Priest">                  <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The priest dips his index finger into the precious Blood and then raises his finger a little from the Blood and makes one sign of the cross with it above the Blood within the chalice, while saying:                       </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Imam mencelupkan jari telunjuknya ke dalam Darah Mulia, lalu mengangkat sedikit jarinya dari Darah itu dan membuat satu tanda salib dengannya di atas Darah di dalam piala, sambil berkata:                       </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     ثم يغمس إصبعه السبابة في الدم الكريم، ويرفعها قليلاً من الدم، ويرشم بها رشماً واحداً على الدم داخل الكأس، وهو يقول:                       </language>               </comment>                                          <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     ...nem pic~nof ettai/out.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     …and the precious Blood                   </language><language id="Indonesian">                     dan Darah yang sangat berharga                   </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     والدم الكريم                  </language>                        </text>            </role>                        <role id="People">                           <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     ...nem pekc~nof ettai/out.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     …and Your precious Blood.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     …dan Darah-Mu yang sangat berharga</language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     ولدمك الكريم                  </language>                        </text>            </role>                           <role id="Priest">                  <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The priest signs the pure Body with the Blood which is on his finger, once on the front and once on the back of It, and says:                       </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Imam membuat tanda salib pada Tubuh yang kudus dengan Darah yang ada di jarinya, satu kali pada bagian depan dan satu kali pada bagian belakangnya, sambil berkata:                       </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     ثم يرشم الجسد بالدم الذي على إصبعه رشماً فوق، ورشماً أسفل أي على ظهره، ويقول:                  </language>               </comment>                                          <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     N~te Pef,~rictoc: n~je pipantokratwr P[oic Pennou].                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     of His Christ, the Pantocrator, the Lord our God.                   </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dari Kristus-Nya, Sang Pantokrator, Tuhan, Allah kami.</div></language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     اللذان لمسيحه، الضابط الكل، الرب إلهنا                  </language>                        </text>            </role>         </season>                  <season id="StGregoryLiturgy">                     <role id="Priest">                                 <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     V/e~tafc~mou m~pic/ou: ]nou on c~mou.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     O You who did bless at that time, now also bless.                   </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Ya Engkau yang telah memberkati pada zaman itu, sekarang juga berkatilah.                   </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     يا الذي بارَكَ في ذلك الزمانِ، الآنَ أيضاً بارِكْ.                  </language>                        </text>            </role>                        <role id="People">                           <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Am/n.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Amen.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Amin.                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     آمين                  </language>                        </text>            </role>                        <role id="Priest">                  <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The priest raises his finger from the chalice and with the Blood makes the sign of the cross on the Body, above and below, while saying:                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Imam mengangkat jarinya dari piala (chalice) dan dengan Darah itu membuat tanda salib pada Tubuh, di bagian atas dan bawah, sambil berkata:                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     يرفع إصبعه من الكأس ويرشم وجه الجسد وأسفله بالدم وهو يقول:                       </language>               </comment>                                          <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     V/e~tafera~giazin m~pic/ou: ]nou on a~ria~giazin.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     O You who did sanctify at that time, now also sanctify.                   </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Ya Engkau yang telah menguduskan pada zaman itu, sekarang juga kuduskanlah.                   </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     يا الذي قدَّسَ في ذلك الزمانِ، الآنَ أيضاً قدِّسْ.                  </language>                        </text>            </role>                        <role id="People">                           <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Am/n.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Amen.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Amin.                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     آمين                  </language>                        </text>            </role>                        <role id="Priest">                  <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The priest breaks the Body into a two-thirds and a one-third part without separating Them, while saying:                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Imam memecah Tubuh menjadi bagian dua pertiga dan satu pertiga tanpa memisahkan keduanya, sambil berkata:                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     يقسم الجسد ثلثين وثلثاً من غير أن يفصله وهو يقول:                       </language>               </comment>                                          <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     V/e~tafvws m~pic/ou: ]nou on vws.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     O You who did break at that time, now also break.                   </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Ya Engkau yang telah memecahkan pada waktu itu, sekarang juga pecahkanlah.</language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     يا الذي قسَّمَ في ذلك الزمانِ، الآنَ أيضاً قسِّمْ.                  </language>                        </text>            </role>                        <role id="People">                           <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Am/n.                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     Amen.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Amin.                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     آمين                  </language>                        </text>            </role>                        <role id="Priest">                  <comment>                  <language id="English">                     The priest separates the two parts, placing the one-third part upon the two-thirds part in the shape of the cross, and says:                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Imam memisahkan kedua bagian itu, lalu meletakkan bagian sepertiga di atas bagian dua pertiga dalam bentuk salib, sambil berkata:                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     ههنا يفصله ويضع أحد الجزئين على الآخر، أي الثلث على الثلثين على مثال الصليب ويقول:                       </language>               </comment>                                          <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     V/e~taf] e~totou n~nefa~gioc m~may/t/c ouoh n~a~poctoloc eyouab m~pic/ou. }nou on penn/b moi nan nem peklaoc t/rf pipantokratwr P[oic Pennou].                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     O You who gave to His saintly disciples and holy apostles at that time, now also give to us and to all Your people, O our Master, the Pantocrator, the Lord our God.                   </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Ya Engkau yang telah memberikan kepada para murid-Nya yang kudus dan para rasul-Nya yang suci pada zaman itu, sekarang juga ya Guru kami, berikanlah kepada kami dan seluruh umat-Mu, ya Sang Pantokrator, Tuhan Allah kami.                   </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     يا الذي أعطَى تلاميذَهُ القديسينَ، ورُسُلَهُ الأطهارَ في ذلك الزمانِ، الآنَ أيضاً يا سيدَنا أعطِنا وكلَّ شعبِكَ، يا ضابِطَ الكلِّ الربُّ إلهُنا.                  </language>                        </text>            </role>         </season>                  <season id="StCyrilLiturgy">                     <role id="Priest">                           <text>                  <language id="Coptic">                     Picwma eyouab: nem pic~nof ettai/out: n~te Pef,~rictoc: n~je pipantokratwr P[oic Pennou].                  </language>                  <language id="English">                     The holy Body and the precious Blood of His Christ, the Pantocrator, the Lord our God.                  </language><language id="Indonesian">                     Tubuh yang suci dan Darah yang berharga dari Kristus-Nya, Sang Pantokrator, Tuhan Allah kami.                  </language>                  <language id="Arabic">                     الجسدُ المقدسُ والدمُ الكريمُ اللذانِ لمسيحِهِ، الضابطِ الكلِّ، الربِّ إلهِنا.                  </language>                        </text>            </role>         </season>      </group>            <role id="Deacon">                     <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Am/n a~m/n p~roceuxacye.            </language>            <language id="English">               Amen. Amen. Pray.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Amin. Amin. Berdoalah.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               آمين. آمين. صلوا            </language>                  </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/LordHaveMercy" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>            <role id="Priest">                     <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ir/n/ paci.            </language>            <language id="English">               Peace be with all.            </language><language id="Indonesian">(Erini Pasi) Salam damai bagi semua.</language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام للكل            </language>                  </text>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/AndWithYourSpirit" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   </section>      <role id="Priest">                  <insertdocument path="include/fractions/Fractions" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/ThreeAbsolutions" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <role id="People">      <comment>         <language id="English">            The people respond while bowing their heads:              </language><language id="Indonesian">            Umat menjawab sambil menundukkan kepala mereka:              </language>         <language id="Arabic">            يقول الشعب وهم مطامنو الرؤوس:         </language>      </comment>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/AmenLordHaveMercy3" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   <insertdocument path="include/Confession" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   <group>      <season id="StBasilLiturgy | StGregoryLiturgy">         <role id="Priest" silent="true">               <comment>               <language id="English">                  The priest places the pearls which are in his hand on the paten in their place, and he gathers all the particles together and rubs his hands over the paten and cleans both of them thoroughly, and with bowed head, he gives glory to God, saying:               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Imam meletakkan “mutiara (tubuh kristus)” yang ada di tangannya di atas patena pada tempatnya, lalu ia mengumpulkan semua partikel dan mengusap tangannya di atas patena serta membersihkan keduanya dengan teliti, dan dengan kepala tertunduk ia memuliakan Allah, sambil berkata:               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وفي أثناء ذلك يضع الكاهن الجواهر التي بيده في الصينية في مكانها، ويجمع جميع الأجزاء بعضها إلى بعض، ويفرك يديه داخل الصينية وينظفهما جيداً.   ثم يعطي المجد لله وهو مطامن الرأس، قائلاً:               </language>            </comment>                        <group>               <season id="StBasilLiturgy">                  <text>                     <language id="Coptic">                        Ere w~ou niben: nem taio niben: nem ]p~rockun/cic niben: n~c/ou niben: erp~repi n~}t~riac eyouab: Viwt nem Ps/ri nem Pip~neuma eyouab.}nou nem n~c/ou niben nem sa e~neh n~te nie~neh t/rou: a~m/n.                     </language>                     <language id="English">                        For at all times, all glory and all honor and all worship are due to the Holy Trinity, the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, now and at all times and unto the age of all ages. Amen.                     </language><language id="Indonesian">                        Sebab setiap waktu, segala kemuliaan, segala hormat, dan segala sembah sujud layak bagi Tritunggal Mahakudus, Bapa dan Putra dan Roh Kudus, sekarang dan selamanya, dan dan dari segala abad hingga seala abad. Amin                     </language>                     <language id="Arabic">                        إن كلَّ مجدٍ وكلَّ كرامةٍ وكلَّ سجودٍ كلَّ حيٍن يليقُ بالثالوثِ القدوسِ، الآبِ والإبنِ والروحِ القدسِ، الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ كلِّها. آمين.                     </language>                           </text>                                    <section>                     <Title data-section-header="true">                        <language id="English">Prayers before the Distribution of the Holy Mysteries</language><language id="Indonesian">Doa-doa sebelum Pembagian Misteri Kudus</language>                                    <language id="Arabic">صلوات قبل التناول</language>                     </Title>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Ariten n~emp~sa t/ren penn/b: e~[i e~bolqen pekcwma eyouab nem pekc~nof ettai/out: e~outoubo n~te nen'u,/ nem nencwma nem nenp~neuma: e~ou,w e~bol n~te nennobi nem nena~nomia: hina n~tenswpi n~oucwma n~ouwt nem oup~neuma n~ouwt nemak.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           Make us all worthy, O our Master, to partake of Your holy Body and Your precious Blood unto the purification of our souls, bodies, and spirits, and unto the remission of our sins and iniquities, that we may be one body and one spirit with You.                         </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Layakkanlah kami semua, ya Guru kami, untuk mengambil bagian dalam tubuh suci-Mu dan darah-Mu yang berharga, untuk penyucian jiwa, tubuh, dan roh kami, dan untuk pengampunan dosa-dosa dan pelanggaran kami, sehingga kami dapat menjadi satu tubuh dan satu roh dengan-Mu                         </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           اجعلْنا مستحقينَ يا سيِّدَنا أن نتناولَ من جسدِكَ المقدس ودمِكَ الكريمِ، طهارةً لأنفسِنا وأجسادِنا وأرواحِنا، ومغفرةً لخطايانا وآثامِنا، لكي نكونَ جسداً واحداً وروحاً واحداً معكَ.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Ouw~ou nak nem Pekiwt n~a~gayoc nem Pip~neuma eyouab sa e~neh: a~m/n.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           Glory to You, with Your good Father and the Holy Spirit, for ever. Amen.                        </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Kemuliaan bagi-Mu, bersama dengan Bapa-Mu yang baik dan Roh Kudus, sekarang dan selama-lamanya.  Amin.                        </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           المجدُ لكَ مع أبيكَ الصالحِ والروحِ القدسِ، إلى الأبدِ. آمين.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <comment>                        <language id="English">                           Another prayer before the distribution of the Holy Mysteries.                        </language><language id="Indonesian">Sebuah doa lainnya sebelum Pembagian Misteri Kudus                        </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           وأيضاً صلاة قبل التناول:                        </language>                     </comment>                                          <insertdocument path="include/LooseRemit" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Kata to e~leoc cou Kurie~: ke m/ kata tac a~martiac /~mwn.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           According to Your mercy, O Lord, and not according to our sins.                        </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Menurut belas kasihan-Mu ya Tuhan, dan bukan menurut dosa-dosa kami.                        </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           كرحمتِكَ ياربُّ وليس كخطايانا.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <comment>                        <language id="English">                           Another prayer before the distribution of the Holy Mysteries.                        </language><language id="Indonesian">Sebuah doa lainnya sebelum Pembagian Misteri Kudus</language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           وأيضاً صلاة قبل التناول:                        </language>                     </comment>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Pa~r,/goc n~te p~wnq ouoh p~ouro n~te nie~neh: pilogoc n~te Vnou] Viwt: Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           Author of life and King of the ages, Logos of God the Father, our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ;                        </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Wahai Pemberi hidup, Raja segala zaman, Allah Bapa, Tuhan kita, Allah dan Juruselamat Yesus Kristus.  </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           يارئيسَ الحياةِ وملكَ الدهورِ، كلمةَ اللهِ الآبِ، ربَّنَا ومخلِّصَنا يسوعَ المسيحِ.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Piwik n~tav~m/i e~tafi~ e~pec/t e~bolqen t~ve: v~ref] m~p~wnq n~n/eyna[i e~bol n~q/tf.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           the true Bread which came down from heaven; the giver of life to those who partake of Him;                        </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Roti sejati yang telah turun dari Surga, yang memberi hidup kepada siapa pun yang memakannya.  </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           الخبزَ الحقيقي الذي نزلَ من السماءِ، واهبَ الحياةِ لمن يتناولَه.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Ariten n~emp~sa at[ne hioui~ m~p~hap: eyren[i e~bolqen pekcwma eyouab nem pekc~nof ettai/out.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           make us worthy, without falling into condemnation, to partake of Your holy Body and Your precious Blood.                        </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Jadikan kami layak tanpa jatuh ke dalam penghukuman untuk mengambil bagian dari tubuh suci-Mu dan darah-Mu yang berharga.  </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           اجعلنا أهلاً، بغيرِ وقوعٍ في دينونةٍ، أن نتناولَ من جسدِكَ المقدسِ ودمِكَ الكريم.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Mare penjin[i e~bolqen nekmuct/rion eyouab: aiten n~ouai nemak sa e~bol: eke~c~mou e~ron.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           May our partaking of Your Holy Mysteries make us one with You unto the end; and bless us.                        </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Biarlah persekutuan kami dari sakramen-sakramen kudus-Mu menyatukan kami dengan-Mu selamanya.  Berkatilah kami;  </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           وليُصَيِّرْنا تناولنا من أسرارِك المقدسةِ، واحداً معك إلى الانقضاءِ وبارِكْنا.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Nyok pe p~s/ri m~Vnou]: piw~ou nak nemaf nem Pip~neuma eyouab n~reftanqo sa e~neh: a~m/n.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           You are the Son of God; Yours is the glory, with Him and the Holy Spirit, the Giver of Life, for ever. Amen.                        </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Engkaulah Anak Allah.  Bagi-Mulah kemuliaan, bersama dengan Dia dan Roh Kudus, yang sehakikat, sekarang dan selama-lamanya.  Amin.                        </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           أنت هو ابنُ اللهِ. لكَ المجدُ معه ومع الروحِ القدسِ المحيي إلى الأبدِ. آمين.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <comment>                        <language id="English">                           Another prayer before the distribution of the Holy Mysteries.                        </language><language id="Indonesian">Sebuah doa lainnya sebelum Pembagian Misteri Kudus</language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           وأيضاً صلاة قبل التناول:                        </language>                     </comment>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           W Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc: ariten n~emp~sa e~[i e~bolqen pekcwma eyouab nem pekc~nof ettai/out.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           O our Lord Jesus Christ, make us worthy to partake of Your pure Body and Your precious Blood,                         </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Ya Tuhan kami Yesus Kristus, layakanlah kami untuk mengambil bagian  akan Tubuh-Mu yang suci dan Darah-Mu yang sangat berharga,                         </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           ياربنا يسوع المسيح اجعلنا مستحقين أن نتناول من جسدك الطاهر ودمك الكريم.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Ouoh n~tens~tem penjin[i swpi nan e~ouhap.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           without it being condemnation for us.                        </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>tanpa menjadikan hal itu penghukuman bagi kita.</div></language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           ولا يكون تناولنا لنا دينونة.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Alla kata v~r/] e~takjoc n~neka~gioc m~may/t/c: je [i e~bolqen pacwma nem pac~nof: e~p,w e~bol n~te netennobi.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           Rather, as You have said to Your holy disciples, “Take my body and blood for the remission of your sins.”                         </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Sebaliknya, seperti yang telah Engkau katakan kepada para murid-Mu yang kudus, “Ambillah tubuh-Ku dan darah-Ku untuk pengampunan dosa-dosamu.”                          </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           لكن كما قلت لتلاميذك الاطهار ”خذوا من جسدي ودمي لمغفرة خطاياكم“                         </language>                              </text>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Pair/] on n~te oukoinwnia swpi nan nem nekmay/t/c eyouab: e~bolqen nekmuct/rion n~reftanqo.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           Likewise, may we have communion with Your holy disciples, partaking of Your life-giving Mysteries                        </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Demikian juga, kiranya  kami memiliki persekutuan dengan para murid-Mu yang suci, mengambil bagian dari Misteri pemberian hidup-Mu.                        </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           هكذا أيضاً تكون لنا شركة مع تلاميذك الاطهار بتناولنا من أسرارك المحيية.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Ouoh nten[i n~ou,w e~bol n~te nennobi: nem oucun,wr/cic n~te nena~nomia: nem outoubo n~te nen'u,/ nen nencwma nem nenp~neuma: nem outajro hijen pinah] etcoutwn qen pekran eyouab sa pinifi n~qae.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           that we may be granted remission of our sins and forgiveness of our iniquities and purity for our souls, bodies, and spirits, unto firmness in the faith of Your holy name till the last breath,                         </language><language id="Indonesian">                           agar kami dapat diberikan pengampunan atas dosa-dosa kami dan atas kesalahan kami, dan kemurnian bagi jiwa, tubuh, dan roh kami, untuk keteguhan iman akan nama-Mu yang kudus sampai nafas terakhir,                         </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                          فننال مغفرةً لخطايانا، وصفحاً لآثامنا، وطهارة لانفسنا واجسادنا وارواحنا وثباتاً على الايمان باسمك القدوس إلى النفس الاخير.                           </language>                              </text>                                          <text>                        <language id="Coptic">                           Hiten nitwbh n~te ]a~gia n~n/b Maria: nem n/eyouab t/rou n~tak: a~m/n.                        </language>                        <language id="English">                           through the prayers of our Lady, Saint Mary, and of all Your saints. Amen.                        </language><language id="Indonesian">                           melalui doa-doa Bunda kita, Santa Maria, dan semua orang kudus-Mu. Amin                        </language>                        <language id="Arabic">                           بطلبات الطاهرة مرتمريم وكافة قديسيك. آمين.                        </language>                              </text>                                          <insertdocument path="include/LordsPrayerNoTitle" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>                  </section>               </season>                              <season id="StGregoryLiturgy">                  <text>                     <language id="Coptic">                        Ouoh n~yok pe etecerp~repi nak n~je ]doxologia: qen ouc~m/ n~ouwt n~te ouon niben: piw~ou pitaio ]metnis] ]p~rockun/cic: nem Pekiwt n~a~gayoc: nem Pip~neuma eyouab n~reftanqo ouoh n~o~mooucioc nemak.                      </language>                     <language id="English">                        And unto You is due the glorification with one voice from everyone: glory, honor, might, and worship, with Your good Father and the Holy Spirit, the Giver of Life, who is of one essence with You,                     </language><language id="Indonesian">                        Dan Engkaulah Dia yang layak dimuliakan dengan satu suara dari setiap orang: Kemuliaan, hormat, kuasa dan sembah sujud, bersama Bapa-Mu yang Baik dan Roh Kudus, Sang Pemberi Hidup, yang sehakikat dengan-Mu,</language>                     <language id="Arabic">                        وأنتَ الذي ينبغي لكَ التمجيدُ بصوتٍ واحدٍ من كلِّ أحدٍ، والمجدُ والإكرامُ والعظمةُ والسجودُ مع أبيكَ الصالحِ، والروحِ القدسِ المحيي المساوِي لكَ.                     </language>                           </text>                                    <text>                     <language id="Coptic">                        }nou nem n~c/ou niben nem sa e~neh n~te nie~neh t/rou: a~m/n.                      </language>                     <language id="English">                        now and at all times and unto the age of all ages. Amen.                     </language><language id="Indonesian">                        sekarang dan selamanya dan dari segala abad hingga segala abad. Amin.                     </language>                     <language id="Arabic">                        الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ كلِّها. آمين.                     </language>                           </text>               </season>            </group>         </role>      </season>   </group>      <role id="People">      <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Doxa ci Kurie doxa ci.         </language>         <language id="English">            Glory to You, O Lord, glory to You.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Doksasi Kireye. Dokasasi (Kemuliaan bagi-Mu, ya Tuhan, kemuliaan bagi-Mu)</language>         <language id="Arabic">            المجد لك يارب، المجد لك         </language>               </text>            <comment>         <language id="English">            Or they say:         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Atau mereka berkata:</language>         <language id="Arabic">            أو يقول الشعب:         </language>      </comment>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Se n~rompi.         </language>         <language id="English">            A hundred years.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Seratus tahun.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            مئة سنة.         </language>               </text>   </role>      <group>       <insertdocument path="include/distribution/CovenantThursday" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   </group></document>