<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Title>      <language id="English">The Prayer of Absolution to the Son</language><language id="Indonesian">Doa Absolusi Sang Putra</language>      <language id="Arabic">تحليل الإبن</language>   </Title>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Vn/b P[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc pimonogen/c n~S/ri ouoh n~logoc n~te Vnou] Viwt: v/etafcwlp n~c~nauh niben n~te nennobi: hiten nefm~kauh n~oujai n~reftanqo.      </language>      <language id="English">         O Master, Lord Jesus Christ, the only-begotten Son and Logos of God the Father, who has broken every bond of our sins through His saving, life-giving sufferings;      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Guru, Tuhan Yesus Kristus, Satu-satunya Putra Tunggal dan Firman dari Allah Bapa, yang telah menghancurkan setiap ikatan dosa-dosa kita melalui penderitaan-Nya yang menyelamatkan dan memberikan hidup;</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         أيها السيدُ الربُّ يسوعُ المسيحُ، الإبنُ الوحيدُ وكلمةُ اللهِ الآبِ، الذي قَطَّعَ كلَّ رباطاتِ خطايانا من قِبَلِ آلامِه المخَلِّصةِ المحييةِ.      </language>   </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         V/etafnifi e~qoun qen p~ho n~nefa~gioc m~may/t/c ouoh n~a~poctoloc eyouab e~afjoc nwou.      </language>      <language id="English">         who breathed into the face of His saintly disciples and holy apostles, and said to them,      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>yang menghembuskan ke wajah para murid dan rasul-Nya yang kudus dan berkata kepada mereka,</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         الذي نَفَخَ في وجه تلاميذِه القديسينَ ورسلِه الأطهارِ وقالَ لهم:      </language>   </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Je [i nwten n~ouPneuma efouab: n/e~tetenna,a nounobi nwou e~bol ce,/ nwou e~bol: ouoh n/e~tetennaa~moni m~mwou cenaa~moni m~mwou.      </language>      <language id="English">         “Receive the Holy Spirit. If you forgive the sins of any, they are forgiven; if you retain the sins of any, they are retained.”      </language><language id="Indonesian">         "Terimalah Roh Kudus. Jika kamu mengampuni dosa seseorang, dosanya diampuni, jika kamu menyatakan dosa seseorang tetap ada, maka dosanya tetap ada."      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         ”اقبَلوا الروحَ القدس، مَنْ غفرتُم لهم خطاياهم، غُفِرَت لهم، ومَنْ أمسكتُموها عليهم أُمسِكَت.“      </language>   </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Nyok on ]nou penn/b hiten neka~poctoloc eyouab akerh~mot n~n/e~terhwb qen oumetou/b kata c/ou qen tekekk~l/cia eyouab: e~,a nobi e~bol hijen pikahi: ouoh e~cwnh ouoh e~bwl e~bol n~c~nauh niben n~te ]a~dikia.      </language>      <language id="English">         Now also, O our Master, You have given grace through Your holy apostles to those who for a time labor in the priesthood in Your holy Church to forgive sin upon the earth and to bind and to loose every bond of iniquity.      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sekarang juga, ya Tuan kami, Engkau telah memberikan anugerah melalui rasul-rasul-Mu yang kudus, yang melaksanakan tugas keimaman di dalam gereja-Mu yang kudus untuk mengampuni dosa di atas muka bumi dan mengikat serta melepaskan setiap ikatan kejahatan. </div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         أنتَ الآن أيضاً يا سيِّدَنا مِنْ قِبَلِ رسلِكَ الأطهارِ، أنعمتَ للذين يعملون في الكهنوتِ كلَّ زمانٍ في كنيستِكَ المقدسةِ أن يغفروا الخطايا على الأرضِ، ويربطوا ويحلُّوا كلَّ رباطاتِ الظلمِ.      </language>   </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         }nou on ten]ho ouoh tentwbh n~tekmeta~gayoc pimairwmi: e~h~r/i e~jen neke~biak.      </language>      <language id="English">         Now also we ask and entreat Your goodness, O Lover of Mankind, for Your servants,      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sekarang juga kami minta dan mohon kebaikan-Mu ya Pengasih umat manusia, sebab hamba-Mu, </div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         الآن أيضاً نسألُ ونطلبُ من صلاحِكَ يا محبَّ البشرِ، عن عبيدِكَ      </language>   </text>      <comment>      <language id="English">         He makes the sign of the cross two times on the people, saying:      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dia membuat tanda salib dua kali diatas umat, berkata      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         ويرشم على الشعب أولاً وثانياً قائلاً:      </language>   </comment>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Naio] nem nac~n/ou.      </language>      <language id="English">         my fathers and my brethren,      </language><language id="Indonesian">         bapa-bapaku dan saudara-saudaraku, </language>      <language id="Arabic">         آبائي وإخوتي.      </language>   </text>      <comment>      <language id="English">         and on himself, saying:      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dia membuat tanda salib pada dirinya sendiri, berkata:</language>      <language id="Arabic">         ويرشم ذاته قائلاً:      </language>   </comment>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Nem tametjwb: nai etkwlj n~noua~v/oui~ m~pem~yo m~pekw~ou eyouab.      </language>      <language id="English">         and my weakness, those who bow their heads before Your holy glory.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         dan kelemahanku, mereka yang menundukkan kepala mereka di hadapan kemuliaan-Mu yang kudus.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         وضعفي. هؤلاء المنحنين برؤوسِهِم أمام مجدِكَ المقدس.      </language>   </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Cahni nan m~peknai: ouoh cwlp n~c~nauh niben n~te nennobi.      </language>      <language id="English">         Dispense to us Your mercy and loose every bond of our sins,      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berikanlah kami rahmat-Mu, dan lepaskanlah setiap ikatan dosa-dosa kami.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         ارزقْنا رحمتَكَ، واقطع كلَّ رباطاتِ خطايانا.      </language>   </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Icje de aner h~li n~nobi e~rok qen oue~mi: ie qen oumetate~mi: ie qen oumets~lah n~h/t: i~te qen p~hwb: i~te qen p~caji: i~te e~bol qen oumetkouji n~h/t: n~yok v~n/b v/etcwoun n~y~metacyen/c n~te nirwmi: hwc a~gayoc ouoh m~mairwmi: Vnou] a~ri,arizecye nan m~p~,w e~bol n~te nennobi.      </language>      <language id="English">         and if we have committed any sin against You knowingly or unknowingly, or through anguish of heart, whether in deed or word or from faint-heartedness,  O Master who knows the weakness of men as the Good One and Lover of Mankind, O God, grant us the forgiveness of our sins,       </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dan jika kami telah berdosa terhadap-Mu, sadar atau tidak sadar, baik dalam kesedihan hati, ataupun dalam perbuatan,  baik dalam perkataan, maupun keputusasaan. Ya Engkau, Tuan, Yang mengetahui kelemahan manusia, Satu-satunya Yang Baik, dan Pengasih umat manusia, ya Allah, berikanlah kami pengampunan atas dosa-dosa kami;       </language>      <language id="Arabic">         وإن كُنَّا قد أخطأنا إليكَ في شيءٍ بعلمٍ، أو بغيرِ علمٍ، أو بجزعِ القلبِ، سواءً كان بالفعلِ، أو بالقولِ، أو بِصِغَرِ القلبِ، أنتَ أيها السيدُ العارفُ بضعفِ البشرِ، كصالحٍ ومحبِّ البشرِ، اللهم انعمْ لنا بغفرانِ خطايانا.      </language>   </text>      <comment>      <language id="English">         He makes the sign of the cross on himself again,      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dia membuat tanda salib pada klerus dan melanjutkan      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         هنا يرشم ذاته قائلاً:      </language>   </comment>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Cmou e~ron.      </language>      <language id="English">         bless us,      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berkatilah kami,</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         بارِكْنا.      </language>   </text>      <comment>      <language id="English">         on the clergy,      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dia membuat tanda salib pada para Klerus</language>      <language id="Arabic">         و يرشم الخدام:      </language>   </comment>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Matoubon: a~riten n~remhe.      </language>      <language id="English">         purify us, absolve us,      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sucikanlah kami;</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         طهِّرْنا، حالِلْنا.      </language>   </text>      <comment>      <language id="English">         and on the congregation.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Dia membuat tanda salib pada jemaat dan melanjutkan</language>      <language id="Arabic">         ويرشم الشعب:      </language>   </comment>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Nem peklaoc t/rf n~remhe.      </language>      <language id="English">         and all Your people.      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>bebaskanlah kami, Dan bebaskanlah semua umat-Mu.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         وحالِلْ سائرَ شعبِك.      </language>   </text>      <comment>      <language id="English">         Here, he remembers those whom he wishes to remember, then continues, saying:      </language><language id="Indonesian">Imam menyebutkan nama orang-orang yang ingin dia sebutkan, lalu dia berkata:</language>      <language id="Arabic">         ههنا يذكر من يريد أن يذكره ثم يكمل قائلاً:      </language>   </comment>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Mahten e~bolqen tekho]: ouoh coutwnen e~qoun e~pekouws eyouab n~a~gayon.      </language>      <language id="English">         Fill us with Your fear and straighten us for Your holy good will,      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Penuhilah kami dengan rasa takut kepada-Mu, dan luruskanlah kami dengan kehendak-Mu yang kudus dan baik.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         املأنا من خوفِكَ، وقوِّمنا إلى إرادتِكَ المقدسةِ الصالحةِ.      </language>   </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Je n~yok gar pe Pennou]: e~re piw~ou nem pitaio~ nem pia~mahi nem ]p~rockun/cic: erp~repi nak nem Pekiwt n~a~gayoc nem Pip~neuma eyouab n~reftanqo ouoh n~o~mooucioc nemak.      </language>      <language id="English">         for You are our God, and the glory, the honor, the dominion, and the worship are due unto You, with Your good Father and the Holy Spirit, the Giver of Life, who is of one essence with You,      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Sebab Engkaulah Allah kami, (dan) kemuliaan, dan hormat, dan kuasa, dan sembah hanyalah bagi-Mu, bersama dengan Bapa-Mu yang Baik dan Roh Kudus, Sang Pemberi Hidup, Yang sehakekat dengan-Mu . </language>      <language id="Arabic">         لأنك أنتَ هو إلهُنا والمجدُ والكرامةُ والعزُّ والسجودُ تليقُ بِكَ مع أبيكَ الصالحِ والروحِ القدسِ المحيِي المساوِي لكَ.      </language>   </text>      <text>      <language id="Coptic">         }nou nem n~c/ou niben: nem sa e~neh n~te nie~neh t/rou: a~m/n.      </language>      <language id="English">         now and at all times and unto the age of all ages. Amen.       </language><language id="Indonesian">         Sekarang, dan selamanya, dan dari segala abad hingga segala abad. Amin.       </language>      <language id="Arabic">         الآنَ وكلَّ أوانٍ وإلى دهرِ الدهورِ كلِّها. آمين.      </language>   </text></document>