<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section>      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">The Prayer of Absolution Addressed to the Father</language><language id="Indonesian">Doa Absolusi kepada Bapa</language>         <language id="Arabic">صلاة التحليل للآب</language>      </Title>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Vn/b P[oic Vnou] pipantokratwr: pireftal[o n~te nen'u,/ nem nencwma nem nenp~neuma.         </language>         <language id="English">            O Master, Lord God the Pantocrator, the healer of our souls, bodies, and spirits,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Tuan, Tuhan Allah Pantokrator, Penyembuh tubuh, jiwa dan roh kami         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أيها السيدُ الربُّ الإلهُ ضابطُ الكلِّ، شافي نفوسِنا وأجسادِنا وأرواحِنا.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Nyok pe e~takjoc m~peniwt Petroc: e~bolqen rwf m~pekmonogen/c n~S/ri: Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc.         </language>         <language id="English">            You are He who said to our father Peter, from the mouth of Your only-begotten Son, our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ,         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Engkaulah yang berkata kepada bapa kami Petrus, melalui mulut Putra Tunggal yang Engkau lahirkan, Tuhan kami, Allah dan Juruselamat Yesus Kristus:</language>         <language id="Arabic">            أنت الذي قلتَ لأبينا بطرس، من فمِ ابنِكَ الوحيدِ ربِّنا وإلهِنا ومخلِّصِنا يسوعَ المسيح:         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Je n~yok pe Petroc: eie~kwt n~taekk~l/cia~ e~h~r/i e~jen taipetra: ouoh nipul/ n~te a~men] n~nous~jemjom e~roc.         </language>         <language id="English">            “You are Peter, and on this rock I will build My Church, and the gates of Hades shall not prevail against it.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            “Engkau adalah Petrus, dan di atas batu karang ini Aku akan mendirikan gereja-Ku dan alam maut tidak akan menguasainya.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ”أنت هو بطرس، وعلى هذه الصخرةِ أَبني كنيستي. وأبوابُ الجحيمِ لن تقوَى عليها.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Eie~] de nak n~nisost n~te y~metouro n~te niv/oui: n/e~teknaconhou hijen pikahi eue~swpi eucwnh qen niv/oui: ouoh n/e~teknabolou e~bol hijen pikahi eue~swpi eub/l qen niv/oui.         </language>         <language id="English">            I will give you the keys of the kingdom of heaven, and whatever you bind on earth shall be bound in the heavens, and whatever you loose on earth shall be loosed in the heavens.”         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kepadamu akan Kuberikan kunci Kerajaan Surga. Apa yang engkau ikat di dunia ini akan terikat di sorga dan apa yang kau lepas di dunia ini akan terlepas di sorga.”         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وأُعطيكَ مفاتيحَ ملكوتِ السمواتِ، ما ربطتَهُ على الأرضِ يكونُ مربوطاً في السمواتِ، وما حللتَهُ على الأرضِ يكونُ محلولاً في السمواتِ.“         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Marouswpi oun v~n/b n~je neke~biaik: naio] nem nac~n/ou nem tametjwb eub/l e~bolqen rwi: hiten Pekp~neuma ey~ouab: pia~gayoc ouoh m~mairwmi.         </language>         <language id="English">            Therefore, O Lord, let Your servants, my fathers and my brethren and my own weakness, be absolved by my mouth, through Your Holy Spirit, O Good One and Lover of Mankind.          </language><language id="Indonesian">            Oleh sebab itu, ya Tuhan, biarlah hamba-Mu, bapaku, saudaraku dan kelemahanku, diampuni oleh mulutku melalui Roh Kudus-Mu, Ya Engkau, Satu-satunya yang baik dan Pengasih umat Manusia.          </language>         <language id="Arabic">            فليكن يا سيدُ، عبيدُكَ، آبائي وإخوتي وضَعفي، محاللين من فمي بروحِك القدوسِ، أيها الصالحُ محبُّ البشرِ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Vnou] v/etw~li m~v~nobi n~te pikocmoc: a~risorp n~[i n~y~meta~noia~ n~te neke~biaik n~totou: e~ououwini n~te p~emi: nem ou,w e~bol n~te ninobi.         </language>         <language id="English">            O God, who takes away the sin of the world, hasten to accept the repentance of Your servants, for the light of knowledge and forgiveness of sins.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Allah, Yang menanggung dosa dunia, terimalah pertobatan hamba-Mu sebagai cahaya dari pengertian dan pengampunan dosa.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            اللهم يا حاملَ خطيةِ العالمِ، اسبِقْ بقبولِ توبةِ عبيدِك منهم، نوراً للمعرفةِ وغفراناً للخطايا.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Je n~yok ounou] n~refsenh/t ouoh n~na/t: n~yok ourefw~oun~h/t: nase peknai ouoh n~y~m/i.         </language>         <language id="English">            For You are a compassionate and merciful God; You are patient; Your mercy is great and true.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Karena Engkau adalah Allah yang penuh belas kasih dan murah hati. Engkau panjang sabar, belas kasih-Mu besar dan benar.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            لأنك أنت إلهٌ رؤوفٌ ورحومٌ. أنتَ طويلُ الأناةِ كثيرُ الرحمةِ وبارٌ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Icje de anernobi e~rok i~te qen p~caji i~te qen nih~b/oui: aricun,wrin ,w nan e~bol: hwc a~gayoc ouoh m~airwmi.         </language>         <language id="English">            If we have sinned against You, either by word or by deeds, pardon and forgive us, as the Good One and Lover of Mankind.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan jika kami telah berdosa kepada-Mu, baik dalam perkataan atau perbuatan, ampunilah kami</div><div>karena Engkaulah Satu-satunya Pengasih Manusia yang baik.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            وإن كنا قد أخطأنا إليكَ بالقولِ أو بالفعلِ، فسامِحْ واغفرْ لنا، كصالحٍ ومحبِّ البشرِ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Vnou] a~riten n~remhe nem peklaoc t/rf  n~remhe.         </language>         <language id="English">            O God, absolve us, and absolve all Your people.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Allah bebaskanlah kami, dan semua umat-Mu.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            اللهمَّ حالِلْنا وحالِلْ كلَّ شعبِكَ         </language>               </text>            <comment>         <language id="English">            Here he remembers those whom he wishes to remember from the living and the dead, then continues, saying:         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Di sini Imam mengingat siapa yang dia kehendaki baik yang hidup maupun yang mati, kemudian melanjutkan doa ini dan berkata:         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ههنا يذكر من يريد أن يذكره من الأحياء والراقدين. ثم يكمل قائلاً:         </language>               </comment>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ariv~meui~ P[oic n~tamete~bi/n hw: ouoh ,w n/i e~bol n~nanobi etos: ouoh v~ma e~ta ]a~nomia~ erhouo~ n~q/tf: mare pekh~mot erhouo~ a~sai m~mau: ouoh eybe nanobi noui~ nem nicwf n~te pah/t: m~perfej peklaoc m~pih~mot n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab.         </language>         <language id="English">            Remember, O Lord, my own weakness and forgive my many sins, and where transgression has abounded, let Your grace be multiplied in abundance. Because of my own sins and the abominations of my heart, deprive not Your people of the grace of Your Holy Spirit.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ingatlah ya Tuhan, kelemahan diriku dan ampunilah banyaknya dosa-dosaku, dan pelanggaranku yang berlimpah, kiranya anugerah-Mu berlipat ganda dalam kelimpahan. Janganlah  cabut anugerah Roh Kudus-Mu dari umat-Mu karena dosa-dosaku dan kekejian hatiku,</language>         <language id="Arabic">            اذكر ياربُّ ضعفي أنا أيضاً، واغفرْ لي خطايايَ الكثيرةَ، وحيث كَثُرَ الإثمُ فلتكثُرْ هناك نعمتُكَ، ومن أجلِ خطايايَ خاصةً ونجاساتِ قلبي، لا تمنعْ شعبَكَ نعمةَ روحِكَ القدوسِ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Vnou] a~riten n~remhe nem peklaoc t/rf  n~remhe: e~bolha nobi niben: nem e~bolha cahoui~ niben: nem e~bolha jwl e~bol niben: nem e~bolha wrk n~nouj niben: nem e~bolha jinera~pantan niben n~te niheretikoc nem nieynikoc.         </language>         <language id="English">            O God, absolve us, and absolve all Your people from every sin, and from every curse, and from every denial, and from every false oath, and from every encounter with the heretics and the heathen.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Allah bebaskanlah kami, dan semua umat-Mu, dari setiap dosa, setiap kutuk, setiap penyangkalan, setiap sumpah palsu, dari setiap perjumpaan dengan kaum bidah dan penyembah berhala.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            اللهمَّ حالِلْنا وحالِلْ كلَّ شعبِكَ، من كلِّ خطيةٍ ومن كلِّ لعنةٍ، ومن كلِّ جحودٍ، ومن كلِّ يمينٍ كاذبٍ، ومن كلِّ ملاقاةِ الهراطقةِ والوثنيين.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ari,arizecye nan penn/b n~ounouc nem oujom nem ouka]: eyrenvwt sa e~bol: e~bolha hwb niben ethwou n~te piantikimenoc: ouoh m/ic nan eyreni~ri m~peyranak n~c/ou niben.         </language>         <language id="English">            O our Master, grant us a reason and power and understanding to flee unto the end from any evil deed of the adversary, and grant us to do what is pleasing to You at all times.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Ya Tuhan kami, berikanlah kami alasan, kekuatan dan pengertian supaya kami dapat melepaskan diri dari perbuatan jahat musuh. Berikanlah kami melakukan apa yang berkenan pada-Mu selalu.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            أَنعِمْ لنا يا سيدَنا بعقلٍ وقوةٍ وفهمٍ لنهربَ إلى التمامِ من كلِّ أمرٍ رديءٍ للمضادِ، وامنحنا أن نصنعَ مرضاتَكَ كلَّ حينٍ.         </language>               </text>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Cqe nenran nem p~,oroc t/rf n~te n/eyouab n~tak n~h~r/i qen y~metouro n~te niv/oui: qen Pi,~rictoc I/couc Pen[oic.         </language>         <language id="English">            Inscribe our names with all the choir of Your saints in the kingdom of heaven, in Christ Jesus our Lord.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Tulislah nama kami bersama paduan suara para kudus-Mu di dalam kerajaan sorga, dalam Yesus Kristus Tuhan kami.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            اكتب أسماءنا مع صفوفِ قديسيكَ في ملكوتِ السمواتِ، بالمسيحِ يسوعَ ربِّنا.         </language>               </text>            <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusionEnding" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   </section></document>