<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation – John 12:27-36         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير – يوحنا 12: 27-36         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            For He came to carry our sorrows and suffer for us with genuine pain, so that we may be gain true salvation.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأنه جاء لكي يحمل أوجاعنا. ويتألم عنا ألماً حقيقياً. ليخلصنا خلاصاً حقيقياً.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Heretics, such as Apollinarius, and the like, who claimed that Christ’s Humanity does not have a reasoning soul and that His divinity replaced the soul and mind in His human body, was addressed by Jesus, who proved His Human nature saying:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولعله بمجيء الهراطقة الذين منهم أبوليناريوس ومن يشبهه قالوا: إن ناسوته ليس له نفس عاقلة. بل اللاهوت كان للجسد مكان النفس والعقل ولذلك أثبت نفسه الناسوتية بقوله:         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Now My soul is troubled.” Divinity does not get troubled. He was troubled and feared death through His humanity just as we do. For He resembled us in everything excluding sin.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "الآن نفسي قد اضطربت" واللاهوت لا يضطرب. بل بنفسه الناسوتية اضطرب وخاف الموت. كما نخافه نحن إذ تشبه بنا في كل شيء ما خلا الخطيئة.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Father, glorify Your name.” He referred to the glory of the hour of death: victory over Satan and being saved from him. Those who glorified in the earthly life, and are saved from every sin, will too be glorified in that hour and will be saved from Satan. As such, the Father said to His Son:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أيها الآب مجد اسمك" ويعني بالتمجيد في ساعة الموت عن الغلبة على إبليس والخلاص منه. وإن من تمجد في هذه الحياة الدنيا وخلص بالتوبة من كل خطيئة فيتمجد أيضا في تلك الساعة ويخلص من إبليس لذلك قال الآب لابنه:         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Glorified it.” Meaning that the Father glorified the Son by victory over all sins in this world at the time of death. This teaches us that forgiveness of sins, glory and victory are achieved through repentance. That’s why He considered His crucifixion, a glory for Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "مجدت" يعني مجدتك بغلبة كل خطيئة في الدنيا ولذلك تتمجد بالغلبة على إبليس في ساعة الموت. وهو تعليم لنا أنه بتعب التوبة يكون غفران الخطايا والمجد والغلبة هكذا أسمى صلبه وهوانه عن خطايانا مجداً له.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            As the Father said to Him, “I have both glorified it and will glorify it again.” The Lord said, “This voice did not come because of Me, but for your sake.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كما قال الآب له: "مجدت وأيضا أمجد" قال الرب: "ليس من أجلي صار هذا الصوت بل من أجلكم".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            As if He is saying to humankind: You are the ones who need salvation from Satan. I have no sin and you should not worry about Me from Satan. But by My death, I judge him. Therefore, I said that this voice is for your sake.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكأنه يقول لهم: أنتم الذين تحتاجون إلى الخلاص من إبليس وأما أنا فلا خطيئة لي ولا خوف علىَّ من إبليس. بل بموتي أدينه لهذا قلت أنه من أجلكم كان هذا الصوت.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Now is the judgment of this world,” that is to say the judgment of Satan. For by My death I judge him and redeem the whole human race.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الآن دينونة هذا العالم" أي دينونة إبليس لأنني بموتي أدينه وأنتقم منه لكل البشر.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “The ruler of this world will be cast out.” That is to say: as he emboldens over Me as on others of the human race who die, I demand “Satan” to be cast out. “And I, if I am lifted up” on the cross, “I will draw all peoples to Myself” and free them from his (Satan) slavery.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "الآن يطرح رئيس هذا العالم خارجاً." أي أنه عندما يجسر علىَّ كما على غيري من الناس الذين يموتون أطالبه بمجيئه غليَّ وأقبض عليه والقيه خارج. "وأنا إن ارتفعت" على الصليب" أجذب إليَّ الجميع" وأعتقهم من عبوديته.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Thus, He called His crucifixion “lifting up,” to teach us that if we lift up our minds above earthly matters, fearing every sin greatly, then we share His kingdom with Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد دعا صلبه ارتفاعاً ليعلمنا أننا غذا ارتفعنا بعقولنا عن الأمور الأرضية. بمخافة متعالية عن كل خطيئة. فإننا نشاركه في ملكه.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “The people answered Him, “We have heard from the law that the Christ remains forever.” Jews had understood the meaning of the writings in the books about His eternal existence. But they did not understand His words about His crucifixion and death.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "فأجابه الجمع نحن سمعنا من الناموس أن المسيح يبقى إلى الأبد". وقد فهم اليهود معنى قول الكتب عن دوامه إلى الأبد. ولم يفهموا معنى قوله عن صلبه وموته.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Therefore, they wondered at the Lord’s saying about Him being lifted up from the earth, and asked Him about it. Then Jesus said to them, “A little while longer, the light is with you. Walk while you have the light.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولذلك عجبوا من قول الرب عن "ارتفاعه عن الأرض وسألوه عن ذلك". فقال لهم يسوع: "النور معكم زماناً قليلاً بعد. فسيروا في النور مادام لكم النور".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            This is to say, I am the Christ, the light of the world, who illuminate it with the teachings and knowledge of the mystery of salvation. And I will remain with you “a little while longer” in the flesh, because the time of My death is near. So, “walk in the light while you have the light.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قيل أن معناه: أنني المسيح نور العالم المنير له بالتعليم ومعرفة أمور الخلاص وسأبقى "زماناً قليلاً بعد" بالجسد إذ اقترب زمان موتي "فسيروا في النور مادام لكم النور".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Therefore, seize the opportunity while I am with you in the flesh this short period of time, believe in Me, and hear Me, so that I may guide you to the path that leads to life.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فاغتنموا فرصة وجودي معكم بالجسد هذا الزمان الوجيز وآمنوا بي واسمعوا لي فأرشدكم إلى طريق الحياة.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            I teach you how I will die and how I will live forever. Beware and do not neglect this opportunity “lest the darkness overtake you.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأعلمكم كيف أموت وكيف أبقى إلى الأبد وإياكم أن تتقاعسوا عن اغتنام الفرصة "لئلا يدرككم الظلام"         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Then I take away My grace and you become blind to the knowledge of the truth; and I abandon you in your foolishness, and hide the light of My death. Then you will be loitering in darkness, seductions and eventually fall into hell where darkness, despair and gloom exist.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فأنزع نعمتي منكم فتعمون عن معرفة الحق وأترككم في جهالتكم وأحجب عنكم النور بموتي فتتسكعون في ظلام الأضاليل والغوايات وأخيراً تقعون في جهنم حيث ظلام اليأس والشقاء الحالك.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            This has been fulfilled in the Jews, for they had rejected Christ and therefore they perished in gloomy darkness without a guide.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد تم هذا القول على اليهود فإنهم برفضهم المسيح صاروا كتائهين في الظلام بلا مرشد ولا غاية.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “While you have the light, believe in the light.” That is to say, that I will not remain on earth, but I will be lifted up to heaven. And as I am the light that lifts the sinner from the darkness of sin; you ought to believe in Me so “that you may become sons of light.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "مادام لكم النور آمنوا بالنور" أي أني لست مقيماً على الأرض بل سأرتفع عنكم إلى السماء وبما أني النور الذي يخرج الخاطئ من ظلمة الخطيئة: لذا يلزمكم أن تؤمنوا بي "لتصيروا من ابناء النور".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            And if you do not believe in Me, you will remain in the shadow of darkness, foolishness and sins. “These things Jesus spoke, and departed, and was hidden from them.” For He knew that His enemies wanted to arrest Him, and His hour has not come yet.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وإن لم تؤمنوا بي فتلبثوا في ظلمة الجهل والخطايا". تكلم يسوع بهذا ثم مضى واختفى عنهم" لأنه علم أن أعداءه يريدون القبض عليه وأن وقته لم يأت بعد.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord disappeared in Bethany on Wednesday. He did not go to Jerusalem as was the case daily.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان اختفاء الرب في بيت عنيا يوم الأربعاء ولم يذهب إلى مدينة القدس كعادته كل يوم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He stayed in Bethany, as if hiding. The reason for this is when He had entered the city in kinglike fashion, the Jews thought that He is a true king and declared that without fear,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بل أقام في بيت عنيا كالمختفي. والسبب في ذلك ايضا أنه لما دخل المدينة في هيئة ملوكية ظنه اليهود حقيقة ملكاً وأعلنوا ذلك بغير خوف.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            believing that He will destroy the Romans who ruled over them with one word uttered from His lips, as if saying (be dead, and all will die.) Thus, with this hope they proclaimed Him King.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            معتقدين أنه سوف يقتل الروم المتسلطين عليهم بكلمة فمه إذ يقول (موتوا فيموت الكل) وعلى هذا الرجاء نادوا علناً به ملكاً.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            So when He hid Himself on Wednesday, the fear of death by the Romans fell upon them. Fear overtook the hearts of the inhabitants of the city.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فلما اختفى عنهم يوم الأربعاء. لحقهم خوف الموت من الروم وقد استولى الرعب على قلوب أهل المدينة.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Therefore, the people said to the priests, we have made a mistake. We have no options but to reflect on the matter before the Romans kill us. Then the priests said we have no option but to find Him, arrest Him, and deliver Him to the Romans,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقال الشعب للكهنة أخطأنا وليس لنا إلا أن نتدبر في الأمر قبل أن يقتلنا الروم. فقالت الكهنة ليس تدبير إلا أن نطلبه حيث كان. ونمسكه ونسلمه للروم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            saying that He acted hypocritically and claimed the kingdom for Himself. So, here we are delivering Him to you, thereby we are saved by this deed. They all approved this decision, and said no one could inform us about His whereabouts except Judas, His disciple.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ونقول لهم: أن هذا قد نافق عليكم وادعى الملك لنفسه. وها هو قد أسلمناه لكم. ونخلص بهذا الفعل. فاستصوب الكل هذا الرأي. وقالوا لا يعلمنا مكانه إلا يهوذا تلميذه.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            So they spoke to Judas and promised to pay him with silver if he led them to Christ. This consultation was on Wednesday, which is the reason the apostles commanded us to fast every Wednesday.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فتحدثوا معه ووعدوه بالفضة وقرر لهم أن يعلمهم مكانه. وبما أن هذه المشورة كانت يوم الأربعاء فلذا أمرنا الرسل بالصوم في كل يوم أربعاء.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Holy Gospel says, “But although He had done so many signs before them, they did not believe in Him, that the word of Isaiah the prophet might be fulfilled, which he spoke; Lord, who has believed our report? And to whom has the arm of the Lord been revealed?”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال الإنجيل المقدس: "ومع أنه كان قد صنع أمامهم آيات هذا عددها لم يؤمنوا به. ليتم قول أشعياء النبي الذي قاله يا رب من صدق خبرنا ولمن استعلنت ذراع الرب".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Evangelist revealed that the Jews, because of the hardness of their hearts, were blinded to the truth and ignored the mighty signs that He performed. The prophet Isaiah had already prophesied this about them.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أوضح الإنجيلي أن اليهود لقساوة قلوبهم وعماهم عن معرفة الحق وتجاهلهم الآيات الباهرة التي صنعها أمامهم قد سبق النبي وقال هذه النبوة عنهم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            And because those who believed were very few, he said, “And to whom the arm of the Lord been revealed?” that is to say, that they are few in numbers and with limited knowledge. For most of the disciples were illiterate. They are the faithful remnant, the chosen out of the Israelites.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولأن الذين آمنوا قليلون جداً قال: "ولمن استعلنت ذراع الرب" أي أنهم قليلون في عددهم وقليلون في معرفتهم. لأن أخيار التلاميذ كانوا أميين. وهؤلاء البقية التي أبقاها الرب له من شعب إسرائيل.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            As Isaiah witnessed in another part and said: “For though your people, O Israel, be as the sand of the sea, a remnant of them will return”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كما شهد أشعياء في موضع آخر وقال: "وإن كان عدد بني إسرائيل كرمل البحر فالبقية ستخلص"         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said also: “Unless the Lord of hosts had left to us a very small remnant, we would have become like Sodom, we would have been made like Gomorrah” Had it not been for the apostles who did believe from the Israelites, the whole nation would have perished.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقال أيضا: "لولا أن رب الجنود أبقى لنا بقية صغيرة لصرنا مثل سدوم وشابهنا عمورة" فلولا التلاميذ الذي آمنوا من بني إسرائيل لهلكت الأمة بأسرها.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            As for those who did not believe, envy and jealousy blinded them. They hated Him even more when He made them aware of their shortcomings concerning the Law. They were blinded to His true Light,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأما الذين لم يؤمنوا فقد أعماهم الحسد والبغضة. وقد ازداد بغضهم له لما رأوه يبكتهم على تهاونهم بالناموس. وأصبحوا عمياناً لا يبصرون نوره الواضح.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            even despite witnessing many signs and miracles like raising the dead, healing the sick and curing the paralyzed. But because of their blindness they couldn’t believe.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ومع أنهم رأوا الآيات الكثيرة من إقامة موتى وشفاء مرضى وإبراء مقعدين. إلا أنهم لعماهم "لم يقدروا أن يؤمنوا.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            For Isaiah also said, “He has blinded their eyes and hardened their hearts, lest they should see with their eyes, lest they should understand with their hearts and turn, so that I should heal them.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن أشعياء قال أيضا: قد أعمى عيونهم وأغلظ قلوبهم لئلا يبصروا بعيونهم ويشعروا بقلوبهم ويرجعوا فأشفيهم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Isaiah said: “This, when he saw His Glory and spoke of Him, saying: “I saw the Lord sitting on a throne, high and lifted up, and the train of His robe filled the temple,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال أشعياء : وهذا حين رأى مجده وتكلم عنه" وقد أشار بذلك إلى قوله: "رأيت السيد جالساً على كرسي عالٍ ومرتفع وأذياله تملأ الهيكل.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            above it stood seraphim; each one had six wings: with two he covered his face, with two he covered his feet, and with two he flew. And one cried to another and said: Holy, holy, holy is the Lord of hosts; the whole earth is full of His glory.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            السيرافيم واقفون فوقه لكل واحد ستة أجنحة. باثنين يغطي وجهه وباثنين يغطي رجليه وباثنين يطير. وهذا نادى ذلك وقال: قدوس قدوس قدوس رب الجنود مجده مليء كل الأرض         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            All scholars agreed that the Glory which Isaiah saw is the second Hypostasis, because “No one has seen God at any time;” “Whom no man has seen or can see;” Isaiah has seen the Messiah thousands of years before His advent.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد أجمع علماء البيعة على أن المجد الذي رآه أشعياء هو مجد الأقنوم الثاني لأن "الله لم يره أحد قط" و"لم يره أحد من الناس ولا يقدر أن يراه" فأشعياء رأى منذ مئات من السنين المسيح.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            but the Jews had Him among them in the flesh, but were blinded.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أما اليهود فكان بينهم متجسداً فعموا عن رؤيته.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The evangelist said, “Nevertheless even among the rulers many believed in Him, but because of the Pharisees they did not confess Him, lest they should be put out of the synagogue. For they loved the praise of men more than the praise of God.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال البشير: "ولكن من ذلك الوقت آمن به كثيرون من الرؤساء أيضا غير أنهم لسبب الفريسيين لم يعترفوا به لئلا يصيروا خارج المجمع. لأنهم أحبوا مجد الناس أكثر من مجد الله".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            This shows their hypocrisy for they did not acknowledge Him, who is the Truth, and remained silent. For they feared that if they acknowledged Him, they would be put out of the synagogue. Therefore they loved the praise of men more than God’s glory.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أوضح قبح الاحتشام من إظهار الحق. وحقق أن الذي يكتم الحق خوفاً من أن يفرز من جماعته. فقد أحب مجد الناس أكثر من مجد الله.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord Jesus said, “He who believes in Me, believes not in Me but in Him who sent Me. And he who sees Me sees Him who sent Me” He proved His equality in Essence and strength. He is true God of true God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال الرب يسوع: "من يؤمن بي ليس يؤمن بي بل بالذي أرسلني. والذي يراني يرى الذي أرسلني". حقق مساواته لأبيه في الجوهر والقوة. وهو إله حق من إله حق.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “I have come as a light into the world, that whoever believes in Me should not abide in darkness” Darkness here means sins,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أنا قد جئت نوراً إلى العالم حتى كل من يؤمن بي لا يمكث في الظلمة". ويعني بالظلمة هنا عن الخطيئة.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            just as light means righteousness, and that is our Lord Jesus Christ. Whoever abides in sin does not believe in Him and is not born of Him. For “whoever has been born of God does not sin.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كما أن النور هو البر الذي هو سيدنا يسوع المسيح. ولذا فان الذى يثبت في الخطية و هو غير مؤمن به وغير مولود منه لأن "كل مولود من الله لا يفعل خطيئة".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “He who rejects Me, and does not receive My words, has that which judges him, the word that I have spoken will judge him in the last day.” For he did hear, but not obeyed, therefore he’ll be judged by what he heard “For I have not spoken on My own authority; but the Father who sent Me gave Me a command, what I should say and what I should speak.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "من رذلني ولم يقبل كلامي فله من يدينه. الكلام الذي تكلمت به هو يدينه في اليوم الأخير". لكونه سمع ولم يعمل لذلك يدان بما سمع" لأني لم أتكلم من نفسي لكن الآب الذي أرسلني هو أعطاني وصية ماذا اقول وبماذا أتكلم".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said this to teach us to obey and abide by the advice and command of our spiritual fathers. By this we know that we will achieve eternal life, just as the only-begotten Son taught us by His words and deeds.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال هذا ليعلمنا أن نكون كل حين تحت وصية آبائنا الروحانيين. وعاملين بها. وعالمين أننا بها نصل إلى الحياة المؤبدة. ولا نقول ولا نعمل إلا ما أوصوا به. وقالوه لنا. كفعل الابن الوحيد الذي علمنا قولاً وفعلاً.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            To Him is due glory forever Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            له المجد دائماً إلى الأبد. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>