<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" Ordination="true">   <Title>      <Language id="English">The Order of Ordaining a Chanter</Language>      <Language id="Arabic">طقس رسامة الأبصلتس</Language>   </Title>          <Comment>      <Language id="English">         The prayer takes place after the Reconciliation Prayer and the Adam Aspasmos.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         تقام الصلاة بعد صلاة الصلح والأسبسمس الادام.      </Language>   </Comment>      <InsertDocument path="consecrations/ordinations/include/Intro"/>      <InsertDocument path="include/StartOfService"/>   <InsertDocument path="include/ThanksgivingPrayer"/>   <InsertDocument path="include/versesofthecymbals/VersesOfTheCymbals"/>      <Title>      <Language id="English">Litanies</Language>      <Language id="Arabic">طلبةٌ</Language>   </Title>          <Comment>      <Language id="English">         The bishops prays the following prayer (developed by the Thrice-blessed Pope Shenouda III)      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         يصلي الأسقف الصلاة الآتية (من وضع مثلث الرحمات البابا شنودة الثالث)      </Language>   </Comment>      <Role id="Bishop">      <Text>         <Language id="English">            O our good God, who appointed Heman and Asaph to chant in Your holy places.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يا إلهنا الصالح، الذي أقام هيمان وآساف للترتيل في مواضعك المقدسة.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            O You who granted David the prophet to chant with the psaltery, the harp, and the lyre with ten strings.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يا مَنْ أعطيت داود النبي أن يرتل على المزمار والقيثار والعشرة أوتار.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            O You who have said, "Out of the mouth of babes and nursing infants, You have perfected praise."         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يا مَنْ قُلْتَ "من أفواه الأطفال والرضعان هيأت سُبْحاً."         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            O You who established praise in Your holy Church that Your people may worship You with psalms, chants, and spiritual songs.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يا مَنْ وَضَعَتَ التسبيح في كنيستك المقدسة، وأن يعبدك شعبك بمزامير وتراتيل وأغاني روحية.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            We ask You, O Lord, to give Your grace to these, Your servants, so that they may do the labor of the Psaltos (the chanter) in Your holy Church and sing to You with hymns, chants, and spiritual songs—chanting from their hearts to the Lord          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            نسألك يا رب أن تعطي نعمتك لعبيدك هؤلاء ليعملوا عمل الإبصلتس في كنيستك المقدسة ويغنوا لك بألحان وتراتيل وأغاني روحية، مرتلين من قلوبهم للرب.         </Language>      </Text>   </Role>      <Role id="Bishop" silent="true">      <InsertDocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusion"/>   </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy3"/>      <Role id="Bishop">      <Text>         <Language id="English">            O our God who commanded us through the prophet David’s mouth, saying, “Sing to the Lord a new song,” and “Praise the Lord, for a psalm is a good thing, Let praise be sweet to our God.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يا إلهنا الذي أمرنا على فم داود النبي قائلاً "سبحوا الرب تسبيحاً جديداً،" و "سبحوا الرب فإن المزمور جيد، ولإلهنا يلذ التسبيح."          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            We ask You, O Lord, to grant Your servants the grace of praise and chanting in the holy Church.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            نسألك يا رب أن تعطي عبيدك نعمة التسبيح والترتيل في الكنيسة المقدسة.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Grant them the ability to chant with good understanding, so that they may chant to You from the depth of their hearts in the spirit of prayer and worship.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أعطهم فهماً حسناً لما يرتلون به، فيرتلون لك من عمق قلوبهم بروح الصلاة والعبادة.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Grant that they may serve You with their hearts, their mouths, and their hymns, and accept their chants as a sweet savor of incense before You.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أعطهم أن يخدموك بقلوبهم وأفواههم وألحانهم، وإقبل تراتيلهم كرائحة بخور قدامك.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Remove from them the spirit of pride, boasting, and love of vainglory.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إبعد عنهم روح الغرور والتظاهر ومحبة المديح.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Make them good servants          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إجعلهم خداماً صالحين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Role>   <Role id="Bishop" silent="true">      <InsertDocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusion"/>   </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy3"/>      <Role id="Bishop">      <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Vn/b P[oic Vnou] Pipantokratwr Viwt m~Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh Pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            O Master, Lord, God the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أيها السيد الرب الإله ضابط الكل، أبو ربنا وإلهنا ومخلصنا يسوع المسيح.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Ten]ho ouoh tentwbh m~mok Pimairwmi pekbwk vai eto~hi e~ratf m~pekm~yo afvwt hay/ eyouab n~kayolik/ ouoh n~a~poctolik/ n~Ekkl/cia n~tak.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            We ask and entreat Your goodness O Lover of Mankind for these, Your servants, who stand before You; who came to Your catholic and apostolic Church.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            نسأل ونطلب من صلاحك يا محب البشر عن عبيدك الواقفين أمامك، الذين جاءوا إلى كنيستك الجامعة الرسولية.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Ariouwini e~rof e~]h~lej n~te nekcaji eyouab.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Shine on them with the sweetness of Your holy words.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أضئ عليهم بحلاوة أقوالك المقدسة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Arih~mot naf e~er'alin e~rok qen ouka] n~nihwc m~p~neumatikon.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Grant them to chant spiritual praises with understanding.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            هب لهم أن يرتلوا بفهم تسابيح روحانية.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Mareferp~emp~sa n~erh/tc qen oumetpictoc e~tekmetbwk n~no/~ra ouoh eyouab.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            May they become worthy to begin [their service] in faithfulness; and worship You in understanding and purity.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وليستحقوا أن يبتدئوا بأمانة ويتعبدوا لك بالعقل والطهارة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Matoubof c~mou e~rof mahf e~bol qen tekho].         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Sanctify them, bless them, and fill them with Your fear.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قدسهم، باركهم، إملاهم من مخافتك.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Rwic e~rof hiten tekjom n~aggelikon.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Guard them with Your angelic power.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            احرسهم بقوتك الملائكية.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Aritf n~ramao~ qen taio niben eynaneu nem dwron niben etj/k e~bol: hina e~afwnq kata pekouws eyouab ouoh m~makarion ouoh etranak n~touyahmef e~nip~rokopion etoi n~nis] n~houo~ ouoh etj/k e~bol n~te Pekp~neuma eyouab hiten ]metmecit/c n~te pekmonogen/c n~S/ri Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Enrich them with every good gift and perfect talent that they may live according to Your holy and blessed will that is pleasing to You, and be called to the most perfect and great growth of Your Holy Spirit, by Your only-begotten Son, our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اغنهم بكل عطية صالحة وموهبة تامة، لكي يعيشوا كإرادتك المقدسة الطوباوية المُرضية لك، ويدعوا إلى النمو الكامل الأفضل جداً الذي لروحك القدوس، بإبنك الوحيد ربنا وإلهنا ومخلصنا يسوع المسيح.         </Language>      </Text>   </Role>   <Role id="Bishop" silent="true">      <InsertDocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusionEnding"/>   </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy3"/>      <Role id="Bishop">      <Text>         <Language id="English">            (...) psaltos in the holy Church of God. Amen.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            (...) إبصلتس في كنيسة الله المقدسة. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Role>   <InsertDocument path="consecrations/ordinations/include/ThreeSignings"/>   <Role id="People">      <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Axioc (3): pekbwk (neke~biaik) (...) pi'alt/c (ni'alt/c).         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Worthy (3), Your servant(s) (...) the chanter(s).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            مستحق (3)، عبدك (عبيدك) (...) الأبصلتس         </Language>      </Text>   </Role></Document>