<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik" Ordination="true">   <Title>      <Language id="English">Ordaining the Metropolitan</Language>      <Language id="Arabic">إقامة المطران</Language>   </Title>      <Comment>      <Language id="English">         A prayer for the Metropolitan: After reading to him the litanies for the bishop; this prayer shall be added:      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         صلاة لأجل المطران: من بعد أن تُقرأ عليه طلبات الأسقف، يُضاف إليها هذه الصلاة:      </Language>   </Comment>      <Role id="Bishop">      <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/etsop v~n/b p~% V] pipantokratwr v~iwt n~tenimetsenh/t V] n~tenom] niben: v~iwt m~mpen% ouoh Pennou] ouoh pencwt/r I/#c# P,#c#         </Language>         <Language id="English">            O BEING, Master, Lord, God the Pantocrator, Father of compassions and God of all comfort, the Father of our Lord, God and Savior Jesus Christ,          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أيها الكائن السيد الرب الإله الضابط الكل، أبو الرأفات وإله كل عزاء: أبو ربنا وإلهنا ومخلصنا يسوع المسيح:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/e~tafyamio~ n~hwb niben hiten tefjom nem tefcovia~. Ouoh qen pefco[ni aftagro n~nicen] n~te ]oikoumen/ t/rc.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Who has created all things through His might and His wisdom, and in His counsel He has laid the foundations of the whole world.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي خلق كل الأشياء بقوته وحكمته. وبمشورته ثبَّت أساس المسكونة كلها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/etcwoun n~hwb niben qajwf m~pioujincwnt: v/etcolcel n~ni,~lom n~n/e~tau swpi e~bolhitotf.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Who knows all things before their creation, who has adorned the crown of those who came into being through Him,          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            العارف بالأشياء قبل كونها. الذي زيَّن أكاليل الذين صاروا من قبله.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/e~taf] n~tefho] e~cwnt niben eyrou[~nejwou m~pia~mahi n~te tefjom.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Who has imposed His fear upon all creation that they may bow their heads beneath the power of His might.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي أخاف كل المخلوقات ليخضعوا لسلطان قوته.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/e~taf erh~mot nan n~ouka] n~tav~m/i: erencouen pin#a# n~te tefmet,#r#c#.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Who has granted us true understanding that we may know the Spirit of His goodness;          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي أنعم لنا بفهم حقيقي لنعرف روح صلاحه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/e~tafy~re nefekk~l/cia~ [iouwini e~bolqen pimoue~ n~atcaji m~mof: n~te pefmonogen/c n~s/ri.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Who has caused His churches to be illumined by the unutterable light of His only-begotten Son.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي أضاء كنائسهِ باللميع الغير الموصوف الذي لإبنه الوحيد.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/e~tafcwtp n~Abraam pefmenrit: e~ouk~l/ronomia~ n~te v~nah]. Nem E~nw, peyouab n~taf: afouoybou e~nia~hwr n~te v~ouwini: eybe je auranaf.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Who chose Abraham His beloved unto an inheritance of faith, and Enoch, His Saint, He translated in the chariots of light, because he pleased Him.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي اصطفى إبراهيم حبيبه لميراث الإيمان، وأخنوخ قديسه، ونقلهما إلى كنوز النور لأنهما أرضياه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/e~taferh~mot m~Mwu~c/c n~oumetremraus: nem Aa~rwn eujwb e~bol n~te oumetou/b.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Who granted to Moses meekness and to Aaron the perfection of the priesthood.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي وهب لموسى الوداعة ولهارون بكمال الكهنوت.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/e~tafywhc n~hanourwou icjenh/: nem hanar,wn: eyrou]hap e~peklaoc qen oumeym/i.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Who has from the beginning anointed kings and rulers that they may judge Your people with justice.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي مسح الملوك منذ البدء والرؤساء ليدينوا شعبك بالحقيقة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            V/e~te m~pef,w m~pefman~erswousi eyouab etqen niv/oui at[ne semsi icjen t~katabol/ m~pikocmoc         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Who has not left Your holy altar which is in the heavens without ministry, since the foundation of the world.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي لم يترك مذبحه الطاهر السمائي بغير خدمة منذ إنشاء العالم         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Meenca t~katabol/ m~pikocmoc: palin aktaho m~peksemsi e~ratf qen niekk~l/cia~ eyroujwk e~bolhiten hanou/b nem hanleut/c eu[I p~tupoc n~niremm~ve.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            And after the foundation of the world, again also, You did establish Your ministry in the churches, that You might achieve it by priests and Levites who were a pattern of the heavenly (ministers)         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ومن بعد تأسيس العالم، أقمت خدمتك أيضاً في البيع لكي يكملوا بالكهنة واللاويين ويأخذوا مثال السمائيين.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Hina n~te p~semsi n~niremm~ve ]ma] eucop nem niremn~kahi.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            So that the service of the heavenly might correspond at the same time to the earthly (ones).          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لتكون خدمة السمائيين متفقة معاً مع الأرضيين.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Hwc de n~touc~mou e~pekran eyouab: V] n~tav~m/i m~mauatf: nem pekmonogen/c n~s/ri: nem pip#n#a# eyouab.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Praising and blessing Your holy name, O only true God, with Your only-begotten Son and the Holy Spirit          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لكي يباركوا اسمك القدوس، يا إله الحق وحدك، مع إبنك الوحيد والروح القدس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Vai e~te e~bolhitotf: tentho ouoh tentwbh n~tekmeta~gayoc: e~h~r/i e~jen pekbwk (n#i#m#) vai n~yok e~takyasf: ouoh ak]wounaf.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Through whom we ask and entreat Your goodness on behalf of Your servant ___ whom You have appointed and glorified;          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            هذا الذي من قبله، نسأل ونطلب من صلاحك عن عبدك (فلان) هذا الذي رسمته ومجدته.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Akctpf nak n~oumetropolit/c: ouoh n~iwt e~jen tekekk~l/cia~: eyrefswpi n~ar,wn: ouoh n~hugoumenoc e~jen peklaoc.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            You have chosen him unto Yourself as a Metropolitan and a father over Your Church, that he may be a ruler and a leader of Your people.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            واخترته لك مطراناً، وأباً على بيعتك، ليكون رئيساً ومقدماً على شعبك.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            A~riouwini e~rof p~% qen piouwini n~te pekho: hina n~tef[iouwini n~je pefh/t qen ]moumi n~te pekw~ou: eyrefcouen nekmuct/rion eth/p: qen oumeym/i.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Enlighten him, O Lord, with the light of Your countenance, in order that his heart may be enlightened by the spring of Your glory, that he may truly know Your hidden Mysteries.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أضئ عليه يارب بنور وجهك لكي يضئ قلبه بينبوع مجدك لكي يعرف سرائرك المخفية بالحقيقة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Eke~vwn e~bol e~jwf qen pekp#n#a# n~h/gemwnikon: n~y/e~teywk n~g~nwcic: vai e~taf[itf qen tekekk~l/cia~ eyouab: eyreferberi qen n/eyranak: kata genea~: pip#n#a# eyouab: pip#n#a# n~te ]meym/i: pip#n#a# n~telion: piparakl/ton: v/e~takt/if n~neka~gioc n~a~poctoloc: nem nip~rov/t/c.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Pour out upon him from the governing spirit of Your own knowledge which he has received in Your holy Church, that he may be renewed in what pleases You in (his) generation; the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of truth, the Spirit of Perfection; the Paraclete;  Which You have given to Your holy Apostles and the Prophets.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أفِض عليه من روحك المسلَّط، التي لمعرفتك، هذا الذي أخذه في بيعتك المقدسة، ليتجدد في ما يرضيك كل جيل روحك القدوس، روح الحق، روح الكمال، المعزي، الذي أعطيته لرسلك القديسين والأنبياء.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Moinaf p~% m~pis~bwt n~te tekjom: e~tafi~ e~p~swi qen y~nouni n~Iecce: vai e~ta pi7 m~p~neuma n~te V] m~ton m~mwou e~h~r/i e~jwf: ouoptn~outah n~te ]meym/i.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Give to him, O Lord, the rod of Your might which sprang up from the root of Jesse, upon whom rested the seven spirits of God, laden with the fruit of righteousness:          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            امنحه يارب عصا قوتك، الذي نبع من أصل يسَّى، هذا الذي استراحت عليه السبعة الأرواح الإلهية الموثقة من ثمرات البر.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Oup~n#a# n~covia~ nem ka]: oup~n#a# n~co[ni nem jom: oup~n#a# n~g~nwcic nem meteuceb/c.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            The spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of council and strength, the spirit of knowledge and piety.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            روح الحكمة والفهم، روح المشورة والقوة، روح المعرفة والعبادة.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Eke~mahf n~ho] n~tak V]: eyref]hap oucwouten.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Fill him with Your fear, O God, that he may judge Your people with uprightness,          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            اللهم املأه من مخافتك، ليقضي بين شعبك باستقامة         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Efa~moni m~piouwnh e~bol n~te pinah] etcoutwn n~ata~riki.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            possessing the profession of the Faith which is upright blamelessly.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويتمسَّك باعتراف الأمانة المستقيمة بلا لومٍ.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Eakjolhf n~ounot/rion n~te tekc~tol/ eyouab n~te pekw~ou.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Clothe him with the robe of the holy vesture of Your glory.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أشمله بخلعة حلتك المقدسة التي لمجدك.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Eakyahcf m~pineh n~te p~yel/l: eyrefswpi nak V] n~oumane~cwou efenhot: e~h~r/i e~jen pek/i: e~te ]ekkl/cia.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Anoint him with the oil of gladness, O God, that he may be a trusted shepherd over Your house, which is the Church.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            امسحه بزيت الفرح، ليكون لك يا الله راعياً، أميناً على بيتك، التي هي الكنيسة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Efsemsi m~mok qen oumetata~riki: n~nie”~hoou t/rou n~te pefwnq: n~jwrh nem meri: qen oumetaymounk.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            That he may serve You blamelessly all the days of his life, night and day unceasingly, with holy sacrifices, with a pure heart and an enlightened soul.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لكي يخدمك بغير لومٍ كل أيام حياته ليلاً ونهاراً بغير فتور.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Qen hansouswousi euouab: qen ouh/t eftoub/out: nem ou',/ e~ac[iouwini.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            with holy sacrifices, with a pure heart and an enlightened soul.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بذبائح طاهرة، بقلبٍ نقيٍ، ونفسٍ مستنيرة.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Qen hann/ctia~ nem hanp~raxic eutoub/out: qen oua~gap/ nem oumetremraus: qen ounah] n~atmetsobi: nem hanp~rov/t/ia~: nem han[wrp e~bol n~te pip#n#a#:          </Language>         <Language id="English">            With fastings, with pure acts, with love and meekness and faith without hypocrisy, with prophecy and revelation of the Spirit,          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بالأصوام والأعمال النقية، بالمحبة والوداعة، بأمانة بغير مرائاه، بالنبوة والإعلانات الروحانية.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            eferp~rocverin nak n~ouyucia~ e~couab n~c/ou niben: efe~enc~yoinoufi e~h~r/I e~jen nimetate~mi n~te peklaoc.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            May he offer to You at all times  holy sacrifices, and incense for the ignorances of Your people. Mourning over the disobedient among the ignorant of the people who are Your sheep, drawing them out from  the snare of sin unto the worship of God.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويقرب لك صعائد نقية كل حين، ويصعد لك بخوراً عن جهالات شعبك.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Eferh/bi e~jen n/etoi n~atywt n~h/t: n~te niatka]: n~te pilaoc e~te neke~cwoune.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Mourning over the disobedient among the ignorant of the people who are Your sheep, drawing them out from  the snare of sin unto the worship of God.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويحزن على العُصاة، الغير الفهماء، الشعب الذين هم خرافك.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Efcwk m~mwou e~bolqen pivas n~te v~nobi: e~qoun e~]metyeo~ceb/c.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            drawing them out from  the snare of sin unto the worship of God.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويجذبهم من فخ الخطية إلى عبادة الله.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Ouhir/n/ eke~er,arizecye m~moc e~jsf: nem e~jen peklaoc.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Grant peace unto him and unto your people.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            انعم عليه وعلى شعبك بالسلامة.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Mounaf p~% m~piersisi n~te pekp#n#a# eyouab: eyreftouw~ e~bol n~c~nauh niben: n~te n/e~tapijaji conhou qen v~nobi.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Give to him, Lord, the authority of Your Holy Spirit that he may loose all the bonds of those whom the Enemy has bound in sin, and the separated members of Your Church, grant to him to reconcile them unto unity.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            امنحه يارب سلطان روح قدسك لكي يحل جميع الوثاقات التي ربطها العدو بالخطية.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Ouoh nimeloc etvwrj e~bol n~te ]ekkl/cia: m/ic naf eyrefhotpou e~oumetouai.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            and the separated members of Your Church, grant to him to reconcile them unto unity.          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأعضاء البيعة المتفرقة، امنحه أن يألفهم إلى واحد.          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Eke~a~reh e~tefmetou/b ecoi n~ata[ni sa e~bol: efsemsi nak qen ousouswousi: m~p~n#a#tikon n~c/ou niben: kata taxic m~pinis] n~ar,/e~reuc: etqen niv/oui:          </Language>         <Language id="English">            Preserve his priesthood unblemished for ever; that he may serve You with spiritual sacrifices at all times according to the order of the great High Priest who is in the heavens,          </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            احفظ كنهوته بلا عيب إلى الأبد ليخدمك بذبائح روحانية كل حين على طقس رئيس الكهنة الأعظم الذي في السموات،          </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            I/#c# P,#c#: Vai e~te e~bol…         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Jesus Christ our Lord, through whom are due unto You with Himself and the Holy Spirit, glory and honor and power, now and forever unto the ages of all ages. Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يسوع المسيح، هذا الذي من قبله... إلخ         </Language>      </Text>   </Role>      <InsertDocument path="consecrations/ordinations/include/BishopConclusion"/></Document>