<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik" agpeya="true">      <Title>      <language id="English">Confession Agpeya Prayers</language><language id="Indonesian">Doa Agpeya untuk Pengakuan Dosa</language>   </Title>      <section expanded="true">           <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Prayer For Repentance</language><language id="Indonesian">Doa Pertobatan</language>         <language id="Arabic">صلاة للتوبة</language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            My Lord, God and Savior Jesus Christ, treasure of mercy and spring of salvation, I come to You confessing my sins. I confess that with boldness I dared to defile Your holy sanctuary with my sins. Now I seek Your mercy and love, for Your mercies are boundless; You never turn back a sinner who comes to You. I confess that my mind is burdened with sin and that I have no strength left. Do not turn away from me; do not rebuke me in Your anger nor chasten me in Your displeasure. I am worn out; have compassion upon me, O Lord. Do not judge me according to Your justice, but according to Your mercy. Remember Your creation; do not put me on trial, because none of Your servants can justify their deeds. Dress me in a new attire that befits Your glory. Forgive my sins and I shall sing, “Blessed is he whose sins are forgiven.” When I confess my sins and reveal my iniquities, You cleanse me. Amen.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Tuhanku, Allah dan Juruselamatku Yesus Kristus, harta belas kasihan dan sumber keselamatan, aku datang kepada-Mu mengakui dosa-dosaku. Aku mengakui bahwa dengan keberanian aku telah berani menajiskan tempat kudus-Mu dengan dosa-dosaku. Sekarang aku mencari belas kasih dan kasih-Mu, sebab belas kasihan-Mu tidak terbatas; Engkau tidak pernah menolak seorang pendosa yang datang kepada-Mu. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Aku mengakui bahwa pikiranku terbebani oleh dosa dan bahwa aku tidak memiliki kekuatan yang tersisa. Janganlah berpaling dariku; janganlah menegurku dalam murka-Mu atau menghukumku dalam ketidaksenangan-Mu. Aku telah lelah; kasihanilah aku, ya Tuhan. Janganlah menghakimiku menurut keadilan-Mu, tetapi menurut belas kasihan-Mu. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Ingatlah bahwa aku adalah ciptaan-Mu; janganlah mengadiliku, sebab tidak ada seorang pun dari hamba-Mu yang dapat membenarkan perbuatannya. Kenakanlah aku pakaian baru yang layak bagi kemuliaan-Mu. Ampunilah dosa-dosaku, dan aku akan bernyanyi, “Berbahagialah dia yang dosanya diampuni.” Ketika aku mengaku dosaku dan menyatakan kesalahanku, Engkau menyucikan aku. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Amin.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            ربي وإلهي ومخلصي يسوع المسيح، كنز الرحمة ونبع الخلاص، آتي إليك مقراً بذنوبي. اعترف بأني بوقاحة تجاسرت ودنست هيكلك المقدس بخطاياي. والآن ألجأ إلى رحمتك وتحننك، لأن مراحمك لا تُحصى، وأنك لا ترد خاطئاً قد أقبل إليك. فها أنا آتي يارب معترفاً بأن آثامي قد طمت فوق رأسي كحمل ثقيل، و قد فارقتني قوتي. فلا تحجب يارب وجهك عني لئلا أرتاع. ولا توبخني بغضبك. ولا تودبني بغيظك. ولا تحاكمني بحسب استحقاقي. ارحمني يارب فإني ضعيف. اذكر يارب أني عمل يديك وارأف بي. لا تدخل فى المحاكمة مع عبدك، لأنه لن يتبرر قدامك أي حي. عد وألبسني حلة جديدة تليق بمجدك. اغفر لي وسامحني، لأترنم قائلاً: طوبى لمن غفر إثمه، وسترت خطيته. اعترف لك بخطيتى، ولا أكتم إثمي. قلت اعترف للرب بذنبي. وأنك رفعت آثام خطيتي. آمين.         </language>      </text>   </section>      <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Prayer Before Confession         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Doa Sebelum Pengakuan Dosa         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            صلاة قبل الإعتراف         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O Holy Father, who desires the repentance of sinners, promising to accept them back; look now, O Lord, at my sinful soul for I have erred and lost my way in the valleys of transgressions for many years, and I am embittered and wretched for being removed from the fountain of my salvation. Yet, now I come to You, asking to be cleansed from all defilement and filth. Do not reject, but accept me. Look at me with compassion and deal with me mercifully and I will be cleansed and saved; do not neglect me lest I perish. Grant me grace that I may approach You with faith and hope, to confess my trespasses and my sins. Enlighten my heart that I may realize my sins, my mistakes and my straying. Grant me determination to forsake evil that I may be established in Your commandments and live for the glory of Your holy name. Amen.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Bapa yang Kudus, yang menghendaki pertobatan orang berdosa dan berjanji untuk menerima mereka kembali, pandanglah sekarang, ya Tuhan, jiwaku yang berdosa, karena aku telah sesat dan menyimpang di lembah pelanggaran selama bertahun-tahun. Aku merasa pahit dan sengsara karena terpisah dari sumber keselamatanku. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Namun sekarang aku datang kepada-Mu, memohon untuk disucikan dari segala kenajisan dan kecemaran. Janganlah menolak aku, tetapi terimalah aku. Pandanglah aku dengan belas kasihan dan perlakukanlah aku dengan kemurahan hati agar aku disucikan dan diselamatkan; janganlah meninggalkanku supaya aku tidak binasa. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Anugerahkanlah kepadaku kasih karunia agar aku dapat mendekati-Mu dengan iman dan harapan, untuk mengakui pelanggaran dan dosa-dosaku. Terangilah hatiku agar aku dapat menyadari dosa-dosaku, kesalahanku, dan penyimpanganku. Berikanlah aku tekad untuk meninggalkan kejahatan agar aku dapat diteguhkan dalam perintah-perintah-Mu dan hidup demi kemuliaan nama-Mu yang kudus. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Amin.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أيها الآب القدوس، الذي يحب رجوع الخطاة. وقد وعدت أنك مستعد لقبولهم. انظر يارب الآن إلى نفس خاطئة قد ضلَّت وتاهت في أودية العصيان زماناً طويلاً. فيه تمررت وشعرت بشقاوتها، لبعدها عن ينبوع خلاصها. الآن تتقدم إليك، تطلب منك تطهيرها من الأدناس والأقذار التي توحلت فيها. اقبلها ولا ترفضها فإنك إن نظرت إليها بحنوك، وعاملتها برحمتك تنقت وخلصت، وإن أهملتها، بادَت وهلكت. امنحني يارب نعمة بها أتقوى على الدنو منك بإيمان وطيد ورجاء تام، لأعترف بذنوبي وأكره العودة إليها. وليبكتني روحك على آثامي. أنر قلبي لأرى كم أخطأت، وأسأت، وتركت، وأهملت. وامنحني عزماً على عدم الرجوع إلى الإثم لأثبت في حفظ وصاياك وأحيا لمجد اسمك القدوس، آمين.         </language>      </text>   </section>      <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Prayer after Confession         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Doa Setelah Pengakuan Dosa         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            صلاة بعد الإعتراف         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            I thank Your goodness, O Lover of Mankind because You did not desire that I perish, but have awakened me from my slumber and guided me to Your path. You saved me from the valley of destruction, and brought me to the safety of Your bosom. Fill me with hope and faith, for I have come to You as the sick one to his physician, and as the hungry to the Spring of living water, as the poor to the Source of riches, as the sinners to the Savior, and as the dead to the Fountain of Life; for You are my salvation, my healer, my life, my strength, my comfort, my joy, and my rest is in you. Help me, protect me, and teach me to put my will in Your hands, that I may live according to Your will. Remove my weakness that I may be firm and continue to be faithful to You until the end. Amen.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Aku bersyukur atas kebaikan-Mu, ya Engkau yang Mengasihi umat manusia, karena Engkau tidak menghendaki aku binasa, tetapi telah membangunkanku dari tidurku dan membimbingku ke jalan-Mu. Engkau menyelamatkanku dari lembah kebinasaan dan membawa aku ke dalam perlindungan-Mu yang aman. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Penuhilah aku dengan harapan dan iman, sebab aku datang kepada-Mu seperti orang sakit kepada tabibnya, seperti orang lapar ke mata air yang memberi kehidupan, seperti orang miskin ke sumber kekayaan, seperti orang berdosa kepada Juruselamatnya, dan seperti orang mati ke sumber kehidupan. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Sebab Engkaulah keselamatanku, penyembuhku, hidupku, kekuatanku, penghiburku, sukacitaku, dan tempat peristirahanku. Tolonglah aku, lindungilah aku, dan ajarilah aku untuk menyerahkan kehendakku ke dalam tangan-Mu, agar aku dapat hidup menurut kehendak-Mu. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Singkirkanlah kelemahanku agar aku dapat tetap teguh dan setia kepada-Mu sampai akhir. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Amin.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أشكر صلاحك أيها الآب محب البشر لأنك لم تشأ هلاكي. بل أيقظتني من غفلتي، وهديتني إلى طريقك. ورددتني من وادي الهلاك إلى حمى حصنك الأمين. فاملأني بالرجاء والإيمان. أقبلت إليك يا رب كالمريض إلى الطبيب الشافي، وكالمفتقر الجائع إلى الغذاء المشبع، وكالعطشان إلى ينابيع المياه الحية، وكالفقير إلى مصدر الغنى، وكالخاطىء إلى المخلص، وكالمائت إلى ينبوع الحياة. لأنك خلاصي، وطبيبي، وحياتي، وقوتي، وتعزيتي، وسعادتي، وفيك راحتي. فأعنّي واحفظني وسيِّج حولي، وعلِّمني أن أضع بين يديك كل إرادتي، لأسير حسب ما تشاء. أعن ضعفي كي أثبت وأدوم أميناً لك إلى النهاية، آمين.         </language>      </text>   </section></document>