<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" agpeya="true">   <Title>      <language id="English">The Prayer of the Veil</language><language id="Indonesian">Doa Tudung</language>      <language id="Arabic">صلاةُ السِتَارِ</language>   </Title>      <comment>      <language id="English">         This prayer concerns monks, yet it is suitable for individual meditation. It is prayed daily in monasteries.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Doa ini ditujukan bagi para bapa sang biarawan, namun cocok untuk meditasi individu. Doa ini didoakan setiap hari di biara-biara.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         وهي خاصَّةٌ بالآباءِ الرُّهبانِ، ولكِنَّها مُناسِبةٌ أيضاً للتأمُلِ الفردي. ويُصلَّى بها يومياً في الأديُرةِ.      </language>   </comment>         <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/Introduction"/>            <role id="Introduction">      <text>         <language id="English">            The blessed prayer of the veil, we offer to Christ our King and our God, beseeching Him to forgive us our sins.         </language><language id="Indonesian">Doa Tudung yang diberkati ini aku panjatkan kepada Kristus Rajaku dan Allahku, dan memohon kepada-Nya untuk mengampuni segala dosaku.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            تسبحةُ السِتارِ أقدِّمُها للمسيحِ ملِكي وإلهي وأرجوهُ أنْ يغفِرَ لي خطايايَ.         </language>      </text>   </role>            <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/FromThePsalms"/>      <comment>      <language id="English">         The following psalms are reserved to be prayed by the priest:         <ul>            <li>Psalm 4</li>            <li>Psalm 118 (20)</li>            <li>Psalm 118 (21)</li>            <li>Psalm 118 (22)</li>         </ul>      </language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur-mazmur berikut ini dikhususkan untuk didoakan oleh imam.         <ul>            <li>Mazmur 5</li>            <li>Mazmur 119 (20)</li>            <li>Mazmur 119 (21)</li>            <li>Mazmur 119 (22)</li>         </ul>      </language>   </comment>      <comment>      <language id="English">         The following Psalms from the First Hour are prayed:      </language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur-mazmur berikut ini diucapkan dalam doa dari Doa Jam Pertama</language>   </comment>      <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/4"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/6"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/12"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/15"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/24"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/26"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/66"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/69"/>            <comment>      <language id="English">         The following Psalms from the Third Hour are prayed:      </language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur-mazmur berikut ini diucapkan dalam doa dari Doa Jam Ketiga</language>   </comment>      <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/22"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/29"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/42"/>            <comment>      <language id="English">         The following Psalms from the Sixth Hour are prayed:      </language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur-mazmur berikut ini diucapkan dalam doa dari Doa Jam Ke-enam</language>   </comment>            <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/56"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/85"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/90"/>            <comment>      <language id="English">         The following Psalms from the Ninth Hour are prayed:      </language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur-mazmur berikut ini diucapkan dalam doa dari Doa Jam Kesembilan</language>   </comment>      <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/96"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/109"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/114"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/115"/>            <comment>      <language id="English">         The following Psalms from the Eleventh Hour are prayed:      </language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur-mazmur berikut ini diucapkan dalam doa dari Doa Jam Kesebelas</language>   </comment>      <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/120"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/128"/>            <comment>      <language id="English">         The following Psalms from the Twelfth Hour are prayed:      </language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur-mazmur berikut ini diucapkan dalam doa dari Doa Jam Keduabelas</language>   </comment>      <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/129"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/130"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/131"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/132"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/133"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/136"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/140"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/145"/>            <comment>      <language id="English">         The following Psalms from the Midnight Prayer are said:      </language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur-mazmur berikut ini diucapkan dalam doa dari Doa Tengah Malam</language>   </comment>      <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/118.20"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/118.21"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/118.22"/>     <role id="Introduction">      <text>         <language id="English">            Holy, holy, holy. A reading from the Holy Gospel according to our teacher Saint John. May his blessings be with us all. Amen.         </language><language id="Indonesian">Kudus, kudus, kudus. Pembacaan Injil Kudus menurut guru kita Santo Yohanes. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita semua. Amin</language>         <language id="Arabic">            قدوسٌ، قدوسٌ، قدوسٌ، فصلٌ مِنْ بِشارةِ الإنجيلِ لمُعلِّمِنا مارِ يوحنَّا البشيرِ بركتِهِ على جميعِنا. آمين.         </language>      </text>   </role>      <role id="Reader">      <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">               Gospel (John 6:15-23)            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Injil (Yohanes 6:15-23)            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               الإنجيل لمُعلِّمِنا يوحنا ص 6: 15-23            </language>         </Title>                  <text>            <language id="English">               When Jesus therefore perceived that they would come and take Him by force to make Him a king, He departed again into a mountain by Himself alone.             </language><language id="Indonesian">               Karena Yesus tahu, bahwa mereka hendak datang dan hendak membawa Dia dengan paksa untuk menjadikan Dia raja, Ia menyingkir pula ke gunung, seorang diri.             </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ولمَّا رَأى يَسوعُ أنَّهُم مُهْتَمُّونَ بأنْ يَأتوا ليَختَطِفوهُ، ويَجعَلوهُ مَلِكاً، انْصَرَفَ إلى الجَبَلِ وَحدَهُ.            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="English">               And when evening came, His disciples went down to the sea, and entered into a ship, and went over the sea toward Capernaum. And it was now dark, and Jesus had not come to them. And the sea arose by reason of a great wind that blew.  So when they had rowed about three or four miles, they saw Jesus walking on the sea, and drawing near to the ship, and they were afraid. But He said to them, "It is I; do not be afraid." Then they willingly received Him into the ship: and immediately the ship was at the land where they were going.             </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan ketika hari sudah mulai malam, murid-murid Yesus pergi ke danau, lalu naik ke perahu dan menyeberang ke Kapernaum. Ketika hari sudah gelap Yesus belum juga datang mendapatkan mereka, 6:18 sedang laut bergelora karena angin kencang. Sesudah mereka mendayung kira-kira dua tiga mil jauhnya, mereka melihat Yesus berjalan di atas air mendekati perahu itu. Maka ketakutanlah mereka. Tetapi Ia berkata kepada mereka: "Aku ini, jangan takut!" Mereka mau menaikkan Dia ke dalam perahu, dan seketika juga perahu itu sampai ke pantai yang mereka tujui.             </language>            <language id="Arabic">               فَلَمَّا كانَ المَسَاءُ، نَزَلَ تَلامِيذُهُ إلى البَحْرِ، وركِبوا السَّفِينَةَ ذاهبينَ إلى عَبْرِ البَحرِ، إلى كَفرِنَاحُومَ. وكانَ الظَّلاَمُ قَدْ حَلَّ، ولمْ يَكُنْ يَسوعُ قَدْ جاءَ إلَيْهِمْ بعدُ. وكانَ البَحْرُ هائجاً، وريحٌ شَديدةٌ تَهُبُّ. فلَمَّا ابتَعدوا نَحوَ خَمْسٍ وعِشرِينَ غَلْوَةً أو ثَلاثِينَ، نَظَرُوا يَسوعَ مَاشِياً على البَحْرِ، مُقتَرِباً إلى السَّفِينَةِ فَخَافُوا. فقالَ لهُمْ: أنَا هُوَ لا تَخَافُوا. وكانوا يُريدونَ أنْ يَحمِلوهُ مَعَهُم في السَّفِينَةِ. ولِلوَقتِ جَاءَتْ السَّفِينَةُ إلى شَاطِئِ الأرضِ، التي كَانوا ذَاهِبينَ إليْهَا.            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="English">               On the following day, the people who stood on the other side of the sea saw that there was no other boat there, except that one which His disciples had entered, and that Jesus went not with His disciples into the boat, but that His disciples had gone away alone. However, there came other boats from Tiberias near the place where they ate bread, after the Lord had given thanks.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Pada keesokan harinya orang banyak, yang masih tinggal di seberang, melihat bahwa di situ tidak ada perahu selain dari pada yang satu tadi dan bahwa Yesus tidak turut naik ke perahu itu bersama-sama dengan murid-murid-Nya, dan bahwa murid-murid-Nya saja yang berangkat. Tetapi sementara itu beberapa perahu lain datang dari Tiberias dekat ke tempat mereka makan roti, sesudah Tuhan mengucapkan syukur atasnya. Ketika orang banyak melihat, bahwa Yesus tidak ada di situ dan murid-murid-Nya juga tidak, mereka naik ke perahu-perahu itu lalu berangkat ke Kapernaum untuk mencari Yesus..            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وفي الغَدِ رَأى الجَمْعُ الذي كانَ واقِفاً عِندَ عَبْرِ البَحْرِ، أنَّهُ لَمْ تَكُنْ هُنَاكَ سَفِينَةٌ أُخْرَى، سِوَى وَاحِدةٍ، وَهِيَ تِلْكَ الَّتِي دَخَلَهَا تلاَمِيذُهُ، وأنَّ يَسوعَ لَمْ يَركبْ السَّفِينَةَ مَع تَلامِيذِهِ، بَلْ مَضَى تَلامِيذُهُ وحْدَهُمْ. وجَاءَتْ سُفُنٌ أُخْرَى مِنْ طَبَرِيَّةَ، عِندَ المَوضِعِ حَيثُ أَكَلوا الخُبزَ الذي شَكَرَ عَلَيهِ الربُّ.            </language>         </text>      </section>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/GospelConclusion"/>      <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Litanies</language><language id="Indonesian">Litani</language>         <language id="Arabic">طلبةٌ</language>      </Title>               <role id="Reader">         <text>            <language id="English">               1. Lord, You know the alertness of my enemies; and as for my weakness, You are aware of it, my Creator.  Therefore, I, hereby, place my soul into Your hands.  So cover me with the wings of Your goodness, lest I might sleep till death. Enlighten my eyes by the greatness of Your sayings, and raise me up at all times for Your glorification, for You alone are Good and Lover of Mankind.            </language><language id="Indonesian">1. Tuhan, Engkau mengetahui kewaspadaan dari musuh-musuhku; dan mengenai kelemahanku, Engkau menyadarinya, ya Penciptaku. Oleh karena itu, kuserahkan jiwaku ke dalam tangan-Mu. Jadi naungilah aku dengan sayap kebaikan-Mu, biar aku tidak tertidur sampai maut menjemput. Terangilah mataku dengan kebesaran firman-Mu, dan bangunkan aku setiap waktu untuk memuliakan-Mu, sebab Engkaulah satu-satunya yang baik dan Pengasih  manusia.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               1. يا ربُّ أنتَ تَعْرِفُ يَقَظةَ أعْدائِي، وضَعْفُ طَبيعَتي أنتَ تَعْلَمُهُ، يا خالِقي. لأنِّي هوذا أضَعُ رُوحِي في يَدَيْكَ، فاستُرْنِي بأجْنحَةِ صَلاحِكَ، لِئَلَّا أنَامَ إلى الوَفاةِ. أضِئْ عَينَيَّ بعَظَمَةِ أقوالِكَ، وانهِضْنِي في كُلِّ حينٍ لِتمجيدِكَ، لأنَّكَ صَالِحٌ وَحدَكَ، ومُحِبُّ البَشرِ.            </language>         </text>      </role>                  <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/DoxaPatri"/>            <role id="Reader">         <text>            <language id="English">               2. Lord, Your judgment is dreadful. When men shall be rushed, the angels shall stand, the books shall be opened, the deeds shall be revealed, and the thoughts examined.  What a judgment mine will be, I who am entangled by sin?!  Who would quench the flames of fire about me?!  Who would enlighten my darkness, other than You, O Lord?! Have mercy on me, for You are compassionate to mankind.            </language><language id="Indonesian">2. Tuhan, penghakiman-Mu sungguh mengerikan. Saat manusia berdesak-desakan, dan para malaikat akan berdiri, kitab-kitab akan dibuka, semua perbuatan akan disingkapkan dan semua pikiran akan diperiksa. Betapa dahsyatnya nanti penghakimanku, aku yang terbelit oleh dosa?! Siapa yang dapat memadamkan kobaran api dariku?! Siapa yang dapat menerangi kegelapanku, selain Engkau, ya Tuhan?! Kasihanilah aku, sebab Engkau berbelas kasih terhadap manusia            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               2. يا ربُّ إنَّ دَيْنونَتَكَ لمرهُوبَةٌ. إذ تُحشَرُ النَّاسُ، وتَقِفُ الملائِكةُ، وتُفْتَحُ الأسْفارُ، وتنكشِفُ الأعمالُ، وتُفحَصُ الأفكارُ. أيَّةُ إدانَةٍ تَكونُ إدانَتِي أنا المَضبُوطُ بالخَطايَا. مَنْ يُطفِئُ لهِيبَ النَّارِ عَنِّي؟! مَنْ يُضِيءُ ظُلمَتِي، إنْ لمْ تَرحَمْنِي أنتَ يا ربُّ؟ لأنَّكَ مُتعَطِّفٌ على البَشَرِ.            </language>         </text>      </role>                  <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/KeNin"/>            <role id="Reader">         <text>            <language id="English">               3. O Theotokos, because we have put our trust in you, we shall not be put to shame, but shall be saved.  And because we have attained your help and intercession, O holy and perfect one, we shall not fear, but shall drive out our enemies and shall disperse them.  And, in everything, we take your great help to protect us as if with a shield.  We ask and entreat you, crying, O Theotokos, to save us by your intercessions, and raise us up from the dark sleep, in order to powerfully glorify God who took flesh from you.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               3. Ya Thetokos, karena kami telah menaruh kepercayaan kami padamu, kami tidak akan dipermalukan, tetapi akan diselamatkan. Dan karena kami telah memperoleh pertolongan dan syafaatmu, wahai yang suci dan sempurna, kami tidak akan takut, tetapi akan mengusir musuh-musuh kami dan mencerai-beraikan mereka. Dan, dalam segala hal, kami mengambil bantuanmu yang  besar untuk melindungi kami seperti dengan perisai. Kami meminta dan memohon kepadamu, berseru, ya Theotokos, selamatkanlah kami melalui syafaatmu, dan bangkitkanlah kami dari gelapnya tidur, agar dengan penuh kekuatan dapat memuliakan Allah yang telah berinkarnasi darimu.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               3. يا والِدةَ الإلَهِ، إذ قد حوَينَا الثقةَ بكِ، فلا نَخزَى بَلْ نَخلُصُ. وإذ قد اقتَنَينَا مَعونَتَكِ وشَفَاعَاتِكِ أيَّتُهَا الطَّاهِرةُ الكامِلةُ فلا نَخَافُ، بَلْ نَطرُدُ أعداءَنَا فَنُبدِّدُهُم. ونَتَّخِذُ لنا سِترَ مَعونَتِكِ القَويَّةِ في كُلِّ شيءٍ، نَظِيرَ التُّرسِ. ونَسألُ ونَتَضرَّعُ إليكِ هاتِفينَ، يا والِدَةَ الإلَهِ. لِكَيْ تُخَلِّصِينا بِشَفاعَاتِكِ. وتُنهِضينَا مِنَ النَّومِ المُظلِمِ إلى التَمجِيدِ، بِقُوَّةِ الإلهِ المُتجسِّدِ مِنْكِ.            </language>         </text>      </role>   </section>      <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/Trisagion"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/HailToYou"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/IntroductionToCreed"/>   <insertdocument path="include/Creed"/>   <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/LordHaveMercy"/>      <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">            Absolution         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Absolusi</language>         <language id="Arabic">            التحليلُ         </language>      </Title>                  <text>         <language id="English">            O Lord and Master, Jesus Christ our God, grant us rest in our sleep, repose of our bodies, and purity of our souls, and protect us from the darkness of devastating sin. May the pangs of pain subside, and the heat of the flesh calm down, and the turmoil of the body come to an end. Grant us an alert mind, a humble thought, a life full of virtue, and a pure and undefiled bed.  Raise us up for the night and morning praises, steadfast in Your commandments, keeping in ourselves, at all times, the thought of Your judgments. Grant us to praise You the whole night, blessing Your holy name full of glory and splendor, with Your good Father, and the Holy Spirit, the Life-Giver, now and at all times and unto the ages of all ages.  Amen.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Yesus Kristus, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Tuhan, Guru </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);"> </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan</span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">  Allah kami, berikanlah  ketenangan dalam tidur kami, istirahat bagi tubuh kami, dan kemurnian bagi jiwa kami, serta lindungilah kami dari kegelapan dosa yang merusak. Kiranya rasa sakit penderitaan mereda, dan panasnya nafsu kedagingan meneduh, serta kegelisahan tubuh berakhir. Berikanlah kami pemikiran yang waspada, pikiran yang rendah hati, kehidupan yang penuh kebajikan, dan tempat tidur yang murni dan tak bernoda. Bangkitkanlah kami untuk pujian malam dan pagi, buat kami teguh dalam perintah-perintah-Mu, serta menyimpan dalam diri kami pemikiran akan </span>hukum-hukum-Mu<span style="color: var(--main-fg);"> setiap saat</span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">. Mampukanlah kami untuk memuji-Mu sepanjang malam, memuliakan nama-Mu yang kudus, penuh kemuliaan dan keagungan, bersama Bapa-Mu yang baik, dan Roh Kudus, Sang Pemberi Hidup, sekarang dan selamanya, dan dari segala abad hingga segala abad. Amin.</span></div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            أيُّها السَّيِّدُ الربُّ يَسوعُ المَسيحُ إلهُنَا، أعطِنَا رَاحَةً في نَومِنَا، ونِياحاً في أجْسَادِنا، وطَهارَةً في أنْفُسِنا. واحفَظْنا مِنْ ظُلمَةِ الخَطيئةِ المُدْلَهِمَّةِ. ولْتَسْكُنْ حَرَكاتُ الآلامِ، ولْتَنطفِئْ حرَارَةُ الجَسدِ. وابطِلْ شَغَبَ الجِسْمِ. وامنَحْنا عَقلاً مُستَيقِظاً، وفِكْراً مُتواضِعاً، وسِيرةً مَملوءَةً فَضيلَةً، وفِراشاً غَيرَ دَنِسٍ، ومَضْجَعاً نَقِيَّاً. وانْهِضْنَا لتَسبِيحِ اللَّيلِ، وبَاكِرِ، ثَابِتينَ في وصَايَاكَ، وحافِظِينَ في ذواتِنا على الدَّوامِ ذِكْرَ أحْكَامِكَ. وَهَبْ لنا تَمجيداً في اللَّيلِ أجمعِ. لِنُبَارِكَ اسمَكَ القُدُّوسَ المَملُوءَ مَجداً وبَهاءً، مَعَ أبيكَ الصَّالِحِ، والرُّوح القُدُسِ المُحيِي، الآنَ وكُلَّ أوانٍ، وإلى دَهرِ الدُّهُورِ. آمين.         </language>      </text>   </section>            <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/Conclusion"/></document>