<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" pascha="true" fixeddatedocument="true">   <forceseason id="Fasts ^ PaschaWeek ^ WatosDays ^ Weekdays ^ GreatFriday ^ Fridays ^ FuneralTune ^ SeasonOfAirAndFruits">      <Title>         <language id="English">Great Friday (The Sixth Hour)</language><language id="Indonesian">Jumat Agung (Jam Keenam )</language>         <language id="Arabic">الجمعة  العظيمة (الساعة السادسة)</language>         <language id="Coptic">Pie~hoou n~]nis] m~parackeu/ (}ajp 6)</language>      </Title>            <comment>         <language id="English">            The priests and deacons put on their service vestments.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Para imam dan diakon mengenakan pakaian kebaktian mereka.         </language>      </comment>            <role id="Priest">         <insertdocument path="include/KhenEfranAmen"/>                  <text>            <language id="English">               The prophecies of the Sixth Hour of Great Friday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Nubuat-nubuat dari Jam Keenam Jumat Agung pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               نبوات الساعة السادسة من يوم الجمعة العظيمة من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Numbers 21:1-9</language><language id="Indonesian">Bilangan 21:1-9</language>               <language id="Arabic">عدد 21: 1-9</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/prophecyIntro/Numbers"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh e~tafcwtem n~je pi&lt;ananeoc p~ouro n~Darad v/etsop hi p~safe: je afi~ n~je pIicra/l e~v~mwit n~Ayarim: ouoh afbwtc e~p~Iicra/l ouoh auwli n~oue,malwcia~ n~q/tou:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Now the Canaanite king of Arad, who was dwelling in the desert, heard the news—for Israel came by way of Atharim—therefore, he made war against Israel; and they carried off captives from them as booty.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Raja negeri Arad, orang Kanaan yang tinggal di Tanah Negeb, mendengar, bahwa Israel datang dari jalan Atarim, lalu ia berperang melawan Israel, dan diangkutnya beberapa orang tawanan dari pada mereka.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وسمع الكـنعانى ملك داراد المقيـم فـى البرية أن اسرائيل قد جاء عن طريق اتاريم. فحارب اسرائيل و سبى منهم سبياً.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh aftwbh n~je p~Iicra/l n~oueu,/ m~P[oic ouoh pejaf: je eswp aksan] m~pailaoc e~q~r/i e~najij: ]naera~nay/mazin m~mof nem nefbaki:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then Israel made a vow to the Lord, and said, "If You will indeed deliver this people into my hand, I will anathematize him and his cities."                </language><language id="Indonesian">Maka bernazarlah orang Israel kepada TUHAN, katanya: "Jika Engkau serahkan bangsa ini sama sekali ke dalam tangan kami, kami akan menumpas kota-kota mereka sampai binasa."                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فنذر اسرائيل نذراً للرب وقال: أن دفعت هذا الشعب إلي أيدينا حرمناه لك مع مدنه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh afcwtem n~je P[oic e~t~c~m/ m~pIicra/l: ouoh af] m~pilaoc n~&lt;ananeoc e~q~r/i e~totf: ouoh afera~nay/matizin m~mof nem nefbaki: ouoh au]ren v~ran m~pima etemmje pia~nay/ma:               </language>               <language id="English">                  So the Lord listened to the voice of Israel and delivered up the Canaanites; and they anathematized him and his cities. Therefore, they called the name of that place Anathema.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  TUHAN mendengarkan permintaan orang Israel, lalu menyerahkan orang Kanaan itu; kemudian orang-orang itu dan kota-kotanya ditumpas sampai binasa. Itulah sebabnya tempat itu dinamai Horma.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فسمع الرب صوت اسرائيل ودفع إليهم الكنعانيين. فحرموهم هم ومدنهم. فدعى اسم ذلك الموضع حرماً.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh e~tauouwteb e~bolqen Wrpitwou e~jen v~mwit mv~iom n~sari: aukwt e~p~kahi n~Edwm: ouoh aferkouji n~h/t n~je pilaoc hi v~mwit:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then they departed from Mount Hor by the Way of the Red Sea; and they went around the land of Edom, and the people became discouraged on the way.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Setelah mereka berangkat dari gunung Hor, berjalan ke arah Laut Teberau untuk mengelilingi tanah Edom, maka bangsa itu tidak dapat lagi menahan hati di tengah jalan.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ثم إرتحلوا من جبل حور على طريق البحر الأحمر وداروا من حول أرض آدوم. فصغر قلب الشعب فى الطريق               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh a~pilaoc caji n~ca Vnou] nem Mwu~c/c: je eybe ou akenten e~bolqen p~kahi n~&lt;/mi e~qoyben hi p~wafe: je m~mon wik oude m~wou: ten'u,/ ach~ros e~piwik etsouw~ou:               </language>               <language id="English">                  So the people spoke against God and against Moses, "Why did you bring us up out of Egypt to kill us in the desert? For there is no bread nor water, and our soul is weary of this worthless bread."                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Lalu mereka berkata-kata melawan Allah dan Musa: "Mengapa kamu memimpin kami keluar dari Mesir? Supaya kami mati di padang gurun ini? Sebab di sini tidak ada roti dan tidak ada air, dan akan makanan hambar ini kami telah muak."                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وتكلم الشعب على الله وعلى موسى قائلين: لماذا أصعدتنا من أرض مصر لنموت فى البرية لأنه لا خبز ولا ماء؟ وقد سئمت نفوسنا هذا الخبز اليابس.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh a~P[oic ouwrp n~nihof e~qoun e~pilaoc e~sauqwteb: ouoh nau[iila.in n~ca pilaoc: ouoh afmou n~je ounis] m~m/s n~te nens/ri m~p~Iicra/l.               </language>               <language id="English">                  So the Lord sent venomous serpents among the people, and they bit the people; and many of the children of Israel died.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Lalu TUHAN menyuruh ular-ular tedung ke antara bangsa itu, yang memagut mereka, sehingga banyak dari orang Israel yang mati.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأرسل الرب على الشعب حيات قاتلة. فكانت تلدغ الشعب. ومات قوم كثيرون من بنى اسرائيل.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh a~pilaoc i~ ha Mwu~c/c eujw m~moc: je anernobi ancaji n~ca Vnou] nem n~cwk: twbh oun m~P[oic marefwli n~naihof e~bolharon: ouoh a~Mwu~c/c twbh m~P[oic eybe pilaoc:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then the people came to Moses, and were saying, "We sinned, for we spoke against the Lord and against you; therefore, pray to the Lord, and let Him take away the serpent from us."                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kemudian datanglah bangsa itu mendapatkan Musa dan berkata: "Kami telah berdosa, sebab kami berkata-kata melawan TUHAN dan engkau; berdoalah kepada TUHAN, supaya dijauhkan-Nya ular-ular ini dari pada kami." </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأتى الشعب إلي موسى وقالوا: قد أخطأنا إذ تكلمنا على الرب وعليك. فأدع الرب أن يبعد عنا هذه الحيات.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh peje P[oic m~Mwu~c/c: je mayamio nak n~ouhof n~homt: ouoh ,af hi oum/ini: ouoh ece~swpi a~resan pihof [ila.in e~ourwmi: efe~joust e~pihof n~homt ouoh safwn:               </language>               <language id="English">                  So Moses prayed for the people. Then the Lord said to Moses, "Make a serpent for yourself and put it on a signal pole; and it shall be, if a serpent should bite someone, when the one bitten looks at it, he shall live."               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Lalu Musa berdoa untuk bangsa itu.Maka berfirmanlah TUHAN kepada Musa: "Buatlah ular tedung dan taruhlah itu pada sebuah tiang; maka setiap orang yang terpagut, jika ia melihatnya, akan tetap hidup."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فتضرع موسى لأجل الشعب. فقال الرب لموسى: إصنع لك حية من نحاس، وإرفعها على سارية حتى إذا لدغت الحية إنساناً فينظر إلى الحية النحاس فيحيا.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh afyamio n~je Mwu~c/c m~pihof n~homt ouoh aftahof hi oum/ini: ouoh acswpi hotan a~resan pihof [ila.in e~ourwmi: ouoh n~tefjoust e~pihof n~homt safwnq:               </language>               <language id="English">                  So Moses made a copper serpent and put it on a signal pole; and it happened, when a serpent bit anyone, and he looked at the copper serpent, he lived.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Lalu Musa membuat ular tembaga dan menaruhnya pada sebuah tiang; maka jika seseorang dipagut ular, dan ia memandang kepada ular tembaga itu, tetaplah ia hidup.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فصنع موسى حية من نحاس ورفعها على راية. فكان أى إنسان لدغته حية ونظر إلي الحية النحاسية يحيا.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ProphecyConclusion"/>         </section>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Isaiah 53:7-12</language><language id="Indonesian">Yesaya 53:7-12</language>               <language id="Arabic">إشعياء 53: 7-12</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/prophecyIntro/Isaiah"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Mv~r/] n~oue~cwou e~auenf e~p~qolqel nem m~v~r/] n~ouhi/b m~pem~yo m~v/etqwk m~mof efoi n~atc~m/: pair/] n~fouwn n~rwf an:               </language>               <language id="English">                  He was led as a sheep to the slaughter, and as a lamb is silent before his shearers, so He opens not His mouth.               </language><language id="Indonesian">tidak membuka mulutnya seperti anak domba yang dibawa ke pembantaian; seperti induk domba yang kelu di depan orang-orang yang menggunting bulunya, ia tidak membuka mulutnya.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  مثل خروف سيق إلى الذبح وكحمل صامت أمام الذى يجـزه. هكذا لم يفتح فاه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Au w~li m~pefhap qen de nim eynas~vir e~roc: je cenaw~li m~pefwnq e~bolhijen p~kahi: eybe nia~nomia~ n~te pilaoc afi~ e~v~mou:               </language>               <language id="English">                  In His humiliation His judgment was taken away, and who will declare His generation? For His life is taken from the earth, and because of the lawlessness of My people He was led to death.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sesudah penahanan dan penghukuman ia terambil, dan tentang nasibnya siapakah yang memikirkannya? Sungguh, ia terputus dari negeri orang-orang hidup, dan karena pemberontakan umat-Ku ia kena tulah.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فرفع حكمه فى تواضعه. وجيله من يقدر أن يصفه. ستنزع حياته من الأرض. ولأجل آثام الشعب جاء إلى الموت.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh eie~] n~nia~nomoc n~t~sebiw~ n~tefkaici nem niramaoi n~t~sebiw~ m~pefmou:je mpefi~ri n~ouanomia~: oude m~poujem ou,~rof qenrwf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  I will appoint evil men for His burial and rich men for His death, because He committed no lawlessness, nor was deceit found in His mouth.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Orang menempatkan kuburnya di antara orang-orang fasik, dan dalam matinya ia ada di antara penjahat-penjahat, sekalipun ia tidak berbuat kekerasan dan tipu tidak ada dalam mulutnya.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وسأعطى المتجاوزى الناموس مجازاة دفنه. والأغنياء مكافأة موته. لأنه لم يصنع اثماً، ولم يوجد فى فمه غش.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  P[oic ouws e~toujof e~bolqen pierqot: e~swp a~reten san] e~jen v~nobi teten'u,/ nanau e~oujroj e~nase pefa~mahi:               </language>               <language id="English">                  The Lord wishes to cleanse Him of His wound, and if You give an offering for sin, Your soul shall see a long-lived seed.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tetapi TUHAN berkehendak meremukkan dia dengan kesakitan. Apabila ia menyerahkan dirinya sebagai korban penebus salah, ia akan melihat keturunannya, umurnya akan lanjut, dan kehendak TUHAN akan terlaksana olehnya.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أما الرب فشاء أن يشفيه من الجراح وإذا ما أسلمتم ذواتكم ذبيحة عن الخطية فسترى نفوسكم زرعاً أيامه كثيرة.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  P[oic ouws e~w~li e~bolqen pim~kah n~te tef'u,/ e~tamof e~ouwini: e~erp~lazin n~ouka]: e~yamio n~oumeym/i: efoi m~bwk n~oum/s n~kalwc: ouoh nounobi n~yof afe~nou e~p~swi:               </language>               <language id="English">                  The Lord wishes to take away the pain of His soul, to show Him light, to form Him with understanding, and to pronounce righteous the Righteous One who serves many well; and He shall bear their sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sesudah kesusahan jiwanya ia akan melihat terang dan menjadi puas; dan hamba-Ku itu, sebagai orang yang benar, akan membenarkan banyak orang oleh hikmatnya, dan kejahatan mereka dia pikul.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وشاء الرب أن ينزع الآلالم عن نفسه ويريه النور ويوجِد الفهم. ويصنع البر ويكون عبداً حسناً للجماعة. إذ يحمل خطاياهم               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eybe vai n~yof efe~erk~l/ronomin n~oum/s: ouoh efe~vws n~niswl n~te nijwri: e~v~ma je af] n~tef'u,/ e~v~mou:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Therefore He shall inherit many, and will divide the spoil with the strong, because His soul was delivered over to death.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebab itu Aku akan membagikan kepadanya orang-orang besar sebagai rampasan, dan ia akan memperoleh orang-orang kuat sebagai jarahan, yaitu sebagai ganti karena ia telah menyerahkan nyawanya ke dalam maut                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ومن أجل هذا هو يرث الكثيرين ويقسم غنائم الأقوياء حيث أسلم نفسه للموت                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh auopf nem nia~nomoc n~yof afen ninobi n~te oum/s e~p~swi: ouoh eybe oua~nomia~ aut/if:               </language>               <language id="English">                  He was considered among the lawless, and He bore the sins of many, and was delivered over because of their sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian">dan karena ia terhitung di antara pemberontak-pemberontak, sekalipun ia menanggung dosa banyak orang dan berdoa untuk pemberontak-pemberontak.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وأحصى مع الأثمة وهو قد حمل خطايا كثيرين وأسلم من أجل ذنوبهم.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ProphecyConclusion"/>         </section>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Isaiah 12:2-13:10</language><language id="Indonesian">Yesaya 12:2-13:10</language>               <language id="Arabic">إشعياء 12: 2 - 13:10</language>            </Title>                           <insertdocument path="pascha/include/prophecyIntro/Isaiah"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  H/ppe ic Vnou] pacwt/r: P[oic eie~swpi e~re h~y/i ,/e~rof: ouoh n~naerho] je: pawcu nem pac~mou pe P[oic: afswpi n/i n~ououjai.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Behold, God is my Savior and Lord. I will trust in Him and be saved by Him. I will not be afraid, for the Lord is my glory and my praise. He has become my salvation."               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sungguh, Allah itu keselamatanku; aku percaya dengan tidak gementar, sebab TUHAN ALLAH itu kekuatanku dan mazmurku, Ia telah menjadi keselamatanku."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  هوذا الله خلاصى. الرب الذى أنا متكل عليه فلا أخاف. مجدى وتسبيحى هو الرب. وقد صار لي خلاصاً.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Moh n~oumwou qen ouounof e~bolqen nimoumi n~te pioujai.               </language>               <language id="English">                  You will draw water with gladness from the wells of salvation.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Maka kamu akan menimba air dengan kegirangan dari mata air keselamatan.                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  املأوا ماء بفـرح مـن ينابيع الخلاص.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh ,~najoc qen piehoou e~tem~mau: je c~mou e~P[oic ws oube pefran:               </language>               <language id="English">                  In that day, you will say, "Praise the Lord; call upon His name.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Pada waktu itu kamu akan berkata: "Bersyukurlah kepada TUHAN, panggillah nama-Nya, </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وتقولون فى ذلك اليوم سبحوا الرب وادعوا اسمه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  hiwis qen nieynoc n~nefh~b/oui~ ettai/out: a~riv~meui~ je af[ici n~je pefran.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Declare His glorious things among the Gentiles and make mention that His name is exalted.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  beritahukanlah perbuatan-Nya di antara bangsa-bangsa, masyhurkanlah, bahwa nama-Nya tinggi luhur!               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وبشروا فى الأمم بأعماله الكريمة. أذكروا بان اسمه قد تعالى.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Hwc e~v~ran m~P[oic je afiri n~hanh~b/oui~ eu[oci.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Sing to the name of the Lord, for He has done great things.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Bermazmurlah bagi TUHAN, sebab perbuatan-Nya mulia; baiklah hal ini diketahui di seluruh bumi!                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  سبحوا اسم الرب لأنه قد صنع أعمالاً عظيمة،                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Yel/l ouoh ounof n/etsop qen Ciwn: je af[ici qen tem/] n~je v/eyu n~te p~Iicra/l.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Exult and be glad, O inhabitants of Zion, for the Holy One of Israel is exalted in her midst."                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Berserulah dan bersorak-sorailah, hai penduduk Sion, sebab Yang Mahakudus, Allah Israel, agung di tengah-tengahmu!"                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وافرحى ياساكنة صهيون لأنه قد إرتفع فى وسطك قدوس اسرائيل.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Alioui~ n~oum/ini hijen nitwou efoi m~metswt: [ici n~netenc~m/ m~pererho]: ma]ouw~ qen ]jij a~ouwn n~hanar,wn                </language>               <language id="English">                  "Lift up a sign on the mountain of the plain and raise your voice to them. Do not fear; comfort with your hand; open the gates, O you rulers.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ucapan ilahi terhadap Babel yang dinyatakan kepada Yesaya bin Amos.Naikkanlah panji-panji di atas gunung yang gundul, berserulah terhadap mereka dengan suara nyaring; lambaikanlah tangan supaya mereka masuk ke pintu-pintu gerbang para bangsawan!               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إرفعوا راية على الجبال السهلة. إرفعوا أصواتكم ولا تخافوا. أشيدوا باليد. إفتحوا للرؤساء               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Anok de eyouahcahni e~e~nou n~ceyou/t: a~nok eynan/ou cenai~ n~je hana~vwv e~jwk m~pajwnt: eue~rasi ouoh eue~]ws eucop.                </language>               <language id="English">                  I command and I lead them. They are sanctified, and I lead them. My mighty ones come to fulfill My anger—rejoicing and insulting at the same time."                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Aku ini telah memerintahkan orang-orang yang Kukuduskan, telah memanggil orang-orang perkasa-Ku untuk melaksanakan hukuman murka-Ku, orang-orang-Ku yang beria-ria dan bangga.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لأنى أنا الذى أمرت أن يأتوا ويجتمعوا. وأنا الآتى وستأتى الجبابرة ليكملوا غضبى، فيفرحون ويعيدون معاً.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Tc~m/ n~oum/s n~eynoc: t~c~m/ n~te hanourwou nem haneynoc euyou/t: P[oic cabawy afouahcahni n~ous~lol n~ref]hoplon.               </language>               <language id="English">                  The sound of many nations upon the mountains, like that of many nations, the voice of kings and nations gathered together—the Lord of hosts commanded a warring nation.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ada suara keramaian di atas gunung-gunung, seperti suara kumpulan orang yang besar jumlahnya! Suara kegaduhan dari kerajaan-kerajaan, dari bangsa-bangsa yang berkumpul! TUHAN semesta alam sedang memeriksa pasukan perang.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  صوت أمم كثيرة وصوت ملوك وشعوب مجتمعة. رب الصباؤوت أمر شعباً مسلحاً،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eyrefi~ e~bolqen oukahi efou/ou: icjen aur/jc n~]cen] n~te t~ve: P[oic nem nefref]hoplon: e~p~jintako n~]oikoumen/ t/rc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  To come from a far country, from the end of heaven, the Lord and His weapons, to destroy all the inhabited world.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Mereka datang dari negeri yang jauh, ya dari ujung langit, yaitu TUHAN serta yang melaksanakan amarah-Nya untuk merusakkan seluruh bumi.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أن يأتى من أرض بعيدة من أقطار أساس السماء. والرب مع جنوده المسلحة ليهلك المسكونة كلها.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Esl/loui~ e~bol f~qent gar n~je pie~hou m~P[oic cabawy: ouqomqem efe~i~ e~bolhiten Vnou].                </language>               <language id="English">                  Wail, for the day of the Lord is at hand, and destruction will come from God.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Merataplah, sebab hari TUHAN sudah dekat, datangnya sebagai pemusnahan dari Yang Mahakuasa.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولولوا فان يوم رب الجنود قد قرب. والأنكسار يأتى من عند الله.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eybe vai jij niben eue~]ouw~ e~bol.u,/ niben n~te nirwmi eue~erslah n~h/t.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Therefore every hand will grow weary, and every man's soul will be fearful.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebab itu semua tangan akan menjadi lemah lesu, setiap hati manusia akan menjadi tawar,               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلذلك تسترخى كل يد. ويذوب قلب كل إنسان.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eue~s~yorter n~je nip~recbuteroc: ouoh hannakhi eue~[itou m~v~r/] n~y/eynamici: ouoh eue~erh/ibi ouai oube ouai m~mwou eue~twmt: ouoh eue~sib] m~pouho mvr/] n~ousah.               </language>               <language id="English">                  The elders will be troubled. Pangs will take hold of them, like a woman in childbirth, and they will wail at one another and be amazed; and their countenance shall change like a flame.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  dan mereka akan terkejut. Sakit mulas dan sakit beranak akan menyerang mereka, mereka akan menggeliat kesakitan seperti perempuan yang melahirkan. Mereka akan berpandang-pandangan dengan tercengang-cengang, muka mereka seperti orang yang demam.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وتضطرب المشائخ ويأخذهم المخاض. ويتضورون كالتى تلد وينوح الواحد قبالة صاحبه ويتحيرون وتتغير وجوههم كاللهيب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  H/ppe gar ic p~e~hoou m~P[oic n~at,w e~bol: f~n/ou qenoum~bon nem oujwnt: e~,w n~]oikoumen/ t/rc hip~safe: ouoh e~tako n~nirefernobi e~bol iwtc.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Behold, the day of the Lord is coming, a day that cannot be averted, a day of anger and wrath, to make all the inhabited world a desert, and to destroy the sinners from it.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sungguh, hari TUHAN datang dengan kebengisan, dengan gemas dan dengan murka yang menyala-nyala, untuk membuat bumi menjadi sunyi sepi dan untuk memunahkan dari padanya orang-orang yang berdosa.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  هوذا يوم الرب يأتى بغير مغفرة. قادم بسخط وغضب. ليجعل المسكونة كلها برية قاحلة. ليبيد الخطاة منها.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Niciou n~te t~ve nem piw~rion nem picolcel t/rf n~te t~ve: n~nef] m~piouwini: ouoh eue~er,aki e~rev~r/ a~sai: piioh n~nef] m~pefouwini:               </language>               <language id="English">                  For the stars of heaven and Orion and all the ornament of heaven will not give their light. It will be dark when the sun goes forth, and the moon will not give its light.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Sebab bintang-bintang dan gugusan-gugusannya di langit tidak akan memancarkan cahayanya; matahari akan menjadi gelap pada waktu terbit, dan bulan tidak akan memancarkan sinarnya.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  كواكب السماء والاوريون (النجوم) وكل زينتها لا تعطى نورها. وتظلم الشمس عند طلوعها. والقمر لا يعطى نوره.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ProphecyConclusion"/>         </section>         <insertdocument path="pascha/friday/interpretations/6thHour/Isaiah.12.2-13.10"/>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Amos 8:9-12</language><language id="Indonesian">Amos 8:9-12</language>               <language id="Arabic">عاموس 8: 9-12</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/prophecyIntro/Amos"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh ece~swpi qen pie~hoou e~tem~mau peje P[oic Vnou]: efe~hwtp n~je v~r/ m~v~nau m~meri ouoh efe~er,aki hijen p~kahi n~je piouwini qen pie~hoou:               </language>               <language id="English">                  "And it will come to pass in that day," says the Lord God, "the sun will set at noon, and the light of day will grow dark over the land.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Pada hari itu akan terjadi," demikianlah firman Tuhan ALLAH, "Aku akan membuat matahari terbenam di siang hari dan membuat bumi gelap pada hari cerah.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ويكون فى ذلك اليـوم يقول السيـد الرب: تغيب الشمس وقت الظهيرة. ويظلم النـور علـى الأرض فى الـنهار.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouou ]navwnh n~netensai e~ouh/b ouoh netenhwd/ t/rou eunehpi. Ouoh ]na,w n~oucwk e~jen ]pi niben: nem oumetkereh e~jen a~ve niben: ouoh ]na,af m~v~r/] nouh/bi n~te oumenrit: ouoh n/eynemaf m~v~r/] n~oue~hoou n~te oum~kah n~h/t.               </language>               <language id="English">                  And I shall turn your feasts into mourning and all your songs into lamentation. I shall place sackcloth on every waist and make every head bald. They shall be as one mourning a 'beloved one, and those with them as a day of grief."               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Aku akan mengubah perayaan-perayaanmu menjadi perkabungan, dan segala nyanyianmu menjadi ratapan. Aku akan mengenakan kain kabung pada setiap pinggang dan menjadikan gundul setiap kepala. Aku akan membuatnya sebagai perkabungan karena kematian anak tunggal, sehingga akhirnya menjadi seperti hari yang pahit pedih."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وأحول أعيادكـم نوحاً وجـميـع تسابيحكم رثاء. وأجعل على كل حقوٍ مسحاً. وعلى كل رأس قرحاً. وأجعله مثل حزن الحبيب والذين معه كمثل يوم الحزن.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  H/ppe ic hane~hoou cen/ou peje P[oic Vnou]: ]naouwrp n~ouh~bwn hijen p~kahi: n~ouh~bwn n~ouwik n~h~bwn an pe: oude ouh~bwn m~mwou an pe: alla ouh~bwn e~cwtem e~p~caji m~P[oic:               </language>               <language id="English">                  "Behold, the days will come," says the Lord, "that I shall send a famine across the land; not a famine of bread nor a thirst for water, but famine to hear the words of the Lord.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Sesungguhnya, waktu akan datang," demikianlah firman Tuhan ALLAH, "Aku akan mengirimkan kelaparan ke negeri ini, bukan kelaparan akan makanan dan bukan kehausan akan air, melainkan akan mendengarkan firman TUHAN.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  هوذا ستأتى أيام يقول السيد الرب، إنى أرسل جوع على الأرض. وليس هو جوع إلى الخبز أو عطش إلى الماء بل هو جوع إلي إستماع كلمة الرب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh eue~kim n~je nimwou sae~q~r/i e~v~iom: ouoh eue~[oji icjen p~emhit sa niman~sai: eue~kwt n~ca p~caji m~P[oic ouoh n~noujemf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  The waters will be unsettled as far as the sea. And from the north to the east men will scurry about seeking to find the word of the Lord, but they will not find it.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mereka akan mengembara dari laut ke laut dan menjelajah dari utara ke timur untuk mencari firman TUHAN, tetapi tidak mendapatnya.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فتتحول المياه إلي قاع البحر. ويجرون من الشمال إلي المشرق ويطلبون كلمة الرب فلا يجدونها.                </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ProphecyConclusion"/>         </section>      </role>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Introduction to the Paschal Praise</language><language id="Indonesian"> Pendahuluan Doksologi Paskah</language>            <language id="Arabic">مقدمة تسبحة البصخة</language>         </Title>               <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PropheciesConclusion"/>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The doxology of the Sixth Hour of Great Friday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Doksologi dari Jam Keenam  Jumat Agung pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  تسبحة الساعة السادسة من يوم الجمعة العظيمة من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="include/LordsPrayerNoTitle"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/Doxology.3"/>            <comment>         <language id="English">            The candles before the icon of the Crucifixion are lit.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Lilin-lilin di depan ikon Penyaliban dinyalakan.         </language>      </comment>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/WeWorshipYouOChrist"/>            <role id="People">         <comment>            <language id="English">               Meanwhile the deacons chant the "Hymn of the Censer (<span class="Coptic">Taisour/</span>)" in the Paschal tune:            </language><language id="Indonesian">Sementara itu, para diakon melantunkan "Himne Kemenyan (Taisour/"dengan melodi Paskah.            </language>         </comment>                  <insertdocument path="include/Taishoree"/>               <insertdocument path="include/HymnOfTheCross"/>         <insertdocument path="include/TenouwstSeasonalResponse"/>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <comment>            <language id="English">               The hymn of the Pauline Epistle, "An Epistle (<span class="Coptic">]e~pictol/</span>)," is chanted in Coptic in the Paschal tune, and then the epistle is translated.            </language><language id="Indonesian">Himne dari Surat Paulus, "Sebuah Surat (]e~pictol/)," dinyanyikan dalam bahasa Koptik dengan melodi Paskah, dan kemudian surat itu diterjemahkan.</language>         </comment>         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Introduction to the Pauline Epistle</language><language id="Indonesian">Pengantar kepada Surat Paulus</language>               <language id="Coptic">}e~pictol/</language>            </Title>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/TiepistoleVerse"/>            <insertdocument path="include/PaulineEpistleIntroduction"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Anok de n~necswpi n/i n~tasousou m~moi e~b/l qen pic~tauroc n~te Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc...               </language>                           <language id="English">                  But God forbid that I should boast except in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ...               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tetapi Allah melarang supaya aku bermegah, kecuali di salib Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus...               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وأما من جهتى فحاشا لي أن أفتخر إلا بصليب ربنا يسوع المسيح...               </language>            </text>            <insertdocument path="include/PaulineEpistleConclusion"/>         </section>      </role>      <role id="People">         <insertdocument path="include/PaulineEpistleResponses"/>      </role>      <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Galatians 6:14-18</language><language id="Indonesian">Galatia 6:14-18</language>               <language id="Arabic">غلاطية 6: 14-18</language>            </Title>            <insertdocument path="include/PaulineEpistleIntroduction"/>            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Anok de n~necswpi n/i n~tasousou m~moi e~b/l qen pic~tauroc n~te Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc: vai e~te ebolhitotf aui~si m~pikocmoc n/i: ouoh a~nok hw auast m~pikocmoc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  But God forbid that I should boast except in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, by whom the world has been crucified to me, and I to the world.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tetapi aku sekali-kali tidak mau bermegah, selain dalam salib Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus, sebab olehnya dunia telah disalibkan bagiku dan aku bagi dunia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وأما من جهتى فحاشا لي أن أفتخر إلا بصليب ربنا يسوع المسيح. هذا الذى به قد صلب العالم لي، وأنا أيضاً صلبت للعالم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nh~r/i gar qen Pi,~rictoc I/couc: oude p~cebi h~li pe oude ]metatcebi: alla oucwnt m~beripe.               </language>               <language id="English">                  For in Christ Jesus neither circumcision nor uncircumcision avails anything, but a new creation.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebab bersunat atau tidak bersunat tidak ada artinya, tetapi menjadi ciptaan baru, itulah yang ada artinya.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لأنه فى المسيح يسوع ليس الختان بشئ ولا الغرلة بل الخليقة الجديدة               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh ouon niben e~tau]ma] qen paikanwn: t~hir/n/ e~h~r/i e~jwou nem pinai: nem e~jen p~Iicra/l n~te Vnou].               </language>               <language id="English">                  And as many as walk according to this rule, peace and mercy be upon them, and upon the Israel of God.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan semua orang, yang memberi dirinya dipimpin oleh patokan ini, turunlah kiranya damai sejahtera dan rahmat atas mereka dan atas Israel milik Allah.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فكل الذين يسلكون بهذا القانون عليهم السلام والرحمة وعلى اسرائيل الله.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Pcepi de n~nai m~peny~reh~li ouah qici e~roi: a~nok gar niswlh n~te Pi,~rictoc ]fai qarwou qen pacwma. Pih~mot m~Penoc I/couc Pi,~rictoc nem petenpna nac~n/ou a~m/n:               </language>               <language id="English">                  From now on let no one trouble me, for I bear in my body the marks of the Lord Jesus. Brethren, the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Selanjutnya janganlah ada orang yang menyusahkan aku, karena pada tubuhku ada tanda-tanda milik Yesus.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فيما بعد لا يجلب أحد علىّ آتٍعاباً، لأنى حامل فى جسدى سمات الرب يسوع. نعمة ربنا يسوع المسيح مع روحكم يا أخوتى آمين.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="include/PaulineEpistleConclusion"/>         </section>      </role>            <comment>         <language id="English">            The deacons begin the "Sixth Hour Litanies (<span class="Coptic">Wv/et qen pie~hoou</span>)" of the Agpeya prayer, then the priest prays the rest of the parts in Coptic and then translates it and the deacons chant the appropriate refrains.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Para diakon memulai "Litani Jam Keenam" (<span class="Coptic">Wv/et qen pie~hoou</span>)" dalam doa Agpeya, kemudian imam melanjutkan dengan sisa bagian-bagian dalam bahasa Koptik dan kemudian menerjemahkannya, sementara para diakon melantunkan bait-bait yang sesuai.         </language>      </comment>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">The Sixth Hour Litanies</language><language id="Indonesian">Litani Jam Keenam</language>            <language id="Coptic">W v/et qen pie~hoou</language>         </Title>                  <role id="Priest">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/OYouWhoOnTheSixthDay"/>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/OYouWhoOnTheSixthDay"/>         </role>                        <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Anok de aiws e~h~r/i ha Vnou] ouoh a~P[oic cwtem e~roi: Vnou] cwtem e~tap~roceu,/ ouoh m~perhip~ho m~patwbh. Mah~y/k e~roi ouoh cwtem e~roi:               </language>               <language id="English">                  I cried to the Lord and He heard me. God hear my prayer, and do not refuse my petition.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ya Engkau, pada hari yang keenam, dan jam keenam dipaku di kayu salib untuk dosa yang dengan berani diperbuat bapa kami Adam di taman Firdaus, robeklah tulisan dosa-dosa  kami, ya Yesus Kristus Allah kami, dan selamatkanlah kami. Aku berseru kepada Allah dan Tuhan mendengarkanku.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أنا صرخت إلى الله والرب سمعنى. اللهم إسمع صلآتٍى ولا ترفض طلبتى إلتفت إلىّ وإسمعنى.               </language>            </text>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Rouhi nem swrp nem v~nau m~meri eie~jw ouoh eie~caji ouoh efe~cwtem e~paq~rwou ouoh efe~cw] n~ta'u,/ qen ouhir/n/.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Be attentive to me and hear me in the evening, in the morning, and at midday. I say my words, and He hears my voice and delivers my soul in peace.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div> Ya Allah dengarlah doaku, dan janganlah menolak permohonanku. Perhatikanlah aku dan dengarlah seruanku pada waktu malam, pagi dan siang hari. Aku berbicara dan Tuhan mendengarkan suaraku dan menyelamatkan jiwaku dalam damai.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  عشية وباكر ووقت الظهر، كلامى أقوله فيسمع صوتى ويخلص نـفــسـى بسلام.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/OYouWhoOnTheSixthDay"/>            <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/DoxaPatriNoRole"/>         </role>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  W I/couc Pi,~rictoc Pennou] v/e~tau]i~ft nak e~qoun e~pictauroc qen ]ajp coou e~akqwteb m~v~nobi hiten pise. Ouoh aktanqo m~porefmwout hiten pekmou: e~te pirwmi pe e~takyamiof qen nekjij e~tafmou hiten v~nobi. Qwteb n~nenpayoc hiten nekm~kauh n~oujai n~reftanqo ouoh qen nii~ft e~tau]i~ft nak n~q/tou.               </language>               <language id="English">                  O Jesus Christ, our God, who was nailed to the cross in the sixth hour, and killed sin by the tree, and by Your death You made alive the dead man, whom You created with Your own hands, and had died in sin. Put to death our pains by Your healing and life giving passions, and by the nails with which You were nailed.                </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Yesus Kristus, Allah kami,</div><div>- yang dipaku di kayu salib pada jam keenam dan telah mematikan dosa dengan kayu,<span style="color: var(--main-fg);">- yang melalui kematian-Mu Engkau menghidupkan orang mati, yang Engkau ciptakan dengan tangan-Mu sendiri; yang telah mati karena dosa.</span></div><div>Matikanlah penderitaan kami melalui sengsara-Mu yang memberi kesembuhan dan kehidupan, dan melalui paku yang ditancapkan kepada-Mu. </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يا يسوع المسيح إلهنا الذى سمرت على الصليب فى الساعة السادسة، وقتلت الخطية بالخشبة، وأحييت الميت بموتك، الذى هو الإنسان الذى خلقته بيديك الذى مآتٍ بالخطية، إقتل أوجاعنا بالامك الشافية المحيية وبالمسامير التى سمرت بها.                </language>            </text>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Matoujo mp~ennouc e~bolha ]b~lab/ n~te nih~b/oui~ n~hul/nikon: e~qoun e~p~erv~meui~ n~nekhap n~e~pouranion kata nekmetsenh/t.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Rescue our minds from thoughtlessness of the earthly deeds and worldly lusts, to the remembrance of Your heavenly commandments, according to Your compassion.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Selamatkan pikiran kami dari kekosongan perbuatan dunia dan nafsu duniawi, kepada ingatan akan hukum Surgawi-Mu menurut belas kasihan-Mu.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إنقذ عقولنا من طياشة الأعمال الهيولية والشهـوات العالمية إلى تذكار أحكامك السـمائـية كرأفتك.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/OYouWhoOnTheSixthDay"/>            <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/KeNinNoRole"/>         </role>                        <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Hwc m~montan h~li n~eukeria eybe p~a~sai n~te nennobi: eyb/] gar w~ ]yeo~tokoc m~paryenoc tenerpar/ciazecye zecye m~mon qaten v/e~taremacf               </language>               <language id="English">                  Since we have no favor, nor excuse, nor justification because of our many sins, we, through you, implore to Him who was born of you, O Theotokos, the Virgin,               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Karena kami tidak memiliki nilai lebih, ataupun alasan, maupun pembenaran, sebab banyaknya dosa kami, maka kami memohon melaluimu mintalah kepada Dia yang engkau lahirkan, ya Theotokos, </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إذ ليس لنا وسيلة من أجل كثرة خطايانا فنحن بك يا والدة الإله الـعـذراء نجد دالة عند الذى ولدتيه.               </language>            </text>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  je nase ne nep~recbia cejemjom ouoh cesop nahren Pencwt/r:               </language>               <language id="English">                  for abundant and acceptable is your intercession with our Savior.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sang Perawan, sebab syafaatmu melimpah, kuat dan diterima oleh Juruselamat kami. </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لأن كثيرة هى شفاعتك، قوية ومقبولة عند مخلصنا.               </language>            </text>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  W ]mau ettoub/out m~per,w n~cw n~nirevernobi qen nep~recbia qaten u/e~taremacf ge ouna/t gar pe: e~ ouon s~jom m~mof e~nahmen je ou/i gar e~taf[im~kah eyb/ten                </language>               <language id="English">                  O pure mother, do not exclude sinners from your intercession with Him whom you bore, for He is merciful and able to save us, because He suffered for us to deliver us.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Bunda yang suci, janganlah abaikan orang berdosa dari syafaatmu kepada Dia yang engkau kandung, sebab Dia murah hati dan sanggup menyelamatkan kami, karena Dia telah menderita bagi kami untuk membebaskan kami. </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أيتها الأم الطاهرة لا ترفضى الخطاة من شفاعتك عند الذى ولدتيه، لأنه رحوم وقادر على خلاصنا لأنه تألم من أجلنا لكى ينقذنا.               </language>            </text>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  hina n~tefnahmen marouer sorp n~tahon n~,wlem n~je nekmetsenh/t je anerh/ki e~masw a~ribo/yin e~ron Vnou] Pencwt/r eybe p~w~ou m~pekran P[oic eke~nahmen k~e~,a nennobi nan e~bol eybe pekran eyouab.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Let your compassion speedily reach us, for we are exceedingly humbled. Help us, O God, our Savior, for the glory of Your name. O Lord, deliver us and forgive us our sins for the sake of Your holy name.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Biarlah belas kasih-Mu segera mencapai kami sebab kami sangatlah hina. Tolonglah kami, ya Allah, Juruselamat kami, demi kemuliaan nama-Mu. Ya Tuhan, bebaskanlah dan ampunilah dosa kami demi nama-Mu yang Kudus.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلتسبق وتدركنا رأفتك سريعاً لأننا قد تمسكنا جداً. أعنا يا الله مخلصنا من أجل مجد إسمكَ، يارب خلصنا وأغفر لنا خطايانا من أجل إسمكَ القدوس.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/OYouWhoOnTheSixthDay"/>            <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/KeNinNoRole"/>         </role>                        <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Akir~i n~oujai qen y~m/] m~pikahi w~ Pi,~rictoc Pennou] qen p~jiny~rekcouten nekjij eyouab e~bol hijen pic~tauroc. Eybe vai nieynoc t/rou cews e~bol je piw~ou nak P[oic.               </language>               <language id="English">                  You wrought salvation in the midst of all the earth, O Christ our God, as You stretched Your holy hands on the cross. Therefore, all nations cry out saying, "Glory to You O Lord".               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ya Kristus, Allah kami, Engkau memberikan keselamatan ke tengah dunia pada saat Engkau merentangkan tangan-Mu yang kudus di kayu salib. Sebab itu semua bangsa berseru mengatakan, "Kemuliaan bagi-Mu ya Tuhan."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  صنعت خلاصاً فى وسط الأرض أيها المسيح الهنا عندما بسطت يديك الطاهرتين على الصليب. فلهذا كل الأمم تصرخ قائلة: المجد لك يارب.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/DoxaPatriNoRole"/>         </role>                        <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Tenouwst n~tekmorv/ n~a~ttako w~ pia~gayoc ene~retin m~p~,w e~bol n~te nennobi w~ Pi,~rictoc Pennou]. Je ou/~i qen pekouws ak]ma] e~a~l/i e~pictauroc eyrektoujo n~n/e~takyamiwou e~bolha ]metbwk n~te pijaji.               </language>               <language id="English">                  We worship Your incorruptible person, O Good One, asking for the forgiveness of our sins, O Christ our God. For, of Your will, You were pleased to be lifted up onto the cross, to deliver those whom You created from the bondage of the enemy.                </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Kristus Allah kami, Yang Maha Baik, kami sujud menyembah pribadi-Mu yang tak dapat hancur, memohon pengampunan atas dosa kami. Karena atas kehendak-Mu, Engkau rela ditinggikan di atas salib untuk membebaskan ciptaan-Mu dari perbudakan musuh.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  نسجد لشخصك غير الفاسد أيها الصالح ونسأل غفران خطايانا أيها المسيح إلهنا، لأن بمشيئتك سررت أن تصعد على الصليب لتنجى الذين خلقتهم من عبودية العدو.                </language>            </text>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Tenws oub/k enseph~mot n~totk je akmoh m~pip~t/rf qen ourasi w~ Pencwt/r e~taki~ e~er~bo/yin e~pikocmoc P[oic piw~ou vwk pe               </language>               <language id="English">                  We cry out unto You and give thanks to You, for You have filled all with joy, O Savior, when You came to help the world. Lord, glory to You.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami berseru dan bersyukur kepada-Mu, karena Engkau telah memenuhi segalanya dengan sukacita, Ya Juruselamat, pada waktu Engkau datang untuk menolong dunia. Kemuliaan bagi-Mu Tuhan.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  نصرخ إليكَ ونشكرك لأنك ملأت الكل فرحاً أيها المخلص لما أتيت لتعين العالم، يارب المجد لكً.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/KeNinNoRole"/>         </role>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nyo te w~ y/eymeh n~h~mot w~ ]yeo~tokoc m~paryenoc: tenhwc er~o je e~bolhiten pic~tauroc n~te pes/ri afhei n~je a~men]: ouoh afkwrf n~je vm~ou:                </language>               <language id="English">                  You are she who is full of grace. O Theotokos, the Virgin, we praise you, for, through the cross of your Son, Hades fell down and death was abolished.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Engkaulah dia yang penuh rahmat, ya Theotokos, Sang Perawan, kami meninggikanmu, sebab melalui Salib Anakmu, alam maut telah jatuh dan kematian sudah dihapuskan. </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أنت هى الممتلئة نعمة يا والدة الإله العذراء، نعظمك لأن من قبل صليب إبنك إنهبط الجحيم وبطل الموت.                </language>            </text>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nanmwout ne ouoh antwoun ouoh anerm~p~sa m~piwnq n~e~neh: ouoh an[i m~p~ounof m~piparadicoc n~te sorp. Eybe vai ten]w~ou naf qen ouseph~mot hwc dunatoc Pi,~rictoc Pennou].               </language>               <language id="English">                  We were dead but we are raised and became worthy of eternal life, and gained the delight of the first Paradise. Therefore, we thankfully glorify the immortal Christ our God.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebelumnya kami mati, tetapi kami dibangkitkan, dan dilayakkan untuk mewarisi kehidupan kekal dan mendapatkan sukacita dari Firdaus yang pertama. Oleh sebab itu dengan penuh ucapan syukur, kami memuliakan-Mu, Kristus Allah kami yang kekal.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أمواتاً كنا فـنهضـنا واستحققنا الحياة الأبدية وأخذنا فرح الفردوس الأول. من أجل هذا نـمجـده بشكر غير المائت المسيح إلهنا.               </language>            </text>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/Omonogenees"/>            <role id="Priest">         <comment>            <language id="English">               The priest offers incense before the icon of the Crucifixion.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Pendeta mempersembahkan dupa di depan ikon Penyaliban.            </language>         </comment>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/trisagion/Seasonal"/>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Psalm 37:21-22, 21:16-18,8</language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur 38:21-22, 22:16-18,8</language>               <language id="Arabic">مزمور 37: 21-22, 21: 16-18, 8</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PsalmOfDavid"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Auberbwrt e~bol a~nok pimenrit m~v~r/] n~ourefmwout efo~reb: ouoh au]fit e~tacarx: m~per,at n~cwk P[oic panou].               </language>               <language id="English">                  They have rejected me, the beloved one, as an abominable dead carcass; they have pierced my body with nails. Do not forsake me, O Lord, O my God.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Jangan tinggalkan aku, ya TUHAN, Allahku, janganlah jauh dari padaku!  Segeralah menolong aku, ya Tuhan, keselamatanku!               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  رفضونى أنا الحبيب مثل ميت مرذول. وجعلوا مساميراً فى جسدى. فلا تهملنى ياربى وإلهى.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Au[wlk n~tot nem rat auwp n~nakac t/rou: auvws n~nah~bwc e~h~raf ouoh tahebcw auhiwp e~roc: aucaji qen nouc~votou aukim n~toua~ve:                </language>               <language id="English">                  They pierced my hands and my feet. I numbered all my bones, They divided my garments among themselves, and for my clothing they cast lots.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Sebab anjing-anjing mengerumuni aku, gerombolan penjahat mengepung aku, mereka menusuk tangan dan kakiku. Mereka membagi-bagi pakaianku di antara mereka, dan mereka membuang undi atas jubahku.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ثقبوا يدى ورجلى وأحصوا كل عظامى. إقتسموا ثيابى بينهم وعلى لباسى إقترعوا.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Aujoc je icje afnah] aferhelpic e~P[oic marefnahmef: mareftou jof icje afouasf: all/louia.                </language>               <language id="English">                  “He hoped in the Lord, let Him rescue him; Let Him save him since He delights in him.” Alleluia.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   "Ia menyerah kepada TUHAN; biarlah Dia yang meluputkannya, biarlah Dia yang melepaskannya! Bukankah Dia berkenan kepadanya?"                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  تكلموا بشفاههم وحركوا رؤوسهم وقالوا إن كان آمن وآتٍكل على الرب. فليخلصه ولينجيه إن كان اراده. الليلويا.               </language>            </text>         </section>      </role>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Matthew 27:27-45</language><language id="Indonesian">Matius 27:27-45</language>            <language id="Arabic">متى 27: 27-45</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/KeEperto"/>         <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroMatthew"/>         <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Tote nimatoi n~te pihugemwn auwli n~I/couc e~qoun e~pipretwrion: ouoh auywou] e~]c~p/ra t/rc e~h~r/ e~jwf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then the soldiers of the governor took Jesus into the Praetorium and gathered the whole garrison around Him.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kemudian serdadu-serdadu wali negeri membawa Yesus ke gedung pengadilan, lalu memanggil seluruh pasukan berkumpul sekeliling Yesus.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  حينئذ أخذ جند الوالى يسوع وأدخلوه إلى الايوان وجمعوا عليه كل الكتيبة.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh e~taubasf au] n~ou,lamic n~kokkoc hiwtf:                </language>               <language id="English">                  And they stripped Him and put a scarlet robe on Him.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mereka menanggalkan pakaian-Nya dan mengenakan jubah ungu kepada-Nya.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فعروه وألبسوه رداءً قرمزياً.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh auswnt n~ou,~lom e~bolqen hancouri aut/if ejen tefa~ve: ouoh au,w n~oukas qen tefjij n~oui~nam: ouoh nauhioui~ m~mwou e~jen noukeli m~pef m~yo eucwbi m~mof eujw m~moc: je ,ere p~ouro n~niIoudai.               </language>               <language id="English">                  When they had twisted a crown of thorns, they put it on His head, and a reed in His right hand. And they bowed the knee before Him and mocked Him, saying, “Hail, King of the Jews!”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mereka menganyam sebuah mahkota duri dan menaruhnya di atas kepala-Nya, lalu memberikan Dia sebatang buluh di tangan kanan-Nya. Kemudian mereka berlutut di hadapan-Nya dan mengolok-olokkan Dia, katanya: "Salam, hai Raja orang Yahudi!"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وضفروا إكليلاً من شوك ووضعوه على رأسه. وجعلوا فى يمينه قصبة. وكانوا يجثون على ركبهم قدامه ويستهزؤن به قائلين: السلام يا ملك اليهود.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh n~touhiyaf e~qoun qen pefho: auw~li m~pikas auhioui~ qen tefa~ve.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then they spat on Him, and took the reed and struck Him on the head.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Mereka meludahi-Nya dan mengambil buluh itu dan memukulkannya ke kepala-Nya.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكانوا يبصقون فى وجهه. وأخذوا القصبة وضربوه على رأسه.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh e~tauouw eucwbi m~mof: aubasf n~],~lamic ouoh au] n~nefh~bwc hiwtf ouoh auolf eyrouasf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  And when they had mocked Him, they took the robe off Him, put His own clothes on Him, and led Him away to be crucified.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sesudah mengolok-olokkan Dia mereka menanggalkan jubah itu dari pada-Nya dan mengenakan pula pakaian-Nya kepada-Nya. Kemudian mereka membawa Dia ke luar untuk disalibkan.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلما هزأوا به نزعوا عنه الرداء وألبسوه ثيابه وأخذوه ليصلب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eun/ou de e~bol aujimi n~ourwmi n~Kurinneoc: e~pefran pe Cumewn: vai au[itf n~,~ba hina n~tef el pefc~tauroc:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Now as they came out, they found a man of Cyrene, Simon by name. Him they compelled to bear His cross.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Ketika mereka berjalan ke luar kota, mereka berjumpa dengan seorang dari Kirene yang bernama Simon. Orang itu mereka paksa untuk memikul salib Yesus.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وفيما هم خارجون وجدوا رجلاً قيروانياً إسمه سمعان فسخروه ليحمل صليبه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh e~taui~ euma e~saumou] e~rof je Golgoya: e~te pima n~te Pik~ranion pe:                </language>               <language id="English">                  And when they had come to a place called Golgotha, that is to say, Place of a Skull,               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Maka sampailah mereka di suatu tempat yang bernama Golgota, artinya: Tempat Tengkorak.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولما أتوا إلى المكان الذى يقال له الجلجثة، الذى هو موضع الجمجمة،                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Au] n~ouhemj naf efmoujt nem ouensasi: ouoh e~tafjem]pi m~pefouws e~cw:               </language>               <language id="English">                  They gave Him sour wine mingled with gall to drink. But when He had tasted it, He would not drink.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Lalu mereka memberi Dia minum anggur bercampur empedu. Setelah Ia mengecapnya, Ia tidak mau meminumnya.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أعطوه خلاً ممزوجاً بمرارة. ولما ذاق لم يرد أن يشرب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Etauasf de auvws n~nefh~bwc e~h~rau e~auhiwp e~rwou.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then they crucified Him, and divided His garments, casting lots.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sesudah menyalibkan Dia mereka membagi-bagi pakaian-Nya dengan membuang undi.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولما صلبوه إقتسموا ثيابه بينهم مقترعين عليها.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh nauhemci eua~reh e~rof m~mau:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Sitting down, they kept watch over Him there.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Lalu mereka duduk di situ menjaga Dia.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ثم جلسوا يحرسونه هناك.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh auc~qe tefe~tia~ cap~swi n~tefa~ve ecc~q/out m~pair/] je Vai Pe I/couc Pouro Nte Niioudai:               </language>               <language id="English">                  And they put up over His head the accusation written against Him: THIS IS THE KING OF THE JEWS.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan di atas kepala-Nya terpasang tulisan yang menyebut alasan mengapa Ia dihukum: "Inilah Yesus Raja orang Yahudi."                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكتبوا قضيته فوق رأسه مكتوبة هكذا: هذا هو يسوع ملك اليهود.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                   Tote aui~si n~keconi c~nau nemaf: ouai catefoui~nam: nem ouai catefja[/.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then two robbers were crucified with Him, one on the right and another on the left.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Bersama dengan Dia disalibkan dua orang penyamun, seorang di sebelah kanan dan seorang di sebelah kiri-Nya.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                   حينئذ صلبوا معه لصين، واحد عن يمينه وواحد عن يساره.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  N/de e~naucini naujeoua~ e~rof pe: eukim n~toua~ve:               </language>               <language id="English">                  And those who passed by blasphemed Him, wagging their heads,               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Orang-orang yang lewat di sana menghujat Dia dan sambil menggelengkan kepala,                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان المجتازون يجدفون عليه ويحركون رؤوسهم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eujw m~moc: je v/eynabel piervei n~te Vnou] e~bol ouoh n~tefkotf qen somt n~e~hoou nahmek: icjen~yok pe p~s/ri m~Vnou]: a~mou e~pec/t e~bolhipic~tauroc:               </language>               <language id="English">                  And saying, “You who destroy the temple and build it in three days, save Yourself! If You are the Son of God, come down from the cross.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  mereka berkata: "Hai Engkau yang mau merubuhkan Bait Suci dan mau membangunnya kembali dalam tiga hari, selamatkanlah diri-Mu jikalau Engkau Anak Allah, turunlah dari salib itu!"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  قائلين يا ناقض هيكل الله وبانيه فى ثلاثة أيام خلص نفسك. إن كنت أنت هو إبن الله فإنزل عن الخشبة.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Vai pe m~v~r/] n~niar,/ e~reuc nem nicaq nem nip~recbuteroc: eucwbi m~mof eujw m~moc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Likewise the chief priests also, mocking with the scribes and elders, said,               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Demikian juga imam-imam kepala bersama-sama ahli-ahli Taurat dan tua-tua mengolok-olokkan Dia dan mereka berkata:                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                   وكذلك رؤساء الكهنة والكتبة والشيوخ كانوا يستهزئون به قائلين:               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je afnohem n~hanke,wouni: m~mons~jom m~mof e~nahmef: icje p~ouro m~Piicra/l pe marefi~ e~pec/t ]nou e~bolhipic~tauroc n~tennah] erof:               </language>               <language id="English">                  “He saved others; Himself He cannot save. If He is the King of Israel, let Him now come down from the cross, and we will believe Him.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Orang lain Ia selamatkan, tetapi diri-Nya sendiri tidak dapat Ia selamatkan! Ia Raja Israel? Baiklah Ia turun dari salib itu dan kami akan percaya kepada-Nya.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  خلص آخرين ولم يقدر أن يخلص نفسه. إن كان هو ملك اسرائيل فلينزل الآن عن الصليب لنؤمن به.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Icje de h~y/f,/ eVnou] marefnahmef ]nou icje f~ouasf je afjoc je a~nok pe p~s/ri m~Vnou]:                </language>               <language id="English">                  He trusted in God; let Him deliver Him now if He will have Him; for He said, ‘I am the Son of God.’”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Ia menaruh harapan-Nya pada Allah: baiklah Allah menyelamatkan Dia, jikalau Allah berkenan kepada-Nya! Karena Ia telah berkata: Aku adalah Anak Allah."                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إن كان متوكلاً على الله فلينقذه الآن إن كان يريده. لأنه قال: أنا هو إبن الله.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Vai de nare nikeconi jw m~mof n/e~taua~sou nemaf euts[n/ni nemaf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Even the robbers who were crucified with Him reviled Him with the same thing.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Bahkan penyamun-penyamun yang disalibkan bersama-sama dengan Dia mencela-Nya demikian juga.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكذلك اللصان اللذان صلبا معه كانا يعيرانه.               </language>            </text>                     <comment>               <language id="English">                  At the reading of “and there was darkness over all the land”, the candles and lights are turned off to resemble the darkness.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Saat pembacaan "dan ada kegelapan di seluruh negeri", lilin dan lampu dimatikan untuk meniru suasana kegelapan.               </language>            </comment>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Icjen v~nau de n~ajp coou: a~ou,aki swpi hijen p~kahi t/rf: sa v~nau n~ajp'i].               </language>               <language id="English">                  Now from the sixth hour until the ninth hour there was darkness over all the land.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mulai dari jam dua belas kegelapan meliputi seluruh daerah itu sampai jam tiga.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ومن وقت الساعة السادسة كانت ظلمة على الأرض إلى وقت الساعة التاسعة.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelContinuationMark"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Mark 15:26-33</language><language id="Indonesian">Markus 15:26-33</language>            <language id="Arabic">مرقس 15: 26-33</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroMark"/>                     <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh ]e~pig~rav/ n~te tefe~tia~ nacc~q/ou pe je p~ouro n~te niIoudai:               </language>               <language id="English">                  And the inscription of His accusation was written above: The King Of The Jews.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan alasan mengapa Ia dihukum disebut pada tulisan yang terpasang di situ: "Raja orang Yahudi".               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان عنوان علته مكتوباً: ملك اليهود.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh auas keconi c~nau nemaf: ouai catefoui~nam nem ouai catefja[/:               </language>               <language id="English">                  With Him they also crucified two robbers, one on His right and the other on His left.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Bersama dengan Dia disalibkan dua orang penyamun, seorang di sebelah kanan-Nya dan seorang di sebelah kiri-Nya.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وصلبوا معه لصين واحداً عن يمينه والآخر عن يساره.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh acjwk e~bol n~je ]g~rav/ je auopf nem nia~nomoc:                </language>               <language id="English">                  So the Scripture was fulfilled which says, “And He was numbered with the transgressors.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  (Demikian genaplah nas Alkitab yang berbunyi: "Ia akan terhitung di antara orang-orang durhaka.")                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                   فتمت الكتابة القائلة: وأحصى مع الأثمة.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh n/e~naucini nau je oua~ e~rof: eukim n~noua~v/oui~ ouoh eujw m~moc: je v/eynabel piervei e~bol: ouoh n~tefkotf qen somt n~e~hoou:               </language>               <language id="English">                  And those who passed by blasphemed Him, wagging their heads and saying, “Aha! You who destroy the temple and build it in three days,               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Orang-orang yang lewat di sana menghujat Dia, dan sambil menggelengkan kepala mereka berkata: "Hai Engkau yang mau merubuhkan Bait Suci dan mau membangunnya kembali dalam tiga hari,               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان المجتازون به يجدفون عليه ويحركون رؤوسهم قائلين يا ناقض الهيكل وبانيه فى ثلاثة أيام،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nahmek e~aki~ e~q~r/i e~bolhipic~tauroc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  save Yourself, and come down from the cross!”               </language><language id="Indonesian">turunlah dari salib itu dan selamatkan diri-Mu!"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  خلص نفسك وإنزل عن الصليب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Pair/] nikear,/e~reuc eucwbi nem noue~r/ou: nem nicaq eujw m~moc: je afnohem n~hanke,wouni: m~mons~jom m~mof e~nahmef:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Likewise the chief priests also, mocking among themselves with the scribes, said, “He saved others; Himself He cannot save.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Demikian juga imam-imam kepala bersama-sama ahli Taurat mengolok-olokkan Dia di antara mereka sendiri dan mereka berkata: "Orang lain Ia selamatkan, tetapi diri-Nya sendiri tidak dapat Ia selamatkan!                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكذلك رؤساء الكهنة كانوا يستهزؤن فيما بينهم مع الكتبة قائلين: خلص آخرين وأما نفسه فلم يقدر أن يخلصها،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Icje Pi,~rictoc p~ouro m~Piicra/l pe marefi~ e~pec/t ]nou e~bolhi pic~tauroc: hina n~tennau ouoh n~tennah]: ouoh n/e~taua~sou nemaf nau]swsnaf:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Let the Christ, the King of Israel, descend now from the cross, that we may see and believe.” Even those who were crucified with Him reviled Him.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Baiklah Mesias, Raja Israel itu, turun dari salib itu, supaya kita lihat dan percaya." Bahkan kedua orang yang disalibkan bersama-sama dengan Dia mencela Dia juga.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إن كان هو المسيح ملك اسرائيل فلينزل الآن عن الصليب لنرى ونؤمن. وكان اللذان صلبا معه يعيرانه أيضاً.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh e~ta v~nau n~ajp coou swpi: a~ou,aki swpi hijen p~kahi t/rf sa v~nau n~ajp'i]:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Now when the sixth hour had come, there was darkness over the whole land until the ninth hour.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Pada jam dua belas, kegelapan meliputi seluruh daerah itu dan berlangsung sampai jam tiga.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولما كانت الساعة السادسة، كانت ظلمة على الأرض كلها إلى الساعة التاسعة.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelContinuationLuke"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Luke 23:26-44</language><language id="Indonesian">Lukas 23:26-44</language>            <language id="Arabic">لوقا 23: 26-44</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroLuke"/>                     <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh hwc euini m~mof e~bol: aua~monin~ouai je Cimewn ne ouKurinneoc pe: efn/ou e~bolqen tkoi: autale pictauroc erof eyreftwoun m~mof cavahou n~I/couc:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Now as they led Him away, they laid hold of a certain man, Simon a Cyrenian, who was coming from the country, and on him they laid the cross that he might bear it after Jesus.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ketika mereka membawa Yesus, mereka menahan seorang yang bernama Simon dari Kirene, yang baru datang dari luar kota, lalu diletakkan salib itu di atas bahunya, supaya dipikulnya sambil mengikuti Yesus.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وبينما هم منطلقون به، أمسكوا واحداً يدعى سمعان القيروانى. وكان آتياً من الحقل ووضعوا عليه الصليب ليحمله خلف يسوع.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nafmosi de n~cwf n~je ounis] m~m/s n~te pilaoc: nem hanhiomi n/e~nautwit ouoh naunehpi e~rof:                </language>               <language id="English">                  And a great multitude of the people followed Him, and women who also mourned and lamented Him.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Sejumlah besar orang mengikuti Dia; di antaranya banyak perempuan yang menangisi dan meratapi Dia.                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان يتبعه جمهور كثير من الشعب والنساء اللواتى كن يندبن وينحن عليه.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Etafvonhf de e~rwou n~je I/couc pejaf: niseri n~te Ieroucal/m mperrimi e~jwi: p~l/n rimi e~jen y/nou nem e~jen netens/ri.               </language>               <language id="English">                  But Jesus, turning to them, said, “Daughters of Jerusalem, do not weep for Me, but weep for yourselves and for your children.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Yesus berpaling kepada mereka dan berkata: "Hai puteri-puteri Yerusalem, janganlah kamu menangisi Aku, melainkan tangisilah dirimu sendiri dan anak-anakmu!                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فألتفت إليهن يسوع وقال: يا بنات أورشليم: لا تبكين علىّ، بل إبكين على أنفسكن وعلى أولادكن،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je h/ppe cen/ou n~je hane~hoou: n/e~tounajoc n~q/tou: je w~ounia~tou n~nia[r/n nem nineji e~tem~poumici: nem nim~no] e~te m~pousans:                </language>               <language id="English">                  For indeed the days are coming in which they will say, 'Blessed are the barren, wombs that never bore, and breasts which never nursed!'               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebab lihat, akan tiba masanya orang berkata: Berbahagialah perempuan mandul dan yang rahimnya tidak pernah melahirkan, dan yang susunya tidak pernah menyusui.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لأنه هوذا ستأتى أيام يقولون فيها طوبى للعواقر والبطون التى لم تلد والثدى التى لم ترضع.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Tote cenaerh/tc n~joc n~nitwou je hei e~jwn: nem nikalamvo je hobcten:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then they will begin 'to say to the mountains, “Fall on us!” and to the hills, “Cover us!”                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Maka orang akan mulai berkata kepada gunung-gunung: Runtuhlah menimpa kami! dan kepada bukit-bukit: Timbunilah kami!                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  حينئذ يبتدئون يقولون للجبال إسقطى علينا، وللآكام غطينا.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je icje cei~ri n~nai qen pise etl/k: ie oupeynaswpi qen petsouw~ou.               </language>               <language id="English">                  'For if they do these things in the green wood, what will be done in the dry?”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebab jikalau orang berbuat demikian dengan kayu hidup, apakah yang akan terjadi dengan kayu kering?"                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لأنهم إن كانوا صنعوا هذا بالعود الرطب فماذا يكون باليابس؟               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Naui~ni de pe n~ke referpethwou c~nau nemaf e~qoybou.               </language>               <language id="English">                  There were also two others, criminals, led with Him to be put to death.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Dan ada juga digiring dua orang lain, yaitu dua penjahat untuk dihukum mati bersama-sama dengan Dia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وجاءوا أيضاً بإثنين آخرين مذنبين ليقتلا معه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh hote e~taui~ e~paima e~toumou] e~rof je Pik~ranion: auasf m~mau nem nikakourgoc: ouai men caoui~nam ouai de caja[/:                </language>               <language id="English">                  And when they had come to the place called Calvary, there they crucified Him, and the criminals, one on the right hand and the other on the left.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ketika mereka sampai di tempat yang bernama Tengkorak, mereka menyalibkan Yesus di situ dan juga kedua orang penjahat itu, yang seorang di sebelah kanan-Nya dan yang lain di sebelah kiri-Nya.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولما بلغوا إلى المكان المسمى الأقرانيون صلبوه هناك مع عاملى الشر، أحدهما عن يمينه والآخر عن يساره               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  I/couc de pejaf je paiwt ,w nwou e~bol: je m~poue~mi e~n/e~toui~ri m~mof: euvws de n~nefh~bwc e~h~rau auhiwp e~rwou.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then Jesus said, “Father, forgive them, for they do not know what they do.” And they divided His garments and cast lots.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Yesus berkata: "Ya Bapa, ampunilah mereka, sebab mereka tidak tahu apa yang mereka perbuat." Dan mereka membuang undi untuk membagi pakaian-Nya.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  . فقال يسوع: يا أبتاه إغفر لهم لأنهم لا يدرون ما يعملون. وإذ إقتسموا ثيابه بينهم إقترعوا عليها.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh nafohi e~ratf n~je Pilaoc efnau: nau elksai pe n~je nikear,wn eujw m~moc: je afnohem n~han ke,wouni marefnahmef hwf: icje vai pe Pi,~rictoc p~s/ri m~Vnou] picwtp.                </language>               <language id="English">                  And the people stood looking on. But even the rulers with them sneered, saying, “He saved others; let Him save Himself if He is the Christ, the chosen of God.”                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Orang banyak berdiri di situ dan melihat semuanya. Pemimpin-pemimpin mengejek Dia, katanya: "Orang lain Ia selamatkan, biarlah sekarang Ia menyelamatkan diri-Nya sendiri, jika Ia adalah Mesias, orang yang dipilih Allah."                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان الشعب قائماً ينظر. والرؤساء أيضاً يستهزؤن به قائلين: خلص آخرين، فليخلص نفسه إن كان هو المسيح إبن الله المختار.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Naucwbi de m~mof n~je nikematoi eun/ou harof eui~ni n~ouhemj naf.                </language>               <language id="English">                  The soldiers also mocked Him, coming and offering Him sour wine,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Juga prajurit-prajurit mengolok-olokkan Dia; mereka mengunjukkan anggur asam kepada-Nya                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان الجند أيضاً يهزأون به ويقدمون له خلاً,               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eujwm~moc je icje n~yok pe p~ouro nniIoudai nahmek.               </language>               <language id="English">                  and saying, “If You are the King of the Jews, save Yourself.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   dan berkata: "Jika Engkau adalah raja orang Yahudi, selamatkanlah diri-Mu!"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ويقولون: إن كنت أنت ملك اليهود فخلص نفسك.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ne ouon ou e~pig~rav/ de hijwf: m~methebreoc m~metrwmeoc m~metoueinin je: Vai Pe Pouro Nte Niioudai:                </language>               <language id="English">                  And an inscription also was written over Him in letters of Greek, Latin, and Hebrew: THIS IS THE KING OF THE JEWS.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Ada juga tulisan di atas kepala-Nya: "Inilah raja orang Yahudi".                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان عنوان فوقه مكتوباً باليونانيه والرومانية والعبرانية: هذا هو ملك اليهود.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouai de e~bolqen nikakourgoc e~taua~sou: nafjeoua~ e~rof pe efjwm~moc: je icje n~yok pe Pi,~rictoc nahmek ouoh nahmen hwn.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then one of the criminals who were hanged blasphemed Him, saying, “If You are the Christ, save Yourself and us.”                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Seorang dari penjahat yang di gantung itu menghujat Dia, katanya: "Bukankah Engkau adalah Kristus? Selamatkanlah diri-Mu dan kami!"                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان واحد من عاملى الردئ الذين صلبا معه يجدف عليه قائلاً: إن كنت أنت المسيح فخلص نفسك وخلصنا.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Afe~rouw~ de n~je pikeouai efere~pitiman naf pejaf: je ou de Vnou] n~yok k~erho] an qatefh/ je an,/ qen paihap nouwt.               </language>               <language id="English">                  But the other, answering, rebuked him, saying, “Do you not even fear God, seeing you are under the same condemnation?               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tetapi yang seorang menegor dia, katanya: "Tidakkah engkau takut, juga tidak kepada Allah, sedang engkau menerima hukuman yang sama?                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأجاب الآخر وإنتهره قائلاً: أما تخشى الله إذ اننا نحن تحت هذا الحكم بعينه؟               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh a~non men qe oumeym/i e~tan[i kata p~emp~sa n~n/e~tanaitou: vai de n~yof m~peferh~li m~pethwou:               </language>               <language id="English">                  And we indeed justly, for we receive the due reward of our deeds; but this Man has done nothing wrong.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kita memang selayaknya dihukum, sebab kita menerima balasan yang setimpal dengan perbuatan kita, tetapi orang ini tidak berbuat sesuatu yang salah."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أما نحن فبعدل جوزينا، لاننا نلنا ما تستوجبه أعمالنا وأما هذا فلم يفعل شيئاً ردياً،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh nafjwm~moc n~I/couc: je P[oic a~ripameui~ hotan akwani~ qen tekmetouro.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then he said to Jesus, “Lord, remember me when You come into Your kingdom.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Lalu ia berkata: "Yesus, ingatlah akan aku, apabila Engkau datang sebagai Raja."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ثم قال ليسوع: إذكرنى يارب متى جئت فى ملكوتك.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh peje I/couc naf je a~m/n ]jwm~moc nak: je m~voou ,~naswpi nem/i qen piparadicoc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  And Jesus said to him, “Assuredly, I say to you, today you will be with Me in Paradise.”                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kata Yesus kepadanya: "Aku berkata kepadamu, sesungguhnya hari ini juga engkau akan ada bersama-sama dengan Aku di dalam Firdaus."                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فقال له يسوع: الحق أقول لك إنك اليوم تكون معى فى الفردوس.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ne v~nau de n~ajp coou pe: ouoh ou,aki afswpi hijen p~kahi t/rf: sa v~nau n~ajp'i]               </language>               <language id="English">                  Now it was about the sixth hour, and there was darkness over all the earth until the ninth hour.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ketika itu hari sudah kira-kira jam dua belas, lalu kegelapan meliputi seluruh daerah itu sampai jam tiga,               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان نحو الساعة السادسة. فكانت ظلمة على الأرض كلها إلى وقت الساعة التاسعة.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelContinuationJohn"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">John 19:13-27</language><language id="Indonesian">Yohanes 19:13-27</language>            <language id="Arabic">يوحنا 19: 13-27</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroJohn"/>                     <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Pilatoc de e~tafcwtem e~naicaji: afenI/couc e~bol ouoh afhemci hijen pib/ma: qen pimae~toumou] e~rof je piliyoc t~rwton: m~methebreoc je Gabbaya:               </language>               <language id="English">                  When Pilate therefore heard that saying, he brought Jesus out and sat down in the judgment seat in a place that is called The Pavement, but in Hebrew, Gabbatha.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Ketika Pilatus mendengar perkataan itu, ia menyuruh membawa Yesus ke luar, dan ia duduk di kursi pengadilan, di tempat yang bernama Litostrotos, dalam bahasa Ibrani Gabata.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلما سمع بيلاطس هذا الكلام أخرج يسوع وجلس على كرسى الولاية فى موضع يقال له رصيف الحجارة، وبالعبرانية جباثا.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Net~pareckeu/ e~te m~pipac,a: ne v~nau de n~ajp coou pe: ouoh nafjw m~moc n~je Pilatoc n~niIoudai je h/ppe ic petouro:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Now it was the Preparation Day of the Passover, and about the sixth hour. And he said to the Jews, “Behold your King!”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Hari itu ialah hari persiapan Paskah, kira-kira jam dua belas. Kata Pilatus kepada orang-orang Yahudi itu: "Inilah rajamu!"                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكانت جمعة الفصح. وكان نحو الساعة السادسة. فقال بيلاطس لليهود: هوذا ملككم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nywou de auws e~bol je a~litf a~litf asf: peje Pilatoc nwou je n~taes petenouro: aue~rouw~ n~je niar,/ereuc je m~monten ouro m~mau e~b/l e~Kecar.                </language>               <language id="English">                  But they cried out, “Away with Him, away with Him! Crucify Him!” Pilate said to them, “Shall I crucify your King?” The chief priests answered, “We have no king but Caesar!”                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Maka berteriaklah mereka: "Enyahkan Dia! Enyahkan Dia! Salibkan Dia!" Kata Pilatus kepada mereka: "Haruskah aku menyalibkan rajamu?" Jawab imam-imam kepala: "Kami tidak mempunyai raja selain dari pada Kaisar!"                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فصرخوا: إرفعه إرفعه إصلبه فقال لهم بيلاطس: أأصلب ملككم؟ أجاب رؤساء الكهنة: ليس لنا ملك إلا قيصر.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Tote oun af] nwou nI/couc hina nceasf au[i oun n~I/couc:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then he delivered Him to them to be crucified. So they took Jesus and led Him away.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Akhirnya Pilatus menyerahkan Yesus kepada mereka untuk disalibkan. Mereka menerima Yesus.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فحينئذ أسلم إليهم يسوع ليصلبوه. فأخذوا يسوع ومضوا به               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  ouoh nyof effai m~pefc~tauroc afi~ e~bol e~pima e~toumou] e~rof je Pik~ranion:m~methebreoc de je PiGolgoya:               </language>               <language id="English">                  And He, bearing His cross, went out to a place called the Place of a Skull, which is called in Hebrew, Golgotha,               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sambil memikul salib-Nya Ia pergi ke luar ke tempat yang bernama Tempat Tengkorak, dalam bahasa Ibrani: Golgota.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فخرج وهو حامل صليبه إلى الموضع الذى يقال له الجمجمة.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Pima e~tauasf m~mof: ouoh aui~si n~keconi c~nau nemaf cam~n/ nem cam~nai m~mof: I/couc de qen y~m/].               </language>               <language id="English">                   Where they crucified Him, and two others with Him, one on either side, and Jesus in the center.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                    Dan di situ Ia disalibkan mereka dan bersama-sama dengan Dia disalibkan juga dua orang lain, sebelah-menyebelah, Yesus di tengah-tengah.                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وبالعبرانية يسمى الجلجثة حيث صلبوه. وصلبوا معه آخرين من هنا ومن هنا ويسوع فى الوسط.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Afc~qe ke titloc de n~je Pilatoc: ouoh af,af hijen pic~tauroc: naf c~q/out de pe je: I/couc Pinazwreoc Pouro Nte Niioudai:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Now Pilate wrote a title and put it on the cross. And the writing was: JESUS OF NAZARETH, THE KING OF THE JEWS.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan Pilatus menyuruh memasang juga tulisan di atas kayu salib itu, bunyinya: "Yesus, orang Nazaret, Raja orang Yahudi."                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكتب بيلاطس صحيفة ووضعوها على الصليب. وكان مكتوباً "يسوع الناصرى ملك اليهود".               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Oum/s de n~te niIoudai auws m~paititloc: je nafqent pe e~]baki n~je pima etaues I/couc m~mof: ouoh nafc~q/out pe m~methebreoc m~metrwmeoc m~metoueinin               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then many of the Jews read this title, for the place where Jesus was crucified was near the city; and it was written in Hebrew, Greek, and Latin.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Banyak orang Yahudi yang membaca tulisan itu, sebab tempat di mana Yesus disalibkan letaknya dekat kota dan kata-kata itu tertulis dalam bahasa Ibrani, bahasa Latin dan bahasa Yunani.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فقرأ هذه الصحيفة كثيرون من اليهود. لأن المكان الذى صلب فيه يسوع كان قريباً من المدينة وكان مكتوباً بالعبرانية والرومانية واليونانية.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Naujw oun m~moc pe m~Pilatoc: n~je niar,/e~reuc n~te niIoudai: je m~perc~qai je p~ouro n~te niIodai: alla je n~yof afjoc je a~nok pe p~ouro n~te niIoudai.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Therefore the chief priests of the Jews said to Pilate, “Do not write, 'The King of the Jews,' but, 'He said, “I am the King of the Jews.”                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Maka kata imam-imam kepala orang Yahudi kepada Pilatus: "Jangan engkau menulis: Raja orang Yahudi, tetapi bahwa Ia mengatakan: Aku adalah Raja orang Yahudi."                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فقال رؤساء كهنة اليهود لبيلاطس: لا تكتب إنه ملك اليهود، بل هو قال: إنى أنا ملك اليهود.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Afe~rouw~ n~je Pilatoc je v/e~taic~q/tf aic~q/tf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Pilate answered, “What I have written, I have written.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Jawab Pilatus: "Apa yang kutulis, tetap tertulis."                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أجاب بيلاطس: ما كتبته قد كتبته.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nimatoi oun e~taui~si n~I/couc: au[i n~nefh~bwc ouoh auaitou n~f~tou n~toi: outoi e~v~ouai n~n~imatoi nem ]kes~o/n: ]sy/n de ne ouatywrp te: n~cwqi e~bol e~p~swi t/rc:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then the soldiers, when they had crucified Jesus, took His garments and made four parts, to each soldier a part, and also the tunic. Now the tunic was without seam, woven from the top in one piece.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sesudah prajurit-prajurit itu menyalibkan Yesus, mereka mengambil pakaian-Nya lalu membaginya menjadi empat bagian untuk tiap-tiap prajurit satu bagian--dan jubah-Nya juga mereka ambil. Jubah itu tidak berjahit, dari atas ke bawah hanya satu tenunan saja.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأما الجند لما صلبوا يسوع، أخذوا ثيابه وجعلوها أربعة أجزاء، لكل جندى جزء. وأخذوا القميص أيضاً وكان القميص غير مخيط منسوجاً كله من فوق.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Pejwou de n~noue~r/ou je m~peny~renvaqc alla marenhiwp e~roc: je acnaer ya nim m~mon: hina n~te ]g~rav/ jwk e~bol ecjwmmoc:                </language>               <language id="English">                   They said therefore among themselves, “Let us not tear it, but cast lots for it, whose it shall be,” that the Scripture might be fulfilled which says:               </language><language id="Indonesian">                    Karena itu mereka berkata seorang kepada yang lain: "Janganlah kita membaginya menjadi beberapa potong, tetapi baiklah kita membuang undi untuk menentukan siapa yang mendapatnya." Demikianlah hendaknya supaya genaplah yang ada tertulis dalam Kitab Suci: </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فقال بعضهم لبعض لا نشقه، لكن نقترع عليه لمن منا يكون. ليتم المكتوب القائل:                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  je auvws n~nahbwc eh~rau: ouoh tahebcw auhiwp e~roc: nai oun e~tauaitou n~je nimatoi:               </language>               <language id="English">                  “They divided My garments among them, And for My clothing they cast lots.” Therefore the soldiers did these things.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Mereka membagi-bagi pakaian-Ku di antara mereka dan mereka membuang undi atas jubah-Ku." Hal itu telah dilakukan prajurit-prajurit itu.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إقتسموا ثيابى بينهم وعلى لباسى ألقوا قرعة. هذا ما فعله الجند.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nauohi de e~ratou pe qaten pic~tauroc n~I/couc: n~je tefmau nem t~cwni n~tefmau: Maria n~te Klew~pa nem Maria ]magdalin/:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Now there stood by the cross of Jesus His mother, and His mother’s sister, Mary the wife of Clopas, and Mary Magdalene.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan dekat salib Yesus berdiri ibu-Nya dan saudara ibu-Nya, Maria, isteri Klopas dan Maria Magdalena.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكانت واقفات عند صليب يسوع أمه وأخت أمه مريم التى لكلوبا ومريم المجدلية.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  I/couc de e~tafnau e~tefmau nem pimay/t/c e~nafmei mmof efohi e~ratf pejaf n~tefmau: je ]c~himi ic pes/ri:                </language>               <language id="English">                  When Jesus therefore saw His mother, and the disciple whom He loved standing by, He said to His mother, “Woman, behold your son!”                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ketika Yesus melihat ibu-Nya dan murid yang dikasihi-Nya di sampingnya, berkatalah Ia kepada ibu-Nya: "Ibu, inilah, anakmu!"                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلما رأى يسوع أمه والتلميذ الذى كان يحبه واقفاً، قال لأمه: يا امرأة هوذا إبنك،                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ita pejaf m~pimay/t/c je h/ppeic tekmau:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then He said to the disciple, “Behold your mother!”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kemudian kata-Nya kepada murid-murid-Nya: "Inilah ibumu!"                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وقال للتلميذ: هوذا أمك.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh icjen ]ounou e~temmau afolc n~je pimay/t/c e~qoun epef/i.               </language>               <language id="English">                  And from that hour that disciple took her to his own home.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan sejak saat itu murid itu menerima dia di dalam rumahnya.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ومن تلك الساعة أخذها ذلك التلميذ إلى بيته.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/BowDownBeforeTheHolyGospel"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>      <role id="Reader">         <insertdocument path="pascha/friday/interpretations/6thHour/gospels"/>      </role>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelConclusionDay"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Exposition</language><language id="Indonesian">Komentari </language>            <language id="Arabic">الطرح</language>         </Title>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The exposition of the Sixth Hour of Great Friday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Komentari Jam Keenam  Jumat Agung pada Pekan Paskah Suci, semoga berkatnya menyertai kita semua. Amin               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طرح الساعة السادسة من يوم الجمعة العظيمة من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  O you dwellers of Jerusalem, come and see. They crucified Jesus, the Son of David, on a cross. They dressed Him in a scarlet robe like the kings, and placed a crown of thorns on His head.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>O  penduduk  Yerusalem, datang dan lihatlah pemandangan ini. Mereka menyalibkan Yesus, Anak Daud di kayu salib. Mereka mengenakan Dia dengan jubah merah padam seperti raja,dan menempatkan mahkota duri di kepala-Nya. </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ياجميع السكان بأورشليم تعالوا إبصروا هذا المنظر. فإنهم علقوا يسوع إبن داود على خشبة الصليب وألبسوه ثوباً أحمر من لباس الملوك والرؤساء، وإكليل شوك على رأسه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  He adorned the heavens with the stars, created the earth and beautified it with flowers. They placed a reed in His right hand as a wise man and a teacher. They compelled a cross on Him as a conqueror.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  . Dia menghiasi langit dengan bintang-bintang dan bumi dengan bunga. Mereka menempatkan buluh di tangan kanan-Nya sebagai orang yang bijaksana dan seorang guru. Mereka meletakkan salib di punggung-Nya sebagai penakluk.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  مزين السموات بحسن النجوم، مؤسس الأرض بروح فيه ومزينها بحسن الأزهار، جعلوا فى يمينه قصبة حكيم معلم كاتب. وحملوا صليبه خلفه كملك غالب فى الحرب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  The women who came to Jerusalem for the Passover wept and wailed when they saw Jesus. He looked at them and said, “Daughters of Jerusalem, do not weep for Me.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Para wanita yang datang ke Yerusalem untuk merayakan Paskah menangis dan meratap ketika mereka melihat Dia. Dia berbalik dan berkata kepada anak-anak perempuan Yerusalem, “Jangan tangisi Aku. </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلما رأين النسوة الآتياتٍ إلى عيد الفصح إنتحبن وبكين على ما كان. فألتفت إليهن وكلمهن هكذا قائلاً: يا كل بنآتٍ أورشليم لا تبكين علىّ               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  Rather, weep for yourselves because of the tribulation that will befall you. There will be days when you envy the barren who never gave birth, nursed, or raised a child.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebaliknya, tangisilah dirimu sendiri karena kesusahan besar yang akan menimpamu.” Ini akan menjadi hari-hari ketika engkau cemburu pada orang mandul yang tidak pernah melahirkan, merawat, atau membesarkan anak.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  بل على ذواتكن. لأجل الشدائد العظيمة التى تدرككن والقلق الكثير بعد زمن قليل. وستأتى عليكن أيام تغبط فيها البطون العواقر التى لم تحبل ولم تلد ولم ترضع ولم ترب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  They will ask the mountains to fall on them, and the hills to cover them. For if they do this when the wood is green what will happen when it is dry.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div> Mereka akan meminta gunung-gunung untuk menimpa mereka, dan bukit-bukit untuk menutupi mereka. Karena jika mereka melakukan ini ketika pohon masih berwarna hijau apa yang akan terjadi jika kayu pohon itu mengering.” </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وسيقولون للجبال أن تقع عليهم والآكام أن تغطيهم. فإن كانوا يفعلون هذا بالعود الرطب فماذا يصنعون باليابس؟               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  When they came to the place called the skull, there they set the cross, and crucified Him.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ketika mereka tiba di tempat yang bernama Golgota, mereka mendirikan salib, dan menyalibkan Yesus. </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولما أتوا به إلى الأقرانيون الذى يدعى الجلجثة أقاموا خشبة الصليب وصلبوه عليها كالتدبير.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  They crucified with Him two criminals, one on His right and one on His left, so that the prophesy of the prophet may be fulfilled.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mereka menyalibkan Dia bersama-sama dengan  dua penjahat, satu di sebelah kanan-Nya dan satu di sebelah kiri-Nya, sehingga nubuatan nabi tergenapi yang berbunyi, "Dia terhitung diantara pemberontak".               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان هناك فاعلا شر صلبوهما معه، واحد عن اليمن والآخر عن اليسار، لكى يكمل قول النبى: إنه أحصى مع المنافقين وجهال الناس.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  The soldiers took His clothes and cast lots to divide His garments. They inscribed on the cross over His head, in Hebrew, Greek, and Roman, “This is the king of the Jews.”               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Para prajurit mengambil jubah-Nya dan membuang undi untuk membagi jubah-Nya. Mereka menuliskan di kayu salib di atas kepala-Nya, dalam bahasa Ibrani, Yunani, dan Romawi, Ini adalah raja orang Yahudi. </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ثم أخذ الجند ثيابه وإقترعوا عليها وإقتسموها على أربعة أجزاء. وهكذا كتبوا فوق رأسه كأمر رئيس الكهنة. كتبوا بالعبرانية وباليونانية وبالرومانية: أن هذا هو ملك اليهود.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  The people stood by, watching, and the rulers mocked Him saying, “He saved others, let Him save Himself if He is the Christ, the chosen one.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Orang-orang berdiri di sana, menonton, dan mengejeknya dengan mengatakan, "Dia yang menyelamatkan orang lain, biarkan Dia menyelamatkan diri-Nya sendiri, jika Dia Kristus                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان جميع الشعب قائماً والرؤساء والمقدمون وكانوا يهزأون به بغير حياء ويحركون رؤوسهم ويقولون: هكذا خلص آخرين فليخلص نفسه إن كان هو المسيح إبن المبارك.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  The soldiers also mocked him saying, “If you are the king of the Jews, save Yourself and come down off the cross.”               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>yang dipilih Allah." Para prajurit juga mengejeknya dengan mengatakan," Jika Kamu adalah raja orang Yahudi, selamatkanlah diri-Mu dan turunlah dari salib." </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وأيضاً الجند كانوا يهزأون به ويجدفون عليه بلا فتور قائلين: إن كنت أنت ملك اليهود إنزل عن الصليب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  One of the criminals railed at Him in front of everyone, saying, “If you are the Christ save Yourself and save us of this shame that we endure.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Pencuri di sebelah kiri-Nya berkata kepada-Nya di depan semua orang, "Jika Engkau adalah Kristus, selamatkanlah diriMu dan kami.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وواحد من فاعلى الشر اللذين صلبا معه كان يفترى عليه أمام الجميع قائلاً: إن كنت أنت المسيح فخلص نفسك وخلصنا من هذا العار الذى نحن فيه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  The other rebuked him saying, “Do you not fear God, since you are under the same sentence and condemnation? We deserve this punishment but He is innocent and without blame.”               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div> Pencuri yang lain menegurnya dengan mengatakan"Apakah engkau tidak takut akan Allah? Melihat dirimu ada dibawah penghukuman yang sama? Kita memang pantas  menerima hukuman ini karena perbuatan kita, tetapi Dia ini tidak melakukan kesalahan apa pun." </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأنتهره الآخر قائلاً: أما تخاف أنت من الله، نحن من أجل آثامنا طرحنا إلى هذا الحكم وهذه العقوبة التى نحن فيها، أما هذا فلم يفعل شيئاً يستحق عليه مثلنا فإنه بغير شر ولا ظلم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  Then he said to Jesus, “Remember me, O Lord in Your kingdom.” The Lord of Glory  replied saying, “Today you will be with Me in Paradise.”               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kemudian dia berkata kepada Yesus, "Tuhan, ingatlah akan aku ketika Engkau  kembali kedalam Kerajaan-Mu." Tuhan Yang Mulia dan Kekasih umat manusia menjawab "Hari ini juga Aku bersamamu di Firdaus.” </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وفتح فاه وابتدأ يقول: إذكرنى يارب متى جئت فى ملكوتك. فإستجاب له رب المجد وخاطبه كمحب للبشر قائلاً: أقول لك إنك اليوم تكون معى فى فردوس النعيم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  There were women standing by the cross of our Savior, His mother, His mother’s sister, Mary Clopas and Mary Magdalene.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Di sana ada para wanita yang berdiri di dekat salib Juruselamat kita, ibu-Nya, saudara perempuan ibu-Nya, Maria, istri Klopas dan Maria Magdalena.</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكن نسوة واقفات عند صليب مخلصنا، أمه وأخت أمه ومريم التى لكلوبا والمجدلية.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  When Jesus saw His mother and the disciple whom He loved standing near, He said to His mother, “Woman, behold your son!” Then He said to the disciple, “Behold your mother,” and from that hour the disciple took her to his own home as the Lord had said.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Ketika Yesus melihat ibu-Nya dan murid yang Dia cintai berdiri di dekat-Nya, Dia berkata kepada ibu-Nya, "Ibu, lihatlah anakmu! Kemudian Dia berkata kepada murid itu, "Lihatlah ibumu," dan sejak saat itu murid itu membawanya ke rumahnya sendiri seperti yang dikatakan Tuhan. </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلما رأى يسوع أمه والتلميذ الآخر الذى كان يحبه، أشار إليها قائلاً: يا امرأة هذا إبنك وقال للآخر هذه أمك. ومن تلك الساعة أخذها التلميذ إلى بيته كقول الرب.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  And from the sixth hour to ninth hour there was darkness on the whole earth.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan dari jam keenam sampai jam kesembilan ada kegelapan di seluruh bumi.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ومن الساعة السادسة إلى الساعة التاسعة كانت ظلمة على الأرض كلها.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  O Lord who adorned the earth with flowers, they dressed You with a scarlet robe, and the skies with the stars, they put a crown of thorns on Your head.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ya Tuhan yang menghiasi bumi dengan bunga-bunga, mereka mendandani-Mu dengan jubah merah. Ya Yang menghiasi langit dengan bintang-bintang, mereka menaruh mahkota duri di kepala-Mu. </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يا من زين الأرض بكثرة الأزهار ألبسوك ثوباً أحمر، والسماء بكثرة النجوم وضعوا عليك إكليلاً من شوك.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  You who have dominion over heaven and earth, they put a reed in Your hand. You who suspended the whole world with one word of Your mouth;               </language><language id="Indonesian">Engkau yang tangannya perkasa memegang langit dan bumi, mereka meletakkan buluh di tangan-Mu. Engkau yang menggantungkan bumi hanya dengan satu Firman yang keluar dari mulut-Mu,  </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يا من السماء والأرض فى قبضتك، وضعوا فى يدك قصبة، يا من علقت الأرض كلها بكلمة من فمك                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  You were crucified on the cross. You were crucified for our sins and abolished the power of death by Your cross, O Omnipotent.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  tetapi sekarang Engkau tergantung diatas kayu salib. Engkau disalibkan untuk dosa dosa kami,  dan menginjak-injak kuasa kematian melalui salib-Mu.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وصلبت على خشبة من أجل خطايانا وأبطلت عز الموت، يا سيدنا بصليبك ياذا القدرة المنيعة.               </language>            </text>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ExpositionConclusion"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/DaytimeLitaniesEmbed"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/EvnotiNaiNan"/>            <role id="People">         <comment>            <language id="English">               The deacons chant "Lord have mercy (<span class="Coptic">Kurie Ele/~con</span>)" three times in the great tune.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Para diakon melantunkan "Tuhan,kasihanilah kami."(<span class="Coptic">Kurie Ele/~con</span>)"tiga kali dengan nada agung.</language>         </comment>      </role>            <insertdocument path="include/AmenLordHaveMercy3"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Remember Me O My Lord</language><language id="Indonesian">Ingatlah aku, ya Tuhanku.</language>            <language id="Arabic">إذكرنى يارب</language>            <language id="Coptic">Aripameui w~Pa[oic</language>         </Title>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="include/RememberMe.1"/>            <insertdocument path="include/RememberMe.2"/>            <insertdocument path="include/RememberMe.3"/>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/Agios"/>            <insertdocument path="include/DoxaPatri"/>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/RememberMe"/>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  O King of kings, Christ our God, Lord of Lords, as You remembered the thief who believed in You on the cross, remember us in Your kingdom.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  O Raja segala raja, Kristus Tuhan kami, Tuhan segala tuan, seperti Engkau mengingat pencuri yang percaya kepada-Mu di kayu salib, ingatlah kami di kerajaan-Mu.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يا ملك الملوك المسيح إلهنا ورب الأرباب كما ذكرت اللص الذى آمن بك على الصليب، إذكرنا فى ملكوتك.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/RememberMe"/>                  </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  Who has ever seen a thief who believed in a king as this thief who through his faith stole the kingdom of heaven and the paradise of joy.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Siapa yang pernah melihat seorang pencuri yang percaya kepada seorang raja seperti pencuri ini, yang melalui imannya mencuri kerajaan surga dan taman kebahagiaan</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  من رأى لصاً آمن بملك مثل هذا اللص الذى بأمانته سرق ملكوت السماوآتٍ وفردوس النعيم.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/RememberMe"/>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  Because of your deeds, O thief, you were hung on the cross as criminals. Through your faith, you deserved the grace, joy, kingdom of heaven and the paradise of joy.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Karena perbuatanmu, wahai pencuri, kamu digantung di salib seperti para penjahat. Melalui imanmu, kamu layak menerima rahmat, sukacita, kerajaan surga, dan taman kebahagiaan.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  من أجل أعمالك أيها اللص علقت على الصليب كالمذنبين وبإيمانك إستحقيت النعمة والفرح وملكوت السموآتٍ وفردوس النعيم.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/RememberMe"/>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  Blessed are you O blessed thief and your good tongue by which you truly deserved the kingdom of heaven and the paradise of joy.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Berbahagialah kamu, wahai pencuri yang diberkati, dan lidahmu yang baik, dengan mana kamu sungguh-sungguh layak menerima kerajaan surga dan taman kebahagiaan.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طوباك أنت أيها اللص الطوباوى ولسانك الحسن المنطق الذى به تأهلت بالحقيقة لملكوت السموآتٍ وفردوس النعيم.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/RememberMe"/>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  O blessed thief, what did you see and what did you observe, that you confessed the Crucified Christ in the flesh, the King of heaven and God of all.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Wahai pencuri yang diberkati, apa yang kamu lihat dan apa yang kamu perhatikan, sehingga kamu mengakui Kristus yang disalibkan dalam rupa tubuh, Raja surga dan Tuhan segala sesuatu</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أيها اللص الطوباوى ماذا رأيت وماذا أبصرت حتى إعترفت بالمسيح المصلوب بالجسد ملك السماء وإله الكل.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/RememberMe"/>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  You did not see Christ God glorified on Mount Tabor in the glory of His Father, but you saw Him hung in Ekranion, wherefore you cried out saying:               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kamu tidak melihat Kristus Tuhan dimuliakan di Gunung Tabor dalam kemuliaan Bapa-Nya, tetapi kamu melihat-Nya digantung di kayu salib, oleh karena itu kamu berseru seraya berkata:               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ما رأيت المسيح الإله متجلياً على طور طابور فى مجد أبيه بل رأيته معلقا على الإقرانيون فلوقتك صرخت قائلاً:               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/RememberMe"/>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  You believed when you saw the heaven and earth disturbed and the sun and moon darkened, the dead rose, the rocks split, and the curtain of the altar torn. Immediately you cried out saying:               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kamu percaya ketika kamu melihat langit dan bumi terguncang, matahari dan bulan gelap, orang-orang mati bangkit, batu-batu terbelah, dan tirai altar terobek. Segera kamu berseru seraya berkata:               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  آمنت لما رأيت السماء والأرض إضطربتا والشمس والقمر إظلمتا والأموآتٍ قامت والصخور تشققت وستر الهيكل إنشق. فلوقتك صرخت قائلاً:               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/RememberMe"/>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  "Assuredly, I say to you," said the Lord, "today you will be with Me in Paradise and inherit My kingdom." The disciple denied and the thief cried out saying:               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Sesungguhnya, Aku berkata kepadamu," kata Tuhan, "hari ini kamu akan bersama-Ku di Firdaus dan mewarisi kerajaan-Ku." Sang murid menyangkal dan pencuri berseru seraya berkata:               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  الحق الحق أقول لك، قال الرب، أيها اللص إنك اليوم تكون معى فى فردوسى وترث ملكوتى. التلميذ أنكر واللص صرخ قائلاً:               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/RememberMe"/>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Wouniatk n~yok w~ D/mac piconi: paraouon niben ethijen pikahi: je aksasni n~yok: e~oueu Kerie m~peouai sasni e~rof e~neh. Akerpekc/ou t/rf: ekoi n~coni hipiiah s~s/n n~te Ieroucal/m: oucaji n~ouwt akjof m~P[oic: afouorpk e~piparadicoc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Blessed are you, O Demas the thief, more than anyone on earth, for you have gained a way no one gained. All your life, you were a thief in the forests of Jerusalem and by one word you said to the Lord He sent you to paradise.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Berbahagialah kamu, wahai Demas sang pencuri, lebih dari siapa pun di bumi, karena kamu telah mendapatkan jalan yang tidak didapatkan oleh siapa pun. Sepanjang hidupmu, kamu adalah seorang pencuri di hutan-hutan Yerusalem, dan dengan satu kata yang kamu ucapkan kepada Tuhan, Dia mengutusmu ke dalam surga.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طوباك أنت يا ديماس اللص أكثر من كل من على الأرض لأنك نلت وسيلة لم ينلها أحد قط. كل زمانك أقمت لصاً فى غابآتٍ أورشليم وكلمة واحدة قلت للرب فأرسلك إلى الفردوس.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/RememberMe"/>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Acswpi e~taui~si m~Pencwt/r: e~jen pise n~te pic~tauroc: aui~si nemaf n~coni c~nau: caoui~nam nem caja[i m~mof. Afws e~bol n~je D/mac piconi: etcaoui~nam afjw m~moc: je a~ripameui~ w~ Pa[oic: aksani~ qen tekmetouro. Pejaf naf n~je Pencwt/r: je m~voou eke~swpi nem/i: n~h~r/i qen piparadicoc: n~tekounof m~mok n~q/tf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  When they crucified our Savior on the cross, they crucified two thieves with Him, one on His right and one on His left. And Demas, the thief on the right, cried out saying, "Remember me O Lord when You come into Your kingdom."               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ketika mereka menyalibkan Juruselamat kita di kayu salib, mereka menyalibkan dua pencuri bersama-Nya, satu di kanan-Nya dan satu di kiri-Nya. Dan Demas, pencuri di sebelah kanan, berseru seraya berkata, "Ingatlah aku, ya Tuhan, ketika Engkau masuk ke dalam kerajaan-Mu."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  كان لما صلب مخلصنا على خشبة الصليب، صلبوا معه لصين عن يمينه وعن يساره. فصرخ ديماس اللص اليمين قائلاً: إذكرنى يارب متى جئت فى ملكوتك.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/RememberMe"/>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  Our Savior said to Him: Today you will be with Me in Paradise.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Juruselamat kita berkata kepadanya: "Hari ini kamu akan bersama-Ku di Firdaus."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  قال له مخلصنا: إنك اليوم تكون معى فى فردوسى وتنعم فيه.               </language>            </text>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Erev/e~taf a~l/i~ e~jen pise n~te pic~tauroc: af] m~pefc~nof n~nou] qaron: afkwrf m~v~mou hiten pefmou: m~p~,w e~bol n~te nennobi. Efe~a~reh e~piwnq m~penpatriar,/c: papa abba ____ nem pefkes~v/r n~litourgoc peniwt abba ____ pie~pickopoc nem na[oic n~io]: etyou/t qen tai ekkl/cia: icjen poukouji sapounis]: a~joc t/rou:               </language>               <language id="English">                  We ask Him who was crucified on the wood of the cross, and shed His divine blood for us, and trampled death by His death to forgive us our sins and preserve the life of our patriarch, Pope Abba ____ and his partner in the [apostolic] liturgy, our father the bishop Abba ____ and my fathers who are gathered here in this church, from the youngest to the oldest. Say, all of you:               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kami memohon kepada-Nya yang disalibkan di kayu salib, yang menumpahkan darah-Nya yang ilahi untuk kami, dan menginjakkan kematian dengan kematian-Nya, untuk mengampuni dosa-dosa kami dan memelihara kehidupan patriark kami, Paus Abba ____ dan rekan-Nya dalam liturgi [apostolik], bapak kami uskup Abba ____ serta para bapak kami yang berkumpul di gereja ini, dari yang termuda hingga yang tertua. Katakanlah, semuanya:               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ونحن نطلب إلى الذى رفع على خشبة الصليب وبذل دمه الإلهى عنا وأبطل الموت بموته أن يغفر خطايانا ويحفظ حياة بطريركِنا أنبا ___ وشريكِهِ في الخدمةِ [الرسوليةِ] أبينا أنبا___ الأسقف و سادتى الأباء المجتمعين فى هذه الكنيسة من صغيرهم إلى كبيرهم قولوا كلكم.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="People">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Am/n: a~m/n: a~m/n.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Amen. Amen. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Amin. Amin. Amin.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  آمين. آمين. آمين.               </language>            </text>         </role>      </section>   </forceseason></document>