<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" pascha="true" fixeddatedocument="true">   <forceseason id="Fasts ^ PaschaWeek ^ WatosDays ^ Weekdays ^ GreatFriday ^ Fridays ^ FuneralTune ^ SeasonOfAirAndFruits">      <Title>         <language id="English">Great Friday (The Twelfth Hour)</language><language id="Indonesian">Jumat Agung (Jam Kedua belas  )</language>         <language id="Arabic">الجمعة  العظيمة (الساعة الثانية عشر)</language>         <language id="Coptic">Pie~hoou n~]nis] m~parackeu/ (}ajp 02)</language>      </Title>            <comment>         <language id="English">            The veil of the Sanctuary is opened, the candles are lit, and the black curtains are removed and replaced by red curtains befitting of Joyous Saturday.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Tirai Sanctuary terbuka, lilin-lilin dinyalakan, dan tirai hitam diangkat dan diganti dengan tirai merah yang layak untuk Sabtu Penuh Kegembiraan.         </language>      </comment>            <role id="Priest">         <insertdocument path="include/KhenEfranAmen"/>                  <text>            <language id="English">               The prophecies of the Twelfth Hour of Great Friday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Nubuat-nubuat dari Jam Kedua belas  Jumat Agung pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               نبوات الساعة الثانية عشر من يوم الجمعة العظيمة من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.            </language>         </text>               <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Lamentations 3:1-66</language><language id="Indonesian">Ratapan 3:1-66</language>               <language id="Arabic">أرميا 3: 1-66</language>            </Title>                        <comment>               <language id="English">                  The Lamentation of Jeremiah is chanted in its Paschal “lamenting” tune.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ratapan Yeremia dinyanyikan dalam nada Paskah “ratapan”nya.               </language>            </comment>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/prophecyIntro/Lamentations"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Anok v~rwmi a~nok eynau e~]meth/ki: afi~ e~h~r/i e~jwi qen pis~bwt n~te pefjwnt. Afa~moni m~moi ouoh afolt e~qoun e~ou,aki e~ouwini an: p~l/n aftacyo n~tefjij n~q~r/i n~q/t m~pie~hoou t/rf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  "I am the man who sees poverty by the rod of His anger upon me. He took me and led me away into darkness, and not into light. Surely He has turned His hand against me throughout the day.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Akulah orang yang melihat sengsara disebabkan cambuk murka-Nya. Ia menghalau dan membawa aku ke dalam kegelapan yang tidak ada terangnya.Sesungguhnya, aku dipukul-Nya berulang-ulang dengan tangan-Nya sepanjang hari.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أنا هو الرجل الذى رأى الـمـذلة. أتى علـىّ بقضيـب غضبه وقادنى وسـيـرنى فـى الظلمة لا فى النـور. والآن رد يـده عـلىّ النهار كله.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Afyreclwm n~je tacarx nem pasar: afqomqem n~nakac. Afkw] e~roi ouoh afw~rf n~taa~ve e~qoun: Aft~hemkoi qen hanma n~,aki: aft~hemcoi e~q~r/i m~v~r/] n~hanrefmwou ne~neh.                </language>               <language id="English">                  "He has aged my flesh and my skin and has broken my bones. He has besieged me and surrounded my head; He has worn me down with hardships. He set me in dark places as those long dead.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ia menyusutkan dagingku dan kulitku, tulang-tulangku dipatahkan-Nya.  Ia mendirikan tembok sekelilingku, mengelilingi aku dengan kesedihan dan kesusahan.Ia menempatkan aku di dalam gelap seperti orang yang sudah lama mati.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أبلى لحمى وجلدى وسحق عظامى. أحاط بى ونكس رأسى، وأذلنى وأجلسنى فى مواضع مظلمة، مثل الموتى من قديم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Afkw] e~roi: ouoh n~]naer e~bol an: aftaso n~nac~nauhnem pahat. ]namou] je e~p~swi oub/f ouoh mpefcwtem e~roi n~taws e~bol harof: m~pef ]ma] je e~y~re tap~roceu,/ [wlk. Afkw] e~h~ren namwit: ouoh afs~yma n~namwit m~mosi.               </language>               <language id="English">                  "He hedged me in, and I cannot come forth; He made my brazen chain heavy. Though I will call and cry out, He shuts out my prayer. He has blocked my ways and obstructed my paths; He has troubled me.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ia menutup segala jalan ke luar bagiku, Ia mengikat aku dengan rantai yang berat.Walaupun aku memanggil-manggil dan berteriak minta tolong, tak didengarkan-Nya doaku.  Ia merintangi jalan-jalanku dengan batu pahat, dan menjadikannya tidak terlalui.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  سيج علىّ حتى لا أخرج، وثقل أغلالى. دعوته فلم يستجيب لي. صرخت إليه فلم يسر بصلأتى. سيج طرقي وألوى سبلى المسلوكة.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Acs~yorter n~je oucarx ecjor. Nyof pe tafermoui~ e~roi qen pima eth/p. Af[oji n~ca v/etohi e~ratf: ouoh afraqt af,at eitak/out. Af[wlk n~tefvi] ouoh aftahoi e~rat m~v~r/] n~ouc~kopoc: eyrefhioui~ m~pefcob] e~qoun e~roi.                </language>               <language id="English">                  "He is a bear lying in wait for me like a lion in a hidden place. After I departed, He eagerly pursued and caught me; He has utterly ruined me. He bent his bow and set me up as a target for the arrow.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Laksana beruang Ia menghadang aku, laksana singa dalam tempat persembunyian. Ia membelokkan jalan-jalanku, merobek-robek aku dan membuat aku tertegun.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                    صار لي كدب كامن وأسد فى موضع مختفى. طاردنى وصرعنى وتركنى هالكاً. أوتر قوسه وأقامنى هدفاً ليلقى فىّ سهامه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Afy~rouse e~qoun e~na[~lwt n~je nicoynef n~te pefc~keuoc n~hicoynef. Aiswpi n~cwbi m~palaoc t/rf: nai oi m~'almoc nwou m~pie~hoou t/rf. Aft~coi n~sasi: ouoh afy~riyaqi qen ouensasi.                </language>               <language id="English">                  "He caused the arrows of His quiver to pierce my loins. I became a laughingstock to all my people, and their song all the day. He has filled me with bitterness and drenched me with gall.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Ia membidikkan panah-Nya, menjadikan aku sasaran anak panah. Ia menyusupkan ke dalam hatiku segala anak panah dari tabung-Nya. Aku menjadi tertawaan bagi segenap bangsaku, menjadi lagu ejekan mereka sepanjang hari. Ia mengenyangkan aku dengan kepahitan, memberi aku minum ipuh.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أدخل فى كليتى نبال جعبته. صرت ضحكة لكل شعبى وأغنية لهم النهار كله. جرعنى الحنظل. وأسكرنى أفسنتينا.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh afyrebio n~nanajhi qenoual n~w~ni: aftemmoi n~oukermi: Ouoh afhioui~ m~ta'u,/ e~bolqen t~hir/n/: aierp~wbs n~naa~gayon: Ouoh actako n~je tahupoc tacic: nem tahelpic e~bol hiten P[oic.                </language>               <language id="English">                  "He also broke my teeth with gravel and fed me with ashes. He took away peace from my soul, and I have forgotten the good things. Therefore I said, ‘My victory and my hope have perished from the Lord.’               </language><language id="Indonesian"> Ia meremukkan gigi-gigiku dengan memberi aku makan kerikil; Ia menekan aku ke dalam debu.  Engkau menceraikan nyawaku dari kesejahteraan, aku lupa akan kebahagiaan. Sangkaku: hilang lenyaplah kemasyhuranku dan harapanku kepada TUHAN.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  هتم بالحصى أسنانى وأطعمنى الرماد. فبعدت نفسى عن السلام. ونسيت الخيرآتٍ. وباد اقنومى ورجائى من الرب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Aierv~meui~ e~bol qen tameth/ki nem padiwgmoc: ousasi nem ouensasi cena erpameui~: ouoh e~re ta'u,/ ermeletan nem/i p~neuma eie~jem ka] qen pah/t.               </language>               <language id="English">                  "I remembered by reason of my poverty, and because of my persecution, I remembered my bitterness and gall. My soul shall remember and meditate within me. I will fix this in my heart; therefore, I will endure.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   "Ingatlah akan sengsaraku dan pengembaraanku, akan ipuh dan racun itu."  Jiwaku selalu teringat akan hal itu dan tertekan dalam diriku.Tetapi hal-hal inilah yang kuperhatikan,               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أذكر بؤسى وشقائى والافسنتين والمرارة التى لم تبرح من ذاكرتى. هذا ما تردده نفسى فى، وأشعر به فى قلبى.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eybe vai eie~a~moni n~tot: e~nimeyna/t n~te P[oic: je m~pef,at n~cwf: oude m~paumounk n~je nefmetsenh/t qen nia~bot nem nie~hoou t/rou. Nainan P[oic qen penmounk: je m~paumounk n~je nekmetsenh/t. &lt;anberi eue~swpi e~]ar,/. peknah] naaf pe. Acjoc n~je ta'u,/ je tatoi pe P[oic: eybe vai eie~a~moni n~tot naf.                </language>               <language id="English">                  It is through the mercies of the Lord that He has not failed me, because His compassions are not exhausted. Pity us, O Lord, early every month: for we are not brought to an end, because His compassions are not exhausted. They are new every morning: great is Your faithfulness. The Lord is my portion, says my soul; therefore will I wait for Him.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  oleh sebab itu aku akan berharap:  Tak berkesudahan kasih setia TUHAN, tak habis-habisnya rahmat-Nya, selalu baru tiap pagi; besar kesetiaan-Mu!  "TUHAN adalah bagianku," kata jiwaku, oleh sebab itu aku berharap kepada-Nya. </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  من أجل ذلك أرجو مراحم الرب لأنه لم يتركنى عنه. لأن رأفته لا تزول على ممر الشهور والأيام كلها. إرحمنا يارب فى فنائنا لأن رأفتك لا تفرغ. هى جديدة فى كل صباح. وعظيم هو إيمانك. قالت نفسى نصيبى هو الرب، فلذلك أرجوه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Oua~gayoc pe P[oic n~n/e~terhupomonin e~rof: nanef gar n~]'u,/ etkw] n~cwf: Ouoh ecohi e~pioujai n~te P[oic: n~tecswpi qen ou/cu,ia~: Nanec m~pirwmi e~swp afsanfai m~pinahbef e~jwf icjen tefmeta~lou.               </language>               <language id="English">                  "The Lord is good to those who wait for Him, To the soul who will seek Him, the Good One. He will wait for and quietly expect the salvation of the Lord. It is good for a man when he takes up a yoke in his youth.               </language><language id="Indonesian">TUHAN adalah baik bagi orang yang berharap kepada-Nya, bagi jiwa yang mencari Dia.  Adalah baik menanti dengan diam pertolongan TUHAN. Adalah baik bagi seorang pria memikul kuk pada masa mudanya.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  صالح هو الرب للذين يترجونه. طيب للنفس التى تطلبه. وتتوقع بسكوت خلاص الرب. جيد للرجل أن يحمل النير من منذ صبائه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Fnahemci e~q~r/i m~mauatf: n~tef,arwf je aftalof e~jwf. f~na,arwf qen p~kahi a~r/ou n~tefjem ouhelpicp~neuma Fnariki n~tefouoji m~v/eynaraqtf e~roc: efe~ci n~s~vit.               </language>               <language id="English">                  "He will sit alone and be silent, because he bears it on himself. He will give his cheek to the one who strikes him, and he will be filled with insults.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Biarlah ia duduk sendirian dan berdiam diri kalau TUHAN membebankannya.  Biarlah ia merebahkan diri dengan mukanya dalam debu, mungkin ada harapan. Biarlah ia memberikan pipi kepada yang menamparnya, biarlah ia kenyang dengan cercaan.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يجلس وحده ويصمت لأنه قد وضعه عليه. يجعل فى التراب فمه لعله يجد رجاء. يميل خده لمن يلطمه ويشبع تعييراً.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je n~nef,af n~cwf n~jeP[oic sae~neh. Je e~ne afyebiof efe~senh/t kata p~a~sai n~te pefnai: Je m~peferkouji n~h/t: ouoh afyebiof e~nis/ri n~te nirwmi.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Yet the Lord shall not reject him forever. "For He who humbles will have compassion according to the abundance of His mercy. For He does not afflict willingly, though He humbles the children of men.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Karena tidak untuk selama-lamanya Tuhan mengucilkan.  Karena walau Ia mendatangkan susah, Ia juga menyayangi menurut kebesaran kasih setia-Nya. Karena tidak dengan rela hati Ia menindas dan merisaukan anak-anak manusia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إلا أن الرب لا يقصيه عنه إلى الأبد. فإنه ولو واضعه يترأف عليه ككثرة رحمته. لأنه لم يرذل من قلبه بل تواضع لبنى البشر.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ep~jin yebio qa nef[a~lauj n~n/t/rou eym/r e~pikahi: Eriki e~bol m~p~hap n~ourwmi: mpem~yo e~bol m~p~ho m~pet[oci. Ehi ourwmi e~p~hap: qen p~jin eyref]hap e~rof: m~pefjoc n~je P[oic.               </language>               <language id="English">                  "To humble all the prisoners of the earth under His feet, "To turn aside the judgment of a man before the face of the Most High, and to condemn a man before he is judged, the Lord does not command.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Kalau dipijak-pijak dengan kaki tawanan-tawanan di dunia, kalau hak orang dibelokkan di hadapan Yang Mahatinggi, atau orang diperlakukan tidak adil dalam perkaranya, masakan Tuhan tidak melihatnya?               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ليذل تحت قدميه جميع المرتبطين بالأرض. أو حرف حكم الرجل أمام وجه العلى. وإذا نكس الإنسان فى خصومته عندما يحكم عليه أفما يقول الرب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nim afjoc m~pair/] ouoh afswpi: m~pefouahcahni n~je P[oic hinai. Ebolqen rwf m~pet[oci: m~paui~ e~bol n~je nipeynaneu nem nipethwou.Pwc f~na,~remrem n~je pirwmi eybe pihap n~te pefnobi efwnq n~je pirwmi.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Who thus speaks, and it comes to pass? The Lord has not commanded it, "For evil and good shall not proceed from the mouth of the Most High. Why should a living man complain, a man concerning his sin?               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Siapa berfirman, maka semuanya jadi? Bukankah Tuhan yang memerintahkannya? Bukankah dari mulut Yang Mahatinggi keluar apa yang buruk dan apa yang baik?  Mengapa orang hidup mengeluh? Biarlah setiap orang mengeluh tentang dosanya!                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  من ذا الذى قال فكان. والرب لم يأمر. أليس من فم العلى تخرج الخيرآتٍ والشرور. كيف يتذمر الإنسان الحي الرجل المعاقب لأجل خطيته.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Maren qotqet n~nenmwit: ouoh n~te moust n~nentatci: n~tentacyon haP[oic. Marenfai n~nenh/t nem nenjij: nahren v/et[oci etqen t~ve. Anernobi anera~ceb/c an]jwntp~neuma n~yok de m~pek,wnan e~bol.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Our way has been searched out and examined; therefore we shall turn to the Lord. "Let us lift our hearts and our hands to the Most High in heaven. We have sinned and acted in an ungodly way; thus You have not shown us mercy.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Marilah kita menyelidiki dan memeriksa hidup kita, dan berpaling kepada TUHAN. Marilah kita mengangkat hati dan tangan kita kepada Allah di sorga:  Kami telah mendurhaka dan memberontak, Engkau tidak mengampuni.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلنفحص طرقنا ونختبر خطوآتٍنا ونرجع إلى الرب. ولنرفع قلوبنا مع الأيدي لدى العلى الذى فى السماء. قد أخطأنا ونافقنا وأغضبنا وأنت لم تغفر لنا.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Akvwrs e~bol ak[ia~ouw qen oujwnt ouoh ak[oji n~cwn akqoyben m~pek]a~co. Akvwrs n~ou[/pinak e~bol e~s~tem voh e~q~r/i harok n~je tap~roceu,/: eyriyebio e~stem nau nem e~hitt e~bol.                </language>               <language id="English">                  But You visited us in anger and drove us away. You have put us to death and not spared us. "You veiled Yourself with a cloud because of our prayer. To close my eyes and to reject me.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Engkau menyelubungi diri-Mu dengan murka, mengejar kami dan membunuh kami tanpa belas kasihan. Engkau menyelubungi diri-Mu dengan awan, sehingga doa tak dapat menembus.  </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  قد التحفت بالغضب وطردتنا وقتلتنا ولم تشفق. التحفت بغمام لئلا تبلغ إليك صلأتى. لأ تضع لكي لا أرى فأطرح.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ak,an n~y~m/] n~nilaoc. Auouwn n~rwou e~h~r/i e~jwn n~je nenjaji t/rou. ~A ouho] nem oujwnt swpi nan: aufai m~mon ouoh auraqten. Nabal aui~ni han moumi~ e~bol n~te hanmwou: e~jen p~qomqem n~t~seri m~palaoc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  You have placed us in the midst of the peoples. All our enemies have opened their mouth against us. "Fear and anger have come upon us, Yes, devastation and destruction. My eyes will shed tears for forgiveness because of the destruction of the daughter of my people.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kami Kaujadikan kotor dan keji di antara bangsa-bangsa. Terhadap kami semua seteru kami mengangakan mulutnya. Kejut dan jerat menimpa kami, kemusnahan dan kehancuran. </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  تركتنا فى وسط الشعوب. ففتح جميع أعدائنا أفواههم علينا فرفعونا ثم طرحونا. فحل بنا خوف وسخط. عيناي تسيل بأنهار مياه على سحق بنت شعبى.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Pabal aferm~kah n~]na,arwi an: e~s~tem fai n~jwi e~p~swi: watefjoust n~je P[oic n~tefnau e~bolqen t~ve. Pabal na] m~kah e~jen ta'u,/ para nis/ri t/rou n~te]baki.                </language>               <language id="English">                  My eyes are drowned with tears, and I will not keep silent; so there shall be no rest, until the Lord bends down and sees from heaven. My eyes will bring suffering in my soul because of all the daughters of the city.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Air mataku mengalir bagaikan batang air, karena keruntuhan puteri bangsaku. Air mataku terus-menerus bercucuran, dengan tak henti-hentinya,  sampai TUHAN memandang dari atas dan melihat dari sorga. Mataku terasa pedih oleh sebab keadaan puteri-puteri kotaku.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  عينىّ تسكب و لا تكف بلا انقطاع . ولا أرفع رأسى حتى يتتطلع الرب وينظر من السماء. عينى تحزن على نفسى أكثر من جميع بنى المدينة.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Qen oujwrj aujwrj e~roi: m~v~r/] n~ou[aj n~je najaji n~jinjp~neuma Auqwteb m~pawnq qen oulakkoc: ouoh auw~li n~ous~ne e~jwi: A hanmwou jws e~jen taa~ve: aijoc je af,at n~cwf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  My enemies hunted me down without cause, like a sparrow. "They put my life to death in the pit and threw a stone at me. Water flowed over my head; I said, 'I am rejected.'               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Seperti burung aku diburu-buru oleh mereka yang menjadi seteruku tanpa sebab.  Mereka melemparkan aku hidup-hidup dalam lobang, melontari aku dengan batu. Air membanjir di atas kepalaku, kusangka: "Binasa aku!"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  قد اصطادنى أعدائى اصطياداً كعصفور بلا سبب. وقرضوا فى الجب حيأتى. وطرحوا علىّ شبكة. فاضت المياه فوق رأسى. وقلت إنه تركنى عنه.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Aiws e~p~swi oube pekran P[oic e~bolqen oulakkoc efcapec/t: Akcwtem e~tac~m/: m~per,w m~pekmasj e~bol hapatwbh: Akqwnt e~qoun e~tabo/yia~ qen pie~hoou e~taiws oub/k akjoc n/i je m~pererho].               </language>               <language id="English">                  I called on Your name, O Lord, from the lowest pit. "You heard my voice; do not hide Your ears from my supplication. You drew near at my call on the day I called upon You. You said to me, 'Do not fear.'               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Ya TUHAN, aku memanggil nama-Mu dari dasar lobang yang dalam. Engkau mendengar suaraku! Janganlah Kaututupi telinga-Mu terhadap kesahku dan teriak tolongku!  Engkau dekat tatkala aku memanggil-Mu, Engkau berfirman: Jangan takut!"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  صرخت إليك ياربى من جب سفلى، فسمعت صوتى. لا تمل أذنك عن طلبتى. فى اليوم الذى صرخت إليك إقتربت من معونتى وقلت لي لا تخف.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ak]hap P[oic e~nihapp~neuma n~te ta'u,/ a,cw] m~pawnj a,nau P[oic e~nas~yorter a,] hap e~pahap: Aknau e~pou[im~p~sis t/rf qen noumokmek t/rou etsope~qoun e~roi.                </language>               <language id="English">                  O Lord, You pleaded the case for my soul; You redeemed my life. "O Lord, You saw my troubles; You judged my cause. You saw all their vengeance in all their reasoning against me.               </language><language id="Indonesian">"Ya Tuhan, Engkau telah memperjuangkan perkaraku, Engkau telah menyelamatkan hidupku.  Engkau telah melihat ketidakadilan terhadap aku, ya TUHAN; berikanlah keadilan! Engkau telah melihat segala dendam mereka, segala rancangan mereka terhadap aku."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  حكمت يارب لاحكام نفسى وخلصت حيأتى. نظرت يارب إلى اضطرابى وحكمت فى دعواى. رأيت إنتقامهم كله. وجميع أفكارهم علىّ.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Akcwtem e~pous~vit P[oic: noumokmek t/rou ~etauaitou e~roi m~pie~hoou t/rf Ouoh p~kim n~nic~votou n~te n/ettwounou e~h~r/i e~jwi: ouoh noumelet/ nausop e~qoun e~roi m~pie~hoou t/rf. qen poujinhemci nem poujin twoun:                </language>               <language id="English">                  You heard their taunts and all their plots against me, "And the lips of those who rose up against me, and their meditations against me all the day. Look at their eyes as they sit down and rise up.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Engkau telah mendengar cercaan mereka, ya TUHAN, segala rancangan mereka terhadap aku,  percakapan orang-orang yang melawan aku, dan rencana mereka terhadap aku sepanjang hari.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  سمعت تعييرهم يارب وكل مشوراتهم و موآمراتهم علىّ اليوم كله، وتحريك شفاة القائمين علىّ. وصرت تلاوتهم النهار كله فى جلوسهم وقيامهم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Joust e~q~r/i e~jen noubal. Eke~]s ebiw~ nwou n~ouqici qat~jom m~pouh/t. Nyok eke~[oji n~cwou n~q~r/i qen m~bon ouoh n~te kmounkou e~bol capec/t n~t~ve P[oic.                </language>               <language id="English">                  You shall render a recompense to them, O Lord, according to the works of their hands. "You shall repay them as a covering Your hardship for them. You shall pursue them in Your wrath and utterly destroy them from under heaven, O Lord.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Amatilah duduk bangun mereka! Aku menjadi lagu ejekan mereka." "Engkau akan mengadakan pembalasan terhadap mereka, ya TUHAN, menurut perbuatan tangan mereka.  Engkau akan mengeraskan hati mereka; kiranya kutuk-Mu menimpa mereka! Engkau akan mengejar mereka dengan murka dan memunahkan mereka dari bawah langit, ya TUHAN!"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أنظر يارب إلى عيونهم واعطهم مجازاة بحسب أعمال أيديهم. وكافئهم بالتعب على قساوة قلوبهم. واطردهم بغضبك. وافنهم يارب من تحت السماء.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ProphecyConclusion"/>         </section>      </role>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Introduction to the Paschal Praise</language><language id="Indonesian">Pendahuluan Doksologi Paskah</language>            <language id="Arabic">مقدمة تسبحة البصخة</language>         </Title>               <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PropheciesConclusion"/>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The doxology of the Twelfth Hour of Great Friday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Doksologi dari Jam Kedua belas  Jumat Agung pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  تسبحة البصخة الساعة الثانية من يوم الجمعة العظيمة من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="include/LordsPrayerNoTitle"/>         </role>      </section>            <comment>         <language id="English">            The Paschal Doxology is chanted alternating one time from inside the sanctuary, and one time from outside the sanctuary, to resemble the heavenly and the earthly who were waiting the resurrection of the Lord.  The deacons should wear the red “patrashel.”         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Doksologi Paskah dinyanyikan secara bergantian, sekali dari dalam sanctuari, dan sekali lagi dari luar sanctuari, untuk menggambarkan langit dan bumi yang menantikan kebangkitan Tuhan. Diakon harus mengenakan "patrashel" merah.         </language>      </comment>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/Doxology.3"/>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Psalm 87:6, 22:4, 44:6,8</language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur  88:6, 23:4, 45:6,8</language>               <language id="Arabic">مزمور 87: 6, 22: 4, 44: 6, 8</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PsalmOfDavid"/>                        <comment>               <language id="English">                  The Psalm “Your Throne (<span class="Coptic">Peky~ronoc</span>)” is chanted in the “Shammy” tune while facing east:               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mazmur "Takhta-Mu(<span class="Coptic">Peky~ronoc</span>)” idinyanyikan dalam nada "Shammy" sambil menghadap ke timur.               </language>            </comment>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Au,at qen oulakkoc efcapec/t: qen hanma n~,aki nem t~q/ibi m~v~mou.                </language>               <language id="English">                  They laid me in the lowest pit, in dark places and in the shadow of death.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Telah Kautaruh aku dalam liang kubur yang paling bawah, dalam kegelapan, dalam tempat yang dalam.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  جعلونى فى جب سفلى. فى مواضع مظلمة وظلال الموت.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eswp aisanmosi qen y~m/] nt~q/ibi m~v~mou: n~naerho] qat~h/ n~han pethwou je n~yok k~,/ nem/i.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Yes, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil, for You are with me.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sekalipun aku berjalan dalam lembah kekelaman, aku tidak takut bahaya, sebab Engkau besertaku; gada-Mu dan tongkat-Mu, itulah yang menghibur aku.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وإن سلكت فى وسط ظلال الموت فلا أخشى من الشر لأنك معى. هلليلويا.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Peky~ronoc Vnou] sae~neh n~te pie~neh: (All/louia.)                </language>               <language id="English">                  Your throne, O God, is forever and ever; [Alleluia.]               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Takhtamu kepunyaan Allah, tetap untuk seterusnya dan selamanya, </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  عرشك يا الله إلى دهر الدهور. ]الليلويا.[                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh pis~bwt m~p~cwouten pe p~s~bwt n~te tekmetouro. Ouc~murna nem ouc~takt/ nem oukacia~ e~bolqen nekh~bwc: all/louia.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Your royal scepter is a scepter of uprightness. Myrrh and stacte and cassia pour forth from Your garments. Alleluia.               </language><language id="Indonesian"> dan tongkat kerajaanmu adalah tongkat kebenaran. </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  قضيب الإستقامة هو قضيب ملكك. المر والميعة والسليخة من ثيابك. الليلويا.               </language>            </text>         </section>      </role>                  <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Matthew 27:57-61</language><language id="Indonesian">Matius 27:57-61</language>            <language id="Arabic">متى 27: 57-61</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/KeEperto"/>         <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroMatthew"/>         <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eta~rouhi de swpi afi~ n~je ourwmi n~ramao e~bolqen Arimayeac: e~pefran pe Iwc/f: vai hwf ne afermay/t/c n~I/couc.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Now when evening had come, there came a rich man from Arimathea, named Joseph, who himself had also become a disciple of Jesus.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Menjelang malam datanglah seorang kaya, orang Arimatea, yang bernama Yusuf dan yang telah menjadi murid Yesus juga.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولما كان المساء جاء رجل غنى من الرامة إسمه يوسف. هذا أيضاً كان تلميذاً ليسوع.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Vai afi~ haPilatoc afere~tin m~picwma n~te I/couc tote Pilatoc afouah cahni e~t/if:               </language>               <language id="English">                  This man went to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus. Then Pilate commanded the body to be given to him.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ia pergi menghadap Pilatus dan meminta mayat Yesus. Pilatus memerintahkan untuk menyerahkannya kepadanya.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فهذا جاء إلى بيلاطس وطلب جسد يسوع. فأمر بيلاطس حينئذ أن يعطى الجسد.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh af[i m~picwma n~je Iwc/f afkoulwlf qen ousentw e~couab                </language>               <language id="English">                  When Joseph had taken the body, he wrapped it in a clean linen cloth,               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan Yusufpun mengambil mayat itu, mengapaninya dengan kain lenan yang putih bersih,               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأخذ يوسف الجسد ولفه بلفائف من الكتان النقى.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh af,af qen pefm~hau m~beri: v/e~taf sokf qen ]petra: ouoh afc~kerker n~ounis] n~w~ni e~rwf m~pim~hau afhwl:               </language>               <language id="English">                  And laid it in his new tomb which he had hewn out of the rock; and he rolled a large stone against the door of the tomb, and departed.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  lalu membaringkannya di dalam kuburnya yang baru, yang digalinya di dalam bukit batu, dan sesudah menggulingkan sebuah batu besar ke pintu kubur itu, pergilah ia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ووضعه فى قبره الجديد الذى كان قد نحته فى الصخرة. ثم دحرج حجراً عظيماً على باب القبر ومضى.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nac,/ de m~mau n~je Maria ]Magdalin/: nem ]ke Maria euhemci m~pem~yo m~pim~hau.               </language>               <language id="English">                  And Mary Magdalene was there, and the other Mary, sitting opposite the tomb.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tetapi Maria Magdalena dan Maria yang lain tinggal di situ duduk di depan kubur itu.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكانت هناك مريم المجدلية ومريم الآخرى جالستين تجاه القبر.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelContinuationMark"/>         </role>      </section>               <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>                  <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Mark 15:42-16:1</language><language id="Indonesian">Markus 15:42-16:1</language>            <language id="Arabic">مرقس 15: 42-16: 1</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroMark"/>                     <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh h/d/et a~r~ouhi swpi epid/ net~parackeu/~ te etqajwf m~picabbaton:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Now when evening had come, because it was the Preparation Day, that is, the day before the Sabbath,               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sementara itu hari mulai malam, dan hari itu adalah hari persiapan, yaitu hari menjelang Sabat.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولما كان المساء ولأنها كانت الجمعة التى هى قبل السبت،                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Etfai n~je Iwc/f e~bolqen Arimayeac: e~oueuc~,emwn pe m~bouleut/c: vai e~te n~yof hwf nafjoust e~bol qat~h/ n~]metouro n~te Vnou]: afertolman afse e~qoun haPilatoc afere~tin mp~cwma n~I/couc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Joseph of Arimathea, a prominent council member, who was himself waiting for the kingdom of God, coming and taking courage, went in to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Karena itu Yusuf, orang Arimatea, seorang anggota Majelis Besar yang terkemuka, yang juga menanti-nantikan Kerajaan Allah, memberanikan diri menghadap Pilatus dan meminta mayat Yesus.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  جاء يوسف الذى من الرامة. وكان شريفاً ذا مشورة. وكان هو أيضاً يترجى ملكوت الله. فتجاسر ودخل إلى بيلاطس وطلب جسد يسوع.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  PiLatoc de afers~v/ri je h/d/ afmou ouoh e~tafmou] e~pie~katontar,oc afsenf: je an afouw~ afmou:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Pilate marveled that He was already dead; and summoning the centurion, he asked him if He had been dead for some time.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Pilatus heran waktu mendengar bahwa Yesus sudah mati. Maka ia memanggil kepala pasukan dan bertanya kepadanya apakah Yesus sudah mati.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فتعجب بيلاطس إنه مات هكذا سريعاً. فإستدعى قائد المئة وسأله هل له زمان قد مات.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh e~tafe~mi e~bolhitotf mpie~katontar,oc: af] m~picwma n~te I/couc n~Iwc/f.                </language>               <language id="English">                  So when he found out from the centurion, he granted the body to Joseph.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sesudah didengarnya keterangan kepala pasukan, ia berkenan memberikan mayat itu kepada Yusuf.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولما عرف من قائد المئة، وهب جسد يسوع ليوسف.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh e~tafsep ousentw af,af qen oum~hau v/ets/k e~bolqen oupetra:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then he bought fine linen, took Him down, and wrapped Him in the linen. And he laid Him in a tomb which had been hewn out of the rock, and rolled a stone against the door of the tomb.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Yusufpun membeli kain lenan, kemudian ia menurunkan mayat Yesus dari salib dan mengapaninya dengan kain lenan itu. Lalu ia membaringkan Dia di dalam kubur yang digali di dalam bukit batu. Kemudian digulingkannya sebuah batu ke pintu kubur itu.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فإشترى يوسف لفافة من الكتان وأنزله ولفه بها. ووضعه فى قبر كان منحوتاً فى صخرة. ودحرج حجراً على باب القبر.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh afc~kerker n~ouw~ni e~rwf m~pimhau Maria ]Magdalin/ nem Maria n~te Iwc/: naunau je au,af ywn.               </language>               <language id="English">                  And Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of Joses observed where He was laid.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Maria Magdalena dan Maria ibu Yoses melihat di mana Yesus dibaringkan.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكانت مريم المجدلية ومريم أم يوسي تنظران أين وضع.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh e~tafswpi n~je picabbaton: Maria }magdalin/ nem Maria n~te Iakwboc nem Calwme: auswpi n~hanc~yoinoufi hina n~toui~ n~touyahcf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Now when the Sabbath was past, Mary Magdalene, Mary the mother of James, and Salome bought spices, that they might come and anoint Him.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Setelah lewat hari Sabat, Maria Magdalena dan Maria ibu Yakobus, serta Salome membeli rempah-rempah untuk pergi ke kubur dan meminyaki Yesus.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولما مضى السبت. إشترت مريم المجدلية ومريم أم يعقوب وسالومة حنوطاً ليأتين ويحنطنه.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelContinuationLuke"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Luke 23:50-56</language><language id="Indonesian">Lukas 23:50-56</language>            <language id="Arabic">لوقا 23: 50-56</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroLuke"/>                     <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh h/ppe ic ourwmi e~pefran pe Iwc/f: e~oubouleut/c pe: ourmmi n~a~gayoc ouoh n~y~m/i:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Now behold, there was a man named Joseph, a council member, a good and just man.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Adalah seorang yang bernama Yusuf. Ia anggota Majelis Besar, dan seorang yang baik lagi benar.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وإذا رجل إسمه يوسف وكان مشيراً ورجلاً صالحاً باراً.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Vai e~naf ]ma] an pe qen pouco[ni nem tou p~raxic ne oue~bolqen Arimayeac ou baki n~te niIoudai: v/e~nafjoust e~bol qajen ]metouro n~te Vnou].               </language>               <language id="English">                  He had not consented to their decision and deed. He was from Arimathea, a city of the Jews, who himself was also waiting for the kingdom of God.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Ia tidak setuju dengan putusan dan tindakan Majelis itu. Ia berasal dari Arimatea, sebuah kota Yahudi dan ia menanti-nantikan Kerajaan Allah.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  هذا لم يكن موافقاً لرأيهم وعملهم. وكان من الرامة مدينة لليهود. وكان هو أيضاً ينتظر ملكوت الله.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Vai e~tafi~ ha Pilatoc ouoh afere~tin m~picwma n~te I/couc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  This man went to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ia pergi menghadap Pilatus dan meminta mayat Yesus.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  هذا تقدم إلى بيلاطس وطلب جسد يسوع.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh e~tafenf e~pec/t afkoulwlf qen ousentw: ouoh af,af qen oum~hau e~afkosf m~patou,a h~li n~q/tf: ouoh afc~kerker n~ounis] n~w~ni hiren v~ro m~pim~hau.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then he took it down, wrapped it in linen, and laid it in a tomb that was hewn out of the rock, where no one had ever lain before.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan sesudah ia menurunkan mayat itu, ia mengapaninya dengan kain lenan, lalu membaringkannya di dalam kubur yang digali di dalam bukit batu, di mana belum pernah dibaringkan mayat.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأنزله ولفه فى لفافة من الكتان ووضعه فى قبر قد نحته ولم يكن قد وضع فيه أحد. ودحرج حجراً عظيماً على باب القبر.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh ne p~e~hoou pe n~]parackeu/ e~reswrp de naswpi m~p~cabbaton.               </language>               <language id="English">                  That day was the Preparation, and the Sabbath drew near.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Hari itu adalah hari persiapan dan sabat hampir mulai.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان يوم الجمعة وقد أخذ السبت يلوح.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh e~taumosi de n~cwf n~je nihiomi n/e~taui~ nemaf e~bol qen ]Galilea~ e~aunau e~pimhau nem pir/] e~tau,a pefcwma m~mof:                </language>               <language id="English">                   And the women who had come with Him from Galilee followed after, and they observed the tomb and how His body was laid.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Dan perempuan-perempuan yang datang bersama-sama dengan Yesus dari Galilea, ikut serta dan mereka melihat kubur itu dan bagaimana mayat-Nya dibaringkan.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكانت النسوة اللواتى يتبعنه وجئن معه من الجليل، فأبصرن القبر وكيف وضع فيه جسده.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Etautacyo de aucebt hancyoinoufi nem hancojen: ouoh picabbaton men: auer/cu,azin kata ]entol/.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then they returned and prepared spices and fragrant oils. And they rested on the Sabbath according to the commandment.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan setelah pulang, mereka menyediakan rempah-rempah dan minyak mur.Dan pada hari Sabat mereka beristirahat menurut hukum Taurat,               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فرجعن وأعددن حنوطاً وأطياباً. وفى السبت إسترحن حسب الوصية.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelContinuationJohn"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">John 19:38-42</language><language id="Indonesian">Yohanes 19:38-42</language>            <language id="Arabic">يوحنا 19: 38-42</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroJohn"/>                     <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Menenca nai de afi~ n~je Iwc/f pirem Arimayeac af]ho e~Pilatoc: e~oumay/t/c hwf n~te I/couc naf,/p de pe eybe t~ho] n~niIoudai:               </language>               <language id="English">                  After this, Joseph of Arimathea, being a disciple of Jesus, but secretly, for fear of the Jews, asked Pilate,               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sesudah itu Yusuf dari Arimatea--ia murid Yesus, tetapi sembunyi-sembunyi karena takut kepada orang-orang Yahudi--meminta kepada Pilatus, </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ومن بعد هذا جاء يوسف الذى من الرامة وهو تلميذ ليسوع. ولكنه كان يستتر خوفاً من اليهود. سأل بيلاطس,               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Hina n~tefw~li m~picwma n~te I/couc: ouoh afouahcahni n~je Pilatoc e~t/if naf afi~ oun ouoh afw~li m~picwma n~te I/couc:                </language>               <language id="English">                  That he might take away the body of Jesus; and Pilate gave him permission. So he came and took the body of Jesus.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  supaya ia diperbolehkan menurunkan mayat Yesus. Dan Pilatus meluluskan permintaannya itu. Lalu datanglah ia dan menurunkan mayat itu.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أن يأخذ جسد يسوع. فأذن له بيلاطس أن يُعطى له. فجاء وحمل جسد يسوع،                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Afi~ de hwf n~je Nikoudimoc v/e~tafi~ haI/couc n~jwrh n~swrp: e~ouon oumigma n~totf ousal nem ouallo/: nau se n~lutra.               </language>               <language id="English">                  And Nicodemus, who at first came to Jesus by night, also came, bringing a mixture of myrrh and aloes, about a hundred pounds.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Juga Nikodemus datang ke situ. Dialah yang mula-mula datang waktu malam kepada Yesus. Ia membawa campuran minyak mur dengan minyak gaharu, kira-kira lima puluh kati beratnya.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وجاء أيضاً نيقوديموس الذى كان قد جاء أولاً إلى يسوع ليلاً ومعه حنوط مر وصبر، نحو مئة رطل.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Au[i oun m~picwma n~te I/couc ouoh aukoulwlfqen ousentw n~iau nem nic~yoi: kata ]kahc n~te niIoudai eukwc:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then they took the body of Jesus, and bound it in strips of linen with the spices, as the custom of the Jews is to bury.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Mereka mengambil mayat Yesus, mengapaninya dengan kain lenan dan membubuhinya dengan rempah-rempah menurut adat orang Yahudi bila menguburkan mayat.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأخذا جسد يسوع ولفاه فى لفائف كتان مع الحنوط كعادة اليهود أن يكفنوا.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ne ouon ou[wm de pe e~pima etauas I/couc m~mof: ouoh ne ouon oum~hau m~beri qen pi[wm: m~patouhi h~li n~rwmi e~qoun e~rof e~neh:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Now in the place where He was crucified there was a garden, and in the garden a new tomb in which no one had yet been laid.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dekat tempat di mana Yesus disalibkan ada suatu taman dan dalam taman itu ada suatu kubur baru yang di dalamnya belum pernah dimakamkan seseorang.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان فى الموضع الذى صلب فيه يسوع بستان. وكان فى البستان قبر جديد لم يوضع فيه أحد قط.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Epid/ nafqent e~rwou n~je pim~hau: eybe je ]parackeu/~ de n~te niIoudai au,a I/couc n~q/tf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  So there they laid Jesus, because of the Jews’ Preparation Day, for the tomb was nearby.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                   Karena hari itu hari persiapan orang Yahudi, sedang kubur itu tidak jauh letaknya, maka mereka meletakkan mayat Yesus ke situ.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فهناك وضعا يسوع لسبب الجمعة لليهود. لأن القبر كان قريباً.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/BowDownBeforeTheHolyGospel"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>      <role id="Reader">         <insertdocument path="pascha/friday/interpretations/12thHour/gospels"/>      </role>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelConclusionDay"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Exposition</language><language id="Indonesian">Komentari </language>            <language id="Arabic">الطرح</language>         </Title>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The exposition of the Twelfth Hour of Great Friday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Komentari Jam Kedua belas  Jumat Agung pada Pekan Paskah Suci, semoga berkatnya menyertai kita semua. Amin               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طرح الساعة الثانية عشر من يوم الجمعة العظيمة من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  And when the evening had come, because it was the day of preparation—that is, the day before the Sabbath—a wealthy man called Joseph, a respected member of the council who was also himself looking for the kingdom of God, and another called Nicodemus, a God loving man, took courage               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan ketika malam telah tiba, karena itu hari persiapan sebelum hari Sabat, seorang lelaki kaya bernama Yusuf , seorang anggota dewan yang disegani yang juga yang sedang mencari kerajaan Allah, dan yang lain bernama Nikodemus, seorang lelaki yang penuh kasih datang. Yusuf dan teman-temannya, para bapa merawat jasad para orang kudus.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وفـى عشية ذلك اليوم الـذى هـو جمعة العيد العظيم، الذى يأتى قبل السبـت، الـذى هو لسر السيد، جاء إنسان غنى إسمه يوسف وكان ذا رأى ويعرف الناموس وإنسان آخر يسمى نيقوديموس طوباوى محب للإله. وكان يوسف هذا هو وآباؤه يهتمون بأجساد القديسين.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  and went to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus, God the Logos. Pilate asked him; "Is he dead?" Then he ordered the centurion to give the body to Joseph.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mereka pergi ke Pilatus dan meminta tubuh Yesus , Sang Firman Allah. Pilatus bertanya kepada Yusuf, "Apakah Ia sudah mati?" Dan Pilatus terheran. Kemudian Pilatus memerintahkan perwira itu untuk memberikan mayat itu kepada Yusuf. </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأتى إلى بيلاطس وسأله عن جسد الإله الكلمة الوحيد. فأستفهم منه: هل مات؟ فتعجب الوالى جداً. وهكذا أمر قائد المئة بأن يعطوه جسد يسوع.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  He bought a linen shroud, took Him down, and wrapped Him in the linen shroud. Nicodemus brought about one hundred pounds of fragrant oil and embalmed Him according to Jewish traditions.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Yusuf oyang saleh itu kemudian mengambil tubuh itu dan menjaganya. Dia juga membawa  kain kafan lenan yang baru dan menurunkan jasad Yesus, dan membungkus-Nya. Nikodemus membawa sejumlah besar minyak wangi </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأخذ صاحب المشورة الصالحة الصديق الجسد وإهتم به وأحضر أكفاناً ناعمة نقية كما يليق بإبن الله. وأحضر أيضاً نيقوديموس أطياباً كثيرة الثمن نحو مائة رطل طيب. وهكذا كفنوه كعادة العبرانيين.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  They laid Him in a tomb which had just been hewn out of the rock; it was never used before. They rolled a stone against the door of the tomb.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  dan mereka mengafani Yesus sesuai dengan tradisi Yahudi dan  meminyaki dengan parfum  pada Yang Diberkati. Mereka meletakkan mayat itu di kuburan yang baru di mana belum ada orang yang dikuburkan sebelumnya. Mereka menggulingkan sebuah batu ke pintu makam               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ووضعوا الطيب على المبارك. وكان قبر جديد فى البستان طاهراً نقياً لم يوضع أحداً فيه. فوضعوا جسد الوحيد فى ذلك القبر وتركوا حجراً عليه               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  Then they rested on the Sabbath in observance of the commandment. Mary Magdalene and Mary the mother of Jesus saw where He was laid.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>dan beristirahat pada hari Sabat untuk mematuhi perintah Allah. Dan ada beberapa wanita berdiri di sana mengamati; Maria Magdalena dan Maria ibu Yesus melihat di mana Ia dibaringkan. </div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  . فإستراحوا كالوصية، من أجل السبت صنعوا هكذا. وكن نسوة واقفات ينظرن ما كان. المجدلية ومريم الآخرى علمن جيداً أين وضع.               </language>            </text>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ExpositionConclusion"/>         <insertdocument path="pascha/include/DaytimeLitaniesEmbed"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/EvnotiNaiNan"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Four Hundred Lord Have Mercy's</language><language id="Indonesian">Empat Ratus Tuhan Kasihanilah Kami.</language>         </Title>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               The servant priest holds up the cross and the congregation chant: "Lord have mercy (<span class="Coptic">Kurie e~le/~con</span>)", one hundred times to the east, one hundred times to the west, one hundred times to the north, one hundred times to the south, then twelve more times back to the east.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               pendeta  mengangkat salib dan jemaat bernyanyi: 'Tuhan kasihanilah kami (<span class="Coptic">Kurie e~le/~con</span>)"seratus kali ke timur, seratus kali ke barat, seratus kali ke utara, seratus kali ke selatan, lalu dua belas kali lagi kembali ke timur.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وبعد الطلبة يرفع الأب البطريرك أو المطران أو الأسقف أو كبير الكهنة الصليب ويبتدئ كل الشعب بالتهليل إلى الرب بصوت عال صارخين كيرياليصون دمجاً ويضربون المطانيات طالبين من الرب غفران خطاياهم فى كل جهة مائة دفعة أولاً شرقاً ثم غرباً وبعده شمالاً فجنوباً وكل جهة يلتفتون إليها، يلتفت الكهنة بالصلبان والأيقونات والمجامر.            </language>         </comment>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               Then a procession circles the altar in the sanctuary three times, followed by three times around the church then ending with one circle around the altar.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kemudian prosesi mengelilingi altar di ruang sakristi tiga kali, diikuti dengan tiga kali mengelilingi gereja, lalu berakhir dengan satu lingkaran mengelilingi altar.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               ثم عند كمال الأربع جهات يعودون إلى الشرق ويبتدئون بقراءة كيرياليصون بالكبير وبالناقوس اثنى عشر دفعة. وينزلون الخورس ويصعدون إلى الهيكل ويطوفون حوله ثلاث دفعات والبيعة ثلاث دفعات ثم يصعدون إلى الهيكل ويدورون دورة واحدة وهم يرتلون كيرياليصون            </language>         </comment>      </section>         <role id="People">         <comment>            <language id="English">               The deacons chant "Lord have mercy (<span class="Coptic">Kurie Ele/~con</span>)" twelve times in the great tune.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Diakon bernyanyi 'Tuhan kasihanilah kami (<span class="Coptic">Kurie Ele/~con</span>) dua belas kali dengan irama agung.            </language>         </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Am/n. Kurie e~le/~con. (i#b##)            </language>            <language id="English">               Amen. Lord have mercy. (12)            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Amin. Tuhan kasihanilah kami. (12)            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               آمين. يارب ارحم. (12)            </language>                  </text>      </role>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">The Burial Hymn</language><language id="Indonesian">Himne Pemakaman</language>            <language id="Coptic">Golgoya</language>         </Title>                  <role id="People">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Golgoya m~met hebreoc: pik~ranion m~metoueinin: pima e~tauask P[oic n~q/tf: akvwrs n~nekjij e~bol aui~si nemak n~keconi c~nau: catekoui~nam nem catek ja[/: n~yok ek,/ qen toum/] w~picwt/r n~a~gayoc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  “Golgotha” in Hebrew, “Kranion” in Greek, the place where You were crucified Lord. You spread out Your hands, and two thieves were crucified with You; at Your right, and at Your left, You in the middle O good Savior.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Golgota bahasa Ibrani, Kranion bahasa Yunani,</div><div>tempat Engkau disalibkan, ya Tuhan.</div><div>Engkau ulurkan tangan-Mu,</div><div><div>dan dua pencuri disalib bersama-Mu; <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">satu di kanan-Mu, dan di kiri-Mu, dan Engkau, ya Juruselamat, ada di tengah.</span></div></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  الجلجثة بالعبرانية. الإقرانيون باليونانية. الموضع الذي صلبت فيه يارب. بسطت يديك. وصلبوا معك لصين. عن يمينك وعن يسارك. وأنت كائن في الوسط أيها المخلص الصالح.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/DoxaPatriNoRole"/>                                 <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Afws e~bol n~je piconi: etcaoui~nam efjw m~moc: je a~ripameui~ w~Pa[oic a~ripameui~ w~Pacwt/r: a~ripameui~ w~Paouro: aksani~ qen tekmetouro.               </language>               <language id="English">                  The thief at Your right cried out saying: “Remember me, O my Lord; remember me, O my Savior; remember me, O my King, when You come into Your kingdom.”               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kemuliaan kepada Bapa, dan Putra, dan Roh Kudus.</div><div>Pencuri di sebelah kanan berseru, “Ingatlah aku, ya Tuhanku, ingatlah aku, ya Penyelamatku, ingatlah aku, ya Rajaku, saat</div><div>Engkau datang di Kerajaan-Mu."</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فصرخ اللص اليمين قائلاً: أذكرني ياربي، أذكرني يامخلصي، أذكرني ياملكي، متي جئت في ملكوتك.                </language>            </text>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                                 Aferouw~ naf n~je P[oic: qen ouc~m/ m~metremraus: je m~voou eke~swpi nem/i: n~h~r/i qen tametouro.               </language>               <language id="English">                  The Lord answered him in a gentle voice saying: “Today you shall be with Me in My kingdom.”               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tuhan menjawabnya dengan lembut berkata: "Hari ini kamu kan bersama-Ku di Firdaus."</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أجابه الرب بصوت وديع أنك اليوم تكون معي في ملكوتي.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/KeNinNoRole"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Aui~ n~je nidikeoc: Iwc/f nem Nikod/moc: au[i n~t~carx n~te Pi,~rictoc: au] n~oucojen e~h~r/i e~jwf: aukocf au,af qen oum~hau: euhwc e~rof eujw m~moc je a~gioc o~ Yeoc: a~gioc ic,uroc: a~gioc a~yanatoc: o~ c~taurwyic dimac e~le/~con /~mac.               </language>               <language id="English">                  The righteous Joseph and Nicodemus came and took the Body of Christ, embalmed Him, prepared Him, put Him in a tomb, singing to Him saying: “Holy God, Holy Mighty, Holy Immortal, who was crucified for us, have mercy upon us.”               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Yang saleh Yusuf dan Nikodemus</div><div>datang mengambil Tubuh Kristus, membungkus-Nya dengan rempah, dan memasukkan-Nya ke</div><div>kubur, memuji Dia dan berkata, “Allah Kudus, Maha Kuasa Kudus, Kekal Kudus, yang</div><div>disalibkan bagi kami, kasihanilah kami."</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أتي الصديقان يوسف ونيقوديموس، وأخذا جسد المسيح. وجعلا عليه طيبا وكفناه، ووضعاه في قبر وسبحاه قائلين: قدوس اللـه، قدوس القوي، قدوس الذي لايموت، الذي صلب عنا ارحمنا.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/DoxaPatriNoRole"/>            <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/KeNinNoRole"/>                                 <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Anon hwn marenouwst m~mof: enws e~bol enjw m~moc: je nai nan Vnou] Pencwt/r: v/e~tauask e~pic~tauroc: eke~qomqem m~p~catanac: capec/t n~nen[alauj.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Let us also worship Him crying out saying: “Have mercy on us, O God our Savior, who was crucified on the cross, trample Satan under our feet.”               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mari kita juga sembah Dia, berseru berkata: "Kasihanilah kami, ya Allah Juru Selamat kami,</div><div>yang disalibkan di atas Salib, hancurkan Setan di bawah kaki kami. Selamatkan kami dan kasihanilah kami."</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ونحن أيضاً فلنسجد له صارخين قائلين: ارحمنا يااللـه مخلصنا. يامن صلبت علي الصليب، اسحق الشيطان تحت أقدامنا.               </language>            </text>                        <comment>               <language id="English">                                 <ol>                     <li>Meanwhile, the priest wraps the icon of the burial in a white linen veil, places a cross on it and places it on the Southern side of the Altar (the right-side of the Altar with respect to the congregation facing the East).</li>                     <li>He then “buries” it amidst the roses and spices and covers it with a white veil.</li>                     <li>The priest then places 2 candles or oil lamps on either side of (longitudinally) to resemble the 2 angels that were at the tomb of Christ, one at His head and the other at His feet.</li>                     <li>The priest chants Psalms 1, 2 and 3 until the verse “I have laid down and slept.” (Ps. 3:2).</li>                                    </ol>               </language><language id="Indonesian">                                 <ol>                     <li>Sementara itu, imam membungkus ikon pemakaman dengan kain linen putih, meletakkan salib di atasnya, dan menaruhnya di sisi Selatan Altar (di sisi kanan Altar jika dilihat dari arah jemaat yang menghadap ke Timur).</li>                     <li>Kemudian dia 'menguburkannya' di antara mawar dan rempah-rempah, lalu menutupnya dengan kain putih.</li>                     <li>Pelayan kemudian meletakkan 2 lilin atau lampu minyak di kedua sisi (secara longitudinal) untuk menyerupai 2 malaikat yang berada di makam Kristus, satu di kepala-Nya dan yang lainnya di kaki-Nya.</li>                     <li>Pelayan bernyanyi Mazmur 1, 2, dan 3 hingga ayat 'Aku telah berbaring dan tidur.' (Mzm. 3:2).</li>                                    </ol>               </language>            </comment>         </role>         </section>            <role id="Priest">         <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/1"/>         <insertdocument path="include/agpeya/psalms/2"/>                  <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">                  Psalm 3 - O Lord, why have they...               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mazmur3- Ya TUHAN, betapa banyaknya lawanku!               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  المزمور الثالث - يا رب لماذا كثر...               </language>            </Title>                        <text>               <language id="English">                  O Lord, why have they who afflict me multiplied? Many have risen up upon me. Many say unto my soul, “There is no salvation for him in his God.” But You, O Lord, are my supporter, my glory, and the elevation of my head.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ya TUHAN, betapa banyaknya lawanku! Banyak orang yang bangkit menyerang aku;  banyak orang yang berkata tentang aku: "Baginya tidak ada pertolongan dari pada Allah." SelaTetapi Engkau, TUHAN, adalah perisai yang melindungi aku, Engkaulah kemuliaanku dan yang mengangkat kepalaku.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يا رب لماذا كثر الذين يحزنونني، كثيرون قاموا علي. كثيرون يقولون لنفسي، ليس له خلاص بإلهه. أنت يا رب أنت هو ناصري، مجدي ورافع رأسي.               </language>            </text>                        <text>               <language id="English">                  With my voice I cried unto the Lord, and He heard me out of His holy mountain. I laid down and slept...               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dengan nyaring aku berseru kepada TUHAN, dan Ia menjawab aku dari gunung-Nya yang kudus. Sela  Aku membaringkan diri, lalu tidur;  </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  بصوتي إلى الرب صرخت. فاستجاب لي من جبل قدسه. أنا اضطجعت ونمت...               </language>            </text>         </section>      </role>            <role id="People">         <comment>            <language id="English">                              The deacons chant the Concluding Hymn:            </language><language id="Indonesian">                              Diakon menyanyikan Hymne Penutup:            </language>         </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               cw] m~mon ouoh nai nan: Kurie e~le/~con: Kurie e~le/~con: Kurie eulog/con: a~m/n: c~mou e~roi: c~mou e~roi: ic ]metanoia: ,w n/i e~bol jw m~pic~mou.            </language>            <language id="English">               Save us and have mercy on us. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord bless us. Amen. Bless me. Bless me. Lo, the metania. Forgive me. Say the Blessing.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Selamatkan kami dan kasihanilah kami. Tuhan, kasihanilah. Tuhan, kasihanilah. Tuhan, berkati kami. Amin. Berkati aku. Berkati aku. Lihatlah, metania. Ampunilah aku. Ucapkan Berkat.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               خلصنا وارحمنا. يارب ارحم يارب ارحم. يارب بارك أمين. باركوا عليّ. ها ميطانية. اغفروا لي. قل البركة.            </language>         </text>               </role>         <comment>         <language id="English">                           The deacons and congregation continue reading the rest of the 150 psalms, inaudiably, beginning with Psalm 4.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Diakon dan jemaat melanjutkan pembacaan sisa 150 mazmur, secara tidak terdengar, dimulai dengan Mazmur 4.</div></language>      </comment>            <insertdocument path="include/ShortBlessingToEnd"/>            <comment>         <language id="English">                           The congregation departs to their homes to rest a little and then returns for the vigil of the Apocalypse.         </language><language id="Indonesian">                           Jemaat pulang ke rumah mereka untuk beristirahat sejenak, kemudian kembali untuk berjaga malam menjelang Wahyu.         </language>      </comment>   </forceseason></document>