<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Gospels         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير الأناجيل         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            We were not born naked but clothed in righteousness but when we disobeyed the commandments of God we became naked and were thrown out of heaven, the place of rest and joy, and onto earth, pain, and suffering after God clothed our nakedness with garments made of skin. We started to work the ground, which had been cursed because of us and brought forth thorns and thistles as God had commanded. Years and generations had passed and we were still naked of righteousness until the Son of God, the second hypostasis of the Divine, condescended and was incarnate from the ever virgin Mary, the morning star, and lived amongst us, healing our sicknesses, raising our dead and giving sight to the blind. Envy filled the hearts of the Jewish priests and they hated Him. The devil tempted them to kill Him so they sentenced Him to death despite the fact that they could not execute this judgment because the Romans who ruled over them had denied the Jewish judges the right to kill any man. So they took Him to Pilate then to Herod then to Pilate again.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إننا لمَّا خُلقنا لمْ نُخلق عُراة كما نحن اليوم ولكننا كنا مُكتسين بِردَاء البر ولما خالفنا وصية الله تَعرينا من هذا الرداء وخرجنا من الفردوس محل الراحة والنعيم إلى أرض التعب والشقاء بعد ما سَتر الله عريِنا برداء من الجلد. وصِرنا نِعمل في الأرض التي لُعنت من أجلنا وهي تنبت الشوك والحسك كأمر الله تعالى. ولقد مَرت السنون والأجيال ونحن على هذه الحال عراة من حلة البر حتى تنازل ابن الله، الأقنوم الثاني من اللاهوت، وتجسد من السيدة البتول نجمة الصبح العذراء مريم وعاش بيننا يَشفي أمراضنا ويُقيم مَوتانا ويُفتح أعين عمياننا. فملأ الحسد قلوب كهنة اليهود بُغضةٌ له وأغراهم الشيطان على قَتلهِ فَحكَموا عليه بالموت بيد أن تنفيذ هذا الحكم لم يكن في يدهم حيث قد نَزعه منهم الرومان المُتمَّلِكين عليهم في ذلك الزمان. فأخذوه وذهبوا به إلى بيلاطس فهيرودس فبيلاطس الثاني.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord was taken to be sentenced before judges and governors six times: three times before the Jewish judges, twice before Pilate and once before Herod. He was humiliated four times. He was declared innocent three times and was sentenced twice. When He was finally brought back to Pilate for the second time, Pilate tried to release Him several times because he was confident of His innocence but his efforts did not yield any results when he saw that the place was full of people and the mob was shouting for him to crucify Jesus. He therefore tried to come up with a solution that would pacify their anger and quench the envy in their heart. "You have brought this Man to me, as one who misleads the people. And indeed, having examined Him in your presence, I have found no fault in this Man concerning those things of which you accuse Him; no, neither did Herod, for I sent you back to him… I will therefore chastise Him and release Him… But they shouted, saying, "Crucify Him, crucify Him”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فقد سِيق الرب إلى الحكم أمام القضاة والولاة ست مرات. ثلاثاَ قدام قضاة من اليهود واثنتين أمام بيلاطس وواحدة أمام هيرودس واستُهزئَ به أربع مرات: وبُررَّ ثلاث مرات وحُكمَ عليه مرتين. ولما جاءوا إلى بيلاطس للمرة الثانية حاول كثيراً أن يُطلِقه وبَذل قصارى جهده في إخلاء سبيله لما تحققه من برﺍءته ولكنه وجد مساعيه ذاهبة سُدى حيث رأى دار الولاية غاصة بالمزدحمين من الشعب والرعاع وقد بلغ صياحهم عنان السماء وهم يصرخون قائلين: اصلبه، دَبر طريقة لعلها تطفئ نار غيظهم وتستأصل جذوة الحسد من قلوبهم. "فدعا بيلاطس رؤساء الكهنة والعظماء والشعب وقال لهم قدمتم إلىَّ هذا الإنسان كمَن يُفسد الشعب. وها أنا قد فَحصت قدامكم ولم أجد في هذا الإنسان علة مما تشتكون عليه ولا هيرودس أيضاً... فأنا أؤدبه وأُطلَقه... فكانوا يلجون بأصوات عظيمة طالبين أن يُصلب".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            When Pilate saw that chastising Him was insufficient for them and that they would not stop shouting to have Him crucified he said, “…”(for it was necessary for him to release one to them at the feast. The Israelites had been enslaved by Pharaoh and were delivered at the same time of year that they celebrate the Passover. Therefore, when Pilate became their governor they agreed that he would release one captive each year at the time of Passover to show them mercy.) As for Pilate’s wife’s dream, interpreters have disagreed on its meaning. A distinguished group of commentators agreed that she saw the Lord sitting on a throne and rising to heaven with great glory surrounded by the creatures of both the earth and the heavens and when she inquired about the scene, a fearful loud voice from Heaven replied, “This is Jesus of Nazareth who was condemned by Pilate.” She suffered for him showing that she was scared by the enormity of what she saw.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما رأى بيلاطس أن تأديبه وإطلاقه لا يرضيهم وأنهم لم ينفكوا من الصراخ طالبين قتله. "وكان الوالي معتاداً في العيد أن يُطلق للجمع أسيراً واحداً من أرادوه" وذلك لأن بني إسرائيل لما كانوا في عبودية فرعون وكان خلاصهم من تلك العبودية في مثل هذا الوقت الذي يُعيِّدون فيه الفصح. ولمَّا تولى عليهم بيلاطس جعلوا لهم عليه هذا الرسم بقرار كان بينهم وبينه بأن يستطلقوا منه في كل سنة تأتي عليهم في عيد الفصح أسيراً واحداً من أرادوه تظاهراً بالرحمة. وأما حلم امرأة بيلاطس فإن المفسرين قد اختلفوا فيه. والذي اتفق عليه جماعة منهم مُميزين هو أنها رأت السيد وهو جالس على كرسي عظيم القدر وهو صاعد إلى السماء بمَجد عظيم. والسمائيون مع الأرضيين حوله. فَسألت ما هذا وإذا صوتٌ مُخيف مُزعج يُنادي من السماء. هذا هو يسوع الناصري الذي قد دانَه بيلاطس. أما تألمها من أجله فيدل على أنها ارتعبت من هول ما قد رأت.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Pilate tried hard to release Him but to no avail because the Chief priests and the teachers had provoked the multitudes to ask for Barabbas and to crucify Jesus. Because their hearts were full of envy they could no longer see the light of truth so they sentenced Jesus to death and released Barabbas, who was a sinful criminal.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وعبثاً حاول بيلاطس إطلاق يسوع لأن "رؤساء الكهنة والشيوخ حرَّضوا الجموع على أن يطلبوا باراباس ويُهلكوا يسوع" لأن الحسد قد ملأ منهم القلوب وأعمى بصائرهم عن نور الحق فحكموا بالموت على يسوع وبالإفراج عن باراباس المجرم الأثيم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            "When Pilate saw that he could prevail nothing, but that rather a tumult was made, he took water, and washed his hands before the multitude, saying, I am innocent of the blood of this just person” because he found no reason to condemn him to death, because of his wife’s dream, and because of the miracles he heard that Jesus had performed. He also knew that the Jews had delivered Jesus out of envy. “Then answered all the people, and said, His blood be on us, and on our children.” It was not sufficient for them to destroy themselves but they also sought to destroy their children. From that point of time onwards, God had become angry with them. They were no longer permitted to be priests or offer offerings or incense for forgiveness.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "فلما رأى بيلاطس أنه لا ينفع شيئاً بل بالحري يُحدث شغب أخذ ماء وغسل يديه قدام الجمع قائلاً أني برئ من دم هذا البار" لأنه لم يجد فيه علة يَستحق عليها الموت ولأنه يَعلم أن اليهود قد أسلموه إليه حسداً ولِعلمهِ بالآيات التي كان يصنعها ولأجل الحلم الذي رأته امرأته "فأجاب جميع الشعب وقالوا دمه علينا وعلى أولادنا" فلم يقنعوا بهلاك أنفسهم بل أهلكوا معهم أولادهم. ومن ذلك الوقت إلى الآن وغضب الله عليهِم حيث لا كهنوت لهم ولا قربان ولا بخور ولا غفران.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Then Pilate therefore took Jesus, and scourged Him.” It was the Roman custom to scourge those sentenced to crucifixion before they were crucified. “And the soldiers platted a crown of thorns, and put it on His head, and they put on Him a purple robe And said, Hail, King of the Jews! And they smote Him with their hands.” By being scourged the Lord paid for the insults and the scourging that Adam and his offspring deserved. The soldiers humiliated Him after they had undressed Him. He was dressed in a purple robe instead of the leather robes given to Adam and Eve when they had fallen. A crown of thorns was put on his head instead of the thorns and thistles that He had ordered the earth to grow when Adam fell. He carried the thorns on His head to ensure that He carried our sins, for sins are thorns. Pilate’s intention of showing them Jesus like this was to persuade them not to kill Him but they shouted even more, “But they cried out, "Away with Him, away with Him! Crucify Him!" Pilate said to them, "Shall I crucify your King?" The chief priests answered, "We have no king but Caesar!" Observe those two-faced evil people and how, despite their extreme hatred of the foreign rule, they now acknowledged Caesar as their King. This was simply a means to achieve their evil end.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "فحينئذ أخذ بيلاطس يسوع وجلده" وهذه كانت عادة الرومانيين جلْد المحكوم عليه بالصَلبِ قبل أن يُصلب. "وضفر العسكر إكليلاً من شوك ووضعوه على رأسه وألبسوه ثوب أرجوان. وكانوا يقولون السلام يا مَلك اليهود وكانوا يلطمونه" وقد أوفى الرب بجلده الإهانة والجلد عن آدم ونسله الذين كانوا يستحقونهما. وهزأ به الجند بعد أن عَروه ثيابه. فأوفى عن آدم الهزء الذي كان يستحقه من الله. وأوفى العُري الواجب عليه إلى الأبد لمَّا عَروه. ولبِس الثوب الأحمر بدل الثياب الجلد التي البسها لآدم وحواء عند مُخالفتهما. ووُضع على رأسه أكليل شوك بدل الشوك والحسك الذي أمَر الأرض أن تنبت لمَّا اخطأ آدم. حَمل الشوك على رأسه حتى يُحقق أنه أحتمل خطاياه. لأن الشوك هو الخطايا. وكان غَرض بيلاطس من عَرض يسوع على اليهود بهذه الحال ليُثنى عزمهم عن قتله ولكنهم كانوا يزدادون صياحاً "أصلبه أصلبه" فقال لهم: "أأصلب ملككم. أجاب رؤساء الكهنة ليس لنا ملك إلا قيصر" فتأمل يا هذا نفاق هذا الشعب الملتوي القلب وكيف أنه مع نفوره من الحكم الأجنبي أشد النفور يُرائي الآن ويَعترف بالقيصر ملكاً عليه وما جعلوا ذلك القول إلا واسطة لنيل أغراضهم السيئة.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And he released unto them him that for sedition and murder was cast into prison, whom they had desired; but he delivered Jesus to their will.” And so Pilate… delivered Jesus, when he had scourged Him, to be crucified… And it was the third hour, and they crucified Him.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "فأطلق لهم الذي طرح في السجن لأجل فتنة وقتل الذي طلبوه" "وأسلم يسوع بعد ما جلده ليُصلب... وكانت الساعة الثالثة فصَلبوه"         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            There is no disagreement between Mark’s statement that Jesus was crucified on the third hour and John’s statement that He was crucified at sixth, because the former talked about the time when He was delivered to be crucified and the second talked about the time when He was actually crucified. Glory be given to our Lord Forever Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقول مرقس هذا أن صلب يسوع كان في الساعة الثالثة لا خلاف بينه وبين قول يوحنا أنه كان في السادسة. لأن الأول قال عن الوقت الذي أُسلم فيه ليُصلب والثاني قال عن الوقت الذي تم فيه الصلب. والمجد لربنا دائماً أبدياً آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>