<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Job 29:21-30:10         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            من أيوب الصديق 29: 21 الخ و 30: 1 – 10         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, "Men listened to me and waited, And kept silence for my counsel” meaning that the Jewish people witnessed the works of the savior and His wonderful miracles but ignored them. The savior directed their attention to their salvation by saying, “"A little while longer the light is with you. Walk while you have the light, lest darkness overtake you”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لما سمعوني تأملوني وسكتوا عند مشورتي" يعني بهذا أن شعب اليهود كان يُبصر أعمال المُخلِّص والآيات الباهرة التي كان يصنعُها. وكان يتغافل عن ذلك. أما المُخلِّص فكان يشير عليهم بما فيه خلاصهم. بقوله لهم: "النور معكم زماناً قليلاً بعد. فسِيروا مادام لكم النور لئلا يدرككم الظلام".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            And His saying “You search the Scriptures, for in them you think you have eternal life; and these are they which testify of Me.” And His saying, “If I do not do the works of My Father, do not believe Me; but if I do, though you do not believe Me, believe the works, that you may know and believe that the Father is in Me, and I in Him."         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله: "فتشوا الكتب لأنكم تظنون أن لكم فيها حياة أبدية. وهي التي تشهد لي". وقوله: "أن كنت لست أعمل أعمال أبي فلا تؤمنوا بي. ولكن إن كنت أعمل فإن لم تؤمنوا بي فآمنوا بالأعمال لكي تعرفوا وتؤمنوا أن الآب فيَّ وأنا فيه".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “And my speech settled on them as dew” which means they longed for His words and for His miracles not to believe but to satisfy their hearts’ desires. They wanted the present not the future and that is why He said, "Most assuredly, I say to you, you seek Me, not because you saw the signs, but because you ate of the loaves and were filled. Do not labor for the food which perishes, but for the food which endures to everlasting life”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ويفرحون إذا كلمتهم" يعني أنهم كانوا يشتهون كلامه ويشتهون أيضا أن يصنع قدامهم الآيات لا ليؤمنوا بل لشهوات قلوبهم لأنهم كانوا مائلين بقلوبهم إلى الحاضرات لا إلى المنتظرات ولذلك قال لهم: "أنتم تطلبونني ليس لأنكم رأيتم آياتٍ بل لأنكم أكلتم من الخبز فشبعتم. أعملوا لا للطعام البائد بل للطعام الباقي للحياة الأبدية".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “If I mocked at them, they did not believe it” meaning that the Lord condescended to the Jews and spoke gently with them. He was not like their teachers but they still wanted to stone Him. Therefore, He told them, "Many good works I have shown you from My Father. For which of those works do you stone Me?"         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وإذا ضَحكت معهم لم يُصدقوني" يعني بهذا أن الرب كان يتنازل مع شعب اليهود ويكلمهم بألطف ما يكون من الكلام ولم يكن معهم كمعلميهم. ومع ذلك كانوا يريدون رجمه. فكان يقول لهم: أعمالاً كثيرة حسنة أريتكم من عند أبى. بسبب أي عمل منها ترجمونني".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, "But now they mock at me, men younger than I” referring to the soldiers of Herod and Pilate and the servants of the priests whom He tolerated willingly.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أما الآن فقد هزأ بي أصاغر الناس" يعني بهذا عن جُند هيرودس وبيلاطس وخدام الكهنة الذين أحتمل منهم المُخلِّص ما فعلوه من سؤ أعمالهم بإرادته.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Whose fathers I disdained to put with the dogs of my flock,” referring to the Jewish priests and teachers.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وقد علِمت شيئا من رذائل أبائهم" يعنى بهذا عن كهنة اليهود ومُعلمي الناموس. فأنه قد رذلهم ونزع كهنوتهم وأعطاه للمؤمنين به.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He had disdained them, took away their priesthood, and gave it to the believers. They put heavy burdens on the people and forbade them from committing the sins that they themselves were submerged in. He mentioned “the dogs of the flock” because these dogs are trained to restore the wandering sheep to the flock by scaring the sheep without hurting them. They watch the flock all night lest the sheep be stolen or lose their way. If the brainless brutes can do this and the keepers of Israel cannot, then the dogs are better than them.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "الذين كنت آنف أن أجعل آباءهم مع كلاب الرعاة" يعني بهذا عن رعاة إسرائيل الذين كانوا يُحمِّلون الناس أحمالا ثقيلة وينهونهم عن خطايا هم غارقون فيها. وذكر كلاب الرعاة لأن هذه الكلاب لأجل تدريبها مع أصحابها إذا رأوا واحداً من القطيع قد ضل فيقاطعونه من هنا وهناك ويخيفونه من غير أن يؤذوه حتى يردوه إلى القطيع. ثم أنهم يسهرون على القطيع ليلاً لئلا يُختَطَف أو يَضل منه شيء. فإذا كانت الوحوش التي لا عقل لها ولا نُطق والمعتادة بطبعها أكل لحم الحيوان والإنسان يحصل منها ما ذكر. ورعاة إسرائيل على عكس ذلك فقد فضل الكلاب عليهم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “They shouted at them as at a thief” referring to their turning on him in front of Pilate shouting “crucify him”. He called them thieves because thieves have a lot of bad qualities as the Lord explained, “The thief does not come except to steal, and to kill, and to destroy.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "قام عليَّ اللصوص" يعنى أنهم قاموا عليه أمام بيلاطس وصاحوا بأجمعهم أصلبه. وأسماهم باللصوص لأن اللص فيه رذائل كثيرة كما قال الرب له المجد: "السارق لا يأتي إلا ليسرق ويذبح ويَهلك".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “They had to live in the clefts of the valleys, In caves of the earth and the rocks,” referring to their rock-like, hardened hearts.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "مساكنهم مغائر الصخور" يعني بذلك قلوبهم الحجرية التي لا تلين.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “They were sons of fools,” because they are the sons of priests and teachers who were rejected by God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "الأبناء الغير المتأدبين" فهو كما قلنا أنهم أبناء الكهنة والمعلمين الذين رذلهم الرب وأبعدهم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Yes, sons of vile men; They were scourged from the land,” meaning that their flame of faith had been put out and their fire turned into ashes because they followed their own whims, whereas the flame of belief in Christ had been ignited in the hearts of the believers who were advised by Paul, “Do not quench the Spirit.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أصحاب الاسم المرذول الذين طُفِيءَّ مجدهم وبُطلت ذبيحتهم من الأرض" يعني بهذا أن نار الإيمان التي فيهم قد انطفأت وبَردت كالرماد لسَيرِهم حسب أهوائهم. واشتعلت نار الإيمان بالمسيح في قلوب المؤمنين به الذين يوصيهم بولس الرسول بقوله: "لا تطفئوا الروح".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “They abhor me, they keep far from me” which means that they hated him because they did not approve of His teachings which held them accountable for their evil doings. As Solomon, the wise had said, “Do not correct a scoffer, lest he hate you; Rebuke a wise man, and he will love you.” When He said, “they keep far from me” He was referring to their lack of faith in Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أَبغَضوني وابتَعدوا عني" يعني بهذا أنهم أبغضوه لأن هواه لم يوافق هواهم ولأنه كان يُبكِّتهم على أعمالهم الشريرة فكانوا لجهلهم يُبغضونه كما يقول سليمان الحكيم: "لا توَّبخْ مُستهزئاً لئلا يُبغضك. وبِّخ حكيماً فيُحِبك". وقوله "ابتعَدوا عني" فهو عدم إيمانهم به.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “They do not hesitate to spit in my face” referring to the events of the life giving passion of Christ. The Holy Spirit revealed this to the prophet, “And now I am their taunting song; Yes, I am their byword.” They used to respect Jesus, calling him Rabbi and wanted to enthrone Him. They even spread their clothes under the feet of His colt but during the week of His passion, they were no longer ashamed, their hearts were blinded, they were drunk with envy and they satisfied their hearts’ desires, which was what their father, Satan, had advised them to do. The Lord bore all this to fulfill the prophecies and achieve His plans. We ask Him to show us mercy and to forgive us our sins and keep us up till the end. Glory be to Him forever. Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ولم يوَّقروني وبَصقوا في وجهي" يعني بهذا ما جرى وقت آلام المُخلِّص المُحييَة. وقد أعلَم الروح القدس النبي بما سيكون في ذلك الوقت. وقوله: "لم يوَّقروني" لأنهم قبل ذلك الوقت كانوا يُبجلونه ويُسمونه بالمعلم الصالح وطلبوا أن يجعلوه ملكاً. وفرشوا ثيابهم تحت حوافر مركوبه. وفي ذلك الوقت (وقت الآلام) كشفوا عن أعينهم بُرقُع الحياء وعَميت قلوبهم وقد أسكرهم الحسد. وعَملوا ما اشتهت قلوبهم. وما أشار عليهم به أبوهم الشيطان. وقد احتمل الرب كل ذلك منهم لإتمام تدبيره ونبوات الأنبياء. فنسأل من رحمته أن يغفر لنا خطايانا ويحفظنا إلى المُنتهى. له المجد إلى الأبد آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>