<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik" pascha="true" fixeddatedocument="true">   <forceseason id="Feasts ^ FeastsOfTheLordPeriods ^ MinorFeastsOfTheLord ^ CovenantThursday ^ Fasts ^ PaschaWeek ^ WatosDays ^ Weekdays ^ Thursdays ^ FuneralTune ^ SeasonOfAirAndFruits">      <Title>         <language id="English">Covenant Thursday Eve (The Sixth Hour)</language><language id="Indonesian">Malam Kamis Perjanjian  <div>(The Sixth Hour)</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">ليلة خميس العهد (الساعة السادسة)</language>         <language id="Coptic">Pie~jwrh m~Ptiou n~nis] (}ajp 6)</language>      </Title>            <role id="Priest">         <insertdocument path="include/KhenEfranAmen"/>                  <text>            <language id="English">               The prophecies of the Sixth Hour of the eve of Thursday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Nubuat-nubuat dari Jam Keenam Malam Kamis Perjanjian pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               نبوات الساعة السادسة، من ليلة الخميس من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Amos 3:1-11</language><language id="Indonesian">Amos 3:1-11</language>               <language id="Arabic">عاموس 3: 1-11</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/prophecyIntro/Amos"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Cwtem e~paicaji vai e~taicaji m~mof e~jen y/nou p~/i m~p~Iicra/l: nem qa vul/ niben e~taie~nou e~bolqen p~kahi n~,/mi eujwm~moc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  O house of Israel, hear this word the Lord has spoken against you, against the whole family which I brought up from the land of Egypt, saying,               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dengarlah firman ini, yang diucapkan TUHAN tentang kamu, hai orang Israel, tentang segenap kaum yang telah Kutuntun keluar dari tanah Mesir, bunyinya:</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أسمعوا هذا القول الذى تكلمت به عليكم يا بيت اسرائيل وعلى كل القبائل التى أخرجتها من أرض مصر قائلاً:               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je t~l/n n~ywten aicouen y/nou e~bol qen nivul/ t/rou n~te p~kahi: eybe vai eie~[i m~psis e~jen y/nou t/rou n~netennobi t/rou.                </language>               <language id="English">                  "Out of all the families of the. earth, I have especially known you. Therefore I shall exact vengeance upon you for all your sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Hanya kamu yang Kukenal dari segala kaum di muka bumi, sebab itu Aku akan menghukum kamu karena segala kesalahanmu.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إياكم عرفت من بين جميع قبائل الأرض، فلذلك أنتقم منكم عن جميع خطاياكم.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  An eue~mosi n~je c~nau eucop n~toustem couen noue~r/ou e~p~t/rf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  If two people walk together, will each one not come to know the other?               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Berjalankah dua orang bersama-sama, jika mereka belum berjanji?               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أيسير اثنان معاً و لا يعرف بعضهما البعض قط؟               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  An efe~hemhem n~je oumoui~ e~bolqen ouiahss/n m~mon tefjorjf: an e~re oumac m~moui~ ]n~tefc~m/ ebolqen pefb/b e~p~t/rf afstemhwlem n~ouh~li.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Will a lion roar from his lair in the forest if he has no prey? Will a lion's whelp cry out from his den if he has nothing?               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mengaumkah seekor singa di hutan, apabila tidak mendapat mangsa? Bersuarakah singa muda dari sarangnya, jika belum menangkap apa-apa?</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أيزمجر الأسد فى الغابة وليس له فريسة؟ أيطلق الشبل صوته من عرينه قط، إلا إذا خطف شيئا؟                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  A~n efehei n~je ouhal/t hijen pikahi m~mon v/etjwrj e~rof: an e~re oujorjc swpi hijen pkahi n~ouesen tahe hli.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Will a bird fall to the earth without a fowler? Will a snare be sprung if it has caught nothing?               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Jatuhkah seekor burung ke dalam perangkap di tanah, apabila tidak ada jerat terhadapnya? Membingkaskah perangkap dari tanah, jika tidak ditangkapnya sesuatu?               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أيسقط طير على الأرض من غير قانص؟ أيكون فخ على الأرض من غير أن يصيد شيئاً ؟               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  An e~re oucalpigx mou] qen oubaki ouoh n~te sten oulaoc nousp: an e~re oukakia~ swpi qen oubaki m~pe~P[oic yamioc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  If a trumpet is sounded in a city, will not the people be alarmed? If evil should be in a city, has not the Lord brought it?               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Adakah sangkakala ditiup di suatu kota, dan orang-orang tidak gemetar? Adakah terjadi malapetaka di suatu kota, dan TUHAN tidak melakukannya?</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أيصوت بوق فى مدينة ولا يهلع الشعب؟ هل تحدث بلية فى مدينة والرب لم يصنعها ؟               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je ou/i n~nefi~ri n~ouhwb n~je N~[oic Vnou] afstem [wrp e~bol n~tefc~bw nnefe~biaik m~p~rov/t/c:                </language>               <language id="English">                  For the Lord God does nothing unless He reveals instruction to His servants the prophets.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sungguh, Tuhan ALLAH tidak berbuat sesuatu tanpa menyatakan keputusan-Nya kepada hamba-hamba-Nya, para nabi.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إن الرب الإله لا يصنع أمراً إلا ويعلن تأديبه لعبيده الآنبياء،                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Oumoui~ afws e~bol nim pe etefnaerho] an: P[oic Vnou] afcaji nim pe e~tefnaer p~rov/teuin an:               </language>               <language id="English">                  A lion shall roar, and who will not fear? The Lord God speaks, and who will not prophesy?               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Singa telah mengaum, siapakah yang tidak takut? Tuhan ALLAH telah berfirman, siapakah yang tidak bernubuat?"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أسد قد زمجر فمن لا يخاف، الرب الإله تكلم فمن لا يتنبأ؟               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Matame ni,wra etqen Niaccurioc nem hijen ni,wra n~te,/mi ouoh a~joc:                </language>               <language id="English">                  "Proclaim it in the regions among the Assyrians and to the lands of Egypt, and say,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Siarkanlah di dalam puri di Asyur dan di dalam puri di tanah Mesir serta katakan:                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أخبروا كور الآشوريين وكور مصر وقولوا:                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je ywou] hijen p~twou n~t~Camaria~: ouoh a~nau e~hans~v/ri euos qen tecm/]: nem ]metrefsepjwri e~te n~q/tc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  'Gather yourself to the mountains of Samaria, and behold the many remarkable things in her midst and the oppression that is within her.               </language><language id="Indonesian">"Berkumpullah di gunung-gunung dekat Samaria dan pandanglah kekacauan besar yang ada di tengah-tengahnya dan pemerasan yang ada di kota itu."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  اجتمعوا على جبل السامرة وأنظروا الغرائب الكثيرة التى فى وسطها، والجور الذى فى داخلها،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh m~pece~mi e~n/eynaswpi m~pecm~yo peje P[oic: n/ethioui~ e~qoun n~ou[i n~jonc nem outalepwrea~ qen nou,wra:               </language>               <language id="English">                  She does not know the things that will come against her,' says the Lord, 'she stores up injustice and misery in her lands.'               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>"Mereka tidak tahu berbuat jujur," demikianlah firman TUHAN, "mereka itu yang menimbun kekerasan dan aniaya di dalam purinya."</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولم تعلم ما يكون أمامها يقول الرب. بما أنهم يكنزون ظلماً وشقاء فى كورهم،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eybe vai naine n/e~tefjw mmwou n~je Po#c# Vnou]: je Turoc pekahi e~te mpekw] efeswf: ouoh efe~i~ni e~pec/t n~je tejom e~bol n~q/].               </language>               <language id="English">                  "Therefore thus says the Lord God: "O Tyre, your land round about you shall be made desolate, and your strength shall be sapped from you.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebab itu beginilah firman Tuhan ALLAH: "Musuh akan ada di sekeliling negeri, kekuatanmu akan ditanggalkannya dari padamu, dan purimu akan dijarahi!"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلذلك هذا ما يقوله الرب الإله لصور: إن أرضك التى حولك تخرب وقوتك تسقط منك.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ProphecyConclusion"/>         </section>      </role>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Introduction to the Paschal Praise</language><language id="Indonesian">Pendahuluan Pujian Paskah</language>            <language id="Arabic">مقدمة تسبحة البصخة</language>         </Title>               <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PropheciesConclusion"/>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The doxology of the Sixth Hour of the eve of Thursday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Doksologi dari Jam Keenam Malam Kamis Perjanjian pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  تسبحة الساعة السادسة، من ليلة الخميس من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="include/LordsPrayerNoTitle"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/Doxology.2"/>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Psalm 139:1-2</language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur 139:1-2</language>               <language id="Arabic">مزمور 139: 1-2</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PsalmOfDavid"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nahmet P[oic cabol n~ourwmi efhwou: e~bolha ourwmi n~ref[in~jonc matoujoi.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Deliver me, O Lord, from the evil man, Rescue me from the unjust man,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Luputkanlah aku, ya TUHAN, dari pada manusia jahat, </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  نجنى يارب من إنسان شرير ومن رجل ظالم أنقذنى.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  N/e~tauco[ni n~han [in~jonc qen pouh/t: m~pie~hoou t/rf aucob] n~hanbwtc: all/louia.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Who devised wrongdoing in their heart; They arrayed themselves for war all day long: Alleluia.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  yang merancang kejahatan di dalam hati, dan setiap hari menghasut-hasut perang: Alleluia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  الذين تفكروا بالظلم فى قلبهم النهار كله كانوا يستعدون للقتال: الليلويا.               </language>            </text>         </section>      </role>               <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">John 12:36-43</language><language id="Indonesian">Yohanes 12:37-43</language>            <language id="Arabic">يوحنا 12: 36-43</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/KeEperto"/>         <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroJohn"/>         <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nai e~taf jotou n~je I/couc afsenaf af,opf e~bol harwou. Naim/s de m~m/ni afaitou mpoumy~o e~bol m~pounah] e~rof:                </language>               <language id="English">                  These things Jesus spoke, and departed, and was hidden from them. But although He had done so many signs before them, they did not believe in Him,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan meskipun Yesus mengadakan begitu banyak mukjizat di depan mata mereka, namun mereka tidak percaya kepada-Nya,                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  قال يسوع هذا ثم مضى وتوارى عنهم، ومع هذه الآيات الكثيرة التى صنعها أمامهم لم يؤمنوا به،                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Hina n~tefjwk e~bol n~je p~caji n~/~cai~ac pip~rov/t/c v/e~tafjof je P[oic nim pe e~tafnah] e~tenc~m/: ouoh p~swbs m~P[oic e~taf[wrp e~nim.                </language>               <language id="English">                  That the word of Isaiah the prophet might be fulfilled, which he spoke: “Lord, who has believed our report? And to whom has the arm of the Lord been revealed?”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  supaya genaplah firman yang disampaikan oleh nabi Yesaya: "Tuhan, siapakah yang percaya kepada pemberitaan kami? Dan kepada siapakah tangan kekuasaan Tuhan dinyatakan?"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ليتم كلام أشعياء النبى الذى قاله: يارب من صدق خبرنا. ولمن أعلنت ذراع الرب.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eybe vai ne m~mons~jom m~mwou e~nah]: je afjoc on n~je ?ca/~ac: Je afywm n~noubal: ouoh afywm m~pouh/t: hina n~tous~temnau n~noubal: ouoh n~toustem ka] qen pouh/t: ouoh n~toukotou haroi n~tatoujwou:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Therefore they could not believe, because Isaiah said again: “He has blinded their eyes and hardened their hearts, Lest they should see with their eyes, Lest they should understand with their hearts and turn, So that I should heal them.”               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Karena itu mereka tidak dapat percaya, sebab Yesaya telah berkata juga: <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">"Ia telah membutakan mata dan mendegilkan hati mereka, supaya mereka jangan melihat dengan mata, dan menanggap dengan hati, lalu berbalik, sehingga Aku menyembuhkan mereka."</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ومن أجل هذا لم يكونوا ليقدروا أن يؤمنوا لأن أشعياء قال أيضاً: قد طمس عيونهم وقفل قلوبهم لئلا يبصروا بعيونهم ويفهموا بقلوبهم ويرجعوا إلى فأشفيهم.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nai afjotou n~je ?ca/~ac je afnau e~p~w~ou m~Vnou] ouoh afcaji eyb/tf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  These things Isaiah said when he saw His glory and spoke of Him.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Hal ini dikatakan oleh Yesaya, karena ia telah melihat kemuliaan-Nya dan telah berkata-kata tentang Dia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  قال أشعياء هذا لأنه رأى مجد الله وتكلم عنه،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  O~mwc men]oi oum/s e~bolqen nikear,wn aunah] e~rof: alla nauouwnh m~mof e~bolan pe eybe nivariceoc: je n~nouaitou n~a~pocunagwgoc:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Nevertheless even among the rulers many believed in Him, but because of the Pharisees they did not confess Him, lest they should be put out of the synagogue;                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Namun banyak juga di antara pemimpin yang percaya kepada-Nya, tetapi oleh karena orang-orang Farisi mereka tidak mengakuinya berterus terang, supaya mereka jangan dikucilkan.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ومع ذلك فإن كثيراً من الرؤساء أيضاً آمنوا به، ولكنهم لسبب الفريسيين لم يعترفوا به لئلا يصيروا خارج المجمع                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Aumenre p~w~ou gar n~nirwmi mallon e~hote p~w~ou m~Vnou].               </language>               <language id="English">                  For they loved the praise of men more than the praise of God.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebab mereka lebih suka akan kehormatan manusia dari pada kehormatan Allah.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لأنهم أحبوا مجد الناس أكثر من مجد الله.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/BowDownBeforeTheHolyGospel"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelConclusionEve"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Exposition</language><language id="Indonesian">Komentari</language>            <language id="Arabic">الطرح</language>         </Title>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The exposition of the Sixth Hour hour of the eve of Thursday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Komentari dari Malam Kamis Perjanjian pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طرح الساعة السادسة، من ليلة الخميس من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  Isaiah the prophet—by the Spirit—chastizes the sons of Israel for their foolishness and rebukes them outright because of the vileness of their deeds and their sins.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Nabi Yesaya—melalui Roh—mengecam bangsa Israel karena kebodohan mereka dan menegur mereka sekaligus karena kekejian perbuatan dan dosa mereka.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أشعياء النبى يصرخ بالروح نحو الشعب الجاهل بنى اسرائيل، يبكتهم بغير محاباة من أجل دنس أعمالهم وآثامهم.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  They rejected the miracles that Immanuel made, rejected His words full of grace and leaned towards myths and vagaries and rejected the glory of His divinity.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mereka menolak banyaknya mukjizat yang dilakukan Imanuel, menolak perkataan-Nya yang penuh kasih karunia, dan condong kepada mitos serta hal-hal yang tidak masuk akal, serta menolak kemuliaan keilahian-Nya.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لما ظهر عمانوئيل وصنع أعمالاً تبهر العقول، فتعدوا أقواله المملوءة نعمة ومالوا إلى الخرافات والأعمال الباطلة، وجحدوا مجد لاهوته،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  O great prophet (Isaiah), chastise these disobedient children and fruitless trees for they have emulated their fathers and followed on their heels: O Lord who believes our word?               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Ya nabi besar (Yesaya), hajarlah anak-anak yang tidak taat dan pohon-pohon yang tidak berbuah ini karena mereka telah mengikuti jejak bapa mereka: Ya Tuhan, siapa yang percaya kepada pemberitaan kami?               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أعنى الأبناء المرذولين والزرع الغير مثمر، بكت رأيهم أيها النبى العظيم، لأنهم تشبهوا بآبائهم وكملوا مكاييلهم فقال: يارب من صدق خبرنا؟               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  And Your arm, O Lord, to whom has it been announced? The voice of the Lord is His only-begotten Son who appeared in the flesh to the sons of Israel.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan kuasa-Mu, ya Tuhan, kepada siapa hal itu disampaikan? Suara Tuhan adalah Putra Tunggal-Nya yang menampakkan diri dalam rupa manusia kepada umat Israel.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وذراعك يارب لمن أعلنت؟ إن صوت الرب هو إبنه الوحيد الذى تراءى بالجسد لبنى اسرائيل                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  He showed in them His mercy and His justice and nevertheless they did not obey Him and did not believe in Him.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dia menunjukkan kepada mereka belas kasihan dan keadilan-Nya, namun mereka tidak menaati-Nya dan tidak percaya kepada-Nya.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وعدله ورحمته أظهرهما فيهم، ومع هذا لم يطيعوا ولم يؤمنوا به.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  How could they believe: Isaiah prophesied about them and said: I blind their eyes, harden their hearts, deafen their ears and their understanding altogether.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Bagaimana mereka bisa percaya: Yesaya bernubuat tentang mereka dan berkata: Aku membutakan mata mereka, mengeraskan hati mereka, menulikan telinga dan pengertian mereka sama sekali.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  كيف يؤمنون وأشعياء سبق فنطق من أجلهم هكذا قائلاً: إنه أطمس عيونهم وبلد قلوبهم وثقل آذانهم وأفهامهم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  Listen O Israel; no one else will save you from God's wrath but Jesus the Savior of the world, He who made the two into one by His Incarnation.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dengarkanlah, hai Israel; tidak ada seorang pun yang akan menyelamatkanmu dari murka Allah, kecuali Yesus, Juruselamat dunia, Dia yang membuat dua menjadi satu melalui Inkarnasi-Nya.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أسمع يا اسرائيل، ليس آخر يقوم يخلص شعبك من قبله إلا يسوع مخلص العالم الذى جعل الإثنين واحداً بتجسده.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  The light has come to His own and His own loved the darkness and the Gentiles accepted His commandments and became His nation everywhere.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Terang itu telah datang kepada milik kepunyaan-Nya, tetapi orang-orang kepunyaan-Nya mencintai kegelapan, namun bangsa-bangsa lain yang tidak percaya menerima perintah-perintah-Nya dan menjadi umat-Nya di segala tempat. </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  جاء النور إلى خاصته وخاصته لم تقبله، بل أحبوا الظلمة والشعوب الغريبة قبلت وصاياه وصارت له شعباً مجتمعاً فى كل مكان،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  They experience His mercy and His immeasurable grace that He bestowed on them.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Mereka mengalami belas kasih dan anugerah-Nya yang tak terukur yang dilimpahkan-Nya kepada mereka.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وعرفوا رحمته وغزير نعمته التى أفاضها عليهم كصلاحه.               </language>            </text>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ExpositionConclusion"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/EveningLitaniesAndConclusionLink"/>   </forceseason></document>