<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Gospels         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير الأناجيل         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            At the time when Jesus, God incarnate, was on earth, the Jews were under the rule of the Romans. Pontius Pilate was their governor as representative of the Roman Emperor, Tiberius. When the Jews arrested Jesus, brought Him to the High Priest’s house at night, and condemned Him to death, they could have executed their judgment. However, fearing the anger of the Jewish people, they decided to deliver Him to Pilate to rid themselves of the responsibility of killing Him, “And when they had bound Him, they led Him away and delivered Him to Pontius Pilate the governor”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كان اليهود في الزمن الذي ظهر فيه المسيح على الأرض خاضعين للحكم الروماني. وكان بيلاطس البنطي والياً عليهم من قبل طيباريوس قيصر ملك الرومان. فلما قَبض اليهود على السيد المسيح وجاءوا به إلى دار رئيس الكهنة ليلا وقضوا عليه بالموت. وقد كان يُمكنهم تنفيذ ما قضوا به إلا أنهم خوفاً من هياج الشعب ضدهم وليلقوا تبعة موته عنهم، انتهت مشورتهم إلى تسليمه لبيلاطس الوالي "فأوثقوه ومضوا به ودفعوه إلى بيلاطس البنطي الوالي".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            This occurred in the morning. “But they themselves did not go into the Praetorium, lest they should be defiled, but that they might eat the Passover.” Pilate therefore came out to them and asked them what they wanted. They answered that they had come with this guilty man who the Sanhedrin had condemned to die by crucifixion by. Pilate asked them, "What accusation do you bring against this Man?" They answered, "We found this fellow perverting the nation, and forbidding them to pay taxes to Caesar, saying that He Himself is Christ, a King."         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان ذلك في الصباح. "ولم يدخلوا هم إلى دار الولاية لكي لا يتنجسوا فيأكلون الفصح". فخرج إليهم بيلاطس وسألهم ماذا تريدون؟ فقالوا جئنا بهذا الإنسان المذنب وقد حَكمَ عليه مَجمعْ السنهدريم بالموت صلباً. فقال لهم: "أية شكاية تُقدمون على هذا الإنسان". فقالوا له "إننا وجدنا هذا يَفسد الأمة ويَمنع أن تُعطىَّ الجزية لقيصر قائلا أنه هو مسيح ملك".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Their accusation had two-fold. First, perverting the nation, which is obviously false because the Lord Christ always promoted love, to the forgiveness of trespasses and bearing offenses. Since Pilate had already heard about the teachings of Christ in this regard, he gave no attention to the first accusation. The second fold of the accusation can also be divided into two points. First, that He was encouraging the people not to pay taxes to Caesar. This was a lie since Pilate heard that Jesus said, “Render therefore to Caesar the things that are Caesar's,” The second point regarding the “King” terrified Pilate and concerned him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وتشتمل هذه الشكاية على تهمتين: الأولى إفساده الأمة وهذه باطلة من طبعها لأن السيد المسيح كان دائما يحث على المحبة والإغضاء عن الإساءة وتحمل الأذى. ولما كان بيلاطس بالطبع قد سمع بعض تعاليمه بهذا الخصوص فقد أغضى عن هذه التهمة ولم يعرها أذناً صاغية. والتهمة الثانية تحتوي على فقرتين: الأولي منهما أنه يمنع أن تعطى الجزية لقيصر. وقد كذبوا فيما ادعوا لأن بيلاطس قد سمع عنه أنه قال لهم: "أعطوا ما لقيصر لقيصر". وأما الفقرة الثانية الخاصة بالملك فهذه قد أرعبت بيلاطس وجعلته أن يهتم بها.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Then Pilate entered the Praetorium again, called Jesus, and said to Him, "Are You the King of the Jews?" Jesus answered him, "Are you speaking for yourself about this, or did others tell you this concerning Me?" Pilate answered, "Am I a Jew? Your own nation and the chief priests have delivered You to me. What have You done?" Jesus answered, "My kingdom is not of this world” which means that Jesus’ kingdom is a spiritual kingdom in which He rules over the hearts. “Pilate therefore said to Him, "Are You a king then?" Jesus answered, "You say rightly that I am a king.” Because I am truly King, I reign over the believers with faith and grace and I lead them to the kingdom of Heaven.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "ثم دخل بيلاطس إلى دار الولاية ودعا يسوع وقال له: أأنت ملك اليهود. أجابه يسوع أمن ذاتك تقول هذا أم آخرون قالوا لك عني. أجابه بيلاطس ألعلي أنا يهودي. أمُتك ورؤساء الكهنة أسلموك إليَّ. أجابه يسوع مملكتي ليست من هذا العالم" وإنما هي مملكة روحية أسود بها على القلوب. "فقال بيلاطس أفأنت إذن ملك؟ أجاب يسوع أنت تقول أني ملك" لأنني حقا كذلك فإني أملك على المؤمنين بالإيمان والنعمة وأقودهم إلى مملكة السماء.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And while He was being accused by the chief priests and elders, He answered nothing.” To fulfill the prophecy “But I, like a deaf man, do not hear; And I am like a mute who does not open his mouth. Thus I am like a man who does not hear, And in whose mouth is no response.” And the saying, “He was led as a lamb to the slaughter, And as a sheep before its shearers is silent, So He opened not His mouth.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبينما كان رؤساء الكهنة والشيوخ يشتكون عليه لم يُجب بشيء" ليتم قول الكتاب "وأما أنا فكأصم: لا أسمع. وكأبكم: لا يفتح فاه. وأكون مثل إنسان لا يسمع". وقوله: "ولم يفتح فاه كشاة تُساق إلى الذبح وكنعجة صامتة أمام جازيها فلم يفتح فاه".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “So Pilate said to the chief priests and the crowd, "I find no fault in this Man." He said this when Jesus told him that His kingdom is a spiritual one and “is not of this world.” However, the Jews were even fiercer, saying, "He stirs up the people, teaching throughout all Judea, beginning from Galilee to this place.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "وقال بيلاطس لرؤساء الكهنة والجموع إني لا أجد علة في هذا الإنسان". (قال ذلك لما علم من يسوع أن مملكته روحية و"ليست من هذا العالم"). أما رؤساء الكهنة "فكانوا يُشددون قائلين أنه يُهيج الشعب وهو يُعلم في كل اليهودية مبتدئا من الجليل إلى هنا.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            When Pilate heard “Galilee,” he asked if the Man were a Galilean." When he realized that Jesus is under Herod's jurisdiction, he wanted to save himself from this critical situation for he was caught between two choices either he releases Him so they report him to Caesar or condemn Him to death with the fear that if Caesar finds out He is innocent he will deal with him harshly. Therefore, when he heard He is a Galilean, he rejoiced and sent Him to Herod, who was also in Jerusalem at that time. Now when Herod saw Jesus, he was exceedingly glad; for he had desired for a long time to see Him, because he had heard many things about Him, and had hoped to see Him do some miracles done. However, the Lord had no purpose except to die for us. He also knew that Herod just wanted to see a miracle for amusement. Herod had no interest in the truth; otherwise, he would have accepted it from John the Baptist. The Lord did not perform any miracles for him. “Then he questioned Him with many words, but He answered him nothing.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فلما سمع بيلاطس ذِكر الجليل سأل هل الرجل جليلي. وحين علم أنه من سلطنة هيرودس" أراد أن يبرئ نفسه ويُخلصها من هذا المأزق الحرج لأنه كان بين عاملين: إن أطلقه فيشكونه لقيصر، وإن حَكم عليه بالموت فيخاف أن يعلم القيصر ببراءته فيناله منه ما يناله ولذلك فإنه لما سمع أنه من الجليل فرح جداً و"أرسله إلى هيرودس" رئيس ربع الجليل وكان يومئذ "في أورشليم" ليحضر عيد الفصح. "وأما هيرودس فلما رأى يسوع فرح جداً لأنه كان يريد من زمان طويل أن يراه لسماعه عنه أشياء كثيرة وتَرجى أن يرى آية تُصنع منه". فلأن الرب لم يكن له غرض سوى الموت عنا ولأنه يعلم أيضاً أن هيرودس يريد أن يلهو بما يراه من الآيات لأنه لو كان قابلاً للحق لقبِلَهُ من يوحنا المعمدان. لم يصنع أمامه آية "وسأله بكلام كثير فلم يجبه بشيء".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            When the chief priests witnessed this, they were happy, “and vehemently accused Him.” Hoping that Herod would sentence Him but he refused. Then either to revenge himself of Jesus because He had refused to perform a miracle in front of him or to please the Jews, he “treated Him with contempt and mocked Him, arrayed Him in a gorgeous robe, and sent Him back to Pilate,” This proves that Herod also found Him blameless fulfilling the prophet’s words, “The kings of the earth set themselves, And the rulers take counsel together, Against the Lord and against His Anointed,” “Kings of the earth” refers to Pilate and Herod. “The rulers” refers to the chief Priests of the Jews and their conspiracy against God and His anointed One because every insult addressed to the Son is also addressed to the Father as He said, glory be to Him, “He who does not honor the Son does not honor the Father who sent Him.” Pilate and Herod were sworn enemies but by sending Christ to one another, they were reconciled, “That very day Pilate and Herod became friends.” The Lord came to the world to reconcile man with his God and bring peace among kings.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فلما رأى رؤساء الكهنة سكوت يسوع فرحوا وأخذوا "يشتكون عليه باشتداد". وكان غرضهم من هيرودس أن يحكم عليه ولكنه أبى ذلك. وإنما أراد أن يُشفي غليله منه لأنه لم يُجبه إلى طلبه من جهة ويرضي اليهود من جهة أخرى. "فاحتقره... مع عسكره واستهزأ به وألبسه لباساً لامعاً ورده إلى بيلاطس". وهذه دلالة على أنه وجده بريئاً. وقد تم قول النبي: "قام ملوك الأرض وتآمر الرؤساء معاً على الرب ومسيحه". فقوله: "ملوك الأرض" يريد بهم بيلاطس وهيرودس. والرؤساء يريد بهم رؤساء كهنة اليهود وتآمرهم على الرب وعلى مسيحه لأن كل إساءة إلى الابن هي لأبيه كما قال له المجد: "من لا يُكرِّم الابن لا يُكرِّم الآب الذي أرسله". ولأنه كان يوجد بين بيلاطس وهيرودس عداوة شديدة فبتبادل المسيح بينهما حصل الصلح وصارا "صديقين مع بعضهما". لأن الرب لهذا جاء إلى العالم أن يكون سبب الصلح بين آدم وخالقه وبين الملوك وبعضهم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Then Judas, His betrayer, seeing that He had been condemned, was remorseful and brought back the thirty pieces of silver to the chief priests and elders, Saying, "I have sinned by betraying innocent blood,"” revealing his horrible deed and the error of the Jews when they condemned Jesus who was innocent, “And they said, "What is that to us? You see to it!" Then he threw the pieces of silver in the temple then departed, and went and hanged himself.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "حينئذ لما رأى يهوذا الذي أسلمه أنه قد دينَ نَدمَ ورد الثلاثين من الفضة إلى الكهنة والشيوخ. قائلا قد أخطأت إذ سَلَّمت دماً بريئاً". وقد أوضح بذلك فظاعة الأمر الذي أتاه وغَلط اليهود في حكمهم على يسوع وهو برئ. "فقالوا ماذا علينا. أنت أبصَر. فطَرح الفضة في الهيكل وأنصرف ثم مضى وخَنق نفسه".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            It is understood that Judas was one of the twelve disciples and was responsible for the moneybox. So when the devil noted Judas’ love for silver, he made him steal from the box that was in his possession, to the extent that he was upset at the woman who rubbed the feet of the Lord with an expensive perfume wishing that the cost of the perfume would have gotten into the box so that he could dip into it. When the Lord rebuked the disciples who agreed with Judas’ corrupt opinion, Judas resented the Lord even more and hated Him enough to deliver Him into the hands of the Jews. But when he saw Him condemned to death he regretted what he had done and returned the silver pieces. When the devil sensed his regret, he made him think that his deed could not be forgiven except if he killed himself. He therefore made for himself a hanging device on a high place. He put the rope around his neck and hanged himself but the rope did not tighten enough around his neck to kill him. He continued to breathe in but not out. He became inflated and was in a very miserable condition. Because of his disturbance, the rope broke and he fell to the ground, “and falling headlong, he burst open in the middle and all his entrails gushed out.” He lost his life on earth and in the age to come and fulfilled the words of the Bible, “When he is judged, let him be found guilty, And let his prayer become sin Let his days be few, And let another take his office Let his children be fatherless, And his wife a widow”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والمفهوم أن يهوذا كان ضمن تلاميذ السيد الإثني عشر وكان صندوق النفقة عنده. فلما وجد فيه الشيطان ميلاً إلى محبة الفضة جعله يسرق من الصندوق الذي كان معه حتى أنه تذمر على الإمرأة التي دَهنت قدمي الرب بالطيِب وتمنى لو أنه حصل على هذا المبلغ في الصندوق لينال منه جزء. ولما وبخ السيد بالتلاميذ الذين وافقوه على رأيه الفاسد ازدادت بغضته للسيد بعد المحبة المفرطة تلك البغضة التي جعلته يُسَلم سيده إلى اليهود. ولكنه لما رأى أنهم قد حكموا عليه بالموت. نَدم على فعلهِ وأعاد الفضة إليهم. فلما رأى الشيطان أنه قد ندم جعل في قلبه فكراً بأن لا غفران لذنبه إلا بقتل نفسه. فَعمَل مشنقة لنفسه في مكان عالٍ عن الأرض ثم جعلها في رقبته وتعلق بها. فلم تخنقه خنقاً يوجب الموت وصار يستنشق الهواء ولم يستطع أن يتنفسه صاعداً حتى إنتفخ وصار في كرب شديد ومن كثرة اضطرابه انقطعت به المشنقة فسقط إلى الأرض و"انشقَ من الوسط فانسكَبت أحشاؤه كلها". وهلك من الدهرين. هنا والآتي: وفاتته الحياتان وتمَّ فيه قول الكتاب: "وصلاته فلتكُن خطيئة. لتكن أيامه قليلة ووظيفته ليأخذها آخر. ليكن بنوه أيتاماً وامرأته أرملة".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “But the chief priests took the silver pieces and said, "It is not lawful to put them into the treasury, because they are the price of blood." This verse indicates that the chief Priests of the Jews realized their error and realized that the silver Judas returned could not be accepted as offerings, “And they consulted together and bought with them the potter's field, to bury strangers in it” they did this to hide their evil deed under the pretext of strangers, “Therefore that field has been called the Field of Blood to this day,” because with its price they bought the blood of Christ and killed him. “Then was fulfilled what was spoken by Jeremiah the prophet, saying, "And they took the thirty pieces of silver, the value of Him who was priced, whom they of the children of Israel priced, and gave them for the potter's field, as the Lord directed me."” The prophet had already foretold of this evil that the Jews willingly committed. We ask our Lord to make us always unconfident of ourselves so that we do not fall into sin and that we continuously cling and hold onto the faith in His name and our hope in Him. Glory be to Him Forever Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "فأخذ رؤساء الكهنة الفضة وقالوا لا يحل أن نلقيها في الخزانة لأنها ثمن دمٍ". ومن ذلك نعلم أن رؤساء كهنة اليهود قد شهدوا على أنفسهم بالخطأ وأن الفضة التي أعادها يهوذا لا يحل أن تُجعل في موضع قرابينهم "فتشاوروا واشتروا بها حقل الفخاري مقبرة للغرباء ليستروا عملهم القبيح باسم الغرباء. "لهذا سمى ذلك الحقل حقل الدم إلى هذا اليوم" لأنه بثمنه ابتاعوا دم المسيح وقتلوه. "حينئذ تم ما قيل بأرمياء النبي القائل وأخذوا الثلاثين من الفضة ثمن المُثمَّنْ الذي ثَمَّنوه من بني إسرائيل. وأعطوها عن حقل الفخاري كما أمرني الرب". وقد سبق فقال النبي هذه النبوة عن هذا الشر الذي ارتكبه اليهود بحرِيتهم ونسأل إلهنا أن يجعلنا دائماً غير واثقين من أنفسنا حتى لا نسقط في هاوية الخطيئة وأن نكون دائماً متعلقين به ومتمسكين بالإيمان باسمه والرجاء به، له المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>