<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Jeremiah 22:29-23:6         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            من أرمياء النبي 22: 29 الخ و23: 1 – 6         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Land, land hear the word of the Lord.” The prophet was not speaking to the land but to the people. He ordered them to listen to the word of God uttered on his tongue. He said, “Write you this man an outcast” By “this man” he meant the kings of the Israelites and although he is speaking about one “man” his words apply to all. By describing the men as “outcasts,” he indicates that they sinned against the Lord and that the prophets have testified against them. He said, “for there shall none of his seed at all grow up to sit on the throne of David or as a prince yet in Judah,” meaning that after the coming of Jesus Christ, none of the descendants of the Israelite kings became a king.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "يا أرض يا أرض اسمعي كلمة الرب". لم يخاطب النبي الأرض ولكن سكانها ويأمرهم أن ينصتوا لسماع كلام الله الذي يتكلَّم به على لسانه. قال: "هكذا قال الرب اكتبوا هذا عقيماً" يعني بالرجل ملوك بني إسرائيل وإن كان الكلام عن واحد إلا أنه يعم جميعهم. قال: "رجلاً مرذولاً منبوذاً" أي أنهم عملوا الرذائل قدام الله. وقد شهد عليهم الأنبياء في أقوالهم أنهم أشرار مرذولون. قال: "لا ينجح في أيامه ولا ينمو من ذريته أحد يجلس على كرسي داود ويتسلط من الآن على بيت يهوذا". يعني أنه من بعد مجيء السيد المسيح لم يقُم من نسل ملوك بني إسرائيل ملكاً.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Woe to the shepherds that destroy and scatter the sheep of their pasture!” By shepherds, he meant the priests and the teachers of the Israelites. Because they were spiteful of Jesus Christ, they prevented the people from believing in Him and they asked the people whether they had seen any of the priests or the scribes believing in Him. They added that only those who do not know the book believe in Him. Those who did not listen to them, they expelled from the Synagogue, damning their souls and the souls of their people.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ويل للرعاة الفسدة الذين يُبددون ويُهلكون غنم الرعية". يعنى بالرعاة كهنة ومعلمي شعب إسرائيل فأنهم لحسدهم السيد المسيح كانوا يمنعون الشعب عن الإيمان به وكانوا يقولون لهم هل رأيتم أحداً من الكهنة أو الكتبة آمن به وإنما يؤمن به من لا يعرف الكتاب. والذي لا يسمع لهم يُخرجُونه من مجمعهم. وبذلك قد أهلكوا نفوسهم ونفوس رعيتهم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Therefore thus says the Lord against them that tend my people; You have scattered My sheep, and driven them out, and you have not visited them.” He meant that God would take revenge upon the leaders of the Israelites who spoiled the hearts of their flocks and ordered them to do unrighteous things until the devil was able to capture and scatter them, meanwhile they did not want to go retrieve them and restore them to God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لأجل ذلك هكذا ما يقوله الرب عن الرعاة الذين يرعون شعبي. أنتم قد شتتم غنمي وبددتموها ولم تفتقدوها" يعني أن الله تعالى ينتقم من مقدمي إسرائيل الذين قد افسدوا قلوب رعيتهم وكلفوها بأعمال تخالف الحق حتى اختطفها الشيطان منهم وشتتها. وهم لم يهووا أن يفتقدوها ويردوها إلى معرفة الله تعالى.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “behold I will take vengeance upon you according to your evil practices.” God will punish them for their sins and the sins of their people because they did not follow the divine teachings. He said, “And I will gather in the remnant of my people in every land, whither I have driven them out, and will set them in their pasture; and they shall increase and be multiplied,” which means that when Jesus came, He gathered all the nations who were scattered in the world and they became His people. For He said, “Other sheep I have which are not of this fold them also I must bring and they will hear My voice and there will be one flock and on shepherd”.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "فها أنذا أنتقم منكم على شر أعمالكم يقول الرب". أي أن الله تعالى يجازيهم على خطاياهم وخطايا شعبهم. لأنهم لم يُعلّموُهم التعاليم الإلهية. قال: "وأنا أيضاً أقبل إلىَّ بقية شعبي من جميع الأراضي التي فرقْتَها إليها وآتيِ بها إلى مراتعها فتثمر وتكثر". أي أنه لما أتى السيد المسيح له المجد. جمع كل الأمم المُبدَدينَ في كل الأصقاع. وصاروا شعباً له كما قال له المجد: "ولي خراف أخرَى ليست من هذه الحظيرة ينبغي أن آتي بتلك أيضاً فتسمع صوتي وتكون رعية واحدة وراعٍ واحد".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “And I will raise up shepherds to them, who shall feed them.” By “the shepherds,” He meant the Apostles and their successors whom He appointed shepherds of the believers. He said, “And they shall fear no more, nor be alarmed says the Lord,” because their shepherds are watching over them therefore they are not afraid of being stolen by the wolf of sin: Satan.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وأقيم عليها رعاة يرعونها". يعني بالرعاة إلى التلاميذ وخلفائهم حيث أقامهم رعاة على المؤمنين به. قال: "فلا تخاف بعد ولا ترتعد" لأن رعاتها ساهرين عليها فلا تخاف شر اختطافها في يد ذئب الخطيئة الذي هو إبليس.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Behold the days come, says the Lord that I will perform that good thing which I have promised to the house of Israel and to the house of Judah” By this, He meant the Incarnation of the Word of God from the house of Judah. He said, “I have promised” referring to God’s promise to David the prophet.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وهوذا ستأتي أيام يقول الرب وأقيم الكلمة الصالحة التي قررتها على إسرائيل وبيت يهوذا" يعني بهذا عن تجسد الإله الكلمة من نسل يهوذا. وقوله: "التي قررتها" فيعني عن القسم الذي قاله لداود النبي وهو"أقسم الرب لداود بالحق لا يرجع عنه. من ثمرة بطنك أجعل على كرسيك".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “when I will raise up to David a righteous branch,” This is our Lord Jesus Christ who is the sun of righteousness and who is David’s descendant.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "في تلك الأيام أقيم لداود غصن بر" فهو كما ذكرنا عن سيدنا يسوع المسيح له المجد. أنه شمس البر وأنه من نسل داود.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “and a king shall reign and understand, and shall execute judgment and righteousness on the earth. In his days both Judah shall be saved and Israel shall dwell securely,” meaning that those who believe in Jesus Christ from the Israelites will be saved from their sins and will dwell in paradise with their father Abraham. They will feel secure when exiting this world purified from their sins and to our Lord be the Glory forever. Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وفي أيامه يخلص يهوذا ويسكن إسرائيل آمناً مطمئناً". يعني أن الذين يؤمنون بالسيد المسيح من شعب إسرائيل فأنه يخلصهم من خطاياهم ويسكنهم الفردوس مع أبيهم إبراهيم. ويكونون مطمئنين لخروجهم من هذا العالم وهم أنقياء من خطاياهم. ولربنا المجد دائماً آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>