<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Jeremiah         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأيضاً من أرمياء النبي         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And Jeremiah said to Pashur:” In this verse, Jeremiah did not address one person but the whole nation whom he warned about God, as is apparent in his saying, “You were resisting the truth for sometime with your father” , which means that in their youth they were evil because they followed their fathers’ abominable ways. They fought the truth, ignored the words of the prophets, and banished them and when they grew old; they did not teach their children and expected them to be ignorant. The prophet also prophesied about their children who talked about themselves with satisfaction saying, “If we had lived in the days of our fathers, we would have not been partakers with them in the blood of the prophets” and when the God of all prophets came to them and they saw Him perform great miracles never performed by any other prophet and despite their knowledge of the prophecies of the prophets that He is their Savior they did not believe Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "ثم قال أرمياء لفشحور" لم يقل النبي هذا القول لشخصٍ واحد لكن للأمة التي كان ينذرها عن الله تعالى كما يتضح ذلك من قوله: "أنكم كنتم زماناً مع أبائكم مقاومين للحق" أي أنهم كانوا أشراراً في حال شبوبيتهم إذ كانوا يتبعون أبائهم في الضلال ومقاومة الحق حيث أنهم طرحوا أقوال الأنبياء وراء ظهورهم. وطردوهم. وفي حال كبرهم كانوا ينتظرون جهل أولادهم ولا يُعلمونهم. هذا وقد سبق وتنبأ النبي بهذه النبوة عن أولادهم الآتين بعدهم الذين كانوا يزكون نفوسهم ويقولون: "لو كنا في أيام آبائنا لما شاركناهم في دم الأنبياء". فلما أتاهم رب الأنبياء ورأوا منه من الآيات ما لم يعلَمها أعظم نبي عندهم. ومع علمهم بشهادات الأنبياء بأنه مُخلصهم فقد كفروا به.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “and your children after you, who did sin worse than you.” It is true that those had rejected the prophets and were incredulous of them but these delivered the God of all prophets to death and therefore their sin is the greatest, “For they set a price to him who has no price,” he was referring to Judas when he came and told them, “And said unto them, What will you give me, and I will deliver Him unto you? And they covenanted with him for thirty pieces of silver” and he was satisfied with this amount to fulfill the word of God. Had he asked much more than this, they would have given him but this sum was set to fulfill the prophecies.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وأولادكم الذين يأتون بعدكم هؤلاء الذين يصنعون خطيئة أشر منكم". وبالحقيقة أن أولئك طردوا الأنبياء ولم يؤمنوا بأقوالهم. أما هؤلاء فقد أسلموا رب الأنبياء إلى الموت وعلى ذلك فخطيئتهم أعظم. قال: "لأنهم يثمنون الذي ليس له ثمن". يعني بهذا لما جاءهم يهوذا وقال لهم: "ماذا تريدون أن تعطوني وأنا أُسَلِمه إليكم. فجعلوا له ثلاثين من الفضة". فاقتنع منهم بهذا المقدار ليكمل قول الرب سبحانه على لسان نبيه. وإلا فإنه لو طلب منهم أضعاف هذا المبلغ لأعطوه.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Some interpreters of the Bible said that one of these silver pieces used by the Jews at that time is about 13 cents, which means that Judas received 405 cents and this was the price of a slave.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد ذكر بعض المُفَسِرين عن الثلاثين الفضة أنها ثلاثون شاقلاً وهو نوع من العملة التي كان يتعامل بها اليهود في ذلك الوقت وهو يساوي نحو13 قرشاً ونصف من قرشنا اليوم فيكون مبلغ ما أخذه يهوذا هو 405 قروش وكان هذا ثمن العبد.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Judas sold the Master of the Jews, the Creator of the heaven and earth, the angels and the human race, the visible and the invisible for 30 pieces of silver. The Jews, because of their ignorance, thought that they needed to go to lengths to capture Him. They did not understand that this was God’s plan to save Adam and his offspring and that Jesus had delivered Himself to them out of His own will. They would not have been able to capture Him otherwise. But He had arranged this to save us and sacrifice Himself for us out of His mercy.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فبهذا المبلغ قد باع يهوذا سيده لليهود وأخذ ثمن الذي لا يُثمنْ إذ هو خالق السماء والأرض والملائكة والبشر ما يُرى وما لا يُرى. والكل خُدام وعبيد له. واليهود لجهلهم ظنوا أنهم لم يستطيعوا القبض عليه إلا بهذه المشورة ودفْع هذا المبلغ ليهوذا. ولم يعلَموا أن هذا تدبير إلهي لخلاص آدم ونسله. وأنه بإيثاره أسلم نفسه لهم وإلا فما كانوا يقدرون على القبض عليه. ولكنه دبَّر ذلك رحمةً بنا ولفدائنا.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said “and grieved Him Who heals sickness and forgives sins” this means the one Who heals the pain, Who ordered the lame man to carry his bed and walk, Who raised Lazarus from the grave after four days of death, Who forgave the sins of the adulteress, Who bore the nails in His hands and feet, Who suffered the spear in His side to free our race and deliver us from our sins. He said, “They took the price which the sons of Israel agreed upon, thirty pieces of silver. And gave it to the potter’s house.” He refers to Judas who when he realized the evil of his doing he returned to them the silver pieces and hung himself and was counted with the murderers because he had delivered his master and did not heed Jesus’ warning to him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ويؤلمون الذي يشفي الأمراض. ويغفر الذنوب". يعني أن الذي شفى الأوجاع. وأمر المُخلَّع منذ سنين كثيرة أن يحمل سريره ويمشي. والذي أقام لعازر من القبر بعد أربعة أيام من موته. والذي غفر خطايا الامرأة الزانية. قد احتمل منهم المسامير في يديه ورجليه. واحتمل طعن جنبه بالحربة. ليُعتق جنسنا ويَغفر خطايانا. قال: "ويأخذون الثلاثين من الفضة الثمن الذي شارط عليه بنو إسرائيل. ويدفعونها في حقل الفاخوري" يعني بهذا عن يهوذا الذي لمَّا رأى شر فعله فإنه ردَّ إليهم ما أخذه منهم ومضي وخنق نفسه. ومات شرَّ ميتة وحُسِبَ مع القتَلة لأنه أسلم سيده ولم يبال بإنذاره له.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            But the chief priests took the silver pieces and bought with them the potter's field” to fulfill the prophecy, “As the Lord commanded me so I say. The judgment of perdition will be upon them and their children forever, for they judged innocent blood” which is exactly what happened after the resurrection of our Lord Jesus Christ when the Roman Emperor laid siege on Jerusalem and defeated them. He killed one hundred and twenty legions and each legion consisted of ten thousand men. He destroyed their temple so their offerings ceased. We therefore ask our Lord Jesus Christ not to punish us for our sins and not to forsake us. Glory be given to Him forever. Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "فأخذ رؤساء الكهنة الفضة... واشتروا بها حقل الفخاري". ليكمُل قول الرب سبحانه على فم نبيه. قال: "ستأتي عليهم دينونة الهلاك إلى الأبد وعلى أولادهم لأنهم القوا دماً زكياً في الحكم". وهكذا كان: فأنه بعد صعود سيدنا المسيح له المجد حاصرهم ملك الروم وفتح المدينة وقتل مائة وعشرين ربوة وكل ربوة عشرة آلاف. وضرب هيكلهم فبطُلتْ قرابينهم. فنسأل ربنا يسوع المسيح له المجد أن لا يُقاصصنا بخطايانا وأن لا يتخلى عنا. له المجد إلى الأبد آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>