<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Wisdom of Solomon 2:12-22         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            من حكمة سليمان 2: 12 – 22         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Let us lie in wait for the righteous man, because he is inconvenient to us” which means that when the Jews saw the miracles that Jesus performed they hated Him for they abhorred the truth. They followed Him to find a fault in Him and entrap Him because they wanted to maintain their position as leaders; their hearts were never able to comprehend what the Lord did. They used to say that whatever He did was from the devil despite their knowledge that this is the truth. The Holy Bible testifies against them saying, “Nevertheless even among the rulers many believed in Him, but because of the Pharisees they did not confess Him, lest they should be put out of the synagogue; for they loved the praise of men more than the praise of God”.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ولنَكمُنْ للصديق فأنه ثقيل علينا". يعني بهذا أن اليهود لما رأوا الآيات والعجائب التي كان يصنعها سيدنا يسوع المسيح: حسدوه على ذلك لبغضهم الحق. وكانوا يترصدونه في كل وقت لكي يجدوا عليه علة يصطادونه بها. ولأجل حفظ رئاستهم ما كانت قلوبهم تستجلي شيئا مما يصنعه المُخلّص. بل كانوا يقولون أن هذا جميعه من الشيطان مع معرفتهم بأنه حق. كما شهد عنهم الإنجيل المقدس بقوله: "آمن به كثيرون من الرؤساء أيضاً غير أنهم لسبب الفريسيين لم يعترفوا... لأنهم أحبوا مجد الناس أكثر من مجد الله".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “and opposes our actions” which means that Jesus always enticed them to be virtuous whereas their hearts were inclined to do evil. He said, “he reproaches us for sins against the law,” which means that Jesus did not give them an opportunity to validate their lack of belief in Him. Because when He performed His miracles and they did not believe, He ordered them to read and search in the books of their prophets saying, “You search the Scriptures, for in them you think you have eternal life; and these are they, which testify of Me.” Jesus not only ordered them to read the scriptures but to search it to understand the meaning of the prophets’ words which show that He is their Savior. He also said, “For if you believed Moses, you would believe Me; for he wrote about Me.” With such words, the Lord made them feel guilty for their lack of understanding of the Scriptures because they did not examine it.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لأنه لا يقاوم أعمالنا". يعني بهذا أن الرب يسوع المسيح كان يحثهم دائماً على عمل الفضيلة. أما هم فكانت قلوبهم مائلة إلى عمل الرذيلة بينما أن أعمال الرب كانت مضادَّة لأعمالهم. قال: "ويُقر عنا على مخالفتنا للناموس". يعنى أن سيدنا يسوع المسيح له المجد لم يترك لهم حجة يحتجون بها لعدم إيمانهم به. لأنه لما عمل أمامهم الآيات الباهرة للعقول ولم يؤمنوا أمرهم أن يفتشوا عنه في كتب أنبيائهم بقوله: "فتشوا الكتب لأنكم تظنون أن لكم فيها حيوة أبدية وهي التي تشهد لي". وقد أمرهم الرب بالتفتيش لا القراءة فقط ليعلموا معاني كلام الأنبياء التي تَدُل على أنه مُخَلّصهم. وقال أيضاً: "لأنكم لو كنتم تصدقون موسى لكنتم تصدقونني لأنه هو كتبَ عني. فإن كنتم لستم تصدقون كُتبَ ذاك فكيف تصدقون كلامي". وبهذا ومثله كان الرب يُبَكتَهمْ على عدم فهمهم الناموس لأنهم لم يفحصوه.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “and calls himself a child of the Lord” This prophecy was first uttered about Jesus that He is the Son of God when the angel informed the Virgin Mary “that Holy One who is to be born will be called the Son of God.” He says, “because his manner of life is unlike that of others, and his ways are strange” which means that the life of Christians is not like the Pharisees’ life and their old laws are unlike the new laws. The old laws were those of justice while the new laws are those of mercy. They are proud and the Christians are humble. They laid heavy burdens on the people whereas the Christians offered to relieve others at their own expense. They fight those who deal unjustly with them whereas Christians turn their cheeks to those who slap them because of their love for Jesus. He said, “We are considered by him as something base, and he avoids our ways as unclean” which means that the Lord forbade His followers from following the Pharisees’ ways by saying, “Take heed and beware of the leaven of the Pharisees and the Sadducees." “Which is hypocrisy”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ويُسمي نفسه ابن الله". وهذه نبوة قد سبقت على فم النبي عن سيدنا المسيح أنه يُدعىَ ابن الله. كما قال الملاك للسيدة الطاهرة العذراء مريم: "القدوس المولود منك يُدعى ابن الله". قال: "شَبَهه لا يُشبهنا وطرقه مخالفة لنا". يعنى بهذا أن سيرة المؤمنين بالمسيح ليست كسيرتهم ولا الشريعة العتيقة كالشريعة الحديثة لأن الأولى شريعة عدل والثانية شريعة تَفضُل: أولئك متعظمون. وهؤلاء متواضعون. أولئك يُحمِّلون الناس أثقالاً. وهؤلاء يبذلون أنفسهم عن الناس ليريحوهم. أولئك يُقاصون من يظلمهم. وهؤلاء يُحَولون وجوههم للاطميهم محبة لسيدهم. قال: "فهو يُجانب طرقنا كمجانبته للوحوش". يعني بهذا أن سيدنا المسيح كان يُنهي المؤمنين به أن يبتعدوا عن طرق المخالفين بقوله: "تحرزوا من خمير الفريسيين والصدوقيين". "الذي هو الرياء".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            His saying “as something base …avoid our ways as unclean” shows that those who subject themselves to what is base will be consumed by it as a person who draws near a monster subjects himself to destruction. Those who come close to the violators of the law subject themselves to damnation. He said, “and boasts that God is His father. Let us see if His words are true, and let us test what will happen at the end of His life” which indicates that they had discussed amongst themselves that if He claims that God is His father then let’s deliver Him to death and watch His end. As for Him, He told them, “When you lift up the Son of Man, then you will know that I am He,”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله "كمجانبته للوحوش" فيعني كما أن من يدنُ من الوحش يُعَرِّض جسده للافتراس. كذلك من يدنُ من المخالفين فأنه يُعَرِّض نفسه للهلاك. قال: "ويفتخر بأن الله أبوه فلننظر إذاً إن كان كلامه حق ولنختبر كيف تكون عاقبته بعد". يعني أنهم كانوا يتشاورون فيما بينهم قائلين: أن هذا قد أدعى أن الله أبوه فلنُسلِّمه للموت وننظر ماذا تكون آخرته. أما هو فكان يقول لهم: "متى رفعتم ابن الإنسان فحينئذ تفهمون أنى أنا هو".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “for if the righteous man is God's child, He will help Him, and will deliver Him from the hand of His adversaries.” This is a prophecy of what Jesus was going to tell the Jews when He is on the cross where they told Him, “If You are the Son of God, come down from the cross." And the criminal on His left hand told Him, “"If You are the Christ, save Yourself and us." They said this to mock Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "فإنه إن كان الصديق حقاً ابن الله. فهو يُخلص نفسه وينقذها من أيدي المضادين". وهذه نبوة من النبي عما كان يقوله اليهود للسيد المسيح وهو على الصليب حيث كانوا يقولون له: "إن كنت ابن الله فانزل عن الصليب". وكذلك اللص الشمال كان يقول له: "إن كنت أنت المسيح فخلص نفسك وإيانا". وكان قولهم استهزاء به ليس إلا.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Let us condemn Him to a shameful death” referring to their decision to crucify Jesus, “Whom you murdered by hanging on a tree.” They considered His death on the cross a great shame for Him because it is written, "Cursed is everyone who hangs on a tree." But Jesus accepted this to fulfill the holy will, “Christ has redeemed us from the curse of the law, having become a curse for us”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ولنقضِ عليه بأشنع ميتة". يعنى أنهم قد حكموا على السيد المسيح بالصلب "مُعلقينَ إياهُ على خشبة". لأنه مكتوب عندهم في الناموس "ملعون كل من عُلقَ على خشبة". وعلى هذا فقد اعتبروا موت المسيح على الصليب عاراً عظيماً لحق به. ولكن السيد المسيح قد قَبِلَ ذلك منهم ليُكملَّ إرادته المقدسة. و"افتدانا من لعنة الناموس إذ صار لعنة لأجلنا".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Thus they reasoned, but they were led astray, for their wickedness blinded them,” After the prophet explained their corrupted reasoning, he added that they were led astray from the road to salvation by their evil deeds and were blinded by their envy of Christ. He said, “and they did not know the secret purposes of God,” which means that they did not realize that their scheming was against their Savior and the God of all. He said, “nor discerned the prize for blameless souls;” which means that they did not follow the righteous path and become disciples to the Lord and hoped for their wages as the righteous disciples hoped and earned eternal joy.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "هذا ما ارتأوه فَضَّلوا. لأن فخرهم أعماهم". بعد أن ذكر النبي مشورتهم الفاسدة قال: "فَضَّلوا" عن طريق الخلاص بما فعلوه وأصبحوا عمياناً وقد أسكرهم الحسد. قال "ولم يُدركوا أسرار الله". أي أنهم لم يفهموا أن هذا الذي أتموا مؤامرتهم عليه هو مُخلصهم وهو إله الكل. قال: "ولم يرجوا أجرة الأبرار". أي أنهم لم يذعنوا للحق ويتتلمذوا للرب ويرجوا أجرهم كما رجاه التلاميذ الأبرار ومن يتبعهم فبلغوا السعادة الأبدية.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “nor hoped for the wages of holiness,” which means that their thoughts were only concerned with this world. They did not think of death nor did they prepare for it with faith and good works to leave this physical body without blemish and make their death a transition to heaven. Since they did not consider their death, it became a transition to hell. Let us ask the Lord to inspire us to do His will and what pleases Him in order to win a sinless departure from this world. Glory be to God Forever, Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ولم يفتكروا في رقاد الأنفس التي لا عيب فيها". يعني أن فكرهم لم يكن إلا في هذه الحياة الدنيا الزائلة. ولم يفكروا في الموت ولم يتزودوا بالأيمان والأعمال الصالحة حتى يَخرُجوا من هذا الجسد وهم بلا عيب ويكون موتهم انتقالاً إلى النعيم ولكن بما أنهم لم يتفكروا هكذا فقد صار موتهم انتقالاً إلى الجحيم. فنسأل إلهنا أن يُلهمنا إلى العمل لما يرضيه لنفوز بالخروج من هذا العالم ونحن أنقياء من الخطايا. ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>