<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">      <Title>      <language id="English">The Absolution of the Woman</language><language id="Indonesian">Absolusi bagi Wanita</language>      <language id="Arabic">تحليل المرأة</language>   </Title>   <comment>      <language id="English">         If the woman gives birth to a boy, she comes to the priest after forty days. If it was a girl, then she comes after eighty days.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Jika seorang wanita melahirkan seorang anak laki-laki, dia datang kepada imam setelah empat puluh hari. Jika anak perempuan, maka dia datang setelah delapan puluh hari.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         إذا ولدت المرأة ذكراً، تأتي إلى الكاهن بعد أربعين يوماً. أما إذا ولدت أنثى، فتأتي بعد ثمانين يوماً.      </language>   </comment>      <insertdocument path="include/StartOfService"/>   <insertdocument path="include/ThanksgivingPrayer"/>      <role id="People">      <insertdocument path="include/TenouwstSeasonalResponse"/>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/PrayerOfIncenseForPaulineEpistle"/>      <role id="Reader">      <group>         <season id="AbsolutionOfWomanBoy">            <biblereference reference="Hebrews 1:8-12" type="section">         </biblereference></season>                  <season id="AbsolutionOfWomanGirl">            <biblereference reference="1 Corinthians 7:12-14" type="section">         </biblereference></season>      </group>   </role>      <insertdocument path="include/trisagion/Seasonal"/>   <insertdocument path="include/LitanyOfTheGospel"/>   <insertdocument path="include/litanies/ThreeShort"/>         <section expanded="true">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Litany</language><language id="Indonesian">Litani</language>         <language id="Arabic">الطلبة</language>      </Title>            <role id="Priest">         <text>            <language id="English">               O Lord, God, the Pantocrator, the Father of our Lord, God, and Savior Jesus Christ; the Treasure of light, the Creator, the Chaser away of all diseases, who reconciles all to the repentance of harmony;            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ya Tuhan, Allah, Sang Pantokrator, Bapa dari Tuhan, Allah, dan Juruselamat kita Yesus Kristus; Harta cahaya, Sang Pencipta, Pembasmi semua penyakit, yang mendamaikan semua orang kepada pertobatan dari keharmonisan;            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               P[oic Vnou] Pipantokratwr Viwt m~Pen[oic ouoh Pennou] ouoh Pencwt/r I/couc Pi,~rictoc: p~yucauroc n~te piouwini Pid/miorgoc Pidiwgmoc/ n~te niswni t/rou efhwtp m~pie~p~t/rf eumetanoia n~te oucumvwnia.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيها الربُ الإلهُ ضابطُ الكل أبو ربِنا وإلهِنا ومخلصِنا يسوعَ المسيحِ، كنزُ النورِ، الخالقُ، المخضعُ جميعَ الأمراضِ، المصلحُ الجميعَ بتوبةِ الإتفاقِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               who have adorned all by the law of His love, through the Economy of His Logos, the only-begotten Son, when He came to us in the flesh through the holy Theotokos and ever-virgin, Saint Mary,              </language><language id="Indonesian">               yang telah menghiasi semua orang dengan hukum kasih-Nya, melalui ke Ekonomian dari Logos-Nya, Putera Tunggal-Nya, ketika Ia datang kepada kita dalam daging melalui Theotokos kudus dan perawan selamanya, Santa Maria,</language>            <language id="Coptic">               V/e~tafcolcel m~pie~p~t/rf qen v~nomoc n~te tefa~gap/: hiten ]oikonomia n~te Peflogoc m~monogen/c Ps/ri e~tafi~ saron qen t~carx: e~bol qen ]yeo~tokoc eyouab: ouoh m~paryenoc n~c/ou niben ]a~gia Maria.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               الذي زيَّنَ كلَّ شيءٍ بناموسِ محبتِه، بتدبيِر كلمتِه، إبنِه الوحيدِ الذي ظَهَرَ لنا بالجسدِ، من والدةِ الإله الطاهرةِ العذراءِ كلَّ حينٍ القديسةِ مريم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               and the Holy Spirit, the Healer and Physician of our nature, our Teacher of Your true knowledge, that we may be saved through the preaching of Your Holy Gospel.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               dan Roh Kudus, Sang Penyembuh dan Tabib dari kodrat kami, Guru kami dari pengetahuan-Mu yang sejati, agar kami diselamatkan melalui pemberitaan Injil-Mu yang kudus.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Nem Pip~neuma eyouab n~reftal[o ouoh n~c/ini n~te tenvucic: n~ref]c~bw nan e~qoun e~peke~mi m~m/i eyrenoujai e~bol hiten pihiwis n~te nekeuaggelion eyouab.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               والروح القدس المشفي، طبيب طبيعتنا ومرشدنا إلى معرفتِكَ الحقيقيةِ، لكي نَخلُصَ من قِبَلِ انذارِ أناجيلِكَ المقدسةِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               For the sake of man whom You have created and the act of the woman whom You have brought out of him, to be a helper to him, after the economy of canonical marriage, You have blessed the fruit of the lawful offspring of the similitude of Your image and Your likeness.              </language><language id="Indonesian">               Demi manusia yang telah Engkau ciptakan dan perbuatan perempuan yang telah Engkau keluarkan dari  manusia (Adam), untuk menjadi penolong bagi dia, sesuai keekonomian dari pernikahan yang kanonikal, Engkau telah memberkati buah keturunan yang sah dari keserupaan gambar dan rupa-Mu.              </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Eybe pirwmi e~takyamiof nem p~hwb n~]c~himi e~takenc e~bol n~q/tf e~oubo/~yoc naf kata ouoikonomia n~gamoc p~kanwnikon: akc~mou e~pikarpoc n~te pijinmici n~nomimon n~te pihucwn n~te tekhukwn nem peki~ni.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               من أجلِ الإنسانِ الذي صنعتَه وفِعلِ المرأةِ التي أخرجتَها منه، معينهً له، كشركةِ الزواجِ الشرعي، وباركتَ ثمرةَ الولادةِ الناموسيةِ المساويةِ لصورتِكَ ومثالِكَ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               And have enlarged the bounds of our nature by a succession of seed, unto the furnishing of the world and all that are therein, through all Your saints and the seed of the kingdom of the heavens.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan telah memperluas batas-batas kodrat kami dengan keturunan yang berkelanjutan, untuk menghiasi dunia dan segala isinya, melalui semua orang kudus-Mu dan benih kerajaan surga.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh nenhoroc n~]vucic aky~rouerenergin kata oudiado,/ n~te ouj~roj oukocm/cic m~pikocmoc n~te n/etw~op n~q/tf t/rou: hiten n/eyouab t/rou n~tak: nem p~j~roj n~te y~metouro n~niv/oui.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وجعلتَ نظامَ الطبيعةِ سارياً بتناسِلِ الزرعِ، وزينتَ العالمَ وكلَّ ما فيه بواسطةِ كافةِ قديسيكَ ونسلِ ملكوتِ السمواتِ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               Therefore, O Lord, You have purified our nature and have delivered us through an inward personal reconciliation in mystical and real fellowship.               </language><language id="Indonesian">               Oleh karena itu, ya Tuhan, Engkau telah menyucikan kodrat kami dan telah membebaskan kami melalui rekonsiliasi pribadi batiniah di dalam persekutuan yang rahasia dan nyata.               </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Eybe vai P[oic aktoubo n~tenvucic akaiten n~remhe e~bol hiten pijinhwtn e~qoun: kata ouhupoctacic qen t~koinwnia m~muctik/ n~p~rakton.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               من أجلِ هذا يارب طهرتَ طبيعتَنا وعَتَقتَنا بالإتحادِ في شخصِكَ في شركةٍ سريةٍ.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               We ask and entreat You, O Lover of Mankind, to look upon Your handmaid (...); may Your Holy Spirit be renewed in her inward parts; purify her from her impurities.             </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kami meminta dan memelas kepada-Mu, ya Pengasih Umat Manusia, lihatlah hamba-Mu (...); kiranya Roh Kudus-Mu diperbaharui di dalam batinnya; sucikanlah dia dari segala kekotorannya.             </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Ten]ho ouoh tentwbh m~mok Pimairwmi hopwc n~tekjoust e~jen tekbwki )nim): mare Pekp~neuma eyouab erberi qen n/etcaqoun m~moc: matouboc e~bol ha necywleb.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسألُ ونطلبُ منكَ يا محبَ البشرِ لكي تتطلعَ على أمَتَك ___، حتى يتجدد روحُ قدسِكَ في أحشائها. طَهرها من أدناسِها.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="English">               May she be renewed in her soul and her body and her spirit; and absolve her from all accusations, and all her old acts, unto a pardoning of all her trespasses.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kiranya dia diperbaharui di dalam jiwanya, tubuhnya, dan rohnya, dan bebaskanlah dia dari segala tuduhan, dan dari segala perbuatannya yang dahulu, kepada pengampunan atas segala kesalahannya.            </language>            <language id="Coptic">               Marecswpi m~beri qen tec'u,/ nem peccwma nem pecp~neuma: n~tekaic n~remhe e~bol qen egk~l/ma niben nem nech~b/oui~ t/rou n~a~poc e~oucun,wr/cic n~te necparap~twma t/rou.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               لتتجدد نفسُها وجسدُها وروحُها. اعتقها من كلَّ لائمةٍ ومن جميعِ أعمالِها القديمةِ، غفراناً لجميعِ آثامِها.            </language>         </text>         </role>            <role id="Priest" silent="true">         <insertdocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusion"/>      </role>   </section>      <insertdocument path="include/ThreeAbsolutions"/>      <role id="Priest">      <comment>         <language id="English">            Then the priest anoints the woman with oil. After the baptism she enters the church and partakes of the holy Mysteries.         </language><language id="Indonesian">            Kemudian imam mengurapi wanita itu dengan minyak. Setelah dibaptis, dia masuk ke dalam gereja dan mengambil bagian dalam Misteri Kudus.         </language>         <language id="Arabic">            ويدهن الكاهن المرأة بالزيت. ثم تدخل الكنيسة، بعد المعمودية، وتتناول من الأسرار المقدسة.         </language>      </comment>   </role></document>