<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation – Luke 22:7-13         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير – لوقا 22: 7-13         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When the children of Israel were in Egypt, in the bondage of Pharaoh and his Egyptian soldiers, they endured a harsh captivity and increased humiliation. God wanted to free them of the bitter slavery and save them from the cruelty of the Egyptians’ captivity and hardships, at the hands of Moses, His prophet and spokesperson.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            من المعلوم أن بني إسرائيل لما كانوا في مصر في عبودية فرعون وجنوده المصريين: وقد استحكم أسرهم، وعظم ذلهم. أراد الله تعالى ذكره أن يعتقهم من تلك العبودية المُرَّة. ويخلصهم من شدة الأسر والضيق اللذين كانوا فيهما عند المصريين على يد موسى نبيه وكليمه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He ordered them through Moses, that every man must slaughter a lamb without blemish in their house, in the fourteenth day of the first month of the year – Nissan; eating its flesh roasted in fire. He promised them to save them from the bondage of Pharaoh and the Egyptians by His divine power, in the night they eat the lamb’s meat. He then ordered them to do this every year.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فأمرهم على لسانه بأن يذبح كل إنسان منهم في بيته خروفاً بلا عيب في الرابع عشر من هلال نيسان. ويأكلون لحمه مشوياً بالنار. ووعدهم أنه بقوته الإلهية يعتقهم من عبودية فرعون والمصريين في الليلة التي يأكلون فيها لحم الخروف. ثم أمرهم بأن تكون هذه عادة سنوية.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            This was a reference to Jesus Christ, the Lamb of God, who is without blemish, and who accepted to shed His blood – of His own will – for the salvation of Adam and his offspring, from the bondage of the devil and his armies. He also freed us from our sins.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان ذلك إشارة إلى السيد المسيح حمل الله الذي لا عيب فيه. الذي رضى أن يُهرق دمه بإرادته من أجل خلاص آدم وذريته من عبودية إبليس وجنوده. وعتقنا نحن من تعبدنا للخطايا.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Evangelist writes, "Then came the day of Unleavened Bread, when the Passover must be killed.” The Day of Unleavened Bread that year fell on a Friday, the fifteenth of Nissan. As is customary, the celebration of feast days happens the night before. As such, the children of Israel would slaughter the Passover sacrifice the night before.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال البشير: "وجاء يوم الفطير الذي ينبغي أن يذبح فيه الفصح" وكان مجيء يوم الفطير في تلك السنة في يوم الجمعة الخامس عشر من هلال نيسان. ولأن العادة جارية بتقديم إكرام الأيام الجليلة من الليل. كان بنو إسرائيل يذبحون ضحية الفصح ليلة العيد.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Since the celebration of Passover must take place exclusively in Jerusalem, “He sent Peter and John, saying, `Go and prepare the Passover for us, that we may eat.’ Just as God had sent Moses and Aaron to command the Jewish congregation to slaughter the Passover lamb.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما كان الأمر لهم بألا يعملوا الفصح إلا في مدينة القدس. "فأرسل بطرس ويوحنا قائلاً اذهبا وأعدا لنا الفصح لنأكل" كما أرسل الله موسى وهارون ليأمرا شعب اليهود بذبح خروف الفصح.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “So they said to Him, `Where do You want us to prepare?’ Since the Law stipulates that the Jews must go to Jerusalem every year to celebrate the Passover, there was a need for everyone to find a place to celebrate. Given the large number of Jews who would come to the feast, those who did not have an arranged place had to go to a relative’s or a friend’s.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "فقالا له أين تريد أن تعد" وذلك أن الناموس يأمر بأن يجتمع اليهود في كل سنة إلى أورشليم ليفصحوا بها. فمن كثرة اليهود الذين كانوا يأتون إلى العيد. كان كل إنسان منهم يحتاج إلى أن يعد لنفسه مكاناً يفصح فيه. ومن لم يكن له مكان معد تحوجه ضرورة العيد إلى أن ينزل إما عند قريب أو صديق له.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            But the Savior and the disciples had made no prior arrangements. Thus given the time constraints and the large crowd traveling to the city, they doubted they would find an adequate place.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والمعلوم أن المخلص لم يكن له منزل معد. وكذلك كان تلاميذه. ولذلك توهموا أنهم من ضيقة الوقت والزحام الذي في المدينة لا يجدون مكاناً".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And He said to them, “Behold, when you have entered the city, a man will meet you carrying a pitcher of water; follow him into the house which he enters. Then you shall say to the master of the house, ‘The Teacher says to you, “Where is the guest room where I may eat the Passover with My disciples?”’         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فقال لهما إذا دخلتما المدينة يستقبلكما إنسان حامل جرة ماء. اتبعاه إلى البيت حيث يدخل. وقولا لرب البيت يقول المعلم أين المنزل حيث آكل الفصح مع تلاميذي."         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Pesah” is a Hebrew word which means “to pass over”, and which was used to designate the lamb that the Jews slaughter. Thus Jesus, the Lamb without blemish, is our Passover, us who crossed over from sin.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والفصح كلمة عبرانية معناها العبور. وكانت تطلق على الخروف الذي كان يذبحه اليهود وهكذا السيد المسيح الخروف الذي بلا عيب هو فصحنا نحن الذين انتقلنا به من الخطيئة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Then he will show you a large, furnished upper room; there make ready. So they went and found it just as He had said to them, and they prepared the Passover.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "فذاك يريكما علية كبيرة مفروشة. هناك أعدا. فانطلقا ووجدا كما قال لهما. فأعدا الفصح."         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            For it was a Jewish tradition that every group delegates a person to bring the sheep to the Temple, assist the Levites to slaughter it and then transport the slaughtered animal to the house where they intended to eat it according to the Law. Thus Peter and John did so in the temple on behalf of our Savior and His disciples.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأنه كان من عوائد اليهود أن "كل جماعة تنيب عنها واحداً ليحضر الخروف إلى دار الهيكل ويساعد أيضا اللاويين على ذبحه ثم ينقل ما يذبح إلى البيت الذي يقصدون أن يأكلون فيه حسب الشريعة. وقد قام بذلك في الهيكل هذه المرة بالنيابة عن مخلصنا وتلاميذه بطرس ويوحنا".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “When the hour had come, He sat down, and the twelve apostles with Him.” This indicates that Jesus entered the city on Thursday and by the power of His divinity, He did not let the Jews see Him; even though they were expecting Him for the feast.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "ولما كانت الساعة اتكأ والإثني عشر رسولاً معه" ويدل ذلك على أنه دخل المدينة يوم الخميس وبقوة لاهوته لم يدع اليهود يبصرونه مع أنهم كانوا مترقبين حضوره في العيد.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            They were gathered in the upper room in Zion.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والمكان الذي كانوا متكئين فيه هو علية صهيون.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “When the hour had come” means sundown, the time that God had commanded the Children of Israel to eat the Passover lamb, saying, “In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month at evening, you shall eat unleavened bread, until the twenty-first day of the month at evening"         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأما قوله: "ولما كانت الساعة" فهي ساعة الغروب وهي الوقت الذي أمر الله بني إسرائيل أن يأكلوا الفصح فيها قائلاً: "في الشهر الأول في اليوم الرابع عشر مساء تأكلون فطيراً إلى اليوم الحادي والعشرين من الشهر مساءً"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “With fervent desire I have desired to eat this Passover with you before I suffer.” Eating the Passover supper that night is necessary for two reasons: the first is to thwart any potential excuse Judas might have with the Jews, that Jesus would not eat the Passover supper, contrary to God’s Law; and the second is His desire to fulfill the old Passover while replacing it with the new one.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "وقال لهم شهوة اشتهيت أن آكل هذا الفصح معكم قبل أن أتألم" وأراد بأكله الفصح في تلك الليلة نوعين: الأول حتى لا يجد يهوذا عليه حجة عند اليهود بانه قد حل العيد ولم يأكل الفصح وضاد ناموس الله. والثاني أنه أراد أن يتمم الفصح القديم وينسخه بالفصح الجديد.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “For I say to you, I will no longer eat of it until it is fulfilled in the kingdom of God,” means I will not eat of the Passover according to the Law after this until My message is spread and My Passover is proclaimed. The term “until” is akin to confirmation and not as the objective, as Isaiah wrote “Surely for this iniquity there will be no atonement for you, Even to your death.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: لأني أقول لكم أني لا أكل منه بعد حتى يكمل في ملكوت الله" معناه أني لا أكل من الفصح الناموسي بعد هذا حتى يكمل ببشارتي وينسخ بفصحي. ولفظة "حتى" هنا هي للقطع وليست توجب غاية كقول في أشعياء: "لا يغفرن لكم هذا الإثم حتى تموتوا"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Then He took the cup, and gave thanks, and said, “Take this and divide it among yourselves.” This was the first cup in the Paschal Supper. For the Jews’ tradition was to drink four cups of wine for the Paschal Supper: the first is drunk at the start of the supper followed by the singing of Psalm 113; then Psalm 114; then after the third cup they sing Psalms 115 to 118; and end with the drinking of the fourth cup.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ثم تناول كأساً وشكر وقال خذوا هذه واقتسموها بينكم" وهذه الكأس كانت الأولى في العشاء الفصحي. لأن العادة كانت عند اليهود أنهم يشربون أثناء العشاء الفصحي أربع كؤوس من الخمر: الأولى يفتتح بها العشاء وبعدها يرتلون مزمور 113 ومزمور 114 ويرتلون بعد الكأس الثالثة مزامير 115-118 ويختمون بالكأس الرابعة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “For I say to you, I will not drink of the fruit of the vine until the kingdom of God comes.” The “kingdom of God” here means His Resurrection from the dead.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لأني أقول لكم أني لا أشرب من نتاج الكرمة حتى يأتي ملكوت الله" يريد بمجيء ملكوت الله قيامته من بين الأموات.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Eating and drinking after resurrection is surprisingly strange. Nonetheless, He meant to accomplish His resurrection.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والأكل والشراب بعد القيامة مستغرب جداً. ولكنه ليحقق لهم قيامته وأنه هو الذي رأوه معلقاً على الصليب.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He showed them the marks of the nails and the location of the spear, and ate and drank with them so that they may know it was He whom they saw hanging on the cross, without doubting that He may be a ghost.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أراهم آثار المسامير ومكان الحربة وأكل وشرب معهم حتى لا يظنوه خيالاً.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            St. Peter the Apostle witnessed, saying, “even to us who ate and drank with Him after He arose from the dead.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كما شهد بذلك بطرس الرسول بقوله: "نحن الذين أكلنا وشربنا معه بعد قيامته"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And He took bread, gave thanks and broke it, and gave it to them, saying, `This is My body which is given for you; do this in remembrance of Me’. Christ intended to fulfill the Economy for which He came.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وأخذ خبزاً وشكر وكسر وأعطاهم قائلاً هذا هو جسدي الذي يُبذل عنكم اصنعوا هذا لذكري" ومعلوم أن السيد المسيح لما أراد إكمال التدبير الذي أتى لأجله،         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He replaced the old Passover, which was a symbol and reference, by His new Passover, offering it to His disciples on the eve of Friday.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            جعل ينسخ الفصح العتيق الذي كان على سبيل الرمز والإشارة إلى فصحه الجديد الذي أعطاه لتلاميذه ليلة الجمعة         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He thus transferred them from the symbolism and reference to the truth and righteousness, as He gave His body saying, "This is my body which is given for you."         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبذلك نقلهم من الرمز والإشارة إلى الحق والصدق عندما أعطاهم جسده قائلاً: "هذا هو جسدي الذي يُبذل عنكم."         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            For when they were greatly humiliated and their misery intensified in Egypt, God instructed them through Moses to eat an unblemished lamb. Accordingly, on the night they eat of the flesh of the lamb, they will be saved from captivity and humiliation, and become free.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويعني لما اشتد ذلهم بمصر وعظم شقاؤهم أمرهم الله على لسان موسى أن يأكلوا من لحم خروف لا عيب فيه. وأن في الليلة التي يأكلون فيها لحم ذلك الخروف يخلصون من الأسر والذل. ويصيرون أحراراً.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            That was a reference to our Lord Jesus Christ, the faultless lamb. That through the blood of His cross, humans gained the way to salvation. For through this blood, Adam and his descendants, being captive by the devil and his armies, gained freedom.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان ذلك إشارة الى السيد المسيح الخروف الذي لا عيب فيه مطلقاً. الذي بدم صليبه صار الخلاص طريقاً مسلوكة لبني البشر لأنه بذلك الدم أطلق آدم ونسله الذين كانوا جميعهم في أسر إبليس وجنوده.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            We, too, were bought from being enslaved by our sins, engaged in a life of iniquity. John the Baptist also testified, saying: "Behold! The Lamb of God who takes away the sin of the world"         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبه اشترانا نحن من تعبدنا للخطايا وانهماكنا في المعاصي. كما شهد يوحنا المعمدان بقوله: "هوذا حمل الله الذي يرفع خطيئة العالم"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Do this in remembrance of Me.” How can we remember Him as He had asked us, unless if we continually remember His benevolences and death? We must be cleansed of every sin so as to eat Him in purity and goodness. Thus, His body becomes a means to always remember Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله: "اصنعوا هذا لذكري" وكيف نذكره به كما أمرنا إلا أن نكون كل حين ذاكرين أنعامه وموته. ونتنقى من كل خطيئة حتى نتناوله بطهارة وصلاح. وبذلك يصير جسده سبباً لذكره كل حين.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Likewise He also took the cup after supper, saying, `This cup is the new covenant in My blood, which is shed for you.’” This means that this is My blood which has been shed for you, and I made it a new covenant between Me and you, to help you remember the passions I accepted of My own will, for the salvation of mankind.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما أعطاهم الكأس أيضا بعد العشاء قال: "هذه الكأس هي العهد الجديد بدمي الذي يُسفك عنكم" يعني أن هذا هو دمي قد سفكته عنكم وجعلته عهداً جديداً بيني وبينكم لتذكروا به الآلام التي قبلتها بإرادتي حباً في خلاص البشر.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The spiritual meaning here is this: he who partakes of His body and blood, has to be always renewing the covenant of his intention, determined with all his heart not to return to sin, desiring that through the partaking of them, he may be forgiven.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والمعنى الروحي في ذلك: أن الذي يتناول جسده ودمه الأقدسين. يلزمه أن يكون دائماً مجدداً عهد نيته. عازماً بكل قلبه ألا يعود إلى الخطيئة التي يلتمس غفرانها بتناولهما.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            For the bread and wine are truly converted into the body and blood of Christ – not a symbol, sign or illustration. Because He who created something of nothing is the One who said this is My body and blood.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن الخبز والخمر يتحولان حقيقة إلى جسد ودم المسيح. وليس رمزاً ولا إشارة ولا مثالاً. لأن الذي قال: للشيء كن فكان. هو الذي قال: هذا جسدي وهذا دمي.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “But behold, the hand of My betrayer is with Me on the table.” St. John Chrysostom said, “Judas was ill-mannered and would usually stretch out his hand with the Lord before the other disciples.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ولكن هوذا يد الذي يسلمني هي معي على المائدة" قال القديس يوحنا ذهبي الفم عن بعضهم: "كانت عادة يهوذا أن يمد يده مع الرب قبل كل التلاميذ وذلك لقلة حيائه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Therefore, because of his habit, our Lord said of him, Behold, the hand of My betrayer is with me on the table," proclaiming and declaring that He is not afraid of what Judas had decided in his heart – even though this saying troubled all the other disciples.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولأن هذه كانت عادته. فلذلك قال سيدنا: هوذا يد الذي يسلمني هي معي على المائدة." إشهاراً وإعلاناً ليهوذا بأن الذي قد أضمره في قلبه ليس يخاف عنه. ولما كان هذا القول مطلقاً أزعج التلاميذ جميعهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The intention was to alert Judas, perhaps he would learn a lesson and refrain from his intention and bad behavior, thus accepting the Grace.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان القصد بذلك أن ينبه يهوذا لعله يتعظ وينثني عن رأيه وطبعه الرديء إلى قبول النعمة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And truly the Son of Man goes as it has been determined.” The Lord meant to outline three things: the first is to reveal to Judas that this matter where you want to implicate Me was mentioned by the prophets;         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وابن الإنسان ماض كما هو محتوم" وقد أراد بذلك ثلاثة أنواع: الأول ليبين ليهوذا أن هذا الأمر الذي تريد أن توقعني فيه، قد سبقت الأنبياء بذكره.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            the second is to reassure the disciples that this matter is not a weakness of His power or contrary to His will, or unbeknownst to Him, but that He is fully aware of what is about to happen, and that it will happen by His own willpower, and is the reason for which He came;         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والثاني أراد به أن يشجع قلوب التلاميذ ويبين لهم أن القضية التي تجري ليست عن ضعف قوته، ولا على غير إرادته ولا أن علمه لم يحط بها، بل إنه عالم بما سيكون وبمشيئته يتم ومن أجله أتى.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            and the third, to say that He will go to the prisoners in the bondage of Satan, and will shine His light on them so that they may rejoice in the salvation, from the darkness of Hades.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والثالث أراد به أنه ماض إلى الأسرى في عبودية الشيطان ويضيء عليهم بنوره ليستبشروا بالخلاص من ظلمات الجحيم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Some people questioned this account, claiming that if Christ saved the world of His own will, through His crucifixion and death, that Judas is guiltless of betraying Him, but should instead be acknowledged for being an instrument in the accomplishment of a good deed and a fulfillment of the prophecies.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد شك قوم وقالوا إن كان المسيح بموته وصلبه خلص العالم بإيثاره فلا ذنب ليهوذا المُسَلِّم له بل هو مشكور على فعله إذ كان سبباً لتمام الخير ومكملاً لكتب الأنبياء.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The response is: had he done so with a good intent, and for the achievement of the prophecies, it would not be punishable. As well those who crucified the Master of everyone: if they purposed the salvation of the world, they would be blameless. But it is not so. Judas and the Jews did what they did in bad faith and malice.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والجواب: أنه لو كان ما فعله قصداً للخير واتمام كتب الأنبياء لكان غير معاقب. وكذلك الذين صلبوا سيد الكل لو كان غرضهم في ذلك خلاص العالم لما كانوا ملومين ولكن ليس الأمر هكذا بل ما فعله يهوذا واليهود هو صار عن سوء نية وخبث طوية.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Seeking to stop any reference of the Savior, and His deed to save the world, if not of their intent, nor of their quest, they must therefore be punished according to their conscience and belief.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولمحبتهم إبطال ذكر مخلص الكل من العالم وما جعل من الخلاص للعالم لم يكن عن قصدهم ولا من سعيهم فلهذا وجب عليهم العقاب بحسب ضميرهم واعتقادهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Those who object might say that Christ came to be crucified and save mankind through His cross. Therefore, someone had to hand Him over to the Jews. If not Judas, there would be someone else. If the whole world were righteous, who would then deliver Him?         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وربما يقول المعترض: أن المسيح جاء لكي ما يصلب ويخلص الكل بصليبه فلابد إذن من مُسَلِم سلمه إلى اليهود ولو لم يكن يهوذا لكان غيره فلو اتفق أن يكون الناس كلهم أبراراً من كان يسلمه؟         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The response is: if sin was not, our Creator would not have a need to unite with us. Such union was not in vain, but was necessary to save man from sin and lead him to the righteous Law, the Law that He established.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والجواب هو أن الخطيئة لو لم تحصل لما كان خالقنا يتحد بنا. فالاتحاد لم يكن عبثاً لكن لإنقاذ الناس من الخطيئة وإهدائهم لشريعة الحق التي سنها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            It is therefore understandable that evil exists, and that someone must take the lead. Thus if Judas had not transgressed, someone else would have. But because Judas pensioned off his conscience and God’s Law, refused Christ’s counsel, and grew wicked germs in his heart, such as greed, betrayal and the refusing of grace, he rightfully deserved punishment.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فمن الضروري أن يوجد أشرار أحدهم يتولى ذلك. فلو لم يكن يهوذا خالف لكان غيره ولكن بما أن يهوذا خالف ضميره وشريعة الله ورفض نصائح المسيح وربى في فؤاده جراثيم الرذائل كالطمع والخيانة وكفران النعمة وجب عقابه عدلاً.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord wanted to reproach Judas in a way that only he would understand – to avoid causing him an ill-reputation among the disciples, saying, “but woe to that man by whom He is betrayed!” But Judas was not deterred because Satan had reigned over his heart and controlled his mind.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد أراد الرب أن يبكت يهوذا تبكيتاً لا يعرفه أحد من التلاميذ إلا هو وحتى لا يشتهر بين التلاميذ بسوء قصده فقال: "لكن ويل لذلك الإنسان الذي يسلمه" ولكن يهوذا لم يرتدع لأن الشيطان قد ملك على قلبه وتسلط على عقله.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Moments later, the devil deceived the disciples, triggering evil thoughts in their hearts, and leading them to argue which of them should be considered the greatest.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبعد ذلك القى الشيطان في قلوب التلاميذ فكراً ردياً أدى بهم إلى المشاجرة على من منهم يظن أنه يكون أكبر.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord preached to them, saying, “The kings of the Gentiles exercise lord it over them, and those who exercise authority over them are called ‘benefactors.’ But not so among you; on the contrary, he who is greatest among you, let him be as the younger, and he who governs as he who serves.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فوعظهم الرب بقوله: "ملوك الأمم يسودونهم والمتسلطون عليهم يدعون محسنين. وأما أنتم فليس هكذا بل الكبير فيكم ليكن كالأصغر. والمتقدم كالخادم         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            For who is greater, he who sits at the table, or he who serves? Is it not he who sits at the table? Yet I am among you as the One who serves.” In other words, I was as your servant when I washed your feet.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن من هو أكبر. الذي يتكئ أم الذي يخدم. أليس الذي يتكئ. ولكني أنا بينكم كالذي يخدم" يعني كنت كالخادم عندما غسلت أرجلكم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “But you are those who have continued with Me in My trials. And I bestow upon you a kingdom, just as My Father bestowed one upon Me, that you may eat and drink at My table in My kingdom, and sit on thrones judging the twelve tribes of Israel.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "أنتم الذين ثبتوا معي في تجاربي. وأنا أجعل لكم كما جعل لي أبي ملكوتاً لتأكلوا وتشربوا على مائدتي في ملكوتي فتحيوا وتتنعموا بلاهوتي كما تغذيتم وتنعمتم بناسوتي". وتجلسوا على كراسي تدينون أسباط إسرائيل الإثني عشر"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            This is to say that you would have a right over them, as when the children of Israel and the people of Nineveh sit on His right – not to convict because judgment is reserved for the Savior alone.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أي توجبون الحق عليهم كما قال في ملكه التيمن مع بني إسرائيل وفي أهل نينوى لا لأنهم يجلسون فيدينون لأن القضاء للمخلص وحده.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord cited the Children of Israel because the disciples are from them and are under the same Law.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وخصص ذلك في بني إسرائيل لأنهم كانوا منهم وتحت شريعة واحدة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Furthermore, He mentioned the number twelve, despite the foreknowledge of Judas’ betrayal, for He did not wish to distinguish him from the rest of the disciples lest he use it as an excuse to blaspheme.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وذكر عدد الإثني عشر مع علمه بخيانة يهوذا ولكنه لم يميزه عن التلاميذ لئلا يجعل ذلك حجة له في الكفر به.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Glory be to God forever, Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولربنا المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>       </Document>