<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Daniel 7:9-15         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير – دانيال 7: 9-15         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Daniel spoke, saying, "I saw in my vision by night.” which means that he saw in front of his eyes in darkness while asleep a vision of this description.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أنا دانيال رأيت في رؤى الليل" أي صور نصب عيني في الظلمة وأنا نائم مثال ثورة على هذه الصفة".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “I watched till thrones were put in place” to judge and rule. Either sooner by judging Antiochus Epiphanes for his horrific prosecution of the Maccabees         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أنه قد وضعت كراسي للقضاء والحكم. إما عاجلاً فعلى أنطيوخوس أبية نيس لأجل اضطهاده المكابيين المريع.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Or later when the Lord Christ and His disciples will sit to judge the living and the dead on Judgment day.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وإما آجلاً فيدل وضع الكراسي على وضع الدينونة العظيم حيث يجلس السيد المسيح وتلاميذه ويدينون الأحياء والأموات.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said “And the Ancient of Days was seated,” to indicate that God preceded all things and that He created time, the world, the ages and the fathers.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وجلس العتيق الأيام" دل بذلك على أزلية الله المتقدمة لكل شيء. وأنه خالق الأزمنة والعاملين والدهور والآباء.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “His garment was white as snow,” with the light of His divinity. He also refers to the transfiguration of the Lord Jesus Christ on Mount Tabor when “His clothes became shining, exceedingly white, like snow, such as no launderer on earth can whiten them”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لباسه أبيض كالثلج" يعني بذلك نور لاهوته. ويرمز بهذا أيضا إلى تجلي ربنا يسوع المسيح على جبل طابور عندما كانت ثيابه بيضاء كالثلج.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “And the hair of His head was like pure wool” to indicate eternity. Such an expression suits the limited minds and knowledge of men.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وشعر رأسه كالصوف النقي" دلالة على أزليته. وهذا التعبير يناسب عقول البشر المحدودة في العقل والمعرفة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “His throne was a fiery flame.” This description conveys awesome and fear, indicating that if His chair is as fearful as this, how would His judgment be.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وكرسيه لهيب نار" وفي هذا الوصف تهويل وتخويف ليدلهم على أنه إذا كان كرسيه هائلاً هكذا فكم بالحرى مداينته.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Its wheels a burning fire,” to indicate that God’s judgment is like a swift flame that immediately consumes all that God wants it consumed         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وعجلاته نار متقدة" دلالة على أن أحكام الله كاللهيب السريع تنزل بكل سرعة حيث يريد الله أنها تنزل.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “A fiery stream issued And came forth from before Him” These are the divine instructions that can’t be revoked. It also shows that the punishment will be severe and very bitter. “For who among us shall dwell with the devouring fire? Who among us shall dwell with everlasting burnings?"         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال "ونهر نار يخرج ويجري أمامه" يعني بذلك أوامره الإلهية التي بلا مانع. ويدل أيضا على أن العقوبة ستكون شديدة ومرة جداً. "لأن إلهنا نار آكلة".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “A thousand thousands ministered to Him; Ten thousand times ten thousand stood before Him.” Referring to the angels and the archangels and all the heavenly hosts while they “stood before Him” as soldiers stand before Kings. How about the King of Kings and the Judge of Judges when the heavenly hosts stand before Him in countless numbers praising Him and glorifying Him and executing His commands.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وألوف كانت تخدمه وربوات وقوف قدامه" يعني بذلك الملائكة ورؤساء الملائكة. وجميع الأجناد السمائية وهم "وقوف قدامه" كوقوف الأجناد أمام الملوك فكم بالأفضل ملك الملوك وقاضي القضاة تقف أمامه أجناد السمائية بعدد لا يحصى لتسبيحه وتقديسه وتنفيذ ما يأمرهم به.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “The court was seated, And the books were opened.” Opening the books doesn’t mean that God is in need of books to read and learn about people and to judge them. This is a metaphor that suits human minds. God speaks to people with what they can understand. The books are the sayings of the prophets.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "فجلس الديان وفتحت الأسفار" لم يعني بفتح الأسفار أن الله تعالى محتاج إلى كتب يقرأها فيعرف منها أمور الناس أو ما يحكم به عليهم. وإنما هذا تعبير بشري يوافق أفهام الناس. وأنه تعالى يخاطب الناس بما يمكنهم فهمه. والأسفار هي أقوال الأنبياء.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            It also shows that His judgment is going to be just so that the condemned may be accepting, and may not complain of injustice, if he deserves punishment, for he would have been sentenced with great justice and fairness.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وتدل أيضا على أن أحكامه تكون بالاعتدال حتى يقنع المحكوم عليه ولا يتذمر إذا وجب عليه العقاب ولا يتشكى من ظلم أو جور لأنه إنما قد حكم عليه بأبلغ العدل والإنصاف.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, "I watched then because of the sound of the pompous words which the horn was speaking.” The horn is Antiochus Epiphanes and the sound is of the words he uttered in contempt of God’s laws.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ورأيت في تلك الساعة أصوات الكلمات العظيمة التي نطق بها ذلك القرن" يعني بالقرن أنطيوخس أبيفانيس وبالأصوات الكلمات العظيمة التي تفوه بها أنطيوخس أبيفانيس إذ كان قد ازدرى بأحكام الله.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “I watched till the beast was slain, and its body destroyed and given to the burning flame” The beast is Antiochus Epiphanes whose Greek blood and rule was shed.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وبينما كنت أنظر وإذ قتل الوحش وهلك جسمه" يعني به أنطيوخس أبيفانيس الذي يستباح هو وملكه المنسوب إلى اليونانيين.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The same verse also refers to the defeat of the devil and the loss of his power when our Lord Christ was incarnated in the flesh. The devil lost the authority he had on man when he committed them to Hades until the Lord Christ came and delivered us from him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويرمز بهذا العدد أيضا إلى ظهور السيد المسيح بالجسد وعند ذلك يسقط الشيطان وتذهب قوته. وينزع منه سلطانه الذي كان متسلطاً به على البشر حيث كان يحدرهم إلى الجحيم حتى أتى السيد المسيح له المجد وخلص جبلته منه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “and given to the burning flame” referring to Antiochus’ death, whose severe punishment will be like fire. He also refers to Christ’s throwing of Satan and his dominions to eternal fire.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ودفع ليحرق بالنار" يقول عن موت أنطيوخوس. أي دفع إلى عقاب شديد شبيه بالنار. ويرمز أيضا إلى أن السيد المسيح له المجد سيلقي الشيطان وجنوده ممن يطيعونه إلى النار المؤبدة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “As for the rest of the beasts, they had their dominion taken away, yet their lives were prolonged for a season and a time.” The beasts are the four kingdoms, Babylon, Media, Persia and Greece. Each of these kingdoms had dominion for a period of time appointed by God and then its power diminished.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أما باقي الحيوانات إلى الأربع مماليك: بابل ومادي وفارس واليونان وسورية اليونانية وقد تولت الرئاسة كل واحدة من هذه المماليك في الزمن المعين لها من الله وزالت إلا بقية ضئيلة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, "I was watching in the night visions, And behold, One like the Son of Man, Coming with the clouds of heaven! He came to the Ancient of Days, And they brought Him near before Him. Then to Him was given dominion and glory and a kingdom, That all peoples, nations, and languages should serve Him.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ثم رأيت في رؤى الليل وإذا مع سحب السماء مثل ابن إنسان آتياً على سحاب السماء، فبلغ وجاء إلى العتيق الأيام وقرب أمامه. فأعطى السلطان والكرامة والملك وجميع الشعوب والأسباط ولغات الألسن تتعبد له" (ابن الإنسان)         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Son of Man is Christ incarnate from the Virgin Mary “And being found in appearance as a man, He humbled Himself and became obedient to the point of death, even the death of the cross. Therefore God also has highly exalted Him and given Him the name which is above every name,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يعني به عن السيد المسيح له المجد الذي تجسد من البكر البتول الطاهرة مريم و "وجد في الهيئة كإنسان. وسار بين خليقته معلماً إياها. ومشفياً أمراضها ووضع نفسه وأطاع حتى الموت موت الصليب لذلك رفعه الله أيضا وأعطاه إسماً فوق كل إسم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            that in the name of Jesus every knee should bow, those in heaven, and those on earth, and those under the earth,  and that every tongue should confess that Jesus Christ is Lord, to the glory of God the Father,” lest someone thinks that His dominion is finite         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لكي تجثو باسم يسوع كل ركبة ممن في السماء وممن على الأرض وممن تحت الأرض. ويعترف كل لسان أن يسوع المسيح هو رب لمجد الله الآب ولئلا يظن ظان أن السلطان الذي أعطاه الآب إياه هو سلطان زمني.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said,” His dominion is an everlasting dominion.” Glory be to Him Forever, Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وسلطانه أبدي لا يزول". له المجد دائماً.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>       </Document>