<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation – Proverbs 9:1-11         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير – أمثال 9: 1-11         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Wisdom has built her house.” Jesus Christ is the wisdom and the house is the holy covenant he made as a port of salvation for the believers.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "الحكمة بنت لها بيتاً" يعني بالحكمة الابن سيدنا يسوع وبالبيت البيعة المقدسة التي جعلها ميناء لخلاص المؤمنين به.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “She has hewn out her seven pillars” referring to the seven sacraments of the holy covenant.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ونصبت فيه سبعة أعمدة" ويعني بهم عن السبعة أسرار البيعة المقدسة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “She has slaughtered her meat, She has mixed her wine, She has also furnished her table” referring to the flesh and blood of God which he offered in His covenant as salvation to His people instead of the sacrifices of the sons of Israel.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ذبحت ذبائحها. ومزجت خمرها في الأواني" يعني بذلك عن جسد الرب ودمه الذي جعلها في بيعته خلاصاً لشعبه عوض الذبائح التي لبني إسرائيل.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “She has sent out her maidens, She cries out from the highest places of the city, “Whoever is simple, let him turn in here!”” The simple are the priests of the Lord whom He set on His covenant and entrusted them not to falter from teaching His people until ignorance departs from them by constant education. The priests must therefore always check on their congregation.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أرسلت عبيدها لينادوا بصوت عالٍ على الزوايا قائلين: من كان فيكم جاهلاً فليأت إلىَّ يعني بالعبيد كهنة الرب الذين جعلهم في بيعته. وأوصاهم ألا يفتروا عن تعليم الشعب ليذهب عنه الجهل بمداومة التعليم. ولذا ينبغي للكهنة أن يفتقدوا في كل وقت أحوال رعيتهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            If any member is ignorant or addicted to sin they should be kind to him until he changes from this initial state and carry the beautiful light of Christ.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فمن كان منهم جاهلاً ومدمناً في الخطايا فيلاطفونه حتى يتغير عن حالته الأولى ويحمل نير المسيح الحلو.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, "Come, eat of my bread and drink of the wine I have mixed,” meaning that if the priests preach their congregations and forbade them to commit any sin and they accepted, then they should give them the holy body and blood of God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "هلموا من طعامي. واشربوا من الخمر التي مزجتها لهم" يعني إذا وعظ الكهنة رعيتهم ونهوها عن فعل الخطايا وقبلت منهم. فحينئذ ينالونها جسد الرب ودمه الأقدسين.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Forsake foolishness and live, And go in the way of understanding” to those who forsook sin and partook of the flesh and blood of the Lord... Those who constantly seek God’s favor don’t perish in sin as our Lord Christ has said, “he who feeds on Me will live because of Me. “         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أتركوا عنكم الجهالات فتحيوا" يعني أن الذي يتناول جسد الرب ودمه ولا يرجع إلى جيل الخطية. ويكون دائماً طالباً مرضاة الله فإنه لا يموت بموت الخطية. كما قال سيدنا المسيح: "من يأكلني فهو يحيا بي"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            In other words the one who works hard on acquiring divine knowledge and seek virtues, will distance himself from the darkness of ignorance and live in the light of truth.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبمعنى آخر إن الذي يقتني العلوم الإلهية ويجتهد باقتنائها على طلب الفضائل. فإنه يبتعد من ظلمة الجهل ويعيش في نور الحق.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom, And the knowledge of the Holy One is understanding. For by me your days will be multiplied, And years of life will be added to you.” Which shows that those who seek knowledge and work on acquiring it never fall in the pit of ignorance as the Lord Christ has said about the man who built his house on the rock.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "اطلبوا الحكمة لتعمروا" يعني أن الذي يطلب العلم ويجتهد في تحصيله فإنه لا يسقط أبداً في هوة الجهل. كما قال السيد المسيح عن الذين شيد بيته على الصخر.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “he who rebukes a wicked man only harms himself.” Means those who reveal divine matters to the unbelievers and they therefore consider them insignificant.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "من يؤدب الأشرار يلحق بنفسه هواناً" يعني أن الذي يعلن الأسرار الإلهية لغير المؤمنين فيتهاونون بها وبمعلنها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As the Lord had said, “Do not give what is holy to the dogs; nor cast your pearls before swine, lest they trample them under their feet, and turn and tear you in pieces.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كما قال السيد له المجد: "لا تعطوا القدس للكلاب ولا تطرحوا درركم قدام الخنازير لئلا تدوسها بأرجلها وتلتفت فتمزقكم"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Give instruction to a wise man, and he will be still wiser,” showing that if you reveal divine matters to the believers who are governed by the law of Christ they will become wiser.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "عظ الحكيم فيزداد حكمة" يعني أنك كلما أظهرت العلوم الإلهية للمؤمنين المتحكمين بشريعة المسيح فإنهم يزدادون فوق حكمتهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            That’s why the Lord Christ said, “For whoever has, to him more will be given, and he will have abundance.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولذلك قال السيد المسيح له المجد: "من له سيعطى ويزداد"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom” which means that a man who does good should not seek worldly gains but should be governed by the fear of God and seek His favor in all matters and he will reach his goal.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "رأس الحكمة مخافة الرب" يعني أنه يجب على الإنسان ألا يعمل الفضيلة ويقصد بها الربح العالمي بل يجعل مخافة الرب دائماً نصب عينيه وفي كل أموره يكون طالباً رضاه وبذلك ينال مقصوده.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “And the knowledge of the Holy One is understanding.” A person must therefore not be satisfied with his own opinion but humble himself and consult the teachers of the covenant concerning his salvation.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ومشورة القديسين فهم" يعني أنه ينبغي على الإنسان ألا يقنع برأي نفسه. بل يتضع ويستشير معلمي البيعة فيما يؤول إليه خلاص نفسه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Consulting the fathers guides man to salvation and deepens his understanding.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فإن مشورة الآباء المعلمين تهدى الإنسان إلى الخلاص وتزيده فهماً.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “The knowledge of the Holy One is understanding.” The holy one refers to the commandments of God in which He revealed what he commands us to do and what he forbade us from doing so that man’s thoughts will stay away from sin and seek virtue.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ومعرفة الناموس هو من صلاح العقل" يعني بالناموس عن وصايا الله تعالى التي أولها بالأوامر والنواهي. لتكون أفكار الإنسان دائماً مصروفة عن الرذائل طالبة للفضائل.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “For by me your days will be multiplied, And years of life will be added to you” which means that a man who follows the commandments of the Lord and seeks virtue will be rewarded with a long life, because the age that God gave him will not be diminished by the death brought about by sin.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "بهذا المنال تعيش زماناً طويلاً وتزداد لك سنو الحياة" يعني إذا كان الإنسان سالكاً في وصايا الرب طالباً للفضائل فإن عمره يكون طويلاً.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Those who live in sin are dead and if they were living their life is shorter because of sin. We ask the Lord to help us do what is pleasing to Him. Glory be to God Forever Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أما الذي يعيش في الخطيئة فإنه ميت وإن كان حياً قصرت عمره الخطيئة. فنسأل الرب أن يعيننا على ما يرضيه. له المجد دائماً إلى الأبد. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>       </Document>