<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">Introduction to the Coptic Gospel When Read by the Pope or a Bishop</Language>      </Title>            <Role id="Deacon">                  <Comment>            <Language id="English">               If the reader is the Pope, the deacon says:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وإذا كان الأب البطريرك هو القارئ يقول الشماس:              </Language>         </Comment>                  <InsertDocument path="include/PopeGospelIntro"/>                  <Comment>            <Language id="English">               If the reader is a metropolitan or bishop, the deacon says:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وإذا كان الأب الأسقف هو القارئ يقول الشماس:             </Language>         </Comment>                  <Text type="GospelIntro">            <Language id="English">               Stand in the fear of God. Let us hear the Holy Gospel from the mouth of our honored and righteous father, the thrice blessed, our honored father the bishop, Abba (...), bishop of the Christ-loving city of (...) and its vicinity. May the God of heaven confirm him on his throne for many years and peaceful times, humiliate all his enemies under his feet speedily, grant him calm and delightful times, and grant us grace and mercy through his prayers and supplications. The Gospel according to our teacher Saint [AUTHOR] the Evangelist. May his blessing be with us. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               قفوا بخوف أمام الله لنسمع من فم أبينا المكرم البار المثلث الطوبى، أبينا المكرم الأسقف أنبا (...) أسقف المدينة المحبة للمسيح (...) وتخومها. إله السماء يثبته على كرسيه سنين وأزمنة سالمة. ويخضع جميع أعدائه تحت قدميه سريعا. ويعطيه زمانا هادئا لذيذا ويعطينا نعمة ورحمة بصلواته وطلباته الأنجيل لمعلمنا [AUTHOR] البشير بركته علينا آمين            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>   </Section></Document>