<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="AbrahamIsaacJacob:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for the Patriarchs Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Para Patriark Abraham, Ishak, dan Yakub</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للقديسين رؤساء الآباء أبراهيم واسحق ويعقوب</language>            <language id="Coptic">Hwc e~Po#c#...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               For the Commemoration of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob            </language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Hwc e~Po#c# qen ouhwc m~beri: qen han'almoc y~ba n~kwb: pierv~meui~ n~nao#c# n~io]: Abraam Icaak Iakwb.            </language>            <language id="English">               Sing unto the Lord a new song, with myriads of psalmodies, for the remembrance of my lords and fathers, Abraham Isaac and Jacob.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Nyanyikan lagu baru bagi Tuhan, dengan banyak nyanyian mazmur, untuk mengenang para tuan dan bapaku, Abraham, Ishak, dan Yakub.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               سبحوا الرب تسبحة جديدة بربوات مزامير بتذكار سادتى الآباء ابراهيم وإسحق ويعقوب.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Moi nan Po#c# n~ou,~bob: qen kenf n~nenio] n~dikeoc: Abraam Icaak Iakwb: qen piparadicoc nem noukep~roc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Grant us O Lord rest, in the bosom of our righteous fathers, Abraham Isaac and Jacob, in Paradise with their prayers.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berilah kepada kami, ya Tuhan, perhentian, dalam pangkuan bapa-bapa kami yang benar, Abraham, Ishak, dan Yakub, di Firdaus dengan doa mereka.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أعطنا يارب راحة فى أحضان آبائنا القديسين ابراهيم وإسحق ويعقوب فى الفردوس بصلواتهم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Mpererp~wbs n~]dia~y/k/: y/etakcemn/tc nem Abraam: ouoh aka~reh e~rof nem Icaak: ouoh aktahof e~ratf nem Iakwb.            </language>            <language id="English">               Do not forget the covenant, which You have made with Abraham, and guarded him with Isaac, and raised him with Jacob.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Jangan lupakan perjanjian, yang telah Kau buat dengan Abraham, dan pelihara dengan Ishak, dan tinggikan dengan Yakub.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لا تنقض العهد الذى قررته مع إبراهيم وحفظته لاسحق وأقمته مع يعقوب.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Cmou e~Po#c# w~ nilaoc: nivul/ nem niacpi n~lac: qen p~sai n~te ninis] qen nidikeoc: Abraam nem Icaak nem Iakwb.            </language>            <language id="English">               Bless the Lord O people, the tribes and all kinds of tongues, in the feast of the great and righteous, Abraham Isaac and Jacob.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Pujilah Tuhan, hai segala bangsa, suku dan bahasa, dalam perayaan besar dan benar, Abraham, Ishak, dan Yakub.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               باركوا الرب ياأيها الشعوب والقبائل ولغات الألسن فى عيد العظماء فى الصديقين إبراهيم واسحق ويعقوب.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Areten[ici e~masw nia~gioc: nem niy~m/i nem nidikeoc: moi nan Po#c# n~oumeroc: nem Abraam nem Icaak nem Iakwb.            </language>            <language id="English">               Exalt the saints greatly, with the righteous and the just, grant us O God an inheritance, with Abraham Isaac and Jacob.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tinggikan para kudus dengan sangat, bersama orang benar dan adil, berilah pada kami, ya Allah, suatu warisan, bersama Abraham, Ishak, dan Yakub.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               تعاليتم جداً أيها القديسين والأبرار والصديقين أعطنا يارب نصبياً مع إبراهيم وإسحق ويعقوب.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Twbh m~Po#c# e~h~r/i e~jwn: w~ nao#c# n~io] n~dikeoc: Abraam Icaak Iakwb: n~tef,a nennobi nan e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               Pray to the Lord on our behalf, O my lords and righteous fathers, Abraham Isaac and Jacob, that He may forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoalah pada Tuhan demi kami, wahai para tuan dan bapa kami yang benar, Abraham, Ishak, dan Yakub, agar Dia mengampuni dosa-dosa kami.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               إطلبوا من الرب عنا ياسادتى الآباء الصديقين إبراهيم وإسحق ويعقوب ليغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </section>   </season></document>