<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="AllMartyrs:Doxology">      <section antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for All the Martyrs</language><language id="Indonesian">Doksologi Untuk Para Martir</language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية لجميع الشهداء</language>            <language id="Coptic">Gewrgioc pimeliton...</language>         </Title>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Gewrgioc pimeliton: Yeo~dwroc pic~tratilat/c: Vilopat/r Merkourioc: a~pa M/na n~te nivaiat.            </language>            <language id="English">               George the Melitian: Theodore the General: Philopater Mercurius: and Abba Mena of Baiat.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>George dari Melitian, Theodore Sang Jenderal, Philopater Mercurius, dan Abba Mena dari Baiat.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               جرجس الملطي ثيؤدوروس الأمير محب الآب مرقوريوس أبا مينا البياضي.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Gewrgioc pimeliton: af[i n~hanm/s n~,/rma: afsenaf sa Cwr ]baki: sa p~ouro Dadianoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               George the Melitian: took a great amount of money: and went to the city of Sor: to King Dadianos.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>George dari Melitian mengambil banyak uang dan pergi ke kota Sor untuk menemui Raja Dadianos.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               جيؤرجيوس الملطي أخذ أموالاً كثيرة ومضي إلي مدينة صور إلي الملك دادانوس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Etafnau e~nii~dwlon: e~re nirwmi semsi m~mwou: afjwr m~petentaf n~nih/ki: afswpi n~cwtp m~marturoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               When he saw the idols: being worshipped by the men: he dispersed what he had to the poor: and became a chosen martyr.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ketika dia lihat berhala-berhala disembah oleh orang-orang, dia membagikan apa yang dia miliki pada orang miskin dan menjadi martir yang terpilih.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فلما رآي الأصنام والناس يعبدونها فرق كل ما له علي المساكين وصار شهيداً مختاراً.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Yeo~dwroc pic~tratilat/c: afsenaf e~h~r/i e~Eu,/toc: afqwteb m~pid~rakwn: afnohem n~nis/ri n~te ],/ra n~c~himi.            </language>            <language id="English">               Theodore the General: went to Euchaita: and killed the dragon: He rescued the sons of the widow.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Theodore Sang Jenderal pergi ke Euchaita dan membunuh naga. Dia selamatkan anak-anak dari seorang janda.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               يثؤدوروس الأمير مضي إلي أوخيطس وقَتلَ التنين وخلص أولاد المرأة الأرملة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Vilopat/r Merkourioc: afsenaf e~h~r/i N~ipercic: afsari e~Ioulia~noc: kata p~caji m~Bacilioc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Philopater Mercurius: went to Persia: he smote Julian: according to the word of Basil.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Philopater Mercurius pergi ke Persia dan menaklukkan Julian sesuai dengan perkataan Basil.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               محب الآب مرقوريوس مضي إلي الفرس وقَتلَ يوليانوس كقول باسيليوس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Apa M/na n~te Nivaiat: auenf e~q~r/i e~t~,wra n~&lt;/mi: a~ peflum'anon eyouab: ] m~p~ounof n~nen'u,/.            </language>            <language id="English">               Abba Mena of Baiat: was brought to the land of Egypt: his holy relics: brought joy to our souls.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Abba Mena dari Baiat dibawa ke tanah Mesir. Relik kudus miliknya membawa sukacita bagi jiwa kami.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أبا مينا البياضي أحضروه ألي إقليم مصر وجسده المقدس فرح نفوسنا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               W ]s~v/ri n~atcaji m~moc: n~te apa Biktwr pic~tratilat/c: je afhip~ho n~ni,/rma t/rou: e~ta pefiwt t/itou n~tefselet.            </language>            <language id="English">               Oh, the wonder that is inexpressible: of Abba Victor the General: he rejected all the wealth: which his father gave his bride.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Oh, keajaiban yang tak terkatakan dari Abba Victor Sang Jenderal, dia menolak semua kekayaan yang diberi ayahnya pada mempelainya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               يا للاعجوبة غير الموصوفة التي لأبا بقطر الأمير فانه رفض جميع الأموال التي دفعها أبوه لعرسه.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pisoumenritf Klaudioc: ouoh p~s~v/r n~apa Biktwr: auerlog,izin m~mof: qen ]polic Antinwou.            </language>            <language id="English">               The beloved Claudius: the friend of Abba Victor: was speared in the city: of Antino.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Claudius yang terkasih, sahabat Abba Victor, ditusuk tombak di kota Antino.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               المحبوب أقلاديوس صديق أبا بقطر طعنوه في مدينة أنصنا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pia~gioc Viloyeoc: n~yof afqwteb m~pimaci: e~tere nefio] semsi m~mof: san~teftacywou ha V] m~m/i.            </language>            <language id="English">               The saint Philotheos: slaughtered the calf: that his fathers were worshipping: until he returned them to the True God.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Santo Philotheos menyembelih anak lembu yang disembah ayahnya, hingga ia mengembalikan mereka kepada Allah yang Sejati.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               القديس فيلوثيؤس هو الذي قتل العجل معبود أبويه حتي ردّهما إلي الآله الحقيقي.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Coucennioc pic~tratilat/c: n~yof afqwteb m~berzelia~: afervorin m~pi,~lom n~atlwm: n~te ]metmarturoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Susenius the General: killed Berzeli: He wore the unfading crown: of martyrdom.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Susenius Sang Jenderal membunuh Berzeli. Dia mengenakan mahkota abadi dari kemartiran.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الأمير سوسنيوس هو الذي قتل المصّاصة ونالوا إكليل الشهادة غير المضمحل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pia~gioc kuri Iouctoc: nem Apali nem Yeoklia~: auo~hi e~ratou m~pem~yo m~p~ouro: qen ounis] m~parr/cia~.            </language>            <language id="English">               The saint and lord Justus: and Apali and Theoclia: stood on their feet: before the king with great boldness.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Santo dan tuan Justus, serta Apali dan Theoclia, berdiri dengan teguh di hadapan raja dengan keberanian besar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               القديسون يُسطس وآبالي وثيؤكليا وقفوا أمام الملك موقفاً عظيماً علانية.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afcaji nemwou n~je pia~ceb/c: piouro Diokl/tia~noc: je nim eterkwlin m~mwten: e~er ouhwb para petenouws.            </language>            <language id="English">               Diocletian, the ungodly king: spoke to them saying: “Who forces you to do: what is against your will?”            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Diokletianus, raja yang fasik, berkata k'pada mereka, "Siapa yang memaksa kalian melakukan apa yang bertentangan dengan kehendakmu?"</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فتكلم معهم الملك المنافق ديقلديانوس قائلاً من يمنعكم أن تعملوا خلاف إرادتكم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Etafc~qai n~toua~navora: afouorpou e~q~r/i e~t~,wra n~&gt;&lt;/mi: auervorin m~pi,~lom n~atlwm: n~te ]metmarturoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               When he decreed their sentence: he sent them to the land of Egypt: they wore the unfading crown: of martyrdom.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ketika dia menetapkan hukuman mereka, dia mengirim mereka ke tanah Mesir. Mereka mengenakan mahkota abadi dari kemartiran.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ولما كتب قضيتهم أرسلهم إلي إقليم مصر فنالوا إكليل الشهادة غير المضمحل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pia~goc Bacilit/c: nem Eucebioc nem Makarioc: auhip~ho n~niprocouc/ou: aukw] n~ca nisa e~neh.            </language>            <language id="English">               The saints Basilidis: Eusebius and Macarius: rejected the temporal: and sought after the eternal.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Para kudus Basilidis, Eusebius, dan Macarius, menolak yang sementara dan mencari yang kekal.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               القديسون وأسيليدس وأوسابيوس ومقاريوس رفضوا الزمنيات وطلبوا الأبديات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pia~gioc kuri Apat/r: e~ti efenkot qen pefkoitwn: a~ Pencwt/r ouonhf e~rof: qen t~vasi m~piejwrh.            </language>            <language id="English">               The saint and lord Apatir: while sleeping in his bedroom: our Savior appeared to him: in the middle of the night.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Santo dan tuan Apatir, saat tidur di kamarnya, Juruselamat kita menampakkan diri di tengah malam.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               القديس السيد أبادير فيما هو نائم في قصره ظهر له مخلصنا في نصف الليل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je twnk [i n~?ra/~ tekcwni: masenak e~t~,wra n~&lt;/mi: n~tekervorin m~pi,~lom n~atlwm: n~te ]metmarturoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Saying, “Arise and take Irae your sister: Go to the land of Egypt: and wear the unfading crown: of martyrdom”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berkata, "Bangkitlah dan bawa Irae, saudara perempuanmu. Pergilah ke tanah Mesir dan kenakan mahkota abadi dari kemartiran."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               قائلاً قم خذ أختك أيرائي وامض إلي إقليم مصر لنوال إكليل الشهادة غير المضمحل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pia~gioc apa Nahrwou: a~ Mi,a/l talof e~jen neftenh: icjen Rako] sa Antio~kia~: n~tefouwnh m~P,#c# e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               The saint Abba Nahro: was lifted by Michael on his wings: from Alexandria to Antioch: to proclaim Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Santo Abba Nahro diangkat oleh Mikhael dengan sayapnya dari Aleksandria ke Antiokhia untuk memberitakan Kristus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               القديس أبا نهروه حمله ميخائيل علي أجنحته من اسكندرية إلي أنطاكية ليعترف بالمسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pia~gioc Ctayioc: e~ti efjwrj n~nizwoun: a~ Pencwt/r ouonhf e~rof: hijen nentap m~pie~ioul.            </language>            <language id="English">               The saint Statius: while hunting animals: our Savior appeared to him: on the horns of a deer.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Santo Statius, saat berburu hewan, Juruselamat kita menampakkan diri di tanduk seekor rusa.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               القديس أسطاتيوس فيما هو يصيد الحيوانات ظهر له مخلصنا علي قرون الأيل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ere pim/ini n~te pic~tauroc: oi n~,~lom e~jen tefa~ve: afervorin n~pi,~lom n~atlwm: n~te ]metmarturoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               The sign of the cross: being a crown on his head: He wore the unfading crown: of martyrdom.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tanda salib sebagai mahkota di kepalanya. Dia mengenakan mahkota abadi dari kemartiran.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وعلامة الصليب تكلل رأسه فنال القديس إكليل الشهادة غير المضمحل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Yeo~dwroc pia~natoleoc: aferp~emp~sa m~piwmc eyouab: n~h~r/i qen ]lumn/ n~,~rwm: n~yof nem pefkes~v/r c~nau.            </language>            <language id="English">               Theodore Anatolius: was worthy of holy baptism: in the lake of fire: also with his two friends.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Theodore Anatolius menerima baptisan kudus di danau api bersama dua temannya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ثيؤدوروس المشرقي استحق الصبغة المقدسة في بحيرة النار هو وصديقاه.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Iakwboc n~te Nipercic: aucwlp n~ca nefmeloc t/rou: e~re pefnouc ,/ qen niv/oui: efhwc nem niaggeloc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Jacob of Persia: has all his limbs cut off: while his mind was in heaven: singing with the angels.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Yakobus dari Persia, semua anggota tubuhnya dipotong, sementara pikirannya berada di surga, bernyanyi bersama para malaikat.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               يعقوب الفارسي قطعوا جميع أعضائه بينما عقله كائن في السموات يسبح مع الملائكة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Iwann/c piremcenhwout: nem Icaak pirem]vre: auervorin m~pi,~lom n~atlwm: n~te ]metmarturoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               John of Senhout: and Isaac of Daphre: wore the unfading crown: of martyrdom.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Yohanes dari Senhout dan Ishak dari Daphre mengenakan mahkota abadi dari kemartiran.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               يوحنا السنهوتي واسحق الدفراوي نالا إكليل الشهادة غير المضمحل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               ?cidwroc nem Cana nimatoi: au] m~pououi hijen pib/ma: ausep hannis] m~bacanoc: eybe Ps/ri m~V] etonq.            </language>            <language id="English">               Isidore and Sana the soldiers: rushed to the throne: they received great tortures: for the Son of the Living God.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Isidore dan Sana, para prajurit, bergegas ke tahta. Mereka menerima siksaan besar demi Putra Allah yang Hidup.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               إيسيدوروس وسانا الجنديان إندفعا إلي المنبر وقبلا عذابات عظيمة لأجل إبن الله الحي.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tiou n~con n~aylovoroc: n~diakwn n~te P,#c#: e~te Kocma nem Demianoc: nem Anyimoc nem Leontioc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Five struggling brothers: the deacons of Christ: Cosma and Demian: and Anthimus and Leontius,            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Lima saudara pejuang, para diakon Kristus, Cosma dan Demian, serta Anthimus dan Leontius,</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               خمسة إخوة مجاهدين خُدام المسيح وهم قزمان ودميان وأنثيموس ولاونديوس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nem Eup~repioc poucon: e~re toumau ]nom] nwou: je nanec nwten n~tetenmou: e~hote e~jel P,#c# e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               And Euprepius their brother: being comforted by their mother: “It is better for you to die: than to deny Christ”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan Euprepius saudara mereka, dihibur oleh ibu mereka, "Lebih baik kalian mati daripada menyangkal Kristus."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وأخوهم إبرابيوس كانت أمهم تعزيهم قائلة حسناً لكم أن تموتوا أفضل من أن تجحدوا المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Apic~mou n~te n/e#y#u#: jwk e~bol e~h~r/i e~jwk: pia~gioc Ioulioc: pibo/~yoc n~rem,bahc.            </language>            <language id="English">               The blessing of the saints: was completed with you: O Saint Julius: the helper: from the land of Akfahs.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berkat para kudus disempurnakan denganmu, Ya Santo Julius, penolong dari tanah Akfahs.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بركة القديسين كمُلت عليك أيها القديس يوليوس المُعين الاقفهصي.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je niqici e~taksopou: nem nimarturoc e#y#u#: a~ pouc~mou kwb e~h~r/i e~jwk: sa ]mahsom] n~genea.            </language>            <language id="English">               Because of the sufferings you received: with the holy martyrs: Their blessing is doubled on you: until the third generation.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Karena penderitaan yang kau terima bersama para martir kudus, berkat mereka dilipatgandakan atasmu hingga generasi ketiga.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأن الأتعاب التي قبلتها مع الشهداء القديسين تضاعفت بركتها عليك إلي الجيل الثالث.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Qen nai akervorin m~pi,~lom: n~te ]metmarturoc: nem peks/ri nem pekcon: nem t~iou se m~bwk n~tak.            </language>            <language id="English">               Through these sufferings: you wore the crown of martyrdom: with your son and your brother: and your five hundred servants.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Melalui penderitaan ini, kau kenakan mahkota kemartiran bersama putramu, saudaramu, dan lima ratus hambamu.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بهذا نلت إكليل الشهادة مع ابنك وأخيك وخمس مئة عبدٍ لك.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               W p~a~sai n~te n/e#y#u#: ]nas~jotou t/rou an: ceos m~v~r/] m~piqemc: kata p~caji n~nig~rav/.            </language>            <language id="English">               Oh, the multitude of the saints: I cannot count them all: They are abundant as wheat: according to the word of the Scriptures.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div><div>Oh, sungguh banyaknya para kudus, aku tidak dapat menghitung semuanya. Mereka berlimpah seperti gandum, menurut firman Kitab Suci.</div></div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               يا لكثرة القديسين لا استطيع أحصيهم جميعاً لأنهم كثيرون مثل السيل كقول الكتب.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ni,~lom n~te nimarturoc: han e~bol qen paikocmoc an ne: alla Pcwt/r aft/itou e~jwou: qen ouw~ou nem outaio~.            </language>            <language id="English">               The crowns of the martyrs: are not from this world: The Savior placed them upon them: with glory and honor.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mahkota para martir bukan dari dunia ini. Juruselamat menempatkannya di atas mereka dengan kemuliaan dan kehormatan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أكاليل الشهداء ليست من هذا العالم بل منحها المخلص إياهم بمجد وكرامة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Kata v~r/] e~tafjoc: n~je Dauid qen pi'almoc: je ouw~ou nem outaio~: aft/itou n~,~lom e~jwou.            </language>            <language id="English">               As was said by David: in the book of the Psalms: “He crowned them with: glory and honor”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Seperti yang dikatakan oleh Daud dalam Kitab Mazmur, "Dia memahkotai mereka dengan kemuliaan dan kehormatan."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               كما قال داود في المزمور إنه بمجد وكرامة وضع عليهم الأكليل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Twbh m~Po#c# e~h~r/i e~jwn: ni,oroc n~te nimarturoc: e~tausepm~kah eybe P,#c#: n~tef,a nennobi nan e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               Pray to the Lord on our behalf: O choruses of the martyrs: who suffered for the sake of Christ: that He may forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoalah pada Tuhan demi kami, hai barisan para martir yang menderita demi Kristus, agar Dia mengampuni dosa-dosa kami.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أطلبوا من الرب عنا ياصفوف الشهداء الذين تألموا من أجل المسيح ليغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>            </section>      <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/AllFemaleMartyrsOrSaints" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   </season></document>