<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section antiphonepitch="1">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Doxology for the Apostles</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Para Rasul</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية لآبائنا الرسل</language>         <language id="Coptic">Pisorp qen nia~poctoloc...</language>      </Title>         <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/Apostles.2.1" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ke ouai on je Iwann/c: f~mei m~mof e~masw: afrwteb m~mof e~h~r/i e~jen: y~mectenh/t m~Pencwt/r.         </language>         <language id="English">            Also another one is John, he loved Him very much, he rested his head, on the shoulders of our Savior.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Juga ada satu lagi, yaitu Yohanes, yang sangat mengasihi-Nya, ia sandarkan kepalanya, di bahu Juruselamat kita.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            وآخر أيضاً يدعي يوحنا يحبه جداً اتكأ علي صدر مخلسنا.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Nem p~cepi n~te nimay/t/c: ouon n~twou n~outaio~ m~mau: eybe toumeta~poctoloc: je aumosi n~ca Pencwt/r.         </language>         <language id="English">            And the rest of the disciples, they have honor also, on account of their apostleship, for they followed our Savior.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan para murid lainnya, mereka juga punya kehormatan, karena kerasulan mereka, sebab mereka mengikuti Juruselamat kita.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            وبقية التلاميذ لهم الكرامة من أجل رسوليتهم لأنهم تبعوا مخلصنا.         </language>      </text>      <insertdocument path="include/praises/ApostlesCommemoration" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   </section>      <section antiphonepitch="1">      <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Another Doxology for the Apostles</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi Lain untuk Para Rasul</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية لآبائنا الرسل</language>         <language id="Coptic">Kurioc I/#c# P,#c#...</language>      </Title>            <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Kurioc I/#c# P,#c#: afcwtp n~nefa~poctoloc: e~te Petroc nem And~reac: Iwann/c nem Iakwboc.         </language>         <language id="English">            Our Lord Jesus Christ: has chosen His apostles: Peter and Andrew: John and James.           </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus: telah pilih rasul-Nya: Petrus dan Andreas: Yohanes dan Yakobus.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            الرب يسوع المسيح اختار رسله وهم بطرس واندراوس ويوحنا ويعقوب.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Loipon Vilippoc nem Matyeoc: Baryolomeoc nem Ywmac: Iakwboc n~te Alveoc: nem Cimwn pikananeoc.         </language>         <language id="English">            And the rest, Philip and Matthew: Bartholomew and Thomas: James the son of Alphaeus: and Simon the Canaanite.         </language><language id="Indonesian">Filipus dan Matius, Bartolomeus dan Tomas, Yakobus anak Alfeus, dan Simon orang Kanaan.</language>         <language id="Arabic">            وفيلبس ومتى وبرثولماوس وتوما ويعقوب بن حلفى وسمعان القانوى.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Yaddeoc nem Matyiac: Pauloc nem Markoc nem Loukac: nem p~cepi n~te nimay/t/c: n/e~taumosi n~ca Pencwt/r.         </language>         <language id="English">            Thaddeus and Matthias: Paul, Mark and Luke: and the rest of the disciples: who followed our Savior.          </language><language id="Indonesian">            Tadeus dan Matias, Paulus, Markus, dan Lukas, dan para murid lainnya, yang ikut Juruselamat kita.          </language>         <language id="Arabic">            وتداوس ومتياس وبولس ومرقس ولوقا وبقية التلاميذ الذين تبعوا مخلصنا.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Matyiac v/e~tafswpi: n~t~sebiw n~Ioudac: nem p~jwk e~bol nem p~cepi: n/e~taumosi n~ca decpota.         </language>         <language id="English">            Matthias, who was chosen: in place of Judas: all of them and the rest: followed the Master.          </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Matias, yang dipilih gantikan Yudas, mereka semua dan yang lainnya, ikut Sang Guru.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            متياس الذي صار عوضا عن يهوذا وكامل وبقية التلاميذ الذين تبعوا السيد.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Apouq~rwou senaf e~bol: hijen p~ho m~p~kahi t/rf: ouoh noucaji auvoh: sa aur/jc n~]oikoumen/.         </language>         <language id="English">            Their voices went forth: throughout the face of the whole earth: and their words have reached: the ends of the world.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Suara mereka terdengar seluruh muka bumi: dan perkataan mereka telah sampai: ke ujung dunia.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            خرجت أصواتهم إلى وجه الأرض كلها وبلغ كلامهم إلى أقطار المسكونة.         </language>      </text>         <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/Apostles" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   </section></document>