<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="CopticNewYearPeriod">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for the Coptic New Year</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Tahun Baru Koptik:</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية فى عيد النيروز</language>            <language id="Coptic">Hwc Po#c#...</language>         </Title>                             <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Coptic New Year:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Tahun Baru Koptik:</div></language>         </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Hwc Po#c# qen ouhwc m~beri: w~ nilaoc m~mai P,#c# Pennou]: je afjempensini qen pefoujai: hwc a~gayoc ouoh m~mairwmi.            </language>            <language id="English">               Sing to the Lord a new song, O people who love Christ our God, for He visited us with His salvation, as the Good One and Lover of Mankind.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Nyanyikan lagu baru bagi Tuhan, hai umat yang mengasihi Kristus, Allah kita, sebab Ia telah mengunjungi kita dengan keselamatan-Nya, Dia-lah Yang Baik dan Pengasih manusia.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               سبحوا الرب تسبيحاً جديداً أيها الشعوب محبو المسيح إلهنا لأنه قد تعهدنا بخلاصه كصالح ومحب البشر.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tenouwrp nak m~pihumnoc: qen hanc~m/ n~]doxologia~: w~ Pencwt/r n~a~gayoc: matajron sa ]cuntelia.            </language>            <language id="English">               We ascribe praise unto You, with voices of glorification, O our good Savior, confirm us unto the end.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami puji-Mu dengan suara penuh kemuliaan, ya Juruselamat kami yang baik, teguhkan kami sampai akhir.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نرسل لك التسبيح بأصوات التمجيد يامخلصنا الصالح ثبتنا إلى الانقضاء.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Moi nan Po#c# n~tekhir/n/: nahmen qen nenjij n~te nenjaji: mayebio~ m~pouco[ni: ouoh matal[o n~nenswni.            </language>            <language id="English">               Grant us O Lord Your peace, and save us from the hands of our enemies, humiliate their counsel, and heal our sicknesses.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Beri damai-Mu ya Tuhan, dan selamatkan kami dari tangan musuh kami, gagalkan rencana mereka, dan sembuhkan penyakit kami.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أعطنا يارب سلامك ونجنا من أيدى أعدائنا وأذل مشورتهم وأشف أمراضنا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Cmou e~pi,~lom n~te ]rompi: hiten tekmet,~r/ctoc Po#c#: niiarwou nem nimoumi: nem nici] nem nikarpoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Bless the crown of the year, with Your goodness O Lord, the rivers and the springs, the plants and the fruits.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berkati permulaan tahun ini, dengan kebaikan-Mu, ya Tuhan, sungai dan mata air, tanaman dan buah-buahan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بارك يارب إكليل السنة بصلاحك الأنهار والينابيع والزروع والأثمار.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Cmou e~ron qen nenh~b/oui~: qen pekc~mou n~e~pouranion: ouwrp nan e~bol qen pek[ici: pekh~mot nem neka~gayon.            </language>            <language id="English">               Bless us in our work, with Your heavenly blessings, and send unto us from on high, Your grace and Your goodness.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berkati kami dalam pekerjaan kami, dengan berkat surgawi-Mu, dan kirimkan bagi kami kasih karunia serta kebaikan-Mu dari tempat tertinggi.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               باركنا فى أعمالنا ببركتك السمائية وأرسل لنا من علوك نعمتك وخيراتك.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               N/ethejhwj nahmou e~bol: n/e~tause e~p~semmo matacywou: nem n/etcwnh bolou e~bol: n/e~tauenkot mam~ton nwou.            </language>            <language id="English">               The afflicted save them, the travelers return them, the bound loosen them, and those who have slept repose them.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Selamatkan yang kesusahan, kembalikanlah para musafir (yang lagi di perjalanan) bebaskan mereka yang terikat masalah, dan  berilah istirahat yang telah meninggal.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               المتضايقين خلصهم والمسافرين ردهم والمربوطين حلهم الراقدين نيحهم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Wli m~pekjwnt e~bol haron: nahmen e~bolha ouh~bwn: nem nivas n~te nidemwn: w~ v~ref] n~nia~gayon.            </language>            <language id="English">               Lift away Your wrath from us, and deliver us from inflation, and from the snares of demons, O Giver of good things.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Jauhkan murka-Mu dari kami, dan lepaskan kami dari inflasi, dan dari jerat iblis, ya Pemberi hal-hal baik.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ارفع غضبك عنا ونجنا من الغلاء ومن فخاخ الشياطين يامعطى الخيرات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tenhwc e~rof ten]w~ou naf: tenerhouo~ [ici m~mof: hwc a~gayoc ouoh m~mairwmi: nai nan kata peknis] n~nai.            </language>            <language id="English">                We praise and glorify Him, and exalt Him above all, as the Good One and Lover of Mankind, have mercy on us according to Your great mercy.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami puji dan muliakan Dia, tinggikan di atas segala sesuatu,</div><div>sebagai Yang Mahabaik dan Pengasih manusia, kasihani kami menurut rahmat-Mu yang besar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسبحه ونمجده ونرفعه بالأكثر كصالح ومحب البشر ارحمنا كعظيم رحمتك.            </language>         </text>      </section>   </season>    </document>