<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="FeastOfTheCross | HolyCross:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for the Feast of the Cross</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Perayaan Salib Suci</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية عيد الصليب</language>            <language id="Coptic">Anon hwn...</language>         </Title>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Feast of the Cross:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Hari Raya Salib Suci:</div></language>         </comment>                           <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Anon hwn qa nilaoc: nis/ri n~oryodoxoc: n~tenouwst m~pic~tauroc: n~te Peno#c# I/#c# P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               We too, the people: the Orthodox children: we bow down to the Cross: of our Lord Jesus Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami juga, umat-Mu,</div><div>anak-anak Ortodoks,</div><div>bersujud kepada Salib-Mu, ya Tuhan kami Yesus Kristus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نحن أيضاً معشر الشعوب أبناء الارثوذكسيين نسجد لصليب ربنا يسوع المسيح .            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pauloc pia~poctoloc: efjw m~p~taio~ m~pic~tauroc: je tennasousou m~mon an: e~b/l qen pic~tauroc n~te P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               Paul the apostle: speaks of the honor of the Cross: saying, “We will not boast: except in the Cross of Christ.”            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Paulus sang rasul berbicara tentang kemuliaan Salib, katanya, "Kami tidak akan bermegah kecuali dalam Salib Kristus."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بولس الرسول ينطق بكرامة الصليب قائلا ليس لنا أن نفتخر إلا بصليب المسيح .            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tenerhumnoc w~ nipictoc: m~Peno#c# I/#c# P,#c#: ouoh tenouwst m~pefc~tauroc: pise e#y#u# n~a~yanatoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               We sing hymns, O faithful: to our Lord Jesus Christ: and we bow down to His Cross: the immortal and holy wood.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami menyanyikan kidung pujian, wahai orang-orang beriman,</div><div>kepada Tuhan Yesus Kristus, dan bersujud kepada Salib-Nya, kayu yang kudus dan penuh kehidupan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيها المؤمنون فلنسبح ربنا يسوع المسيح  ونسجد لصليبه الخشبة المقدسة غير المائتة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tensousou m~mok w~ pic~tauroc: v/e~taui~si ejwk n~I/#c#: je e~bol hiten pektupoc: answpi ene~leuyeroc.            </language>            <language id="English">               We take pride in you, O Cross: on which Jesus was crucified: for through your type: we were set free            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami bermegah atasmu, wahai Salib yang mulia, tempat Yesus disalibkan, melalui bayanganmu, kami dibebaskan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               تفتخر بك أيها الصليب الذى صُلب عليك يسوع لأنه من قبل مثالك صرنا احراراً .            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Rwou n~nioryodoxoc: nem sasf n~tagma n~aggeloc: cesousou m~mok w~ pic~tauroc: n~te Pencwt/r n~a~gayoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               The mouths of the Orthodox: and the seven orders of the angels: take pride in you, O Cross: of our good Savior            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mulut-mulut umat Ortodoks, dan tujuh tingkatan malaikat surgawi, bermegah atasmu, wahai Salib dari Juruselamat kita yang baik.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أفواه الأرثوذكسيين والسبع الطغمات الملائكية يفتخرون بك أيها الصليب الذى لمخلصنا الصالح .            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tentalo m~mok w~ pic~tauroc: v~nas] n~ni,~rictia~noc: e~jen nenmo] n~dunatoc: ouoh n~tenws e~bol r/twc.            </language>            <language id="English">               We carry you, O Cross: the strength of the Christians: powerfully around our necks: and we cry out openly            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami membawa-Mu, wahai Salib, kekuatan umat Kristiani, dengan penuh keyakinan di leher kami, dan berseru dengan suara lantang.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نحملك على أعناقنا أيها الصليب ناصر المسيحيين بشجاعة ونصرخ جهارأ.            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pic~tauroc: v~rasi n~ni,~rictia~noc: pi[ro oube piturannoc: nem pentajro a~non qa nipictoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you, O Cross: the joy of the Christians: the conqueror of the tyranny: and our stead-fastness, we the faithful.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, wahai Salib, sukacita umat Kristen, penakluk kezaliman, dan peneguhan bagi kami, umat setia.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيها الصليب فرح المسيحيين الغالب ضد المعاندين وثباتنا نحن معشر المؤمنين.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pic~tauroc: v~nom] n~nipictoc: ouoh p~tajro n~nimarturoc: sa n~toujwk e~bol n~noubacanoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you, O Cross: the comfort of the faithful: the steadfastness of the martyrs: until they completed their tortures            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, wahai Salib, penghiburan bagi orang percaya, keteguhan para martir,</div><div>hingga mereka menyelesaikan penderitaan mereka.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيها الصليب عزاء المؤمنين وثبات الشهداء حتى أكملوا عذاباتهم .            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pic~tauroc: pihoplon n~te pi[ro: ,ere nak w~ pic~tauroc: piy~ronoc m~piouro.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you, O Cross: the weapon of victory: Hail to you, O Cross: the throne of the King.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, wahai Salib, senjata kemenangan; Salam bagimu, wahai Salib, takhta Sang Raja.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيها الصليب سلاح الغلبة السلام لك أيها الصليب عرش الملك.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pic~tauroc: pim/ini n~te pioujai: ,ere nak w~ pic~tauroc: piouwini e~tafsai.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you, O Cross: the sign of salvation: Hail to you, O Cross: the shining light.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, wahai Salib, tanda keselamatan; Salam bagimu, wahai Salib, cahaya yang bersinar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيها الصليب علامة الخلاص السلام لك أيها الصليب النور المشرق.            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pic~tauroc: ]c/fi n~te Pip#n#a#: ,ere nak w~ pic~tauroc: ]moumi n~ni,aricma.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you, O Cross: the sword of the Spirit: Hail to you, O Cross: the spring of grace.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, wahai Salib, pedang Roh Kudus; Salam bagimu, wahai Salib, mata air anugerah.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيها الصليب سيف الروح السلام لك أيها الصليب ينبوع النعم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pic~tauroc: piyucauroc n~te nia~gayon: ,ere nak w~ pic~tauroc: sa p~jwk e~bol n~nie~wn.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you, O Cross: the treasure of good things: Hail to you, O Cross: to the end of the ages.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, wahai Salib, harta dari segala yang baik; Salam bagimu, wahai Salib, hingga akhir segala zaman.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيها الصليب كنز الخيرات السلام لك أيها الصليب إلى كمال الدهور .            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je ,ere nak w~ pic~tauroc: v/e~ta p~ouro Kwctantinoc: olf nemaf e~pipolemoc: afsari n~niBarbaroc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you, O Cross: which King Constantine: carried with him to war: and smote the barbarians.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, wahai Salib, yang dibawa Raja Konstantinus menuju medan perang,</div><div>dan menghancurkan musuh kafir.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               قائلين السلام لك أيها الصليب الذى حمله الملك قسطنطين معه إلى الحرب وقتل البربر .            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ftai/out gar e~masw: n~je pim/ini n~te pic~tauroc: n~te I/#c# P,#c# p~ouro: Pennou] n~al/yinoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Greatly honored: is the sign of the Cross: of Jesus Christ the King: our True God.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sungguh besar kemuliaanmu, wahai tanda Salib Yesus Kristus Sang Raja, Allah sejati kita.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               مكرمة جداً علامة الصليب الذى ليسوع المسيح الملك إلهنا الحقيقى.            </language>         </text>         <text>            <language id="Coptic">               V/e~tauasf e~pic~tauroc: san~tefcw] m~pengenoc: a~non de hwn marentaiof: enws e~bol enjw m~moc.            </language>            <language id="English">               He, who was crucified on the Cross: in order to save our race: We too, let us honor Him: crying out saying.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dia yang disalibkan di atas Salib, demi menyelamatkan umat manusia, kita pun menghormati-Nya, dengan berseru dan berkata:</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الذى صُلب على الصليب حتى خلص جنسنا  ونحن أيضاً فلنكرمه صارخين قائلين.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pic~tauroc pe penhoplon: pic~tauroc pe tenhelpic: pic~tauroc pe pentajro: qen nenhojhej nem neny~li'ic.            </language>            <language id="English">               The Cross is our weapon: The Cross is our hope: The Cross is our steadfastness: in our troubles and sufferings.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salib adalah senjata kami, Salib adalah harapan kami,</div><div>Salib adalah keteguhan kami, di tengah penderitaan dan kesusahan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الصليب هو سلاحنا الصليب هو رجاؤنا الصليب هو ثباتنا فى ضيقاتنا وشدائدنا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je f~c~marwout n~je P,#c# Pennou]: nem pefc~tauroc n~reftanqo: v/etauasf e~h~r/i e~jwf: sa n~tefcotten qen nennobi.            </language>            <language id="English">               For blessed is Christ our God: and His life-giving Cross: on which He was crucified: in order to save us from our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sebab terberkatilah Kristus, Allah kita, dan Salib-Nya yang menghidupkan, tempat Dia disalibkan untuk menyelamatkan kita dari dosa.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأنه مبارك المسيح إلهنا وصليبه المحيى الذى صُلب عليه حتى خلصنا من خطايانا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tenhwc e~rof ten]wou naf: tenerhouo~ [ici m~mof: hwc a~gayoc ouoh m~mairwmi nai nan kata peknis] n~nai.            </language>            <language id="English">               We praise and glorify Him: and exalt Him above all: as the Good One and Lover of Mankind: have mercy on us according to Your great mercy.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami memuji dan memuliakan-Nya, dan meninggikan Dia di atas segalanya, sebagai Yang Baik dan Pengasih manusia: kasihanilah kami menurut belas kasih-Mu yang besar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسبحه ونمجده ونزيده علواً كصالح ومحب البشر إرحمنا كعظيم رحمتك.            </language>         </text>      </section>               </season>  </document>