<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="HosannaSunday">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for Hosanna Sunday</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Minggu Hosanna</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية لأحد الشعانين</language>            <language id="Coptic">Aricalpizin qen oucouai...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For Hosanna Sunday in the Hosanna tune:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Minggu Hosanna dengan nada Hosanna:</div></language>         </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Aricalpizin qen oucouai: qen ouc~m/ n~calpiggoc: qen oue~hoou n~netensai: je ouahcahni n~Yeoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Blow the trumpet at the new moon: with the sound of the trumpet: on your festive day: for it is an order from God.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tiuplah sangkakala pada bulan baru, dengan suara nafiri yang nyaring, pada hari raya sucimu, sebab itu adalah perintah dari Allah.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بوقوا فى رأس الشهر بصوت البوق فى يوم أعيادكم لأنه أمر الله.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               V/ethemci hijen ni,eroubim: aftalof e~oue~w~: afse e~qoun e~Ieroucal/m: oupe painis] n~yebio.            </language>            <language id="English">               He who sits upon the cherubim: rode on a donkey: and entered into Jerusalem: what is this great humility!            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dia yang bersemayam di atas para kerubim, mengendarai keledai, dan masuk ke Yerusalem — alangkah besar kerendahan hati-Nya!</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الجالس على الشاروبيم ركب على أتان ودخل إلى أورشليم ما هذا التواضع العظيم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Kata v~r/] e~tafjoc: n~je Dauid qen pi'almoc: je f~c~marwout n~je v/eyn/ou: qen v~ran m~Po#c# n~te nijom.            </language>            <language id="English">               According to what David said: in the Psalms: blessed is He who comes: in the name of the Lord of Hosts.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sesuai dengan yang dikatakan Daud di dalam Mazmur-Nya: "Diberkatilah Dia yang datang dalam nama Tuhan semesta alam."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               كما قال داود فى المزمور مبارك الآتى باسم رب القوات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Palin on afjw m~moc: je e~bolqen rwou n~hankouji: n~a~lwoui~ nem n/eyouem[i: n~yok akcebte pic~mou.            </language>            <language id="English">               Again he said: out of the mouth of babes: and nursing infants: You have perfected praise.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Lagi Daud berkata: "Dari mulut bayi-bayi dan anak-anak menyusui, Kau telah sempurnakan pujian."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وقال أيضاً أن من أفواه الأطفال والرضعان أعددت سبحاً.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tote afjwk e~bol m~picaji: n~te Dauid pip~neumatovoroc: je e~bol qen rwou n~hankouji: n~a~lwoui~ m~pair/] efjw m~moc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Then He completed the saying: of David the spirit-bearer: who likewise said: out of the mouth of babes.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kemudian Tuhan genapi sabda dari Daud, sang pembawa Roh, yang berkata pula: "Dari mulut bayi-bayi…"</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               حينئذ كمل قول داود الروحى من أفواه الأطفال الصغار هكذا قائلا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Cehwc e~rof qen ounehci: auje vai pe Emmanou/l: w~canna qen n/et[oci: vai pe p~ouro m~Pic~ra/l.            </language>            <language id="English">               They praise Him watchfully: saying, This is Immanuel: Hosanna in the highest: this is the King of Israel.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mereka puji Dia dengan penuh perhatian, seraya berseru, "Inilah Imanuel, Hosanna di tempat yang mahatinggi, inilah Raja Israel!"</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               يسبحونه بيقظة قائلين هذا هو عمانوئيل أوصنا فى الأعالى هذا هو ملك إسرائيل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Anioui~ m~Po#c# n~nis/ri n~te V]: anioui~ m~Po#c# n~ouw~ou nem outaio~: e~sl/loui~ e~bol m~Pennou]: qen handoxologia n~c~mou.            </language>            <language id="English">               Bring to the Lord, O sons of God: bring to the Lord glory and honor: rejoice in our God: with doxologies of blessing.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Persembahkanlah bagi Tuhan, hai anak-anak Allah, persembahkanlah kemuliaan dan hormat kepada Tuhan. Bersukacitalah dalam Allah kita dengan pujian dan berkat.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               قدموا للرب أبناء الله قدموا للرب مجداً وكرامة هللوا لالهنا بتماجيد البركة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nyok V] f~ersau nak: n~je pijw qen Ciwn: nem Ieroucal/m eue~] nak: n~haneu,/ sa nie~wn.            </language>            <language id="English">               Praise is due to You, O God: in Zion and Jerusalem: they send to You: prayers unto the ages.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Engkau yang layak terima pujian, ya Allah, di Sion dan Yerusalem. Mereka angkat doa pada-Mu, hingga selama-lamanya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أنت الله يليق بك النشيد فى صهيون وفى أورشليم يقدمون لك النذور إلى الدهور.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Wcanna qen n/et[oci: vai pe p~ouro m~Pic~ra/l: f~c~marwout n~je v/eyn/ou: qen v~ran m~Po#c# n~te nijom.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hosanna in the highest: this is the King of Israel: blessed is He, who comes in the name: of the Lord of Hosts.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Hosanna di tempat tinggi! Inilah Raja Israel! Diberkatilah Dia yang datang dalam nama Tuhan semesta alam.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أوصنا فى الأعالى هذا هو ملك إسرائيل مبارك الآتى باسم رب القوات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tenhwc e~rof ten]w~ou naf: tenerhouo~ [ici m~mof: hwc a~gayoc ouoh m~mairwmi: nai nan kata peknis] n~nai.            </language>            <language id="English">               We praise Him and glorify Him: and exalt Him above all: as the Good One and Lover of Mankind: have mercy on us according to Your great mercy.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami puji dan muliakan Dia, tinggikan di atas segalanya, karena Dia-lah Sang Baik dan Pengasih, kasihanilah kami menurut belas kasihan-Mu yang besar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسبحه ونمجده ونزيده رفعة كصالح ومحب البشر إرحمنا كعظيم رحمتك.            </language>         </text>      </section>            <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Second Doxology for Hosanna Sunday</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi Kedua untuk Minggu Hosanna</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية ثانية لأحد الشعانين</language>            <language id="Coptic">Dauid gar pihumnodoc...</language>         </Title>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               For Hosanna Sunday in the Hosanna tune:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Minggu Hosanna dengan nada Hosanna:</div></language>         </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Dauid gar pihumnodoc: p~ouro m~Pic~ra/l: afjw m~p~taio~ m~painis] n~sai: m~pair/] efjw m~moc.            </language>            <language id="English">               For David the hymnist: the King of Israel: spoke of the honor of this great feast: in this manner saying,            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tentang Daud sang pemazmur, Raja Israel, bernubuat kehormatan pesta besar ini, dan berkata:</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأن داود المرتل وملك إسرائيل نطق بكرامة هذا العيد العظيم هكذا قائلا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je e~bolqen rwou n~hankouji: n~a~lwoui~ nem n/eyouem[i: n~yok akcebte pic~mou: kata petehnak Po#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               “Out of the mouth of babes: and nursing infants: You have perfected praise: according to Your will, O Lord”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>"Dari mulut anak-anak dan bayi yang menyusu, Kau telah sempurnakan pujian, sesuai dengan kehendak-Mu, ya Tuhan."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ان من أفواه الأطفال الصغار والرضعان أنت أعددت سبحاً كإرادتك يا رب.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Cc~q/out on m~pererho]: w~ t~seri n~Ciwn: h/ppe gar peouro efn/ou ne: eftal/out e~jen ouc/j.            </language>            <language id="English">               It is also written: “Do not fear, O Daughter of Zion: behold your king is coming to you: riding on a colt”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Juga tertulis: "Jangan takut, hai Putri Sion, lihatlah Rajamu datang kepadamu, duduk di atas anak keledai."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               و مكتوب أيضاً لاتخافي يا ابنة صهيون هوذا ملكك يإتيك راكباً علي جحش.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Oupe painis] n~yebio: v/e~tafaif n~je Pencwt/r: e~tafse e~qoun e~Ieroucal/m: e~tafa~l/i e~oue~w~.            </language>            <language id="English">               What is this great humility: which was shown by our Savior: when He entered Jerusalem: after sitting on a donkey.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sungguh luar biasa kerendahan hati ini, yang ditunjukkan  Juruselamat kita, saat Ia masuk ke Yerusalem menunggangi keledai.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               يا لهذا التواضع العظيم الذي صنعه مخلصنا لما دخل إلي أورشليم راكباً علي أتان.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Mvoou gar aujwk e~bol: n~je naip~rov/tia~: hanouon au[i n~hanbai: nem hank~ladoc n~te hanjwit.            </language>            <language id="English">               For today these prophecies: have been completed: some took palm branches: and branches of olives.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Hari ini, nubuatan itu digenapi sepenuhnya: ada yang membawa daun palma dan ranting pohon zaitun.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               اليوم كملت هذه النبوات البعض أخذوا سعف النخيل وأغصان الزيتون.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Hanke,wouni auvwrs n~nouh~bwc: hi pimwit m~pefm~yo: nia~lwoui~ auws e~bol: je Wcanna p~s/ri n~Dauid.            </language>            <language id="English">               Others spread their garments: upon the road before Him: the children cried out saying: “Hosanna, Son of David”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Yang lain hamparkan pakaian mereka di jalan yang akan dilalui-Nya; anak-anak berseru dan berkata: "Hosanna, Anak Daud!"</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وأخرون فرشوا ثيابهم في الطريق أمامه والأطفال صرخوا قائلين أوصنا لابن داود.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Wcanna qen n/et[oci: vai pe p~ouro m~Pic~ra/l: f~c~marwout n~je v/eyn/ou: qen v~ran m~Po#c# n~te nijom.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hosanna in the highest: this is the King of Israel: blessed is He who comes: in the name of the Lord of Hosts.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Hosanna di tempat tinggi, inilah Raja Israel!</div><div>Diberkatilah Dia yang datang dalam nama Tuhan semesta alam!</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أوصنا فى الأعالى هذا هو ملك إسرائيل مبارك الآتى باسم رب القوات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tenhwc e~rof ten]w~ou naf: tenerhouo~ [ici m~mof: hwc a~gayoc ouoh m~mairwmi: nai nan kata peknis] n~nai.            </language>            <language id="English">               We praise Him and glorify Him: and exalt Him above all: as the Good One and Lover of Mankind: have mercy on us according to Your great mercy.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami puji dan muliakan Dia, kami tinggikan di atas segalanya, karena Dia Sang Baik dan Pengasih, kasihanilah kami menurut belas kasih-Mu yang besar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسبحه ونمجده ونزيده رفعة كصالح ومحب البشر إرحمنا كعظيم رحمتك.            </language>         </text>      </section>            <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Third Doxology for Hosanna Sunday</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi Ketiga untuk Minggu Hosanna</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية ثالثة لأحد الشعانين</language>            <language id="Coptic">V/ethemci hijen Ni,eroubim...</language>         </Title>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               For Hosanna Sunday in the Hosanna tune:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Minggu Hosanna dengan nada Hosanna:            </language>         </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               V/ethemci hijen ni,eroubim: hijen piy~ronoc n~te pefw~ou: afhemci e~h~r/i e~jen oue~w~: afse e~qoun e~Ieroucal/m.            </language>            <language id="English">               He, who sits upon the cherubim: and on the throne of His glory: sat on a donkey: and entered Jerusalem.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dia yang duduk di atas kerubim, di atas takhta kemuliaan-Nya, duduk di atas keledai dan masuk ke Yerusalem.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الجالس فوق الشاروبيم علي كرسي مجده جلس علي جحشٍ ودخل إلي أورشليم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               B/yania~ nem B/eyvagia: qaten pitwou n~te nijwit: e~tafouwrp n~nefmay/t/c: e~bol m~mau n~je P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               Bethany and Bethphage: at the Mount of Olives: when Christ sent His disciples: from that place.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dari Betania dan Betfage, di Gunung Zaitun, Kristus utus para murid-Nya dari tempat itu.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بيت عنيا وبيت فاجي عند جبل الزيتون لما أرسل المسيح تلميذيه من هناك.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Aubwl e~bol n~]e~w~: nem pic/j auenou naf: auvwrs n~nouh~bwc e~jwou: afhemci cap~swi m~mwou.            </language>            <language id="English">               They loosened the donkey: and a colt and brought them to Him: they spread their garments on them: and He sat upon them.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mereka lepaskan keledai dan anaknya, dan bawa kepada-Nya.</div><div>Mereka tebarkan pakaian mereka di atasnya, dan Ia duduk di atasnya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فحلا الأتان والجحش وأتيا بهما إليه وفرشا ثيابهما عليهما فجلس فوقهما.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Etafqwnt n~je P,#c#: e~nica n~te Ierocal/m: aurasi n~je nim/s nem nimay/t/c: eybe nijom e~taunau e~rwou.            </language>            <language id="English">               When Christ came close: to the outskirts of Jerusalem: the crowd rejoiced with the disciples: because of the powers they saw.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ketika Kristus dekati pinggiran kota Yerusalem, kerumunan orang bersukacita bersama para murid-Nya karena mukjizat-mukjizat yang mereka lihat.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ولما قرب المسيح إلي نواحي اورشليم فرحت الجموع مع التلاميذ من أجل القوات التي رأوها.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nia~lwoui~ n~te nihebreoc: aujw m~pihumnoc n~te t~ve: je Wcanna qen n/et[oci: vai pe p~ouro m~Pic~ra/l.            </language>            <language id="English">               The children of the Hebrews: said the hymn of heaven: “Hosanna in the highest: this is the King of Israel”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Anak-anak bangsa Ibrani menyanyikan kidung surgawi, "Hosanna di tempat tinggi, inilah Raja Israel!"</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أطفال العبرانيين نطقوا بالتسبيح السمائي أوصنا في الأعالي هذا هو ملك إسرائيل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nieuaggelion auermeyre: eujw m~moc m~pair/]: je aftalof e~oue~w~: kata p~tupoc n~ni,eroubim.            </language>            <language id="English">               The Gospels witnessed: saying likewise: “He mounted a donkey: as a symbol of the cherubim”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Injil pun menjadi saksi,</div><div>dan berkata: "Ia menunggangi keledai, sebagai lambang kerubim."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               شَهدت الأناجيل قائلة هكذا أنه ركب الجحش كمثال الشاروبيم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nicaq de hwou n~te ]ekkl/cia: auws e~bol eujw m~moc: je f~c~marwout n~je Po#c# I/#c#: v/e~tafi~ afcw] m~mon.            </language>            <language id="English">               And the scribes of the Church: cried out saying: “Blessed is the Lord Jesus: who came and saved us”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Para ahli Taurat Gereja berseru dan berkata: "Diberkatilah Tuhan Yesus, yang datang dan selamatkan kita!"</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ومعلموا الكنيسة أيضاً صرخوا قائلين مبارك الرب يسوع الذي أتي وخلصنا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Anon de hwn tenhwc e~rof: nem nia~lwoui~ etc~marwout: e~taut~cabwou qen Pip#n#a# e#y#u#: je Wcanna Ps/ri n~Dauid.            </language>            <language id="English">               We also sing to Him: with the blessed children: who were taught by the Holy Spirit: “Hosanna, Son of David”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami pun bernyanyi bagi-Nya, bersama anak-anak yang terberkati, yang telah diajar Roh Kudus: "Hosanna, Putra Daud!"</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ونحن أيضاً نسبحه مع الأطفال المباركين الذين تعلموا من الروح القدس قائلين أوصنا لإبن داود.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Fc~marwout n~je v/eyn/ou: qen v~ran m~Po#c# n~te nijom: ouoh qen tefmahc~nou] m~paroucia~: f~erhouo~ [ici sa nie~neh.            </language>            <language id="English">               Blessed is He who comes: in the name of the Lord of Hosts: and in His second coming: He is highly exalted forever.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Diberkatilah Dia yang datang dalam nama Tuhan semesta alam! Dan kedatangan-Nya yang kedua, Ia dimuliakan selamanya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               مباركٌ الآتي باسم رب القوات وفي ظهوره الثاني يزداد رفعة إلي الأباد.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tenhwc e~rof ten]w~ou naf: tenerhouo~ [ici m~mof: hwc a~gayoc ouoh m~mairwmi: nai nan kata peknis] n~nai.            </language>            <language id="English">               We praise Him and glorify Him: and exalt Him above all: as the Good One and Lover of Mankind: have mercy on us according to Your great mercy.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami puji dan muliakan-Nya, kami tinggikan di atas segalanya, karena Dialah Sang Baik dan Pengasih, kasihanilah kami menurut belas kasih-Mu yang besar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسبحه ونمجده ونزيده رفعة كصالح ومحب البشر إرحمنا كعظيم رحمتك.            </language>         </text>                     </section>            <insertdocument path="melodies/include/hosannasunday/1" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      <insertdocument path="melodies/include/hosannasunday/2" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>   </season></document>