<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="LazarusSaturday">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">                  <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for Lazarus Saturday</language><language id="Indonesian">Doksologi untuk Sabtu Lazarus</language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية سبت لعازر</language>            <language id="Coptic">Lazaroc pie~pickopoc...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For Lazarus Saturday:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Pada Sabtu Lazarus</language>         </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Lazaroc pie~pickopoc: pimenrit n~te P,#c#: v/etaftounocf qen n/eymwout: menenca f~tou n~e~h~oou.            </language>            <language id="English">               Lazarus the bishop, the beloved of Christ, who was risen from the death, after four days.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Lazarus sang uskup, yang dikasihi Kristus, yang dibangkitkan dari kematian, setelah empat hari.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               لعازر الأسقف حبيب المسيح الذى اقامه من الأموات بعد أربعة أيام.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh afwnq n~h~me n~rompi: ouoh afswpi n~oue~pickopoc: hijen piy~ronoc n~te Kuproc: afa~moni nio~hi n~te P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               And he lived for forty years, and became a bishop, on the throne of Cyprus, he shepherded the flock of Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dan ia hidup selama empat puluh tahun, dan menjadi uskup, di takhta Siprus, ia menggembalakan kawanan domba Kristus.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وعاش أربعين سنة وصار أسقفاً على كرسى قبرص ورعى قطيع المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Wouniatk peniwt e#y#u#: Lazaroc pie~pickopoc: je akerp~emp~sa n~t~c~m/ n~te I/#c#: V] n~n/etwnq nem nirefmwout.            </language>            <language id="English">               Blessed are you O our holy father, Lazarus the bishop, for you were worthy to hear the voice of Jesus, the Lord of the living and the dead.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Berbahagialah kau wahai bapa suci kami, Lazarus sang uskup, sbab kau layak mendengar suara Yesus, Tuhan orang hidup dan orang mati.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               طوباك يا أبانا القديس لعازر الأسقف لأنك استحققت صوت يسوع إله الأحياء والأموات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Rasi Lazaroc pimenrit: je akemp~sa n~]mete~pickopoc: aka~moni n~nie~cwou: w~ pinis] m~mane~cwou.            </language>            <language id="English">               Rejoice O Lazarus the Beloved, for you were worthy of the episcopate, you tended the sheep, O great shepherd.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Bersukacitalah, hai Lazarus yang terkasih, karena kau layak menerima jabatan episkopat, kau menggembalakan domba, hai gembala agung.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               افرح يا لعازر الحبيب لأنك استحققت الأسقفية ورعيت الخراف أيها الراعى العظيم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tentwbh m~mok w~ pat/r u~mwn: n~tekerp~recbeuin e~jwn: nahren P,#c# v/etafmenritk: ouoh aftounock qen n/eymwout.            </language>            <language id="English">               We entreat you O our father, to intercede on our behalf, before Christ who has loved you, and has risen you from the dead.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Kami mohon padamu, ya bapa kami, agar kau berdoa syafaat bagi kami, di hadapan Kristus yang t'lah mengasihimu, dan membangkitkanmu dari kematian.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               نطلب إليك يا أبانا لكى تشفع فينا أمام المسيح الذى أحبك وأقامك من الأموات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Twbh m~Po#c# e~h~r/i e~jwn:  w~ pimane~cwou n~te P,#c#: Lazaroc pie~pickopoc: n~tef,a nennobi nan e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               Pray to the Lord on our behalf, O shepherd of Christ, Lazarus the bishop, that He may forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Berdoalah pada Tuhan demi kami, hai gembala Kristus, Lazarus sang uskup, agar Dia mengampuni dosa-dosa kami.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               أطلب من الرب عنا أيها الراعى الذى للمسيح لعازر الأسقف ليغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </section>   </season></document>