<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">            <Title data-section-header="true">         <language id="English">Doxology for the Patriarch</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Sang Patriarkh</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للآب البطريرك</language>         <language id="Coptic">Ak[i t~,aric m~Mwuc/c...</language>      </Title>         <comment>         <language id="English">            The following doxology is said on the ordinations (while wearing the schema) and the visits of the Patriarch and the bishops during the Morning and Evening Raising of Incense         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi berikut diucapkan saat penahbisan (dengan mengenakan skema) dan saat kunjungan Patriarkh serta para uskup pada waktu Pengasapan Pagi dan Petang.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            تقال فى رسامته وفى حضوره بالكنيسة عند رفع بخور عشية وباكر وفى سيامة الأساقفة وقت لبس الاسكيم         </language>      </comment>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Ak[i t~,aric m~Mwuc/c: ]metou/b n~te Mel,icedek: ak[i m~p~taio m~peniwt Petroc: pianjwj n~nia~poctoloc.         </language>         <language id="English">            You received the grace of Moses, the priesthood of Melchizedek, you received honor from our father Peter, the first of the apostles.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Engkau telah menerima karunia Musa, keimamatan Melkisedek, dan menerima kehormatan dari bapa kita Petrus,</div><div>rasul yang pertama.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            نِلتَ نعمة موسى وكهنوت ملشيصاداق وأخذت كرامة أبينا بطرس بكر الرسل.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            AP,#c# talo n~tefjij: n~oui~nam e~jen teka~ve: aftenhoutk e~nisost: n~te y~metouro n~niv/oui.         </language>         <language id="English">            Christ lifted His right hand, on your head, He gave you the keys, of the kingdom of heaven.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kristus angkat tangan kanan-Nya di atas kepalamu, Dia beri kunci-kunci Kerajaan Surga kepadamu,</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            رفع المسيح يده اليمنى على رأسك وأئتمنك على مفاتيح ملكوت السموات.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Eyrekswpi n~oureferhemi: cap~swi n~]ekkl/cia: eyreka~moni m~peklaoc: qen outoubo nem oumeym/i.         </language>         <language id="English">            That you may govern, over the church, and that you may shepherd your people, in purity and righteousness.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Agar kau memerintah atas gereja, dan gembalakan umat-Mu dalam kemurnian dan kebenaran.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            لتصر مدبراً على الكنيسة وترعى شعبك بطهارة وبر.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Kata v~r/] e~tafjoc: n~je Pauloc pia~poctoloc: je kata v~r/] n~Aa~rwn: pair/] hwf m~P,#c#.         </language>         <language id="English">            As Paul: the Apostle, has said,: “Likewise as Aaron, Christ is also.”         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Seperti yang Paulus sang Rasul katakan, “Demikian pula Kristus adalah imam menurut aturan Harun.”</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            كما قال بولس الرسول كمثل هرون كذلك المسيح.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Wcautwc ten[ici m~mok: nem pihumnodoc Dauid: je n~yok pe piou/b sa e~neh: kata t~taxic m~Mel,icedek.         </language>         <language id="English">            Likewise we magnify You, with David the Psalmist, You are the priest forever, according to the order of Melchizedek.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Demikian juga kami muliakan-Mu bersama Daud sang pemazmur, Kau-lah imam selamanya menurut peraturan Melkisedek.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            كذلك نرفعك مع المرتل داود قائلين أنت هو الكاهن إلى الأبد على طقس ملشيصادق.         </language>      </text>         <text>         <language id="Coptic">            Twbh m~Po#c# e~h~r/i e~jwn: w~ pao#c# n~iwt m~patriar,/c: peniwt e#y#u# abba (...): n~tef,a nennobi nan e~bol.         </language>         <language id="English">            Pray to the Lord on our behalf, O my father the patriarch, our holy father abba (...), that He may for give us our sins.         </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doakan kami pada Tuhan, ya bapa Patriarkh kami, bapa kudus, Abba (…), agar Dia mengampuni dosa-dosa kami.</div></language>         <language id="Arabic">            إطلب من الرب عنا ياسيدى الآب البطريرك أبانا الطاهر أنبا (...)   ليغفر لنا خطايانا.         </language>      </text>            <group>         <season id="Enthronement | MyronConsecration">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Twbh m~Po#c# e~h~r/i e~jwn: neniw] e#y#u# n~dikeoc: nim/tropolit/c nem nie~pickopoc n/et,/ neman: n~tef,a nennobi nan e~bol.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Pray to the Lord on our behalf: O my saintly fathers the righteous: the metropolitans and the bishops assembled with us: that He may forgive us our sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doakan kami pada Tuhan, ya para kudus kami, orang benar, para metropolit dan uskup yang berkumpul bersama kami, agar Dia mengampuni dosa-dosa kami.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إطلبوا من الرب عنا يا ابائنا القديسين الأبرار المطارنة والأساقفة المجتمعين معنا ليغفر لنا خطايانا.               </language>            </text>         </season>                  <season id="Other">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Twbh m~Po#c# e~h~r/i e~jwn: peniwt eyouab n~dikeoc: abba (...) pie~pickopoc (m~m/tropol/t/c): n~tef ,a nennobi nan e~bol.                                     </language>               <language id="English">                  Pray to Lord on our behalf, our holy righteous father, Abba (…) the bishop (the metropolitan), that He may forgive us our sins.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doakan kami pada Tuhan, ya bapa kudus kami yang benar, Abba (…) uskup (metropolit),</div><div>agar Dia mengampuni dosa-dosa kami.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  اطلب من الرب عنا يا ابانا القديس البار  انبا (...) الأسقف (المطران) ليغفر لنا خطايانا.               </language>            </text>         </season>      </group>   </section></document>