<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="PopeKyrillos:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for Pope Kyrillos</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Paus Kyrillos</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية البابا كيرلس السادس </language>            <language id="Coptic">Papa Abba Kurilloc...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of Pope Kyrillos:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Peringatan Paus Kirilos:</div></language>         </comment>                   <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Papa Abba Kurilloc pimah ^#: pim~akarioc ’qen oumeym/i: v/etaf tajron qen pinah]: n~oryozoxoc n~tav~m/i.            </language>            <language id="English">               Pope Kyrillos the sixth: the truely honored: who founded us in the true: orthodox faith.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Paus Kyrillos keenam, yang sungguh dihormati, teguhkan kami dalam iman, yang benar dan ortodoks.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               البابا كيرلس الســــادس: الطوبــــاوي بالحقيقة: الذي ثبتنا في الإيمان: الأرثوذكسي الحقيقــــــي .            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouran n~sousou pe pekran: w~ pimona,oc ettoub/out: pimand~rit/c ettajr/out: pis~v/r n~niana,writ/c.            </language>            <language id="English">               Your name is a pride: O pure monk: the strengthened hermit: the friend of the anchorites.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Namamu adalah kebanggaan, hai biarawan yang murni, pertapa yang kuat, sahabat para anakhoret.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               إسـم فخـر هو إسمك: يا أيها الراهب الطاهر: والمتوحـــد القوي: صديق الســــــواح .            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Eybe vai akswpi nan: n~outupoc qen p~caji: qen ]agap/: qen pijinmosi: qen pitoubo qen v~nah].            </language>            <language id="English">               For you have become: a leading example: of words, love, and deeds: and of purity in faith.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sebab kau teladan, dalam kata, kasih, dan perbuatan, juga dalam kemurnian, dan keteguhan iman.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               من أجل هذا صرت لنا: قدوة في الكلام: في المحبـــة في التصرف: في الطهارة في الإيمـــــــان .            </language>         </text>                   <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere pimainefs/ri: v/etaftal[o n~n/etswni: afer p~rov/teuin n~nis~v/ri: ouoh nidumwn afhitou e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you loving father: who healed the sick: and foresaw miracles: and cast out demons.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, bapa yang penuh kasih, yang sembuhkan orang sakit, yang lihat mukjizat, dan usir roh jahat.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لمحب أولاده: الذي شفى المرضى: وتنبأ بالعظائم: وأخــــرج الشياطيــــن .            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Fc~marwout n~je pekbioc: w~ peniwt m~makarioc: aktacyo nan m~picwma n~abba Markoc: ouoh aki~ri m~pimuron eyouab.            </language>            <language id="English">               Your era was blessed: O our honored father: you restored St. Mark's relics: and made the sacred Myron            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Masa kepemimpinanmu diberkati, hai bapa kami yang mulia, kau pulihkan relikui Santo Markus, dan buat minyak suci Myron.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               مبارك هـو عهـدك: يـا أبانا الطوبــــاوي: أعدت لنا جسد مارمرقـــس: وعملت الميرون المقــــدس .            </language>         </text>                   <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Maria ]macnou]: acouwnh qen ounis] n~s~v/ri: nem ni[~rompi nem nic~yoinoufi: qen tecekk~l/cia qen Zaitoun.            </language>            <language id="English">               Mary the Mother of God: appeared miraculously: with doves and incense: above her church in Zeitoun.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Maria Bunda Allah, menampakkan diri secara ajaib, dengan burung merpati dan dupa, di atas gerejanya di Zeitoun.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               مريـم والدة الإله: ظهـرت بإعجوبـــــة عظيمة: مع حمام وبخور: في كنيستها بالزيتــــــون .            </language>         </text>                   <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Akkwt n~oumankayedra m~beri: nem pinis] n~a~b/t n~abba M/na: nem hanm/s n~ekk~l/cia: pekh/t m~pef[ac nahbi e~p~t/rf.            </language>            <language id="English">               You built a new cathedral: and St. Mina’s great monastery: and many more churches: but you remained humble.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kau bangun katedral yang agung, dan biara besar Santo Mina, dan banyak gereja lainnya, namun kau tetap rendah hati.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بنيت كاتدرائية جديدة: والـدير العظيــــــم لمارمينــــــــا: وكنائس كثيرة: أمّـا قلبــك لـم يستكبـر مطلقـاً .            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Saktwnk m~b~nau n~sorp: ’qen tekjom nem nekswni: eyrek hwc nem niaggiloc: nem n/eyouab etekmenritou.            </language>            <language id="English">               You rose at dawn: both in health and sickness: to praise with the angels: and your beloved saints.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kau bangun tiap fajar, sehat maupun sakit, untuk memuji bersama para malaikat, dan para kudus yang kau kasihi.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               تعـودت القيام وقت السحر: في قوّتـــــك وفي أمراضك: لتسبّح مع الملائكة: ومع القديسين أحبائـــــك .            </language>         </text>                   <text>            <language id="Coptic">               }nou aripenmeui~: nahren Pennou]: eyrefjwk nan e~bol m~pekr/]: qen ]agap/ qen v~nah].            </language>            <language id="English">               And now remember us: before our God: that He may keep us: in His love and faith.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan sekarang ingatlah kami, di hadapan Allah kami, agar Ia menjaga kami, dalam kasih dan iman-Nya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               والآن أذكرنا: أمـام إلـهنــــا: ليكملنــا مثلـك: فـي المحبـة في الإيمــــــان .            </language>         </text>                  <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/PopeKyrillos" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>