<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="PresentationInTemple">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for the Presentation of the Lord Christ in the Temple</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Pesta Persembahan Tuhan Kristus di Bait Allah</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية لعيد دخول السيد إلى الهيكل بأورشليم</language>            <language id="Coptic">Apeno#c# I/#c# P,#c#...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Feast of the Presentation of the Lord Christ in the Temple:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Perayaan Persembahan Tuhan Kristus di Bait Suci:</div></language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Apeno#c# I/#c# P,#c#: piw~ou vwf nem pihumnoc: nem Pefiwt n~a~gayoc: nem Pip#n#a# m~parakl/ton.            </language>            <language id="English">               Our Lord Jesus Christ, glory and praise be to Him, with His good Father, and the Spirit of Comfort.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus, segala kemuliaan dan pujian bagi-Nya, beserta Bapa yang baik, dan Roh Penghibur yang kudus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ربنا يسوع المسيح له المجد والتسبيح مع أبيه الصالح والروح المعزى.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               I~ e~qoun e~piervei e#y#u#: e~jen nenjij n~tefmau: menenca h~me n~e~hoou: m~pefjinmici e#y#u#.            </language>            <language id="English">               He entered the holy temple, on His mother's hands, after forty days, from His holy Birth.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia masuk ke Bait Suci, dalam pelukan bunda-Nya, setelah empat puluh hari, sejak kelahiran-Nya yang kudus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               دخل إلى الهيكل المقدس على يدى أمه بعد أربعين يوماً من مولده المقدس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afi~ n~je Iwc/f pidikeoc: nem Maria y~mau m~P,#c#: auyamio~ m~p~jwk m~pinomoc: eybe pia~lou n~cwt/r I/#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               Joseph the Righteous came, with Mary the Mother of Christ, they followed the law, for the boy Jesus the Savior.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Yusuf yang benar datang, bersama Maria, Bunda Kristus, mereka taat hukum Taurat, bagi Yesus, Sang Juruselamat kecil.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               جاء يوسف الصديق مع مريم أم المسيح وصنعا إتمام الناموس لأجل الصبى المخلص يسوع.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afolf n~je Cumewn piou/b: e~jen nefjij e#y#u#: ouoh afhwc e~p~ouro P,#c#: m~pair/] efjw m~moc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Simeon the Priest lifted Him, on his holy hands, and praised Christ the King, likewise saying.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Simeon sang imam mengangkat-Nya, dalam tangan kudusnya, memuji Kristus Sang Raja, sambil berkata demikian:</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               حمله سمعان الكاهن على يديه الطاهرتين وسبح الملك المسيح هكذا قائلا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               }nou pan/b ,~na,a pekbwk: e~bol qen ouhir/n/ kata pekcaji: je aunau n~je nabal e~peknohem: v/e~takcebtwtf m~pem~yo n~nilaoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               "Lord now You are letting Your servant depart, in peace according to Your word, for my eyes have seen Your salvation, which You have prepared before the face of the people.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>“Tuhan, kini biarlah hamba-Mu pergi, dengan damai menurut firman-Mu, sebab mataku lihat keselamatan-Mu, yang telah Kau sediakan di hadapan segala bangsa.”</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الآن ياسيد تطلق عبدك بسلام كقولك لأن عينى قد أبصرتا خلاصك الذى أعددته قدام الشعوب.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tenhwc e~rof ten]w~ou naf: tenerhouo~ [ici m~mof: hwc a~gayoc ouoh m~mairwmi: nai nan kata peknis] n~nai.            </language>            <language id="English">               We praise and glorify Him, and exalt Him above all, as the Good One and Lover of Mankind, have mercy upon us according to Your great mercy.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami puji dan muliakan Dia, dan tinggikan di atas segalanya, sebagai Yang Baik dan Pengasih manusia, kasihanilah kami seturut belas kasih-Mu yang besar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسبحه ونمجده ونزيده رفعة كصالح ومحب البشر إرحمنا كعظيم رحمتك.            </language>         </text>      </section>   </season></document>