<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="(PentecostPeriod | Joyful29thOfTheMonth) ^ !ThirdProstration">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for the Resurrection</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi Kebangkitan</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية لعيد القيامة المجيد والخمسين</language>            <language id="Coptic">Tote rwn...</language>         </Title>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Feast of the Resurrection and the Holy Fifty Days:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Hari Raya Kebangkitan dan Masa Lima Puluh Hari Kudus:</div></language>               </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tote rwn afmoh n~rasi: ouoh penlac qen ouyel/l: je Peno#c# I/#c# P,#c#: aftwnf e~bol qen n/eymwout.            </language>            <language id="English">               Then our mouths are filled with joy, and our tongues with rejoicing, for our Lord Jesus Christ, is risen from the dead.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Maka mulut kami penuh sukacita, dan lidah kami dengan sorak sorai, sebab Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus telah bangkit dari antara orang mati.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               حينئذ امتلأ فُمنا فرحاً ولساننا تهليلاً لأن ربنا يسوع المسيح قام من بين الأموات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afkwrf m~v~mou qen tefjom: afy~rep~wnq e~rouwini e~ron: n~yof on v/e~tafsenaf: e~nima etcapec/t m~p~kahi.            </language>            <language id="English">               He has abolished death by His might, and made life shine upon us, He is the one who has descended, to the lower parts of the earth.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dengan kuasa-Nya Ia telah kalahkan maut, dan buat terang kehidupan bagi kita. Dialah yang turun ke bagian terdalam bumi.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               بقوته أبطل الموت وجعل الحياة تضئ لنا وهو أيضاً الذي مضى إلى الأماكن التي أسفل الأرض.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nim~nout n~te a~men]: aunau e~rof auerho]: aftako n~ninakhi m~v~mou: m~pous~jemjom n~a~moni m~mof.            </language>            <language id="English">               The gatekeepers of Hades, saw Him and were afraid, He abolished the pangs of death, for He was not held by them.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Para penjaga Hades lihat Dia dan gemetar, Ia hancurkan sengsara maut, sebab maut tak dapat menahan-Nya.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               بوابو الجحيم رأوه وخافوا وأهلك طلقات الموت فلم تستطع أن تمسكه.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afqomqem n~hanpul/ n~h~omt: afkws n~hanmo,louc m~benipi: afi~ni n~nefcwtp e~bol: qen ouounof nem ouyel/l.            </language>            <language id="English">               He has crushed the gates of brass, and broke the bars of iron, and brought out His chosen ones, with rejoicing and with joy.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ia hancurkan pintu-pintu gerbang tembaga, dan patahkan palang-palang besi, serta bebaskan umat pilihan-Nya dengan sorak dan sukacita.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               سحق الابواب النحاس وكسر المتاريس الحديد وأخرج مختاريه بفرح وتهليل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afo~lou e~p~[ici nemaf: e~qoun e~nefman~emton: afnahmou eybe pefran: afouwnh n~tefjom nwou e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               He lifted them up with Him, into His place of rest, and saved them for the sake of His name, and revealed His power to them.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Ia angkat mereka bersama-Nya, ke tempat perhentian-Nya, selamatkan mereka demi nama-Nya, dan nyatakan kuasa-Nya bagi mereka.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               وأصعدهم معه إلى العلو إلى موضع راحته خلصهم لأجل إسمه وأظهر قوته لهم..            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Eybe vai tenoi n~ramao~: qen nia~gayon etj/k e~bol: qen ounah] tener'alin: enjw m~moc je all/louia.            </language>            <language id="English">               Therefore we are rich, with perfect good things, and in faith we sing, saying Alleluia.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Karena itu kita dipenuhi berkat, dan dengan iman kita nyanyi dan serukan: Alleluia!</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فلهذا نحن أغنياء بالخيرات الكاملة وبايمانٍ نرتل قائلين الليلويا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               All/louia all/louia: all/louia all/louia: I/#c# P,#c# p~ouro n~te p~w~ou: aftwnf e~bol qen n/eymwout.            </language>            <language id="English">               Alleluia Alleluia, Alleluia Alleluia, Jesus Christ the King of glory, is risen from the dead.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Alleluia, Alleluia. Yesus Kristus, Raja Kemuliaan, telah bangkit dari orang mati.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الليلويا الليلويا الليلويا الليلويا يسوع المسيح ملك المجد قام من بين الأموات.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/FaiErePeoo" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>               </section>            <section antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Second Doxology for the Resurrection</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi Kedua untuk Kebangkitan</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية ثانية لعيد القيامة المجيد والخمسين</language>            <language id="Coptic">V/e~tafsans m~Pic~ra/l...</language>         </Title>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Feast of the Resurrection and the Holy Fifty Days:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Hari Raya Kebangkitan &amp; Lima Puluh Hari Suci:</div></language>               </comment>                   <text>            <language id="Coptic">               V/e~tafsans m~Pic~ra/l: n~h~me n~rompi hi p~safe: af] m~pimanna nwou e~ouomf: p~wik n~te niaggeloc.            </language>            <language id="English">               He who nourished Israel, forty years in the wilderness, He gave them manna to eat, the bread of the angels.            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Dia yang beri makan umat Israel, selama empat puluh tahun di padang gurun, Ia beri mereka manna untuk dimakan, roti para malaikat.            </language>            <language id="Arabic">               الذى عالَ إسرائيل، أربعين سنة فى البرية، وأعطاهم المنَّ، خُبز الملائكة ليأكلوا            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nt~sebiw gar m~pimanna: au] n~ouhemj efensasi naf: n~t~sebiw n~nia~gayon: au],~lom n~couri e~jwf.            </language>            <language id="English">               But instead of the manna, they gave him bitter vinegar, instead of the good things, they placed a crown of thorns on Him.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Namun sebagai ganti manna, mereka memberi-Nya cuka yang pahit; sebagai ganti segala yang baik, mereka taruh mahkota duri di kepala-Nya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               عوض المنَّ، أعطوه خلاً مُراً، وبدل الخيرات جعلوا، إكليل شوك على رأسه            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Aukocf au,af qen pim~hau: v/e~t,/ cabol n~]baki: e~taujoc qen toumetath/t: je vai s~natwnf an je.            </language>            <language id="English">               They wrapped Him and placed Him in the tomb, which was outside of the city, saying foolishly, "This One cannot rise again."            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mereka bungkus tubuh-Nya dan letakkan dalam kubur, di luar kota, sambil berkata dengan bodoh, “Orang ini takkan bangkit lagi.”</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               كُفن ووُضع فى القبر، الكائن خارج المدينة، وقالوا بجهلهم أن هذا، لا يستطيع أن يقوم بعد            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Swrp m~v~ouai n~te nicabbaton: a~P,#c# twnf e~bolqen n/e~ymwo~ut: aftacyo n~nefjaji e~vahou: af] nwou n~ous~vit sa n~e~neh.            </language>            <language id="English">               Early on the first day of the week, Christ rose from among those who are dead, and turned back His enemies, and gave them eternal shame.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Namun pada pagi pertama di minggu itu, Kristus bangkit dari antara orang mati, putar balik para musuh-Nya, dan beri aib kekal bagi mereka.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               باكر أحد السبوت، قام المسيح من بين الأموات، ورد أعداءه إلى خلف، وأعطاهم عاراً أبدياً            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Eybe vai tener,oreuin: nem pihumnodoc Dauid: je aftwnf n~je V]: m~v~r/] m~v/e~tenkot.            </language>            <language id="English">               Therefore we sing, with the hymnist David, saying "God arose, like he who is asleep."            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Maka kami pun bernyanyi bersama pemazmur Daud, sambil berkata, “Allah bangkit seperti orang yang terjaga dari tidurnya.”</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               من أجل هذا، نمدح مع المرتل، داود قائلين، قد قام الله مثل النائم            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               All/louia all/louia: all/louia all/louia: I/#c# P,#c# p~ouro n~te p~w~ou: aftwnf e~bol qen n/eymwout.            </language>            <language id="English">               Alleluia Alleluia, Alleluia Alleluia, Jesus Christ the King of glory, is risen from the dead.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Alleluia Alleluia, Alleluia Alleluia, Yesus Kristus Raja Kemuliaan, telah bangkit dari antara orang mati.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الليلويا الليلويا الليلويا الليلويا يسوع المسيح ملك المجد قام من بين الأموات.            </language>         </text>      </section>            <group>         <insertdocument path="melodies/include/MatinsResurrection" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </group>         </season></document>