<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StAnthony:Doxology | MonkOrdination | NunConsecration">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Anthony</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Santo Antonius</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية القديس أنبا أنطونيوس</language>            <language id="Coptic">Bwl e~bol...</language>         </Title>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Anthony:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Peringatan Santo Antonius:</div></language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Bwl e~bol qen netenh/t: n~nimokmek n~te ]kakia~: nem nimeui~ etsebswb: eti~ri m~pinouc n~,aki.            </language>            <language id="English">               Purge from your hearts: thoughts of vice: and deceiving ideas: that darken the mind.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sucikanlah hatimu dari pikiran jahat, dan tipu daya iblis yang menggelapi akal budi.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               انزعوا من قلوبكم أفكار الشر والظنون الخداعة التى تظلم العقل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Arinoin qen ou]h~y/f: n~nikayartwma et[oci: n~te penmakarioc n~iwt: pao#c# pinis] Abba Antwni.            </language>            <language id="English">               Contemplate with understanding: the great purifications: of our blessed father: my lord, the great Abba Antony.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Renungilah dengan bijaksana penyucian agung dari bapa kita yang diberkati, Tuanku, Abba Antonius yang agung.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               تفهموا بتأمل الى المعجزات العالية التى لأبينا الطوباوى سيدى العظيم أنبا انطونيوس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Vai e~tafswpi nan n~[aumwit: n~lum/n n~te pioujai: afywhem m~mon qen oue~rouwt: e~qoun e~piwnq n~e~neh.            </language>            <language id="English">               He has become our: guide and harbor of salvation: with joy he invites us: to life everlasting.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia telah menjadi penuntun dan pelabuhan keselamatan kita. Dengan sukacita ia undang kita menuju kehidupan yang kekal.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               هذا الذى صار لنا مرشدا وميناء خلاص ودعانا بفرح الى الحياة الأبدية.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Apic~yoinoufi n~te nefaret/: ] m~p~ounof n~nen'u,/: m~v~r/] m~piarwmata: etr/t qen piparadicoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               The incense of his virtues: delights our souls: as fragrant aroma: throughout Paradise pervades.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kemenyan kebajikan-nya menghibur jiwa kita, seperti bau harum yang semerbak mengisi seluruh Taman Firdaus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بخور فضائله أعطى الفرح لنفوسنا مثل العنبر المزهر فى الفردوس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Marentajron qen pinah]: etcoutwn qen oumeym/i: n~te pinis] Antwnioc: enws e~bol e~njw m~moc:            </language>            <language id="English">               Let us be confirmed in the faith: upright and true: of Antony the great: proclaiming and saying:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mari kita teguhkan dalam iman yang lurus dan benar, dari Antonius yang agung, sambil berseru dan berkata:</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فلنثبت في الإيمان المستقيم بالحقيقة الذى للعظيم انبا أنطونيوس صارخين قائلين:            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je aikw] ouoh aijimi: aie~retin ouoh ai[i: aikwlh ouoh ]nah]: je cenaa~ouwn n/i.            </language>            <language id="English">               “I sought and I found: I asked and I was given: I knocked and I believed: that it will be opened to me.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>“Aku cari dan temukan, aku minta dan terima, aku mengetuk dan percaya, bahwa pintu akan dibukakan bagiku.”</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               طلبت فوجدت سألت فأخذت قرعت وأؤمن أنه سيفتح لى.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere peniwt Antwnioc: piq/bc n~te ]metmona,oc: ,ere peniwt abba Paule: pimenrit n~te P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to our father, Abba Antony: the light of monasticism: Hail to our father Abba Paul: the beloved of Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagi bapa kami, Abba Antonius, cahaya bagi hidup monastik. Salam bagi bapa kami Abba Paulus, yang dikasihi oleh Kristus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لأبينا انبا أنطونيوس مصباح الرهبنة السلام لأبينا أنبا بولا حبيب المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StAnthony" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>