<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StAnthony:Doxology | StPaulTheHermit:Doxology | MonkOrdination | NunConsecration">      <section antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Anthony and St. Paul</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Antonius dan St. Paulus</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية القديسين أنبا أنطونيوس وأنبا بولا</language>            <language id="Coptic">W nictulloc...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               The following doxology is said at anytime, during the placing of the monk’s schema and the prayer of the monk’s funeral            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>(Dibacakan kapan saja, khususnya saat pemberkatan biarawan dan doa pemakaman biarawan)</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               تقال فى أي وقت وفي صلاة لبس الاسكيم وفي صلاة تجنيز الرهبان            </language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               W nictulloc n~referouwini: nivwct/r n~al/yinon: e~terouwini n~nen'/,/: hiten noua~r/t/ e#y#u#.            </language>            <language id="English">               O the pillars of light: the stars in truth: that enlighten our souls: through their holy virtues,            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Wahai tiang-tiang terang, bintang-bintang sejati, yang menerangi jiwa kami dengan kebajikan hidupmu yang suci.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيها العمودان النيران الكوكبان الحقيقان المضيئان لنفوسنا بفضائلهما المقدسة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Abba Antwni nem Abba Paule: nai e~taucolcel m~poubioc: qen hann/ctia~ nem hans~l/l: nem ounis] n~toubo.            </language>            <language id="English">               Abba Antony and Abba Paul: who decorated their lives: with fastings and prayers: and great purity,            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Abba Antonius dan Abba Paulus, yang menghiasi hidup mereka dengan puasa dan doa serta kemurnian yang agung.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               انبا أنطونيوس وأنبا بولا اللذان زينا سيرتهما بأصوام وصلوات وطهارة عظيمة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Eusop n~q~r/i qen nisafeu: euhwc V] qen oumetatmounk: m~pie~hoou nem pie~jwrh: m~v~r/] n~niaggeloc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Dwelling in the wilderness: and praising God incessantly: by day and by night: in the likeness of angels,            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tinggal di padang gurun sambil puji Allah tanpa henti, siang dan malam dalam keserupaan dengan para malaikat.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ساكنان في البراري مسبحان الله بلا فتور نهاراً وليلاً مثل الملائكة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               San~toujwk m~poubioc e~bol: qen ouounof nem ouyel/l: au[i m~pi,~lom n~attako: qen Ieroucal/m n~te t~ve.            </language>            <language id="English">               Until they completed their lives: in joy and happiness: they received everlasting crowns: in the heavenly Jerusalem;            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Hingga mereka mengakhiri hidupnya dengan sukacita dan kebahagiaan, mereka terima mahkota abadi di Yerusalem surgawi.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               حتي أكملا عمرهما بفرح وتهليل ونالا الاكليل غير الفاسد في أورشليم السمائية.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Euhwc nem niaggeloc: nem nitagma n~e~pouranion: nem p~,oroc n~te n/e#y#u#: qen oucumvwnia~ n~ouwt.            </language>            <language id="English">               Singing with the angels: and the heavenly orders: and the chorus of the saints: in a single symphony,            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mereka bernyanyi dengan para malaikat dan bala surgawi, juga paduan suara para kudus dalam harmoni yang satu.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               مسبحين مع الملائكة والطغمات السمائية ومصاف القديسين بصوت واحد.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Eu]w~ou n~}t~riac: e#y#u# n~o~mooucioc: e~te n~yoc te ]ar,/: nem p~jwk e~bol n~agayon niben.            </language>            <language id="English">               Glorifying the Holy Trinity: who is of one essence: who is the beginning and the end: of all good things.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Memuliakan Tritunggal Mahakudus, yang satu hakekat, yang awal dan akhir dari segala yang baik.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               يمجدان الثالوت الأقدس المساوي في الجوهر الذي هو بداية ونهاية كل الخيرات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Wouniatou qen oumeym/i: nenio] e#y#u# n~dikeoc: Abba Antwnioc nem Abba Paule: nimenra] n~te P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               Truly blessed are you: our holy and righteous fathers: Abba Antony and Abba Paul: the beloved of Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sungguh diberkatilah engkau hai bapa kami yang kudus dan benar, Abba Antonius dan Abba Paulus, yang dikasihi oleh Kristus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               طوباهم بالحقيقة أبوينا القديسين البارين أنبا أنطونيوس وأنبا بولا محبي المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Twbh m~Po#c# e~h~r/i e~jwn:  nao#c# n~io] m~mainous/ri: abba Antwnioc nem abba Paule: n~tef,a nennobi nan e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               Pray to the Lord on our behalf: my lords and fathers who love their children: Abba Antony and Abba Paul: that He may forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mohonlah pada Tuhan demi kami, wahai tuanku dan bapa kami, yang mengasihi anak-anaknya, Abba Antonius dan Abba Paulus, agar Ia mengampuni dosa-dosa kami.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               إطلبا من الرب عنا ياسيدى الأبوين محبى أولادهما أنبا انطونيوس وأنبا بولا ليغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>                     </section>   </season></document>