<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StApanoub:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Apa-Noub of Nehis</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Santo Apa-Noub dari Nehis</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للشهيد أبانوب النهيسي</language>            <language id="Coptic">Nyok oua~lou n~cabe...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Apanoub:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>(Untuk peringatan Santo Apanoub)</div></language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nyok oua~lou n~cabe: w~ Apanoub piremneh/c: eybe pektoubo nem pekcemnoc: akswpi m~menrit m~pidecpout/c.            </language>            <language id="English">               You are a wise child: O Apa-Noub of Nehis: because you are pure and chaste: you are loved by the Master.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kau anak yang bijak, ya Apa-Noub dari Nehis, karena kau murni dan suci, dikasihi Sang Penebus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أنت صبي حكيم يا أبانوب النهيسي من أجل طهارتك وعفتك صرت حبيباً للسيد.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Af,w m~pikocmoc t/rf: efkw] n~ca na niv/oui: afwl m~pefc~tauroc e~jwf: afjemh/ou n~tef'u,/.            </language>            <language id="English">               He abandoned the whole world: in order to seek the heavens: he carried his cross: and he gained his soul.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia tinggalkan seluruh dunia, 'tuk cari Kerajaan Surga, ia pikul salibnya,</div><div>dan dapat keselamatan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ترك عنه العالم كله طالبا السمائيات وحمل صليبه وربح نفسه.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Etafes e~bol qen nef[alauj: ouoh tefa~ve e~pec/t: e~h~r/i e~jen piywk n~joi: m~pefkim afertajro n~h/t.            </language>            <language id="English">               When he was hung by his feet: his head was down on the ship’s pole: he did not move: his heart was full of strength.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Saat ia digantung terbalik, dengan kepala di tiang kapal, ia tak bergeming, hatinya penuh kekuatan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لما علقوه من قدمية ورأسه إلي أسفل علي صاري المركب لم يتزعزع وثبت قلبه.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afswpi n~oulu,nia~ n~noub: qen nitopoc n~te nipictoc: pijwri eyouab Apanoub: v/e~tafsep n~nibacanoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               He became a golden lampstand: in the places of the faithful: the strong saint Apa-Noub: who received tortures.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia jadi kandil emas, di tengah umat yang setia, santo yang kuat, Apa-Noub, yang terima banyak siksaan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صار منارة ذهبية في ديار المؤمنين القوي القديس أبانوب الذي تحمل العذاب.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Hanm/s e~taunau e~pefagwn: nem pefnah] ettajr/out: auero~mologin qen ouq~rwou: Pennou] pe I/couc v/e~tc~marwout.            </language>            <language id="English">               The people who saw his struggle: and his firm faith: voiced their confessions: “Our God is Jesus the Blessed”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Orang-orang yang lihat perjuangannya, dan imannya yang teguh, menyatakan pengakuan mereka: "Allah kami adalah Yesus yang Terberkati."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               كثيرون لما رأوا جهاده وأيمانه الثابت اعترفوا باعلان إلهنا هو يسوع المبارك.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Au[i nemaf m~pi,~lom n~atlwm: n~te ]metmarturoc: hiten pounah] etcoutwn: e~qoun e~Pen[oic I/couc Pi,~rictoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               They took with him the unfading crown: of martyrdom: through their upright faith: in our Lord Jesus Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mereka pun turut terima mahkota kemartiran yang takkan layu, melalui iman yang benar pada Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ونالوا معه اكليل الشهادة الغير المضمحل من قبل إيمانهم المستقيم بربنا يسوع المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pimarturoc: n~te Peno#c# I/#c# P,#c#: ,ere piswij n~genneoc: Apanoub piremneh/c.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you, O martyr: of our Lord Jesus Christ: Hail to the courageous hero: Apa-Noub of Nehis.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, hai martir, dari Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus. Salam bagi pahlawan pemberani, Apa-Noub dari Nehis.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك يا شهيد ربنا يسوع المسيح السلام للشجاع البطل أبانوب النهيسي.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StApanoub" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>