<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StAthanasius:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Athanasius the Apostolic</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Athanasius Sang Apostolik</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للقديس الأنبا أثناسيوس البطريرك</language>            <language id="Coptic">Pikebernit/c...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Athanasius:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Peringatan St. Athanasius:</div></language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pikebernit/c ettajr/out: pirefmisi n~kalwc: piref[ro qen nibwtc: piq/bc e~tafe~rouwini.            </language>            <language id="English">               O you who are strong in managing the ship, O you the distinguished fighter, who is victorious in the wars, the luminous lamp.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Wahai kau yang kuat kendalikan bahtera, ya pejuang unggul yang menang dalam peperangan, pelita yang bersinar terang.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيها المدبر القوي لدفة السفينة أيها المقاتل البارع أيها الظافر في المعارك أيها المصباح المنير.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pikurix n~te ]oryodoxia: pe Ayancioc pia~poctolikoc: piref]c~bw n~te pio~hi: n~logikon n~te P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               The leader of Orthodoxy, is Athanasius the apostolic, the instructor of the eloquent sheep, That is for Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Pemimpin Iman Ortodoks, itulah Athanasius sang apostolik, membimbing umat Kristus dengan perkataan yang bijak.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               رائد الأرثوذكسية هو أثناسيوس الرسولي ومعلم القطيع الناطق الذي للمسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Anekdogma etcoutwn: misi m~p~h/t n~niheretikoc: m~v~r/] n~ouc/fi n~ro2: hiten t~jom n~}t~riac.            </language>            <language id="English">               Your truthful teachings, pierced the hearts of the heretics, like a double-edged sword, by the power of the Trinity.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ajaranmu yang benar menusuk hati para bidat, bagai pedang bermata dua, dengan kuasa Tritunggal Mahakudus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               تعاليمك القويمة نفذت في قلوب الهراطقة مثل سيف ذي حدين بقوة الثالوث.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Akeli niben kwlj m~Po#c#: a~lac niben c~mou e~rof: a~p~w~ou m~V] ouwsc e~bol: afmoh m~p~ho n~]oikoumen/.            </language>            <language id="English">               Every knee worshiped the Lord, and every tongue praised Him, The Glory of God was announced, and filled the entire universe.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Setiap lutut menyembah Tuhan, dan setiap lidah memuji-Nya, Kemuliaan Allah dinyatakan, memenuhi seluruh alam semesta.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               كل ركبة جثت للرب و كل لسان سبحه و مجد الله ذاع وملأ وجه المسكونة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Wcautwc ten[ici m~mok: nem pihumnodoc Dauid: je n~yok pe piou/b sa e~neh: kata t~taxic m~Mel,icedek.            </language>            <language id="English">               We therefore magnify You, along with David the prophet, For You are the priest forever, on the order of Melchizedek.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Maka kami pun memuliakan-Mu, bersama Daud sang nabi, sebab Kau-lah imam selama-lamanya, menurut perkataan Melkisedek.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               إننا هكذا نعظمك مع المرتل داود فإنك أنت الكاهن إلى الأبد على طقس ملكي صادق.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere pinis] m~patriar,/c: peniwt eyouab Abba Ayanacioc: v/e~ta nefc~bwoui~ eyouab: erouwini m~pennouc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to the great patriarch, our holy father Abba Athanasius, whose holy teachings, enlightened our minds.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, patriark agung, bapa kudus kami Abba Athanasius, ajarannya yang kudus menerangi pikiran kami.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام للبطريرك العظيم أبينا القديس الأنبا أثناسيوس يا من تعاليمه المقدسة أنارت عقولنا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Wouniatk qen oumeym/i: peniwt eyouab m~patriar,/c:  Abba Ayanacioc pia~poctolikoc: pimenrit n~te Pi,~rictoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Blessed are you indeed, our holy father the patriarch, Abba Athanasius the apostolic, beloved of Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Terpujilah engkau, Bapa Patriark kami yang kudus, Abba Athanasius sang apostolik, kekasih Kristus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               مبارك أنت بالحقيقة أيها الاب القديس البطريرك القديس أثناسيوس الرسولي حبيب المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StAthanasius" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>            <section antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Athanasius the Apostolic</language><language id="Indonesian">Doksologi untuk St. Athanasius Sang Apostolik</language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للقديس الأنبا أثناسيوس البطريرك</language>            <language id="Coptic">Ayanacioc...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Athanasius:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Athanasius:            </language>         </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ayanacioc piapoctolikoc: picaq n~te ]ekkl/cia: e~tafswpi m~piaylovoroc: eybe teforyodoxia~.            </language>            <language id="English">               Athanasius the Apostolic, the teacher of the Church, who became a champion, because of his Orthodoxy.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Athanasius sang Apostolik, Guru Gereja, yang menjadi pahlawan iman karena kesetiaannya pada ajaran Ortodoks.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أثناسيوس الرسولي: مُعلِّم الكنيسة: الذي صارَ بطلاً: لأجل أرثوذكسيته.            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je afswpi n~ouq/bc: eferouwini m~pikocmoc t/rf: etaf[ro n~Arioc: nefmetkakia~ afjorou e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               For he became a lamp, illuminating the entire world, when he defeated Arius, purging his darkness.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia menjadi pelita, terangi seluruh dunia saat ia kalahkan Arius, dan singkirkan kegelapannya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأنه صار سراجاً: منيراً للعالم كله: لمَّا هَزَمَ أريوس: مبدِّداً ظلماتِه.            </language>         </text>                   <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh aft~cabon je pilogoc: n~o~mooucioc nem V~iwt: efj/k e~bolqen tefmeynou]: qen ouvucic n~ouwt.            </language>            <language id="English">               And he taught us that the Logos, is consubstantial with the Father, whole in His divinity, with one nature.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia ajarkan kita bahwa Sang Logos (Firman) sehakikat dengan Sang Bapa, utuh dalam keilahian-Nya, satu kodrat.<br/></div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وعلَّمنا أن الكلمة: مساوياً للآب: كاملاً في ألوهيَّتِه: بطبيعة واحدة.            </language>         </text>                   <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Af] oube niremn~i~dolon: ke on niheretukoc: afcek erwou e~pinah]: ef] tajro m~peflaoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               He fought the pagans, and the heretics, drew them to the faith, fortifying his people in the faith.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia melawan penyembah berhala dan bidat, menarik mereka kepada iman dan kuatkan umatnya dalam kebenaran iman.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               قاوَم الوثنيين: وأيضاً الهراطقة: جذبهُم إلى الإيمان: مُثَبِّتاً شعبَه.            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ava]meynou] jeke~bol: pefc/ou t/rf qen piagwn: ouoh afswpi oube pikocmoc: je nafoi nem P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               The father of theology spent, all his life in struggles, and became against the world, for he was with Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bapa Teologi ini habiskan seluruh hidupnya dalam perjuangan dan menentang dunia, karena ia berpihak pada Kristus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وقضى أبو اللاهوت: كلَّ زمانه في الجهاد: وصارَ ضِدَّ العالم: لأنه كان مع المسيح.            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               V/etafswpi nem nia~poctoloc: pinis] qen nipatriar,/c: afhicen] n~]metmona,oc: qen nemh/t enafoi n~,aki .            </language>            <language id="English">               He who was like the apostles, great among the patriarchs, who established monasticism, in the dark West.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia serupa dengan para rasul, agung di antara para patriark, yang mendirikan monastisisme di Barat yang gelap.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الذي صار مع الرسل: العظيم في البطاركة: الذي أرسى الرهبنة: في الغرب المُظلِم.            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afhicen] on n~]ekkl/cia: qen t~polic n~nie~yaus: akouwrpnwou n~apouncalama: e~te pihiwis n~te piouwini.            </language>            <language id="English">               He also established the Church, in the land of Ethiopia, and sent to them Father Salama, who is the preacher of light.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia juga mendirikan Gereja di tanah Etiopia, dan mengutus kepada mereka Abba Salama, pewarta terang.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أرسى أيضاً الكنيسة: في بلدة الحبشة: أرسل لهم أبونا سلامه: الذي هو مُعلِن النور.            </language>         </text>                        <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Twbh m~Po#c# e~h~r/i e~jwn: w~pinis] m~patriar,/c: abba Ayanacioc piapoctolikoc: n~t#e#f# ...            </language>            <language id="English">               Pray to the Lord on our behalf, O great Patriarch, Abba Athanasius the Apostolic, that He may forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoalah pada Tuhan demi kami, ya Patriarkh agung, Abba Athanasius sang Apostolik, agar Dia mengampuni dosa-dosa kami.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أطلب من الرب عنَّا: أيها البطريرك العظيم: أنبا أثناسيوس الرسولي: ليغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </section>   </season></document>