<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StBarbara:Doxology | StJuliana:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Barbara and St. Juliana</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Barbara dan St. Juliana</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية القديسة بربارة والقديسة يوليانه</language>            <language id="Coptic">Piouwini n~}t~riac...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Barbara and St. Juliana:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Peringatan Santa Barbara dan Santa Juliana:</div></language>         </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">                        Piouwini n~}t~riac e#y#u#: afsai e~jen taiparyenoc: ]a~gia Barbara: ]selet n~te P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               The light of the holy Trinity, has shone upon this virgin, Saint Barbara, the Bride of Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Terang Tritunggal Mahakudus telah sinari perawan suci ini, Santa Barbara, mempelai Kristus yang murni.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نور الثالوث الأقدس أشرق على هذه العذراء القديسة برباره عروس المسيح.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">                        Ecmenre n~}t~riac e#y#u#: ouoh eymoc] gar m~peciwt: pirwmi n~a~nomoc e~tafsat: n~teca~ve qen tefjij.            </language>            <language id="English">               She loved the holy Trinity, and disdained her father, the lawless man, who cut her head with his hand.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia mengasihi Tritunggal Mahakudus, dan mengabaikan ayahnya yang durhaka, yang memenggal kepalanya dengan tangannya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأنها أحبت الثالوث الأقدس وأبغضت أباها. الرجل مخالف الناموس الذى قطع رأسها بيده.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">                        Rasi w~ ]selet m~m/i: e/e~tacswpi n~oue~rvei: n~te Pip~neuma e#y#u#: icjen tecmetkouji n~a~lou.            </language>            <language id="English">               Rejoice O true bride, who has become a sanctuary, for the Holy Spirit, since her early childhood.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bersukacitalah, hai mempelai sejati, yang telah menjadi bait suci, bagi Roh Kudus, sejak masa kecilnya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               افرحى أيتها العروس الحقيقية. التى صارت هيكلا للروح القدس منذ طفوليتها.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">                        Ereswpi gar n~yo: tseri m~Viwt et qen niv/oui: ouoh e~reswpi gar n~ouseri: m~Maria ]paryenoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               For you became a daughter, of the heavenly Father, and you became a daughter, of Mary the Virgin.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sebab kau telah menjadi puteri Bapa Surgawi, dan puteri Maria sang Perawan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأنك صرت ابنة للآب السماوى وصرت أيضا ابنة لمريم العذراء.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">                        Tentaio~ m~mwten qen ouounof: w~ niselet n~te P,#c#: ]a~gia Barbara: nem ]a~gia Iwliana.            </language>            <language id="English">               We honor you joyfully, O brides of Christ, Saint Barbara, and Saint Juliana.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami memuliakanmu dengan sukacita, hai para mempelai Kristus, Santa Barbara dan Santa Juliana.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نكرمكما بابتهاج ياعروسا المسيح. أيتها القديسة الحقيقية بربارة والقديسة يوليانه.            </language>         </text>                  <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StBarbaraAndStJuliana" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>