<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StGeorge:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. George</language><language id="Indonesian">Doksologi untuk St. George</language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للشهيد مار جرجس</language>            <language id="Coptic">Sasf n~rompi...</language>         </Title>                        <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. George:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Peringatan Untuk St. George:            </language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Sasf n~rompi afjokou e~bol: n~je v/e#y#u# Gewrgioc: e~re pis~be n~ouro n~a~nomoc: eu]hap e~rof m~m/ni.            </language>            <language id="English">               Saint George completed: seven whole years: being judged daily: by seventy lawless kings.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Santo George selesaikan tujuh tahun penuh, dihakimi setiap hari: oleh tujuh puluh raja yang durhaka.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               سبع سنين أكملها القديس جيؤرجيوس ال٧٠ ملكا منافقين يحكمون عليه كل يوم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Mpous~vwnh m~peflogicmoc: oude pefnah] etcoutwn: oude tefnis] n~a~gap/: e~qoun e~p~ouro P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               They could not change his mind: nor his upright faith: nor his great love: for Christ the King.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Namun mereka tak dapat ubah pikirannya: pun imannya yang teguh: juga kasihnya yang besar: pada Kristus Sang Raja.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ولم يقدروا أن يميلوا أفكاره ولا إيمانه المستقيم ولا عظم محبته في الملك المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nafer'alin nem Dauid: je aukw] e~roi n~je nieynoc t/rou: alla qen v~ran n~I/#c# Panou]: ai[i m~pa[i m~p~sis nemwou.            </language>            <language id="English">               He was singing with David saying: "All the nations surrounded me: but in the name of Jesus my Lord: I took revenge upon them.”            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia nyanyi bersama Daud, katanya: "Segala bangsa mengepung aku, tetapi dalam nama Yesus Tuhanku, aku kalahkan mereka."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وكان يرتل مع داود قائلا أحاط بي جميع الأمم لكن بإسم يسوع الهي انتقمت منهم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ounis] gar pe pektaio~: w~ pao#c# p~ouro Gewrgioc: e~re P,#c# rasi nemak: qen Ieroucal/m n~te t~ve.            </language>            <language id="English">               For great is your honor: O my lord Prince George: for Christ rejoices in you: in the heavenly Jerusalem.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div><div>Sungguh besar kehormatanmu, ya tuanku Pangeran George, sebab Kristus bersukacita atasmu di Yerusalem surgawi.</div></div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               عظيمة هي كرامتك ياسيدى الملك جيؤرجيوس المسيح يفرح معك في أورشليم السمائية.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pimarturoc: ,ere piswij n~genneoc: ,ere piaylovoroc: pao#c# p~ouro Gewrgioc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you, O martyr: Hail to the courageous hero: Hail to the struggle-mantled: my lord Prince George.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, hai martir: Salam bagi pahlawan pemberani: Salam bagi dia yang berjubah perjuangan: tuanku Pangeran George.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيها الشهيد السلام للشجاع المجاهد السلام للابس الجهاد سيدى الملك جيؤرجيوس.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StGeorge" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>            <section antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Another Doxology for St. George</language><language id="Indonesian">Doksologi Lain untuk St. George</language>                     <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية آخر للشهيد مار جرجس</language>            <language id="Coptic">Ni,oroc n~te nimarturoc...</language>         </Title>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ni,oroc n~te nimarturoc: nem niy~m/i nem nidikeoc: euermakarizin m~mok: w~ piouro Gewrgioc.            </language>            <language id="English">               The choruses: of the martyrs: the just and the righteous: bless you O King George;            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Paduan suara: para martir: yang benar dan saleh: memujimu, ya Raja George.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صفوف الشهداء والأبرار والصديقين يطوبونك أيها الملك جيؤرجيوس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je n~yok ounis] gar n~q/tou: eybe tekomologia~: menenca sasf n~rompi n~c/ou: m~peh~li erv~meui~ m~P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               For you are great among them: because of your confession: after seven years’ time: no one remembered Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian">Karena kau agung di antara mereka: sebab pengakuan imanmu: setelah tujuh tahun lamanya: tak seorang pun mengingat Kristus.</language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأنك أنت العظيم فيهم من أجل اعترافك بعد سبع سنوات من الزمن لم يكن يذكر اسم المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Akouwnh m~P,#c# e~bol: qen ouparr/cia~ n~aterho]: afswpi n~hans~be n~ouro: nem noui~dwlon et[wqem.            </language>            <language id="English">               You proclaimed Christ: boldly and fearlessly: Seventy kings were there: with their defiled idols.            </language><language id="Indonesian">Kau beritakan Kristus: dengan berani tanpa takut: Ada tujuh puluh raja di sana: bersama berhala mereka yang cemar.</language>            <language id="Arabic">               اعترفت بالمسيح علناً بغير خوف وكان سبعون ملكاً مع أوثانهم النجسة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Aksepm~kauh e~bolhitotou: n~sasf n~rompi etj/k e~bol: auerbacanizin m~mok: qen ounis] m~bacanoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               You received sufferings from them: for seven whole years: They tortured you: with great tortures;            </language><language id="Indonesian">Engkau terima banyak derita dari mereka selama tujuh tahun penuh. Mereka menyiksamu dengan siksaan yang berat.</language>            <language id="Arabic">               قبلت الآلام منهم سبع سنوات كاملة عذبوك بعذابات عظيمة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Qen nai aP,#c# piouro: ]taio~ m~mok e~masw: e~hote nimarturoc: afmou] e~rok je ounis] n~q/tou.            </language>            <language id="English">               With these, Christ the King: honored your greatly: more than the martyrs: He called you, “great”, among them.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengan itu, Kristus Sang Raja: memuliakanmu: lebih dari para martir: Ia menyebutmu, "agung", di antara mereka.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وبهذا الملك المسيح كرمك جداً أكثر من الشهداء ودعاك العظيم فيهم..            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afervorin m~mok qen tefjij: n~oui~nam n~sasf n~,~lom: afolk nemaf e~tefmetouro: qen ouw~ou nem outaio~.            </language>            <language id="English">               With His right hand he adorned you: with seven crowns: He lifted you with Him: to His kingdom with glory and honor.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Melalui tangan kanan-Nya, Ia hiasimu dengan tujuh mahkota. Ia gangkat kau bersama-Nya: ke kerajaan-Nya dengan kemuliaan dan kehormatan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وألبسك سبع اكاليل بيمينه ورفعك معه إلي ملكوته بمجد وكرامة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pimarturoc: ,ere piswij n~genneoc: ,ere piaylovoroc: pao#c# p~ouro Gewrgioc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you, O martyr: Hail to the courageous hero: Hail to the struggle-mantled: my lord King George.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, hai martir: Salam bagi pahlawan pemberani: Salam bagi dia yang berjubah perjuangan: tuanku Raja Georgius.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيها الشهيد السلام للشجاع المجاهد السلام للابس الجهاد سيدى الملك جيؤرجيوس.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StGeorge" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>