<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StGeorgeTheZahimian:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. George Muzahim</language><language id="Indonesian">Doksologi untuk St. George Muzahim</language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية الشهيد مار جرجس المزاحم</language>            <language id="Coptic">Gewrgioc piremzahim...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. George Muzahim:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan  St. George Muzahim:            </language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Gewrgioc piremzahim: e~tafsep hannis] n~qici: eybe pefmei m~P,#c#: af[i n~]metmarturia~.            </language>            <language id="English">               George Muzahim: who accepted great sufferings: because of his love for Christ: He received martyrdom.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>George Muzahim terima derita yang besar karena kasihnya pada Kristus sehingga terima mahkota martir.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               مار جرجس المزاحم الذي قبل أتعاباً كثيرة من أجل محبته للمسيح وأخذ إكليل الشهادة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pefiwt ne oulamit/c pe: af[i tefmau n~,~ba m~moc: je n~yoc ou,~rictianoc te: ac]c~bw naf n~nis] n~aret/.            </language>            <language id="English">               His father was a Pagan: He took his mother against her will: because she was a Christian: She taught him great virtues.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ayahnya adalah penyembah berhala: yang ambil ibunya dengan paksa: meski ibunya seorang Kristen: Namun sang ibu ajarkan kepadanya banyak kebajikan besar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               والده كان حنيفياً تزوج أمه عنوة ولأنها كانت مسيحية علمته الفضائل العظيمة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afouws n~tefer,~rictianoc: af,w n~neni~ri n~nilamit/c: pefiwt afwrk n~tefqoybef: afvwt afqici n~tef[iwmc.            </language>            <language id="English">               He desired to become Christian: He left his father’s religion: His father swore to kill him: so he fled and suffered to be baptized.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia rindu menjadi orang Kristen: Lalu tinggalkan agama ayahnya. Ayahnya bersumpah 'kan membunuhnya, maka ia melarikan diri dan berjuang agar dapat dibaptis.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أراد أن يكون مسيحياُ وترك أعمال دين أبيه حلف أبوه أن يقتله هرب وتعب لكي يعمد.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Af[i c~himi n~ouseri n~ou/b: acy~ref[i m~piwmc m~m/i: afsep nibacanoc nem tefc~himi: je afouwnh qen P,#c# e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               He took a priest’s daughter as a wife: who directed him to the true baptism: He received tortures with his wife: because he manifested Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia menikahi putri seorang imam, yang tuntun dia kepada baptisan yang benar. Ia pun terima siksaan bersama istrinya karena ia mengakui Kristus dengan berani.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               تزوج إبنة كاهن جعلته ينال العماد الحقيقي قبل العذابات مع زوجته لأنه اعترف بالمسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &gt;&lt;ere naf auveq tefa~ve: auvetvwtf afermarturoc: pi,~rwm m~pef]ywbs n~q/tf: afma] e~p~w~ou m~p~ounof.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to him who was beheaded: cut in pieces, he was martyred: Fire did not affect him: he received joyful glory.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam baginya yang dipenggal kepalanya: tubuhnya dicincang dan mati martir: Api tidak melukainya: ia terima kemuliaan penuh sukacita.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام له شقوا رأسه وقطعوه فصار شهيداً والنار لم تؤثر فيه ونال مجد النعيم.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StGeorgeTheZahimian" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>