<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StGregoryTheTheologian:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Gregory the Theologian</language><language id="Indonesian">Doksologi untuk St. Gregory Sang Teolog</language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية القديس اغريغوريوس الناطق بالإلهيات</language>         </Title>                        <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Gregory the Theologian:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Gregory Sang Teolog:            </language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="English">               Gregory of Nazianzus: O great shepherd: the luminous pillar: of the Orthodox people.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div><div>Gregorius dari Nazianzus: Oh gembala agung: tiang terang yang menuntun umat Ortodoks.</div></div></language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="English">               O great Archbishop: of Constantinople: you authored the liturgy: with the sweetness of your words.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ya Uskup Agung yang hebat: dari Konstantinopel, yang tulis liturgi penuh keindahan dengan manisnya kata-katamu.</div></language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="English">               His father, a bishop: by heresies was led astray: but returned to the true faith: through his son, Saint Gregory.             </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ayahnya, seorang uskup: pernah tersesat ajaran sesat: namun kembali ke iman yang benar: melalui putranya, Santo Gregorius.</div></language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="English">               With your holy sayings: concerning the Trinity: you rebuked the heretics: and corrected their false teachings.             </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengan kalimatmu yang suci tentang Tritunggal Mahakudus: kau tegur para bidat: luruskan ajaran sesat mereka.</div></language>         </text>                   <text>            <language id="English">               Blessed are you indeed: our holy father the patriarch: Abba Gregory the Theologian: the beloved of Christ.             </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Diberkatilah kau: ya Bapa patriark kami yang kudus: Abba Gregorius sang Teolog: kekasih Kristus.</div></language>         </text>                   <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StGregoryTheTheologian" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>