<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StJohnTheShort:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. John the Short</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Yohanes si Pendek</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للقديس أنبا يؤانس القصير</language>            <language id="Coptic">Akswpi gar...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. John the Short:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Peringatan St. Yohanes si Pendek:</div></language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Akswpi gar n~ouvwct/r: n~refe~rouwini hijen pikahi: w~ pimakarioc e#y#u#: pao#c# n~iwt abba Iwann/c.            </language>            <language id="English">               For you have become a star, of light upon the earth, O blessed and holy one, my master and father Abba John.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Karena kau telah menjadi bintang  penerang bumi, hai yang diberkati dan kudus, guruku dan bapaku, Abba Yohanes.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صرت كوكبا منيرا على الأرض أيها الطوباوى الطاهر سيدى الآب أنبا يؤانس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Hwcte hiten pekyebio~: nem pekbioc n~aggelikon: akes Sih/t t/rf n~ca pekt/b: m~v~r/] n~outeltili m~mwou.            </language>            <language id="English">               That through your humility, and angelic life, you made Shiheet like the stars, with your finger.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Melalui kerendahan hatimu dan hidupmu yang seperti malaikat, kau buat Shiheet seperti bintang-bintang dengan jarimu.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               حتى أنك من قبل تواضعك وسيرتك الملائكية اعتبرت كل شيهات كنقطة ماء فى أصبعك.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh akw~fi m~pekcwma: qen hanack/cic euqoci: san~tekswpi n~atkundinoc: qen pie~hoou n~te ]k~ricic.            </language>            <language id="English">               And you subdued your body, with many ascetic pains, so that you may be blameless, in the day of judgment.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan kau taklukkan tubuhmu dengan penderitaan asketik (latihan rohani yang keras), agar engkau tidak bercela pada hari penghakiman.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               و أقمعت جسدك بنسك متعب لتكون بغير شدة فى يوم الدينونة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Akswpi n~lum/n n~ououjai: nirefmwout aktounocou: nidemwn akhitou e~bol: n/etswni aktal[wou.            </language>            <language id="English">               You became a harbor of salvation, you have raised the dead, you have exorcised the demons, and you have healed the sick.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kau jadi pelabuhan keselamatan, kau bangkitkan orang mati, kau usir roh jahat, dan sembuhkan orang sakit.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صرت ميناء خلاص أقمت الأموات وأخرجت الشياطين وشفيت المرضى.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh on akerp~emp~sa: pao#c# n~iwt abba Iwann/c: n~tekhemci nem nia~poctoloc: n~tek]hap n~tekgenea.            </language>            <language id="English">               And also you were worthy, O my master and father Abba John, to sit with the Apostles, and judge your generation.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kau layak, ya tuanku Abba Yohanes, untuk duduk bersama para Rasul, dan hakimi generasimu.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أيضا استحققت ياسيدى الآب أنبا يؤانس أن تجلس مع الرسل وتدين جيلك.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StJohnTheShort" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>