<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StMaurice:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Maurice</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Maurice</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية القديس موريس</language>            <language id="Coptic">Mour/c pijwri...</language>         </Title>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Maurice:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Maurice:            </language>         </comment>                   <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Mour/c pijwri m~marturoc: piswij m~m/i qen nibwtc: pianjwj n~nimatoi: n~te ]parabol/ n~remn~tiba.             </language>            <language id="English">               Maurice the strong martyr, truly brave in the wars, the head of the soldiers, of the Theban legion.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Maurice, martir yang gagah berani dalam peperangan, pemimpin para prajurit, dari legiun Theba.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               موريس الشهيد القوي،  الشجاع في الحروب،  رئيس الستمائة والستين جندياً،  للكتيبة الطيبية.            </language>         </text>                     <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouran  n~sousou pe pekran: w~ v/eyouab Mour/c n~tan: Maximianoc piouro: afrasi je e~tak[~ro.            </language>            <language id="English">               A name of pride is your name, O our Saint Maurice, King Maximianos was delighted, in your victory.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Namamu adalah kebanggaan, ya St Maurice, Raja Maksimianos pun bersukacita, atas kemenanganmu.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               إسمك إسم فخر،  يا قديس موريس،  يا من أبهجت الملك مكسيميانوس،  بإنتصاراتك.            </language>         </text>                     <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Umnologia niben: cetwmi e~rok n~c/ou niben: je akhip~ho m~p~ouro ethoou: ouoh akermeyre qa v~nou].             </language>            <language id="English">               All glory is due to you, at all times, for you have opposed the evil king, and bore witness to the God of glory.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Segala kemuliaan layak bagimu, sepanjang waktu, karena kau melawan raja yang jahat, dan bersaksi tentang Allah yang mulia.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لك كل التمجيد،  في كل الأوقات، لأنك تصديت للملك الشرير، وشهدت لإله المجد.            </language>         </text>                     <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Rasi  Mour/c ouoh yel/l: w~ pimenrit n~Emmanou/l: je aksasni n~ounis] n~h~mot: w~ peniwt eyouab e~tenhot.             </language>            <language id="English">               Be joyful Maurice and delight, O beloved of Immanuel, for you have received great grace, O faithful father and saint.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bersukacita, Maurice, dan bergembiralah, ya kekasih Imanuel, sebab kau terima anugerah yang besar, hai bapa dan santo yang setia.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               إفرح وإبتهج يا موريس،  حبيب عمانوئيل،  لأنك وجدت نعمة،  أيها القديس والأب الأمين.            </language>         </text>                     <text>            <language id="Coptic">               ?ppe ic nikematoi: n/etau[im~kah nemak: au[i on m~pi,~lom n~aylwm: qen ]prompi c~nau se pic~tau.             </language>            <language id="English">               Behold your soldiers also, who suffered with you, have received unfading crowns, in the year two-hundred-ninety.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Lihatlah prajuritmu juga, yang menderita bersamamu, telah terima mahkota yang takkan pudar, pada tahun dua ratus sembilan puluh.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وأيضاً جنودك،  الذين تألموا معك، حصلوا علي أكاليل لا تضمحل، سنة مائتان وتسعين ميلادية.            </language>         </text>                     <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Cwten e~ t~c~m/ eymeh n~rasi: n~te Pen[oic I/couc Pennou]: je a~mou e~qoun e~v~rasi: n~te pek[oic n~refnas].            </language>            <language id="English">               Listen to the voice full of joy, of our Lord Jesus our God, saying enter into the joy, of your Lord Giver of victory.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengarlah suara yang penuh sukacita, dari Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus, berkata, “Masuklah dalam sukacita Tuhanmu, Sang Pemberi kemenangan.”</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               إسمع صوت الفرح،  لربنا يسوع المسيح،  قائلاً إدخل الي فرح سيدك،  معطي النصرة.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pimarturoc: ,ere piswij n~genneoc: ,ere piaylovoroc: abba Mour/c n~te Tiba.             </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you  O martyr: Hail to the courageous hero: Hail to the struggle-bearer: Saint Maurice the Theban.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, hai martir: Salam bagi pahlawan pemberani: Salam bagi pejuang sejati: St. Maurice dari Theba.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيها الشهيد، السلام للبطـل الشجاع، السلام للابس الجهاد، القديس آفا موريس.            </language>         </text>                  <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StMaurice" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>