<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StMaximusAndStDometius:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Maximus and St. Dometius</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Maximus dan St. Dometius</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للقديسين الروميين مكسيموس ودوماديوس</language>            <language id="Coptic">Nivwct/r...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Maximus and St. Dometius            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Maximus dan St. Dometius            </language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nivwct/r n~te ]meym/i: ouoh ninis] n~ar,/goc: n~te tencunoudia~ e#y#u#: Maximoc nem Dometioc.            </language>            <language id="English">               The stars of the truth, and the great princes, of our holy congregation, Maximus and Dometius.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bintang-bintang kebenaran, dan para pangeran agung, dari jemaat kudus kita, Maximus dan Dometius.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               كوكبا الحق والرئيسان العظيمان اللذان لمجمعنا المقدس مكسيموس ودوماديوس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nai e~tacyouwten qen nouran: n~je }t~riac n~reftanqo: eyrenmosi n~ca nousentatci: n~tenervorin m~pouc~,/ma e#y#u#.            </language>            <language id="English">               These whom the Life-giving Trinity, has gathered us in their name, that we may follow in their footsteps, and wear their holy images.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mereka yang telah dikumpulkan oleh Tritunggal yang menghidupkan, agar kita ikut jejak mereka, dan kenakan gambar kudus mereka.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               هذان اللذان جمعنا باسميهما الثالوث المحيى لكى نتبع آثارهما ونلبس شكلهما المقدس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Au] e~toten n~niws: etc~q/out qen pieuaggelion: e~te yai te ]metmaicon: p~jwk e~bol n~niare~t/ t/rou.            </language>            <language id="English">               They gave us the written promises, that were in the Gospel, this is the love of brothers, the perfection of all virtues.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mereka berikan pada kita janji-janji tertulis, yang ada dalam Injil. Inilah kasih persaudaraan, kesempurnaan segala kebajikan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وسلما لنا المواعيد المكتوبة فى الانجيل التى هى المحبة الأخوية كمال جميع الفضائل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Enersai qen touekk~l/cia~: enjwk m~pouerv~meui~ e~bol: en]w~ou n~}t~riac: m~pie~hoou nem pie~jwrh.            </language>            <language id="English">               We celebrate in their church, and we complete their remembrance, we glorify the Trinity, by day and by night.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kita rayakan di gereja mereka, dan kenang mereka dengan sempurna, muliakan Tritunggal Kudus, siang dan malam.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نعيد فى كنيستهما ونكمل تذكارهما ونمجد الثالوث نهارا وليلا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nwten w~ nidikeoc: ,ere nip#n#a#tovoroc: ,ere nenio] e#y#u# n~rwmeoc: Maximoc nem Dometioc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you O righteous ones, hail to the spirit mantled, hail to our holy roman fathers, Maximus and Dometius.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, hai orang-orang benar, salam bagi yang berjubah roh, salam bagi bapa-bapa Roma kita yang kudus, Maksimus dan Dometius.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لكما أيها الصديقان السلام للابسى الروح السلام لأبوينا القديسين الروميين مكسيموس ودوماديوس.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StMaximusAndStDometius" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>