<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StMoses:Doxology | MonkOrdination">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for the Strong Abba Moses</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Abba Musa yang Kuat.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية الشهيد أنبا موسى الأسود</language>            <language id="Coptic">Pisorp m~marturoc...</language>         </Title>                  <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Moses            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Musa:</language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pisorp m~marturoc e#y#u#: e~tafjwk e~bol n~kalwc: qen pitwou n~te Sih/t: pe peniwt e#y#u# abba Mwc/.            </language>            <language id="English">               The first holy martyr, who was well perfected, on the mountain of Shiheet, is our holy father Abba Moses.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Martir kudus yang pertama, yang disempurnakan dengan baik, di gunung Shiheet, yakni Bapa kudus kita Abba Musa.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الشهيد الأول القديس الذي كمل حسنا في جبل شيهات هو أبونا القديس أنبا موسى.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afswpi gar n~ouref]: efoi n~ho] oube nidemwn: afo~hi e~ratf hijen ]petra: kata p~tupoc m~pic~tauroc.            </language>            <language id="English">               He became a fighter, whom the demons fear. He stood upon the rock, as a type of the Cross.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia menjadi seorang pejuang, yang ditakuti iblis. Ia berdiri di atas batu, sebagai lambang Salib.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأنه صار محاربا مخوفا ضد الشياطين ووقف على الصخرة كمثال الصليب.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Hiten tefnis] n~hupomon/: nem piqici n~te nibacanoc: afervorin m~pi,~lom: n~te ]metmarturoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Through his great patience, of the travails of his torments, he wore the crown, of martyrdom.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Melalui kesabarannya yang besar dalam menanggung penderitaan, ia kenakan mahkota kemartiran.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بعظم صبره وتعب العذابات لبس الإكليل الذي للشهادة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afhwl e~p~[ici qen pip#n#a#: e~qoun e~nefman~emton: e~tafcebtwtou n~je Po#c#: n~n/eymei m~pefran e#y#u#.            </language>            <language id="English">               He flew in the spirit to the heights, to the place of rest, which the Lord has prepared, for those who love His holy name.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia terbang dalam roh ke tempat tinggi, ke tempat perhentian, yang telah disiapkan Tuhan, bagi mereka yang mengasihi nama kudus-Nya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ذهب بالروح إلي العلو إلي مواضع النياح التي أعدها الرب لمحبي اسمه القدوس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afcwjp nan m~pefcwma: nem pefc~p/leon e#y#u#: eyrenjwk e~bol n~q/tf: m~peferv~meui~ ettai/out.            </language>            <language id="English">               He left for us his holy body, and his holy cave, that we may complete in it, his honored memorial.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia tinggalkan bagi kita gua dan tubuh kudusnya, agar kita dapat rayakan peringatan mulianya di dalamnya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وأبقى لنا جسده ومغارته المقدسة لنكمل فيها تذكاره المكرم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Enws e~bol enjw m~moc: je V] n~abba Mwc/: nem n/e~taujwk e~bol nemaf: a~riounai nem nen'u,/.            </language>            <language id="English">               Proclaiming and saying, “O God of Abba Moses, and those who were perfected with him, have mercy upon our souls.”            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berseru dan berkata, "Ya Allah Abba Musa, dan mereka yang disempurnakan bersamanya, kasihanilah jiwa kami."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               إذ نصرخ قائلين يا اله أنبا موسى والذين كملوا معه اصنع رحمة مع نفوسنا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh n~tensasni e~niws: e~tafcebtwtou n~n/e#y#u#: e~tauranaf icjen p~e~neh: eybe toua~gap/ e~qoun e~rof.            </language>            <language id="English">               That we may win the promises, which He has prepared for the saints, who have pleased Him since the beginning, because of their love for Him.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Agar kita dapat menangkan janji-janji yang telah disediakan-Nya bagi para kudus, yang telah senangkan hati-Nya sejak semula, karena kasih mereka kepada-Nya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ونفوز بالمواعيد المعدة للقديسين الذين أرضوه منذ البدء لأجل حبهم فيه.            </language>         </text>         <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Twbh m~Po#c# e~h~r/i e~jwn:  w~ pao#c# n~iwt abba Mwc/: nem nefs/ri n~c~taurovoroc: n~tef,a nennobi nan e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               Pray to the Lord on our behalf, O my master the father Abba Moses, and his children the cross-bearers, that He may forgive us our sins.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Berdoalah pada Tuhan demi kami, ya guruku dan bapaku Abba Musa, bersama anak-anakmu para pemikul salib, agar Ia mengampuni dosa-dosa kami.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أطلب من الرب عنا ياسيدى ألآب أنبا موسى وأولاده لباس الصليب ليغفر لنا خطايانا.            </language>         </text>      </section>   </season></document>