<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StParsoumaTheNaked:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Parsouma the Naked</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Parsouma yang Telanjang</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية أنبا برسوم العريان</language>            <language id="Coptic">Marenywou] w~ namenra]...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Parsouma the Naked:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Parsouma yang Telanjang:</language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Marenywou] w~ namenra]: nt~entaio qen ou]ma]: m~pimairwmi n~dikeoc: peniwt eyouab abba Parcwma.            </language>            <language id="English">               Let us gather O my beloved, with pleasure to honor, this righteous man, our holy father Abba Parsouma.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mari kita berkumpul, hai saudaraku terkasih, dengan sukacita untuk hormati, orang benar ini, bapak suci kita Abba Parsouma.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فلنجتمع يا أحبائى لنكرم بسرور هذا الرجل البار أبانا القديس أنبا برسوم.             </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Vai e~tafhip~ho m~paikocmoc: nem pefbioc eymeh n~qici: qen ounis] n~hupomon/: afmei m~P,#c# pef[oic.             </language>            <language id="English">               This one who forsook the world, and its painful life, with great patience, loved Christ his Lord.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia tinggalkan dunia ini, dan segala penderitaannya, dengan kesabaran yang besar, karena ia mengasihi Kristus, Tuhannya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               هذا الذى رفض العالم وحياته المملؤة تعبا بعظم صبر وأحب المسيح ربه.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afcwr e~bol n~je pefran: qen ]oikoumen/ t/rc: eybe nefe~ret/ et[oci: nem peftoubo na~ggelikon.            </language>            <language id="English">               His fame has spread, onto all the world, because of his high virtues, and his angelic purity.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Namanya tersebar luas, ke seluruh penjuru dunia, karena kebajikannya yang besar, dan kemurniannya yang seperti malaikat.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وذاع اسمه فى المسكونة كلها من أجل فضائله العالية وطهارته الملائكية.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Naf]nom] n~ouon niben:eyn/ou harof e~bolqen mai niben: qen oua~gap/ ecj/k e~bol: nem oumetrefw~ou n~h/t.             </language>            <language id="English">               He comforted everyone, who came to him from everywhere, through perfect love, and long suffering.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia hibur setiap orang, yang datang padanya dari mana saja, melalui kasih yang sempurna, dan penderitaan yang panjang.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وكان يقوى كل من يأتى إليه من كل مكان بمحبة كاملة وطول أناة.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Wouniatk qen oumeym/i: peniwt eyouab abba Parcwma: je akjwk e~bol n~nicaji: n~te pencwt/r n~a~gayoc.             </language>            <language id="English">               Blessed are you indeed, O our holy father Abba Parsouma, for you fulfilled the words, of our good Savior.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sungguh diberkatilah kau, ya bapak suci kami Abba Parsouma, karena kau telah genapi firman, dari Juruselamat kita yang baik.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               طوباك أنت بالحقيقة يا أبانا القديس البار أنبا برسوم لأنك أكملت أقوال مخلصنا الصالح.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StParsoumaTheNaked" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>