<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StPeterAndStPaul:Doxology | ApostlesFeast">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Peter and St. Paul</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Petrus dan St. Paulus</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للقديسين بطرس وبولس</language>            <language id="Coptic">Petroc pia~poctoloc...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Peter and St. Paul:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Petrus dan St. Paulus:</language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Petroc pia~poctoloc: nem Pauloc picovoc: niar,/ m~may/t/c: n~te Peno#c# I/#c# P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               Peter the Apostle, and Paul the wise, the heads of the disciples, of our Lord Jesus Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Petrus sang rasul, dan Paulus yang bijak, kepala para murid Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بطرس الرسول وبولس ذو الحكمة رؤساء تلاميذ ربنا يسوع المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Petroc nem Pauloc: aukwrf n~t~jom n~te p~catanac: ouoh autacyo n~nieynoc: e~qoun e~v~nah] n~}t~riac.            </language>            <language id="English">               Peter and Paul, trampled the power of Satan, and restored the nations, to the faith of the Trinity.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Petrus dan Paulus, injak kuasa Setan, dan kembalikan bangsa-bangsa, kepada iman Tritunggal.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بطرس وبولس سحقا قوة الشيطان وردوا الأمم للأيمان بالثالوث.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Petroc nem Pauloc: de on niou/b m~p#n#a#tikon: ausorser n~nierv/oui~: nem p~semsi n~nii~dwlon.            </language>            <language id="English">               Peter and Paul, are the spiritual priests, they demolished the temples, and the worship of idols.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Petrus dan Paulus, adalah imam rohani, mereka runtuhkan kuil, dan penyembahan berhala.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بطرس وبولس هما الكاهنان الروحيان هدما هياكل وعبادة الأوثان.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Petroc nem Pauloc: eucop niergat/c n~referhwb: autacyo n~nieynoc t/rou: e~pirefyamio n~kecop.            </language>            <language id="English">               Peter and Paul, together are the workers and craftsmen, they restored all the nations, once more to the Creator.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mereka adalah pekerja dan pengrajin, pulihkan semua bangsa, kembali pada Sang Pencipta.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بطرس وبولس معا الفاعلين العاملين ردا جميع الأمم إلى الخالق دفعة أخرى.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Petroc nem pencaq Pauloc: auswpi qen pic~tadion: n~te ]meta~poctoloc: qen ounis] n~agwn.            </language>            <language id="English">               Peter and our teacher Paul, with great struggle, were in the stadium, of the apostles.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Petrus dan guru kita Paulus, dengan perjuangan besar, berada di medan pelayanan para rasul.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               بطرس ومعلمنا بولس كانا في ميدان الرسولية فى جهاد عظيم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Peniwt Petroc jwk e~bol: qen oumou n~te pic~tauroc: qen ]nis] m~polic Rwme: eybe v~ran n~I/#c# P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               Our father Peter completed, his struggle with death on the cross, in the great city of Rome, for the name of Jesus Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bapa kita Petrus selesaikan, perjuangannya dengan matinya di kayu salib, di kota besar Roma, demi nama Yesus Kristus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أبونا بطرس أكمل بموت الصليب في مدينة روما العظمى لأجل اسم ربنا يسوع المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pauloc de on m~pair/]: auw~li n~tefa~ve m~mau: e~bolhiten p~ouro Niron: qen pie~hoou n~ouwt.            </language>            <language id="English">               Paul also likewise, was beheaded in that place, by Emperor Nero, all in one day.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Paulus juga demikian, dipenggal di tempat itu, oleh Kaisar Nero, pada hari yang sama.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وهكذا أيضا بولس نزعت رأسه هناك من قبل الملك نيرون في يوم واحد.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ausep w~ou ha p~ouro P,#c#: ouoh aum~ton m~mwou nemaf: qen tefmetouro n~e~neh: nem piwnq efm/n e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               They received glory from Christ, the King and they rested with Him, in His eternal kingdom, in the everlasting life.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mereka terima kemuliaan dari Kristus, Sang Raja dan beristirahat bersama-Nya, di kerajaan-Nya yang kekal, dalam kehidupan abadi.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ونالا المجد من الملك المسيح واستراحا معه في ملكوته الأبدي والحياة الدائمة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Anon de hwn tentaio~ m~mwou: nem Dauid p~ouro pihumnodoc: je a~pouq~rwou senaf e~bol: hijen p~ho m~p~kahi t/rf.            </language>            <language id="English">               We also honor them, with David the psalmist, saying "Their voices went forth, throughout the face of the whole world."            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kita pun menghormati mereka, bersama Daud sang pemazmur, sambil berkata: "Suara mereka telah terdengar, ke seluruh muka bumi."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ونحن أيضا نكرمهم مع داود الملك المرتل أن أصواتهم خرجت إلى وجه الأرض كلها.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StPeterAndStPaul" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>