<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StPhilopaterMercurius:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Philopater Mercurius</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Filopater Merkurius:</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للشهيد مرقوريوس ذى السيفين</language>            <language id="Coptic">Vilopat/r Merkourioc...</language>         </Title>                     <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Philopater Mercurius:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Filopater Merkurius:            </language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Vilopat/r Merkourioc: piremn~jom n~te P,#c#: af]hiwtf n~]panoplia~: nem piqwk t/rf n~te pinah].            </language>            <language id="English">               Philopateer Mercurius: the mighty one of Christ: put on the full battle gear: and the whole armor of faith.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Filopater Merkurius: yang perkasa dalam Kristus: kenakan perlengkapan perang lengkap: dan seluruh zirah iman.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               محب الآب مرقوريوس القوى بالمسيح لبس الخوذة وكل سلاح الإيمان.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh af[i qen tefjij: n~]c/fi n~ro c~nau: y/e~ta piaggeloc n~te Po#c# tajroc: qen tefjij n~oui~nam.            </language>            <language id="English">               He took in his hand: the two-edged sword: that an angel of the Lord: placed in his right hand.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia ambil pedang bermata dua di tangannya, yang diberikan malaikat Tuhan di tangan kanannya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وأخذ بيده السيف ذا الحدين الذي ثبته ملاك الرب في يده اليمنى.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afsenaf e~pipolemoc: qen ]jom n~te P,#c#: afsari e~nibarbaroc: qen ounis] n~erqot.            </language>            <language id="English">               He went to war: in the power of Christ. He smote the barbarians: with severe wounds.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia pergi berperang: dalam kuasa Kristus. Ia pukul mundur orang-orang barbar: dengan luka-luka parah.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               مضى إلي الحرب بقوة المسيح وقتل البربر بجراحات عظيمة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Afernumvin e~bolha na p~kahi: ouoh afkw] e~na niv/oui: af[oji qen pic~tadion: n~te ]metmarturoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               He refused the earthly: and sought the heavenly. He fought in the stadium: of martyrdom.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia tolak yang duniawi: dan cari yang surgawi. berjuang di gelanggang: kemartiran.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               تيقظ عن الأرضيات وطلب السمائيات وتشجع في ميدان الشهادة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Af]sipi n~Dekioc: piouro n~a~ceb/c: hiten tefnis] n~hupomon/: nem p~qici n~te nibacanoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               He embarrassed Decius: the ungodly emperor: through his great patience: in the travails of his torments.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia permalukan Decius, kaisar yang fasik, melalui kesabarannya yang besar dalam penderitaan dan siksaan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أفضح داكيوس الملك المنافق بصبره العظيم وتعب العذابات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Qen nai afervorin m~pi,~lom n~atlwm n~te ]metmarturoc: afersai nem n/e#y#u# t/rou: qen t~,wra n~te n/etonq.            </language>            <language id="English">               In this he wore the unfading crown: of martyrdom: he celebrated with all the saints: in the region of the living.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dengan ini ia kenakan mahkota kemartiran yang takkan pudar: ia rayakan bersama semua orang kudus: di tempat kehidupan kekal</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وبهذا لبس اكليل الشهادة غير المضمحل وعيد مع جميع القديسين في كورة الأحياء.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pimarturoc: ,ere piswij n~genneoc: ,ere piaylovoroc: Vilopat/r Merkourioc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you O martyr: hail to the noble hero: hail to the struggle-bearer: Philopateer Mercurius.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, hai martir. Salam bagimu, pahlawan yang mulia. Salam bagimu, pembawa perjuangan, Filopater Merkurius.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيها الشهيد السلام للشجاع البطل السلام للمجاهد محب ألآب مرقوريوس.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StPhilopaterMercurius" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>