<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StPishoyAndStPaulOfTammah:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Pishoy and St. Paul of Tammah</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Pishoy dan St. Paul dari Tammah</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية لأنبا بيشوى و أنبا بولا الطموهى</language>            <language id="Coptic">Iwc/f piar...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Pishoy and St. Paul of Tammah:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Pishoy dan St. Paul dari Tammah:</language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Iwc/f piar,/e~reuc: n~te ]nis] m~baki Rako]: piparyenoc eutoub/out: etjolh m~piyebio m~m/i.            </language>            <language id="English">               O Joseph the archpriest, of the great city of Alexandria, the pure virgin, adorned with true humility.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Hai Yusuf sang imam agung, dari kota besar Aleksandria, perawan yang murni,  dihiasi dengan kerendahan hati yang sejati.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               يايوساب رئيس كهنة المدينة العظمى الاسكندرية البتول النقى الملتحف بالتواضع الحقيقى.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nh~r/i qen nie~hoou: n~te tekmetar,/e~reuc: a~painis] n~h~mot tahon: a~non qa niatemp~sa.            </language>            <language id="English">               For in the days, of your high-priesthood, this great grace came to us, we the undeserving.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sebab di masa imamatmu yang tinggi, rahmat agung ini datang kepada kami, kami yang tak layak.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فى أيام رئاستك أدركتنا هذه النعمة العظيمة نحن غير المستحقين.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ete pijini~ saron: n~te nenio] n~c~taurovoroc: abba Piswi nem abba Paule: nivwct/r e~terouwini.            </language>            <language id="English">               That is the coming of our fathers, the cross-bearers, Abba Pishoy and Abba Paul, the shining stars.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Itulah kedatangan bapa kami, para pemikul salib, Abba Pishoy dan Abba Paulus, bintang yang bersinar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أى مجىء أبوينا لابسى الصليب الينا أنبا بيشوى وأنبا بولا الكوكبين النيرين.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nai e~tauswpi nan: c~nau n~lum/n n~te pioujai: aue~rouwini n~nen'u,/: hiten noulum'anon e#y#u#.            </language>            <language id="English">               These who became unto us, two harbors of salvation, they have enlightened our souls, through their holy bodies.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mereka telah menjadi dua pelabuhan keselamatan bagi kami, mereka terangi jiwa kami, melalui tubuh-tubuh kudus mereka.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               هذان اللذان صارا لنا ميناء للخلاص وأضاءا أنفسنا بواسطة جسديهما الطاهرين.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere peniwt abba Piswi: piy~m/i pirwmi n~telioc: ,ere peniwt abba Paule: pimenrit n~te P,#c#.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to our father Abba Pishoy, the just and perfect man, hail to our father Abba Paul, the beloved of Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, ya bapa kami Abba Pishoy, orang benar dan sempurna. Salam bagimu, ya bapa kami Abba Paul, kekasih Kristus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لأبينا أنبا بيشوى الرجل البار الكامل السلام لأبينا أنبا بولا حبيب المسيح.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StPishoyAndStPaulOfTammah" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>