<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StSamuelTheConfessor:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Samuel the Confessor</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Samuel Sang Pengaku Iman</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للقديس أنبا صموئيل المعترف</language>            <language id="Coptic">&lt;ere peniwt...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Samuel the Confessor:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Samuel Sang Pengaku Iman:</language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere peniwt abba Camou/l: pinis] qen nia~gioc: v/e~tafi~ri n~hannis] n~are~t/: qen p~twou n~te Sih/t.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to Abba Samuel, the great among the saints, who has gained great virtues, in the mountain of Shiheet.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagi, Abba Samuel, agung di antara para kudus, yang peroleh banyak kebajikan, di gunung Shiheet.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لأبينا أنبا صموئيل العظيم فى القديسين الذى صنع فضائل عظيمة فى جبل شيهات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere peniwt abba Camou/l: v/e~tafvwq m~p~tomoc n~Lewn: ouoh aftajro n~nefc~n/ou: qen pinah] n~oryodoxoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to our father Abba Samuel, who tore the Tome of Leo, he confirmed his brothers, in the Orthodox faith.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagi bapa kami Abba Samuel, yang robek Tome Leo, ia kuatkan saudara-saudaranya, dalam iman Ortodoks.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لأبينا أنبا صموئيل الذى مزق طومس لاوون وثبت اخوته فى الايمان الأرثوذكسى.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Eybe vai af[oji n~cwf: n~je Makic Atria~noc pia~ceb/c: ouoh afi~ ha p~twou n~Kalamon: nem f~tou n~cwtp m~mona,oc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Wherefore the impious one, Macius Atrianus sought him, he sent him to the mountain of Qualamon, with four chosen monks.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Maka si fasik Macius Atrianus, mencarinya dengan niat jahat, dan kirim dia ke gunung Qualamon, bersama empat biarawan pilihan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأجل هذا طارده ماكيس اتريانوس المنافق فأتى الى جبل القلمون مع أربعة رهبان مختارين.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Abba Camou/l pio~mologit/c: n~yof aferhupomonin: e~jen niqici n~te pidiwgmoc: nem ]e,malwcia~ n~te nibarbaroc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Abba Samuel the confessor, was very patient, through the pains of the sufferings, and the captivity of Barbarians.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Abba Samuel sang pengaku iman, sangat sabar, tanggung derita dan sengsara, juga tawanan orang barbar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أنبا صموئيل المعترف قد صبر على أتعاب الاضطهاد وسبى البربر.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere peniwt abba Camou/l: v/e~tafi~ri n~hanm/ini nem hans~v/ri: ouoh aftal[o n~n/etswni: qen pimonact/rion nem y~baki n~nibarbaroc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to our father Abba Samuel, who performed wonders and signs, he healed the sick, in the monastery and the city of the Barbarians.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagi Bapa kami Abba Samuel, yang lakukan mujizat dan tanda-tanda, sembuhkan orang sakit, di biara dan kota orang Barbar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لأبينا أنبا صموئيل الذى صنع آيات وعجائب وشفى المرضى فى الدير ومدينة البربر.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere peniwt abba Camou/l: V/e~tafswpi n~iwt n~na/t: nem ouref]c~bw n~a~gayoc: n~nefs/ri m~mona,oc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to our father Abba Samuel, who became a merciful father, and a good teacher, for his children the monks.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagi bapa kami Abba Samuel, yang jadi bapa penuh belas kasih, dan guru yang baik, bagi anak-anaknya para biarawan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لأبينا أنبا صموئيل الذى صار أبا رحوما ومعلما صالحا لأبنائه الرهبان.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere peniwt abba Camou/l: v/e~tafernis] e~masw: qen t~ve nem hijen pikahi: qaten V] nem nirwmi.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to our father Abba Samuel, who became exceedingly great, in heaven and on earth, before God and men.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagi Bapa kami Abba Samuel, yang dimuliakan dengan sangat, di surga dan di bumi, di hadapan Allah dan manusia.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لأبينا أنبا صموئيل الذى صار عظيما جدا فى السماء وعلى الأرض عند الله والناس.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StSamuelTheConfessor" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>