<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StTaklaHaymanout:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Takla Haymanout</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Santo Takla Haymanout</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية أنبا تكلا هيمانوت</language>            <language id="Coptic">Pip~neuma m~Parakl/ton...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Takla Haymanout:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Takla Haymanout:            </language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pip~neuma m~parakl/ton: e~tafi~ e~pec/t e~bol qen t~ve: e~jen v~iwt pimakarioc: pia~gioc Yekla Humanoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               The Spirit of comfort, came down from heaven, upon the blessed father, Saint Takla Haymanout.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Roh Penghibur, turun dari surga, atas bapa yang diberkati, Santo Takla Haymanout.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الروح المعزى لما نزل من السماء على الطوباوى القديس تكلا هيمانوت.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Qen pie~hoou m~mah somt (g#): n~te pefjinmici etc~marwout: efws e~bol je ouai pe: Viwt nem Ps/ri  nem Pip~neuma e#y#u#.            </language>            <language id="English">               On the third day, of his blessed birth, he proclaimed "One is the Father, the Son and the Holy Spirit."            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Pada hari ketiga, dari kelahirannya yang diberkati, ia nyatakan, "Satu adalah Bapa, Putra, dan Roh Kudus."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فى اليوم الثالث لميلاده المبارك. صرخ قائلا واحد هو الآب والابن والروح القدس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ouoh icjen tefmeta~lou: afmoh e~bol qen Pip~neuma e#y#u#: ouoh nia~geloc n~te t~ve: nau erq/ibi e~h~r/i e~jwf.            </language>            <language id="English">               And from his childhood, he was filled with the Holy Spirit, and the angels of heaven, overshadowed him.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sejak masa kecilnya, ia dipenuhi Roh Kudus, dan para malaikat surga, menaunginya dengan sayap mereka.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ومنذ طفوليته امتلأ من الروح القدس وملائكة السماء كانت تظلل عليه.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Mi,a/l p~ar,wn n~na niv/oui: ef,/ nemaf n~c/ou niben: kata v~r~/] e~tafjoc: n~je Dauid qen pi'almoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Michael the head of the heavenly, was always with him, as was said by, David in the Psalms.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mikhael kepala surgawi, selalu bersamanya, seperti yang dikatakan oleh, Daud dalam Mazmur.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ميخائيل رئيس السمائيين كائن معه كل حين. كما قال داود فى المزمور.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               AP,#c# ouwnh nak e~bol: ouoh af] nak m~pie~rsisi: piconh nem pibwl e~bol: m~v~r/] n~nefa~poctoloc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Christ was revealed to you, and He gave you the authority, to loosen and to bind, like the Apostles.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kristus nyatakan diri padamu, berikan kuasa padamu, 'tuk ikat dan lepaskan, seperti para rasul dahulu.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               والمسيح ظهر لك وأعطاك سلطان الربط والحل كمثل رسله.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Akswpi n~oua~poctoloc: f~cwtp n~I/#c# P,#c#: ar,/e~reuc n~niE~yafs: v~iwt n~te nimona,oc.            </language>            <language id="English">               You became an apostle, chosen by Jesus Christ, the Patriarch of the Ethiopians, the father of the monks.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Engkau jadi seorang rasul, pilihan Yesus Kristus, Patriark bangsa Etiopia, bapa para biarawan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وصرت رسولا مختارا ليسوع المسيح رئيس كهنة للأحباش وأبا للرهبان.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               F~holj n~je pekran afswpi: qen nenrwn nem niremEyaus: je V] m~pia~gioc: Yekla Humanoc senh/t qaron.            </language>            <language id="English">               Your name became sweet, on our lips and the Ethiopians, O God of Saint Takla, the Ethiopian have pity upon us.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Namamu manis di bibir kami dan di tengah bangsa Etiopia, ya Allah dari St. Takla, kasihanilah kami umat Etiopia.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               صار اسمك حلو فى أفواهنا وأفواه الأحباش بقولنا يااله القديس تكلا هيمانوت تراءف علينا.            </language>         </text>                  <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StTaklaHaymanout" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>