<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StTheodoreShotep:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for Prince Theodore The Son of John of Shotep</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Pangeran Theodore Putra Yohanes dari Shotep</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية للشهيد الأمير تادرس بن يوحنا الشطبى</language>            <language id="Coptic">APeno#c# I/#c# P,#c#...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Theodore:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan Pangeran Theodore Putra Yohanes dari Shotep:</language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               APeno#c# I/#c# P,#c#: sanah~y/f qa niermwoui~: n~te ],/ra et qen Nai~n: aftounoc pecs/ri nac.            </language>            <language id="English">               Our Lord Jesus Christ, was compassionate to the tears, of the widow of Nain, He raised her son.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus, berbelas kasih atas air mata, janda dari Nain, Ia bangkitkan putranya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ربنا يسوع المسيح تحنن على دموع الأرملة ببلدة نايين وأقام لها ابنها.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Yeo~dwroc pic~tratilat/c: afsanah~y/f qa niermwoui~: n~te ],/ra et qen Eu,/toc: aftouje necs/ri nac.            </language>            <language id="English">               Theodore the general, was compassionate to the tears, of the widow of Eucaita, he saved her sons.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Teodorus sang jenderal,</div><div>berbelas kasih atas air mata, janda dari Eucaita, ia selamatkan putra-putranya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وثيؤدوروس الاسفهسلار تحنن على دموع الأرملة التي ببلدة أوخيطس وخلص لها أولادها.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Eybe vai tener,oreuin: nem pihumnodoc Dauid: je eke~hwmi e~jen ouhof: nem oubacilickoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Wherefore we sing, with David the Psalmist, saying "Tread upon serpents, and the power of scorpions."            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Maka kami bernyanyi, bersama Daud sang Pemazmur, berkata: "Injaklah ular, dan kuasa kalajengking."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فلهذا نمدح مع المرتل داود قائلين تدوس الثعبان وملك الحيات.            </language>         </text>         <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ounis] gar pe pektaio~: Yeo~dwroc pictratilat/c: e~re P,#c# rasi nemak: qen Ieroucal/m n~te t~ve.            </language>            <language id="English">               For great is your honor: O Theodore the general: for Christ rejoices in you: in the heavenly Jerusalem.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Besar hormat bagimu, hai Teodorus sang jenderal, sebab Kristus bersukacita atasmu, di Yerusalem surgawi.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               عظيمة هي كرامتك ثؤدوروس الاسفهسلار المسيح يفرح معك في أورشليم السمائية.            </language>         </text>         <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pimarturoc: ,ere piswij n~genneoc: ,ere piaylovoroc: Yeo~dwroc pictratilat/c.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you O martyr: Hail to the courageous hero: Hail to the struggle-mantled: Theodore the general.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, hai martir: Salam bagi pahlawan pemberani: Salam bagi yang berjubah perjuangan, Teodorus sang jenderal.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك ايها الشهيد. السلام للشجاع البطل. السلام للابس الجهاد. ثؤدوروس الاسفهسلار.            </language>         </text>         <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StTheodoreShotep" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>            <section antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Another Doxology for Prince Theodore The Son of John of Shotep</language><language id="Indonesian">Doksologi lain untuk Pangeran Theodore Putra Yohanes dari Shotep</language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية آخري للشهيد الأمير تادرس بن يوحنا الشطبى</language>            <language id="Coptic">APeno#c# I/#c# P,#c#...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Theodore:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan Pangeran Theodore Putra Yohanes dari Shotep:            </language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               APeno#c# I/#c# P,#c#: sanah~y/f qa niermwoui~: n~te ],/ra et qen Nai~n: aftounoc pecs/ri nac.            </language>            <language id="English">               Our Lord Jesus Christ: was compassionate to the tears: of the widow of Nain: and He raised a son for her.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus, berbelas kasih atas air mata, janda dari Nain, Ia bangkitkan putranya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ربنا يسوع المسيح تحنن على دموع الأرملة ببلدة نايين وأقام لها ابنها.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Genoc niben n~te nirwmi: etsop qen t~,wra n~Eu,/toc: aunau e~teknis] m~metjwri: w~ pia~gioc Yeo~dwroc.            </language>            <language id="English">               Every generation of men: who lived in the land of Euchaita: saw your great strength: O Saint Theodore.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Tiap generasi manusia, yang tinggal di tanah Eucaita, saksikan kekuatanmu yang besar, ya Santo Teodorus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               كل جنس البشر سكان اقليم أفخيتوس نظروا قوتك العظيمة أيها القديس ثيؤدوروس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Mv~nau e~takqok e~jen tek]pi: ouoh akqwteb m~pid~rakon: n~reftake kouji n~a~lou: aknohem n~nis/ri n~te ],/ra.            </language>            <language id="English">               At the time you girded your loins: and killed the dragon: the destroyer of young children: you rescued the widow’s sons.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Pada saat kau ikat pinggangmu: dan bunuh naga: penghancur anak kecil: kau selamatkan putra-putra janda itu.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لما نظروا سلاحك علي وسطك وقتلت التنين مُهلك الاطفال الصغار وانقذت أولاد الارملة.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Etakqolqel m~p~catanac: pinis] m~pid~rakon ethwou: hiten piqellibs n~te pinah]: nem t~c/fi n~te Pip~neuma eyouab.            </language>            <language id="English">               You slayed Satan: the great and evil dragon: through the breastplate of faith: and the sword of the Holy Spirit.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Engkau bunuh Setan, naga besar yang jahat itu, dengan perisai iman,</div><div>dan pedang Roh Kudus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لما ذبحت الشيطان التنين العظيم الشرير من قبل ثبات الايمان وسيف الروح القدس.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Yeo~dwroc pic~tratilat/c: piagwnict/c m~m/i: pirefmisi n~kalwc: pijwri n~ref[ro.            </language>            <language id="English">               Theodore the General: the righteous struggler: the good fighter: and the strong victor.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Teodorus sang Jenderal: pejuang yang benar: petarung yang baik: dan pemenang yang kuat.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ثيؤدوروس الاسفهسلار الأمير الحقيقي المقاتل حسناً القوي الغالب.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               V/etafjwk e~bol e~jwf: n~je p~caji m~pip~rov/tikon: je akhwmi e~jen ouhof: nem oubacilickoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               He who upon him was fulfilled: the prophetic word, saying: “You trampled upon a serpent: and a basilisk”.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Padamulah genap nubuat, yang berkata, “Kau injak ular, dan basilisk yang berbisa.”</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الذي كمل عليك القول النبوي لانك دست علي الثعبان ملك الحيات.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pimarturoc: ,ere piswij n~gennoc: ,ere piaylovoroc: Yeo~dwroc pic~tratilat/c.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you, O martyr: Hail the courageous hero: Hail the struggle-mantled: Theodore the General.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, hai martir: Salam bagi pahlawan pemberani: Salam bagi yang berjubah perjuangan, Teodorus sang jenderal.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيها الشهيد السلام للشجاع البطل السلام للمجاهد ثيؤدوروس الاسفهسلار.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StTheodoreShotep" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>