<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StVerena:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Verena</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk St. Verena</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية القديسة فيرينا</language>            <language id="Coptic">Wounia] qen oumeym/i...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Verena:            </language><language id="Indonesian">Untuk Peringatan St. Verena:</language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Wounia] qen oumeym/i: w~ y/eyouab Bir/na ]paryenoc: ]selet n~te Pi,~rictoc: Pipatselet m~m/i.            </language>            <language id="English">               Truly you are blessed, O the holy Verena the virgin, The bride of Christ, The pure bridegroom.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sungguh kau diberkati, ya Santa Verena yang suci, mempelai Kristus, mempelai yang murni.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               مباركة أنت بالحقيقة، القديسة فيرينا العذراء، عروس المسيح، العريس الطاهر.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je a~resws: mp~w~ou m~paikocmoc: nem ]met[acih/t m~pibioc: aremenre pitoubo.            </language>            <language id="English">               For you despised, The whole glory of this world, And the pride of this life, And you loved the purity.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sebab kau pandang rendah, segala kemuliaan dunia ini, dan keangkuhan hidup ini, kau mencintai kemurnian.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأنكِ تركتى، كل أمجاد هذا العالم، و كل مباهج هذه الحياة، و أحببتى الطهارة.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Acsosf m~p~catanac: nem nefdemwn euhwou: hiten tecnis] n~hupomon/: qen pitoubo n~te tecparyenia.            </language>            <language id="English">               She embarrassed Satan, And his evil demons, Through her great endurance, In the purity of her virginity.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia permalukan Setan, dan segala roh jahatnya, melalui ketekunan besarnya, dalam kemurnian keperawanannya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               قد فضحت الشيطان، و كل جنوده الأشرار، بثباتها العظيم، فى الطهارة و العفّة.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je ounis] pe qen  oumeym/i: pe picwtp n~toubo: n~te y/eyouab Bir/na: ]selet n~te Pi,~rictoc.            </language>            <language id="English">               For truly great , Is the chosen sanctity, Of Saint Verena, The bride of Christ.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sungguh agunglah, kekudusan yang terpilih, dari St. Verena, mempelai Kristus.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأنه هو عظيم، إختيار القداسة، للقديسة فيرينا، عروس المسيح.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Acjwk e~bol m~pecbioc: qen pecnis] n~yebio: acenkot nem n/eyouab: qen t~,wra n~n/etonq.            </language>            <language id="English">               She completed her life, In her great humility, She reposed with the saints, In the land of the living.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia akhiri hidupnya, dalam kerendahan hati yang besar, beristirahat bersama para kudus, di tanah kehidupan.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أكملت حياتها، بتواضعها العظيم، و إستراحت مع القديسين، فى أرض الأحياء.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere ne w~]a~lou m~paryenoc: w~ panagia m~p~colcel: w~]selet ectoub/out: ]a~gia m~m/i Bir/na.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail O the virgin maiden, The all-holy adornment, The pure bride, The true Saint Verena.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam, hai perawan yang suci, perhiasan mahakudus, mempelai yang murni, St. Verena yang sejati.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام للعذراء العفيفة، كليّة الزينة المقدسة، العروس الطاهرة، القديسة فيرينا الحقيقية.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere ne w~ ]a~gia: ,ere ne w~ y/ey~ouab: ,ere ne w~ ack/t/c: ]selet n~te v~n/b p~[oic.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you O saint, Hail to you O pure one, Hail to you O the ascetic one, The bride of the Master.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu ya santa, salam bagimu hai yang murni, salam bagimu petapa, mempelai Sang Guru.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك أيتها القديسة، السلام لك أيتها الطاهرة، السلام لك أيتها الناسكة، عروس السيد.            </language>         </text>                  <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StVerena" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>