<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="StVictor:Doxology">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for St. Victor</language><language id="Indonesian">Doksologi untuk St. Victor</language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية القديس أبا بقطر</language>            <language id="Coptic">Matamoi je k~se e~ywn...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Commemoration of St. Victor:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Peringatan St. Victor:            </language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Matamoi je k~se e~ywn: w~ Biktwr pamenrit n~s/ri: e~re pik/moc ,/ qen rwk: e~re niped/c qen nekjij.            </language>            <language id="English">               Teach me where do you flee, O Victor my beloved son, for the muzzle is on your mouth, and the chains are on your hands.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ajari aku, ke mana kau pergi, hai Victor, anakku terkasih, sebab mulutmu terbungkam, dan tanganmu dirantai.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               اعلمنى الى أين تذهب. يا بقطر ابنى الحبيب واللجام فى فمك والقيود فى يديك.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pejaf je ]se e~t~,wra: n~&lt;/mi e~ratf n~Armenioc: n~tamou e~jen v~ran m~paCwt/r: n~tef,a nanobi n/i e~bol.            </language>            <language id="English">               He said "I fled to the land, of Egypt to Armenius, that I may die in the name of my Savior, and that He may forgive me my sins."            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ia berkata, "Aku lari ke tanah Mesir kepada Armenius, agar aku dapat mati demi nama Juruselamatku, agar Ia mengampuni dosa-dosaku."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               قال أنا ذاهب الى اقليم مصر الى أرمانيوس لأموت على اسم مخلصى ليغفر لى خطاياى.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pia~bot menenca vai: w~ Biktwr pamenrit n~s~/ri: ]cebtwt e~i~ri n~tekselet: n~ta] n~hanm/s n~,~r/ma nak.            </language>            <language id="English">               "After that month, O Victor my beloved son, I am prepared to marry you off, and give you many riches."            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>“Setelah bulan ini berlalu, ya Victor anakku terkasih, aku telah siap untuk menikahimu, dan memberimu banyak kekayaan.”</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               من بعد هذا الشهر يابقطر ابنى الحبيب أنا مستعدة لعمل عرسك ولأعطيك أموالا كثيرة.            </language>         </text>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pac/ou a~nok taselet ,/: w~ Marya tamenri] m~mau: taselet te ]e~kkl/cia: papatselet pe pacwt/r.            </language>            <language id="English">               "My time and my wedding will come, O Martha my beloved mother, for the Church is my wedding, and my Savior is my bridegroom."            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>"Waktuku dan pernikahanku akan tiba, hai Marta ibuku tersayang, sebab Gereja adalah pernikahanku, dan Juruselamatku adalah mempelai priaku."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ان زمانى وعرسى صائر يا مرثا أمى الحبيبة. عروسى هى الكنيسة وعريسى هو مخلصى.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               &lt;ere nak w~ pimarturoc: n~te peno#c# I/#c# P,#c#: ,ere piswij n~genneoc: pia~gioc apa Biktwr.            </language>            <language id="English">               Hail to you O martyr, of our Lord Jesus Christ, hail to the courageous hero, the saint Abba Victor.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagimu, hai martir, dari Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus, salam bagi pahlawan yang gagah berani, St. Abba Victor.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               السلام لك يا شهيد ربنا يسوع المسيح السلام للشجاع القوى القديس أبا بقطر.            </language>         </text>               <insertdocument path="include/doxologies/conclusions/StVictor" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument>      </section>   </season></document>