<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="TheophanyParamoun">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for the Theophany Paramoun</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Paramoun Teofani</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية برمون الغطاس المجيد</language>            <language id="Coptic">Ounis] m~muct/rion...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Paramoun of the Theophany:            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Untuk Paramoun Teofani:</div></language>         </comment>                  <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Ounis] m~muct/rion: e~tafouonhf nak e~bol: w~ Iwann/c pip~rodromoc: p~s/ri n~Za,ariac.            </language>            <language id="English">               A great mystery, was revealed to you, O John the Forerunner, the Son of Zacharias.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sebuah misteri agung, diungkapkan padamu, hai Yohanes Pembaptis, Putra Zakharia.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               سر عظيم الذي أعلنه لك يا يوحنا السابق إبن زكريا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Rwf m~V] afermeyre: qarok w~ piref]wmc: je m~mon v/ettenywnt e~rok: qen nimici n~te nihio~mi.            </language>            <language id="English">               The mouth of God witnessed, to you O Baptizer, “No one is like you, among those born of women.”            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mulut Allah bersaksi padamu, hai Pembaptis yang kudus, "Tak seorang pun sepertimu di antara mereka yang lahir dari wanita."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فم الله شهد لك أيها المعمدان لأنه ليس مَن يشبهك في مواليد النساء.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nyok pe p~jwk n~nip~rov/t/c: e~taui~ qajwf m~Pencwt/r: akcob] n~nefmam~mosi: kata p~caji n~Ica/~ac.            </language>            <language id="English">               You are the culmination of the prophets, who came before our Savior, you prepared His paths, as said by Isaiah.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kaulah puncak para nabi, yang datang sebelum Juruselamat kita, kau persiapkan jalan-Nya, seperti yang dikatakan Yesaya.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               أنت هو كمال الأنبياء الذين جاءوا قبل مخلصنا لتعدّ طرقه كقول أشعياء.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Nak hiwis ekjw m~moc: je a~nok men ]wmc m~mwten: qen oumwou m~metanoia~: e~p~,w e~bol n~te ninobi.            </language>            <language id="English">               You preached saying, “I baptize you with water, with the waters of repentance, for the forgiveness of sin.”            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kau beritakan dan berkata, "Aku membaptis kau dengan air, air pertobatan, untuk pengampunan dosa."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               وكنت تكرز قائلا أما أنا فأعمدكم بماء التوبة لمغفرة الخطايا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pete ouon taf s~y/n 2: efe~] m~pete m~mon n~taf: ouoh pete ouon taf n~ouwik: marefi~ri on m~pair/].            </language>            <language id="English">               He who has two cloaks, let him give to him who has none, and he who has bread, let him do the same.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dia yang memiliki dua jubah, biarlah dia berikan pada dia yang tak punya, dan dia yang memiliki roti, biarlah dia lakukan hal yang sama.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               مَن له ثوبان فليعط من ليس له والذي عنده خبز فليصنع هكذا أيضاً.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Eybe vai tener,wreuin: enws e~bol nem pip~rov/t/c: je eue~nau n~je carx niben: e~picwt/r n~te V].            </language>            <language id="English">               Therefore we praise, proclaiming with the prophet, saying all flesh will see, the salvation of God.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Maka kami puji dan berseru bersama sang nabi, berkata seluruh manusia 'kan lihat keselamatan dari Allah."</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لهذا نمدح صارخين مع النبي قائلين أن كل جسد ينظر خلاص الله.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Marenouwst m~pencwt/r: pimairwmi n~a~gayoc: je n~yof afsenh/t qaron: afi~ ouoh afcw] m~mon.            </language>            <language id="English">               Let us worship our Savior, the Good Lover of Mankind, for he had compassion upon us, He came and saved us.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Marilah kita sembah Juruselamat kita, Sang Pengasih Manusia yang Baik, sebab Ia telah berbelas kasih pada kita, Ia datang dan selamatkan kita.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               فلنسجد لمخلصنا الصالح محب البشر لأنه تراءف علينا أتى وخلصنا.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tenhwc e~rof ten]wou naf: tenerhouo~ [ici m~mof: hwc agayoc ouoh m~mairwmi: nai nan kata peknis] n~nai.            </language>            <language id="English">               We praise and glorify Him, and exalt Him above all, as the Good One and Lover of Mankind, have mercy upon us according to Your great mercy.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami puji dan muliakan-Nya, serta tinggikan Dia di atas segalanya. Ya, Engkau Sang Baik dan Pengasih umat manusia, kasihanilah kami menurut belas kasihan-Mu yang besar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسبحه ونمجده ونزيده رفعة كصالح ومحب البشر إرحمنا كعظيم رحمتك.            </language>         </text>                     </section>   </season></document>