<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <season id="WeddingCana">      <section expanded="true" antiphonepitch="1">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Doxology for the Wedding at Cana of Galilee</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi untuk Pesta Pernikahan di Kana Galilea</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">ذوكصولوجية لعيد عرس قانا الجليل</language>            <language id="Coptic">Amwini a~nau a~ris~v/ri...</language>         </Title>               <comment>            <language id="English">               For the Feast of the Wedding at Cana of Galilee:            </language><language id="Indonesian">               Untuk Perayaan Pernikahan di Kana Galilea:</language>         </comment>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Amwini a~nau a~ris~v/ri: w~ nilaoc m~mai P,#c#: hijen paimuct/rion: e~tafouwnh nan m~voou.            </language>            <language id="English">               O people who love Christ, come see and be amazed, about this mystery, that was revealed to us today.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Hai umat yang mengasihi Kristus, mari datang dan kagum, atas misteri ini, yang dinyatakan kepada kita hari ini.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               تعالوا انظروا وتعجبوا أيها الشعوب محبوا المسيح على هذا السر الذى ظهر لنا اليوم.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Je a~Peno#c# I/#c# P,#c#: afywou] nem tefmau m~paryenoc: nem nenio] n~a~poctoloc: ouoh afouwnh nwou n~tefmeynou].            </language>            <language id="English">               For our Lord Jesus Christ, gathered with His virgin mother, and our fathers the apostles, He revealed to them His divinity.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Sebab Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus, berkumpul bersama Perawan Maria, ibu-Nya yang suci, dan para rasul kita yang kudus, Ia menyatakan keilahian-Nya kepada mereka.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               لأن ربنا يسوع المسيح اجتمع مع أمه العذراء وأبائنا الرسل واظهر لهم لاهوته.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Coou n~hudria~ m~mwou: eu/rp efcwtp afouw~teb m~mwou: e~bol hiten pefnis] n~wou: qen p~hop n~t~Kana n~te ]Galilea~.            </language>            <language id="English">               Six jars of water, changed into chosen wine, through His great glory, in the Wedding of Cana of Galilee.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Enam tempayan berisi air, diubah menjadi anggur pilihan, oleh kemuliaan-Nya yang agung, di Pesta Pernikahan Kana di Galilea.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               ستة أجران ماء حولها إلى خمر مختار بمجده العظيم فى عرس قانا الجليل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               V/ethemci hijen ni,eroubim: afouwnh n~tefmeynou]: afi~ri n~hanm/ini nem hanjom: ouoh afhemci nem nirwmi hwc nou].            </language>            <language id="English">               He who sits upon the cherubim, revealed His divinity, He performed signs and wonders, and sat with men as God.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dia yang bertakhta di atas kerubim, menyatakan keilahian-Nya, Ia melakukan tanda-tanda dan mukjizat, dan duduk bersama manusia sebagai Allah.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               الجالس على الشاروبيم أظهر لاهوته وصنع أيات وقوات وجلس مع البشر كإله.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Pio~mooucioc nem Viwt: v/etsop qajwou n~nie~wn t/rou: m~voou qen y~m/] m~pihop: n~t~Kana n~te ]Galilea~.            </language>            <language id="English">               The coessential of the Father, who is before all ages, today was in the Wedding, of Cana of Galilee.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dia yang sehakikat dengan Bapa, yang ada sebelum segala abad, hari ini hadir dalam perjamuan nikah, di Kana Galilea.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               المساوى فى الجوهر للآب الكائن قبل كل الدهور اليوم فى وسط عرس قانا الجليل.            </language>         </text>               <text>            <language id="Coptic">               Tenhwc e~rof ten]w~ou naf: tenerhouo~ [ici m~mof: hwc a~gayoc ouoh m~mairwmi: nai nan kata peknis] n~nai.            </language>            <language id="English">               We praise and glorify Him, and exalt Him above all, as the Good One and Lover of Mankind, have mercy upon us according to Your great mercy.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kami memuji dan memuliakan Dia, serta meninggikan-Nya di atas segala-galanya, sebagai Yang Baik dan Pengasih, kasihanilah kami menurut belas kasihan-Mu yang besar.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نسبحه ونمجده ونزيده علواً كصالح ومحب البشر إرحمنا كعظيم رحمتك.            </language>         </text>                     </section>   </season></document>