<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Gospels         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير الأناجيل         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            We have to be alert during our fasts and our prayers. We should not be negligent or postpone them from one time to another. We must persist in doing what we are required to do in meekness and humility as long as we are able, so that we would be considered obedient rather than sinful. The prayers and the fasting required were imposed by the disciples to remind us, at all times, of the pain and suffering of our Lord Who died on the cross to redeem us from the death of sin. He completed His sacrifice on Friday night as the evangelist said, “Now when evening had come” which means when Friday was over and Saturday eve had started. This indicates that the suffering of the Lord started on the eve of Friday and ended on the day of Friday and that is why the disciples imposed fasting and prayers on that day. We must honor that day with charity, mercy, and humility remembering what the Lord endured in terms of humiliation and suffering to save us.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لقد يجب علينا أن نكون متيقظين في أوقات أصوامنا. وساعات صلواتنا المفروضة علينا. وان نأخذ لنفوسنا الحذر من الإهمال والونية. أو التسويف من وقت لآخر. ونثابر على أداء ما فُرض علينا في كل وقت بحسب ما يستحقه بكل تواضع ومسكنة ما دام لنا الاستطاعة لنحسب من زمرة أهل الطاعة. ولا نعد من جملة أهل المعصية إذا أدينا فروض الصوم والصلوات في الأوقات التي عينها لنا الرسل لنتذكر كل حين الآلام التي قاساها الرب عنا حتى أنه أسلم نفسه ليُفدينا بتعليقه على خشبة الصليب وموته ليبطل موت الخطية وكان تمام هذا العمل العظيم عمل الفداء في مساء الجمعة. كما يقول البشير: "ولما كان المساء" أي انقضاء يوم الجمعة ودخول عشية السبت. ونستدل بذلك على أن الآلام التي قبلها الرب في جسده. كان أولها ليل الجمعة وآخرها نهارها. ولهذا فرض الرسل الأطهار على جميع المؤمنين صوم هذا اليوم وتوقيره بالبر والرحمة والخشوع متذكرين جميع ما أحتمله سيدنا من الهزأ والألم لأجل خلاصنا.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The disciples also implemented the fasting on Wednesday because this was the day when the Jews conspired against the Master. The disciples made both days equal in honor. They also implemented praying at all times, day and night, in praise and humility at known hours.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثم فرضوا علينا أيضا صوم يوم الأربعاء لأن فيه كانت مؤامرة اليهود على آلام السيد. وجعلوا هذين اليومين متساويين في الكرامة والوقار. ثم فرضوا أن تكون صلواتنا مستمرة على الدوام. ومر الليالي والأيام. بخشوع وابتهال. في ساعات مفهومة. وأوقات معلومة.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            At the third hour of the eve of Friday the Lord was arrested and tied. At midnight, He was presented to the Chief Priest of the Sanhedrin to be judged and beaten. On the first hour of Friday morning, He was presented before Pilate and his soldiers to be found guilty. On the third hour, He was sentenced to crucifixion and delivered to humiliation and beating. On the sixth hour, He was nailed to the cross. On the ninth hour, He gave up the spirit and was pierced. On the eleventh hour, He was buried in earth.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وذلك أن في الساعة الثالثة من ليلة الجمعة قبضوا على السيد وربطوه. وفى نصف الليل كان قائما قدام رئيس كهنة اليهود تحت الحكم والضرب. وفى باكر الجمعة كان واقفا قدام بيلاطس وجنده تحت الدينونة. وفى ثالث ساعة من النهار حكموا عليه بالصلب وأُسلم للهزأ والضرب والهوان. وفى السادسة سُمر على خشبة الصليب. وفى التاسعة أسلم الروح وطُعن. وفى الحادية عشرة دُفن في الأرض.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            It is therefore our duty as Christians to take the trouble to stand before the Lord in fear and trembling and pray those seven prayers leaving behind the worries of the world only remembering the pains of Christ which He willingly took at these hours for our sake, thanking Him for His blessing, praising Him for what He has done for us whether we are young or old, free men or slaves wherever we are, whether comfortable or exhausted, standing or sitting continuing without any disruption accomplishing what’s required of us day and night without any excuses.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وعلى ذلك قد وجب علينا نحن الذين قد صرنا تحت لواء الإيمان بالمسيح أن نتجثم العناء ونتحمل المشاق وننهض واقفين أمام وجه الرب بخشية وخوف. ونؤدي في هذه الساعات السبع صلوات مقبولة خالية من الطيش بهموم العالم. متذكرين فيها آلام السيد المسيح التي قبلها عن رضا في مثل هذه الأوقات لأجلنا. شاكرين نعمه. مادحين سعة فضله وكرمه. الصغار منا والكبار. العبيد والأحرار. في أي موضع. و على أي حال مستريحين كنا أم تعبين. قياماً كنا أم قعوداً. مشاة كنا أم وقوفاً. جلوساً كنا أم رقوداً. مواصلين بلا قنوط. قائمين بلا سقوط. مؤدين فرضنا في الليل والنهار. ضاربين صفحاً عن حجج الاعتذار.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The evangelist said, “Now when evening had come, there came a rich man from Arimathea, named Joseph, who himself had also become a disciple of Jesus,” which means that he was one of those learning the teachings of Christ in hope of entering the kingdom of God and that’s why Luke said, “a council member, a good and just man. He had not consented to their decision and deed,” because he was a member of the council which was made up of 70 members and which had sentenced Christ to death but Joseph of Arimathea had not agreed to this, “This man went to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus,” because he honored Him and knew Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال البشير: "ولما كان المساء جاء رجل غني من الرامة اسمه يوسف. وكان هو أيضا تلميذاً ليسوع" أي من جملة الذين يتعلمون تعاليم السيد لرجائهم في ملكوت الله. ولهذا قال لوقا: "وكان مشيراً ورجلاً صالحاً باراً هذا لم يكن موافقاً لرأيهم وعملهم" لأنه كان أحد أعضاء مجلس السبعين الذي حكم على الرب بالموت ولم يوافق أعضاءه يوسف الرامي هذا الذي "تقدم إلى بيلاطس وطلب جسد يسوع" لوجاهته عنده ولأنه كان مقبول الشفاعة لديه ولدالة المعرفة التي بينهما.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He came secretly fearing the Jews, as John and Mark said, “coming and taking courage, went in to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus.” He did this because he strived to reach the Kingdom of God so he risked his life for the love of God. The evidence of his love is his giving up his own tomb, which he had carved in stone in a garden, as John has testified he preferred the Body of the Lord over his own. He did not think about the tomb and how difficult it is to get another like it.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان مجيئه سراً خشية من اليهود كما شهد يوحنا وكما شهد مرقس أنه "تجاسر ودخل إلى بيلاطس وطلب جسد يسوع "والذي حمله على ذلك كثره الاجتهاد في نيل ملكوت الله. لأنه قد خاطر بنفسه إلى الموت محبة للرب. والدليل على كثرة محبته أنه كان قد نحت قبراً لنفسه في صخرة وتلك الصخرة في بستان كما شهد بذلك يوحنا فآثر جسد الرب على نفسه. ولم يفكر في كرامة الموضع وأنه قل أن يوجد مدفناً مثله.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            While he was doing this, Nicodemus came with the spices “Then they took the body of Jesus, and wrapped it in strips of linen with the spices, as the custom of the Jews is to bury. Now in the place where He was crucified there was a garden, and in the garden a new tomb in which no one had yet been laid.” The new grave held its own mystery because had he been buried in an old grave with others, people would have said that another had been risen, “So there they laid Jesus.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وفيما هو في مثل ذلك إذ حضر إليه نيقوديموس ومعه الحنوط "فأخذ جسد يسوع ولفاه بأكفان مع الأطياب كما لليهود عادة أن يكفنوا. وكان في الموضع الذي صُلب فيه بستان وفي البستان قبر جديد لم يوضع فيه أحد قط" وفى قوله "قبر جديد لم يوضع فيه أحد قط" سر عظيم وذلك حتى لا يقولوا لم يكن هو الذي قام إذا كانوا وضعوه في قبر قديم مع آخرين "فهناك وضعا يسوع" وجعلا على بابه حجراً عظيماً.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            The tomb was in a garden to remind us of Adam’s first sin, which was committed in the Garden of Eden where he deserved death along with his offspring. The second Adam was resurrected in a garden, granting the first Adam and all of his virtuous offspring eternal life.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والسر في وجود القبر في البستان ليفيدنا بذلك أن آدم الأول في بستان قد أخطأ الخطيئة التي كان منها الموت له ولجميع ذريته. وآدم الثاني في بستان أيضا كانت قيامته التي وهبت لآدم الأول الحيوة الأبدية ولجميع الأبرار من نسله.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “And Mary Magdalene was there, and the other Mary, sitting opposite the tomb” the other Mary refers to the Virgin Mary mother of our Lord. Glory be to Him Forever, Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله: "وكانت هناك مريم المجدلية ومريم الأخرى جالستين تجاه القبر" فيعني بمريم الأخرى عن السيدة البتول والدة المُخلص الذي له المجد دائما أبديا آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>       </Document>