<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Agia t~riac e~le/~con /~mac: pana~gia t~riac e~le/~con /~mac: ]t~riac e#y#u# nai nan.      </language>      <language id="English">         O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us. O Holy Trinity, have mercy on us.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Ya Tritunggal Maha Kudus, kasihanilah kami,<div>Ya Tritunggal Maha Kudus, kasihanilah kami,</div><div>Ya Tritunggal Maha Kudus, kasihanilah kami</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا، أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا، أيُّها الثالوثُ القُدُّوسُ ارحَمْنا،      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Po#c# ,a nennobi nan e~bol: Po#c# ,a nena~nomia nan e~bol: Po#c# ,a nenparaptwma nan e~bol.      </language>      <language id="English">         O Lord, forgive us our sins. O Lord, forgive us our iniquities. O Lord, forgive us our trespasses.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Ya Tuhan, ampunilah dosa kami. Ya Tuhan, ampunilah kesalahan kami. Ya Tuhan, ampunilah pelanggaran kami.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا خَطايانا، ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا آثامَنا، ياربُّ اغفِرْ لَنا زَلاّتِنا.      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Po#c# jemp~sini n~n/etswni n~te peklaoc: matal[wou eybe pekran e#y#u#: nenio] nem nenc~n/ou e~tauenkot Po#c# mam~ton n~nou'u,/.      </language>      <language id="English">         O Lord, visit the sick of Your people, heal them for the sake of Your holy name. Our fathers and brethren who have fallen asleep, O Lord, repose their souls.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Ya Tuhan, kunjungilah mereka yang sakit, sembuhkanlah mereka demi Nama-Mu yang kudus. Ya Tuhan, istirahatkanlah jiwa-jiwa para leluhur dan semua saudara kami yang telah tertidur.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         ياربُّ افْتَقدْ مَرْضَى شَعْبِكَ. اشْفِهمْ مِنْ أجْلِ اسْمِكَ القُدُّوسِ. آباؤُنا وإخْوَتُنا الَّذينَ رَقدوا ياربُّ نَيِّحْ نُفوسَهُم.      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Piaynobi Po#c# nai nan: piaynobi Po#c# a~ribo/~yin e~ron sep pen]ho e~rok.      </language>      <language id="English">         O You who are without sin, Lord, have mercy on us. O You who are without sin, Lord, help us and receive our supplications.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Ya Tuhan Engkau yang tanpa dosa, kasihanilah kami. Ya Tuhan Engkau yang tanpa dosa, topanglah kami dan terimalah doa kami.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         يا مَنْ هُوَ بِلا خَطيئَةٍ ياربُّ ارحَمْنا. يا الَّذي بِلا خَطيئَةٍ ياربُّ أَعِنّا واقْبَلْ طَلباتِنا إليكَ،      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Je vwk pe piw~ou nem pia~mahi nem pit~riac a~gioc: Kurie e~le/~con Kurie e~le/~con Kurie eulog/con: a~m/n.                  </language>      <language id="English">         For Yours is the glory, the dominion, and triple holiness. Lord have mercy. Lord have mercy. Lord bless us. Amen.      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Karena bagi-Mulah kemuliaan, hormat kuasa, dan Trisagion  kekudusan. Tuhan kasihanilah kami, Tuhan kasihanilah kami, Tuhan berkatilah kami. Amin.      </language>      <language id="Arabic">         لأنَّ لَكَ المجْدَ والعِزَّةَ والتَّقْديسَ المثلَّثَ، ياربُّ ارحَمْ، ياربُّ ارْحَمْ، ياربُّ بارِكْ. آمين.      </language>   </text></document>