<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <comment>      <language id="Coptic">         Eybe ]paryenoc      </language>      <language id="English">         For the Virgin      </language><language id="Indonesian">         Untuk Perawan</language>      <language id="Arabic">         لأجل العذراء      </language>   </comment>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Nyo y~mau m~piouwini: ettai/out m~macnou]: a~refai qa pilogoc: pia~,writoc.      </language>      <language id="English">         You are the Mother of Light, the honored Mother of God, you have carried, the uncircumscript Logos.       </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Kau Bunda Sang Terang, Theotokos yang terhormat, engkau t’lah membawa Logos Tanpa Batas.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         أنت يا أم النور المكرمة والدة الاله حملت الكلمة غير المحوى.      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Menenca y~remacf: a~reo~hi e~reoi m~paryenoc: qen hanhwc nem hanc~mou: ten[ici m~mo.      </language>      <language id="English">         After you gave birth to Him, you remained a virgin, with praises and blessings, we magnify you.      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Setelah kau melahirkan Dia, kau tetaplah perawan, dengan pujian dan berkat, kami agungkanmu.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         ومن بعد أن ولدته بقيت عذراء  نعظمك بتسابيح وبركات.      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Je n~yof qen pefouws: nem p~]ma] m~Pefiwt: nem Pip#n#a# e#y#u#: afi~ afcw] m~mon.      </language>      <language id="English">         For of His own will, and the pleasure of His Father, and the Holy Spirit, He came and saved us.      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Atas kehendak-Nya sendiri, dan kesenangan Bapa-Nya, dan Roh Kudus, Ia datang dan s’lamatkan kami.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         لأنه بارادته ومسرة أبيه والروح القدس أتى وخلصنا.      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Anon hwn tentwbh: eyrensasni eunai: hiten nep~recbia: n~totf m~pimairwmi.      </language>      <language id="English">         And we too, hope to win mercy, through your intercessions, with the Lover of Mankind.       </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dan kami pun berharap, memenangkan belas kasihan, melalui syafaatmu, bersama Pengasih Umat Manusia.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         ونحن أيضا نطلب أن نفوز برحمة بشفاعاتك لدى محب البشر.      </language>   </text>   <comment>      <language id="Coptic">         Eybe ]paryenoc on      </language>      <language id="English">         Also for the Virgin      </language><language id="Indonesian">Juga untuk Perawan</language>      <language id="Arabic">         وأيضا لأجل العذراء      </language>   </comment>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Apic~yoinoufi etcwtp: n~te teparyenia~: afsenaf e~p~swi: sa piy~ronoc m~V~iwt.      </language>      <language id="English">         The select incense, of your virginity, ascended to the throne, of the Father.      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dupa pilihan, dari keperawananmu, naik ke takhta Sang Bapa.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         البخور المختار الذى لبتوليتك صعد الى كرسى الآب.      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Ehote pic~yoinoufi: n~te ni,eroubim: nem niceravim: Maria ]paryenoc.      </language>      <language id="English">         Better than the incense, of the cherubim, and the seraphim, O Virgin Mary.       </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Lebih baik dari, dupa Kerubim dan Serafim, wahai Perawan Maria.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         أفضل من بخور الشاروبيم والسارافيم يامريم العذراء.      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         &lt;ere ]ve m~beri: y/e~ta Viwt yamioc: af,ac n~ouman~emton: m~Pefs/ri m~menrit.      </language>      <language id="English">         Hail to the new heaven, whom the Father has created, and made a place of rest, for His beloved Son.       </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagi surga kedua, yang Bapa t’lah ciptakan dan jadikan, s’bagai tempat perhentian, bagi Putra-Nya yang terkasih.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         السلام للسماء الجديدة التى صنعها الآب وجعلها موضع راحة لابنه الحبيب.      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         &lt;ere piy~ronoc: m~bacilikon: m~v/e~toufai m~mof: hijen ni,eroubim.      </language>      <language id="English">         Hail to the royal throne, of Him who is, carried by, the cherubim.      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagi takhta kerajaan, Dialah yang dibawa, oleh Kerubim.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         السلام للكرسى الملوكى الذى للمحمول على الشاروبيم.      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         &lt;ere ]p~roctat/c: n~te nen'u,/: n~yo gar a~l/ywc: pe p~sousou m~pengenoc.      </language>      <language id="English">         Hail to the advocate, of our souls, you are indeed, the pride of our race.      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Salam bagi, pembela jiwa kami, engkaulah sungguh, kebanggaan kami.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         السلام لشفيعة نفوسنا  أنت بالحقيقة فخر جنسنا.      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Arip~recbeuin e~jwn: w~ y/eymeh n~h~mot: nahren Penc#w#r#: Peno#c# I/#c# P,#c#.      </language>      <language id="English">         Intercede on our behalf, O full of grace, before our Savior, our Lord Jesus Christ.      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Bersyafaatlah demi kami, hai yang penuh rahmat, di hadapan Jurus’lamat kita, Tuhan kita Yesus Kristus.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         اشفعى فينا ياممتلئة نعمة لدى مخلصنا ربنا يسوع المسيح.      </language>   </text>   <text>      <language id="Coptic">         Hopwc n~teftajron: qen pinah] etcoutwn: ouoh n~teferh~mot nan: m~pi,w e~bol n~te nennobi.      </language>      <language id="English">         That He may confirm us, in the upright faith, and grant us the forgiveness, of our sins.      </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Agar Dia teguhkan kami, dalam iman yang lurus, dan berikan kami pengampunan, atas dosa kami.</div></language>      <language id="Arabic">         لكى يثبتنا فى الايمان المستقيم وينعم لنا بمغفرة خطايانا.      </language>   </text>   <insertdocument path="include/hiten/StMary" self-closing="true"> </insertdocument></document>