<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation – Luke 11:37-52         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير – لوقا 11: 37-52         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Then Jesus spoke to the multitudes and to His disciples, saying: "The scribes and the Pharisees sit in Moses' seat.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            حينئذ خاطب الجموع وتلاميذه. قائلاً "على كرسي موسى جلس الكتبة والفريسيون.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Therefore whatever they tell you to observe, that observe and do, but do not do according to their works; for they say, and do not do.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فكل ما قالوا لكم أن تحفظوه فإحفظوه وافعلوه ولكن حسب أعمالهم لا تعملوا لأنهم يقولون ولا يفعلون".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He clarified that they instructed according to Moses instruction and taught his teachings but did not follow them         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أوضح بذلك أنهم كانوا يأمرون بأوامر موسى ويعلمون تعاليمه. ولم يكونوا يعملون بذلك.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            That’s why He said, “Observe and do. He said,” but do not do according to their works” teaching us that the priest and teacher who teach Christ’s teachings and the teachings of His disciples must be obeyed in all that they teach even though they may not follow these teachings themselves because their teaching stems from Christ and His disciples.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولهذا قال: احفظوه وافعلوه قال: "ولكن حسب أعمالهم لا تعملوا. علمنا بهذا أن المعلم والكاهن اللذان يأمران بتعاليم المسيح وتعاليم تلاميذه يجب إطاعتهما في ما يعلمان به ولو كانا غير عاملين بما يقولان لأن ذلك التعليم صادر من السيد المسيح وتلاميذه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            All those who teach the teachings of Christ and His disciples sit on their chair.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكل من يعلم تعليم السيد المسيح وتلاميذه فهو على كرسيهم جالس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “For they bind heavy burdens, hard to bear, and lay them on men's shoulders; but they themselves will not move them with one of their fingers”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "فإنهم يحزمون أحمالاً ثقيلة عسرة الحمل ويضعونها على أكتاف الناس وهم لا يريدون أن يحركوها بأصبعهم"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            They urge people to follow the difficult and hefty Laws but they do not abide by them.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يعني أنهم يحثون الناس على العمل بأوامر الناموس الصعبة الثقيلة وهم لا يعملون شيئاً من ذلك.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Their purpose is to receive vainglory from people and benefit from it.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وإنما جل قصدهم الحصول على مجد الناس والفائدة منهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “But all their works they do to be seen by men. They make their phylacteries broad and enlarge the borders of their garments.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وكل أعمالهم يعملونها لكي تنظرهم الناس. فيعرضون عصائبهم ويعظمون أهداب ثيابهم".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He refers to God’s instruction to them on Moses tongue regarding the Law, “It shall be as a sign on your hand and as frontlets between your eyes,” and also “You shall bind them as a sign on your hand, and they shall be as frontlets between your eyes”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يعني أن الله لما أمر شعبه على فم موسى النبي بشأن الناموس قائلاً: "فيكون علامة على يدك وعصابة بين عينيك" وقال بشأن كلماته: "اربطها علامة على يدك ولتكن عصائب بين عينيك".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The scribes and the Pharisees took this image literally and wrote the ten commandments on gold plates and wore it around their necks to show people that they are stricter in keeping the Law.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أخذ الكتبة والفريسيون هذا المجاز حقيقة فكانوا يكتبون العشر وصايا على صفائح ذهبية ويعلقونها في أعناقهم حتى يظهروا أمام الناس أنهم أشد تمسكاً بحفظ الناموس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And enlarge the borders of their garments” These borders are blue threads God ordered the Israelites on Moses' tongue to put in the borders of their garments. God made it like wrapping a piece of string around one’s finger to help as a reminder.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "ويعظمون أهداب ثيابهم" وهذه الأهداب هي على هدب الذيل. وقد جعلها الله اشبه بمن يعقد على أصبعه خيطاً لتذكيره عن شيء.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said to Moses, “Again the Lord spoke to Moses, saying: "Speak to the children of Israel: Tell them to make tassels on the corners of their garments throughout their generations, and to put a blue thread in the tassels of the corners.  And you shall have the tassel, that you may look upon it and remember all the commandments of the Lord and do them."         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقال عن ذلك لنبيه موسى: "كلم بني إسرائيل وقل لهم أن يصنعوا لهم أهداباً في أذيال ثيابهم في أجيالهم ويجعلوا على هدب الذيل عصابة من إسمانجوتن فتكون لهم هدباً فترونها وتذكرون كل وصايا الرب وتعلمونها".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Pharisees therefore exaggerated in enlarging these borders seeking more honor from people.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولذلك قد غالى في تعظيم هذه الأهداب الفريسيون الذين كانوا يكبرون أهداب ثيابهم وقصدهم من ذلك اكتساب التبجيل من الناس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “They love the best places at feasts, the best seats in the synagogues.” The Lord forbade us from seeking glory from people and showed this as a sin.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقال: "ويحبون المتكأ الأول في الولائم والمجالس الأولى في المجامع" نهانا السيد المسيح عن طلب مجد الناس وأوضح أن ذلك خطيئة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Yet the chiefs and the teachers fought over it. God warned us against it and ordered us not to love human glory and if the devil tempts us with the love of vainglory we must hasten and blame ourselves for it and remove it from our souls and seek God’s help in getting rid of it.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولكون الرؤساء والمعلمين يتقاتلون بذلك جداً. فلهذا حذرنا منه وأمرنا ألا نحبه البتة. وإن أغرانا الشيطان بمحبة المجد الباطل نسرع ونلوم أنفسنا على ذلك وننزع تلك المحبة من بين جوانبنا ونتضرع إلى الله ليساعدنا على ابادتها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Because the chief or the teacher who embellishes himself with clothes and by presiding over assemblies is without a doubt insane. He thinks he gets human glory but on the contrary, he only earns humiliation in place of honor.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن المعلم والرئيس الذي يتجمل باللباس ويرأس المجالس هو مجنون لا محالة. لأنه يظن أنه بذلك يحصل له مجد الناس ولا يحصل له إلا الإهانة والمنقصة عوض المجد الذي يلتمسه منهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said “But you, do not be called 'Rabbi'; for One is your Teacher, the Christ, and you are all brethren.” Our teacher taught the disciples not to seek glory by being called Rabbi for this title is reserved for the true Rabbi, Jesus Christ.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وأما أنتم فلا تدعوا سيدي لأن معلمكم واحد المسيح وأنتم جميعاً إخوة" علمنا معلمنا بهذا ألا يتعظم التلاميذ لتسميتهم معلمين. فإن هذا الاسم ليس لهم بل للمعلم الحقيقي يسوع المسيح.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Since they taught His teachings to the faithful, they are called after Christ the Rabbi, yet they shouldn’t hold themselves higher than their own disciples.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ومن أجل أنهم يعلمون من تعليمه للمؤمنين ولذا يدعوهم (المؤمنون) باسم المسيح المعلم فلا يجب عليهم أن يتعظموا على تلاميذهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            They know that they are all brethren and disciples to one Rabbi, Jesus Christ. Calling them fathers and Rabbis is not for their sake but for the sake of their heavenly Father.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بل يعلمون أنهم وإياهم إخوة وتلاميذ لمعلم واحد هو المسيح. وتسميتهم آباء ومعلمين ليست لهم بل للآب السمائي .         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            They are only representatives, like a teacher who teaches his students while he and they are students to one teacher.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وإنما هم في ذلك خلفاء ونواب. كمعلم يعلم تلاميذه وهو وإياهم تلاميذ لمعلم واحد.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And whoever exalts himself will be humbled,” for the power of God abandons those who exalt themselves by pride and vainglory and they fall from their high places “and he who humbles himself will be exalted.” Those who are adorned with good qualities like humility and meekness are exalted to the highest position in Christian perfection and are aided in reaching the kingdom of God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "فمن يرفع نفسه يتضع" يعني أن الذي يرفع نفسه بالكبرياء والعظمة الكاذبة تتخلى عنه قوة الله فيسقط من شاهق "ومن يضع نفسه يرتفع" يعني أن الذي يتخلق بالأخلاق الحميدة التي منها التواضع والوداعة يرتفع إلى أعلاه ذروة الكمال المسيحي ويعان على الوصول إلى ملكوت الله.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “But woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites!” He told them woe to you because they use hypocrisy to achieve human glory. He called the Pharisees hypocrites to show us that it is such a bad disease that can blind the heart from seeing the true glory of Christ.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ويل لكم أيها الكتبة والفريسيون المراؤون" أعطاهم الويل لاستعمالهم الرياء واسطة للحصول على مجد الناس وتسميته الفريسيين بالمرائين فلكي يحقق لنا أن المراءاة هي مرض عضال قد أعمى قلوبهم عن نظر مجد المسيح المنير.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He clarifies that we should not use hypocrisy seeking vainglory which blinds the hearts from seeing the truth.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد أوضح لنا حتى لا نستعمل الرياء في طلب المجد الباطل الذي يعمي البصائر عن معرفة الحقائق.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “For you shut up the kingdom of heaven against men; for you neither go in yourselves, nor do you allow those who are entering to go in” for they did not believe in Him and blocked others from believing in Him by their teachings, especially those who wanted to believe.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            . قال: "لأنكم تغلقون ملكوت السموات قدام الناس فلا تدخلون أنتم ولا تدعون الداخلين يدخلون" لأنهم لم يؤمنوا به وكان شأنهم أن يصدوا بتعليمهم الناس عن الإيمان ولاسيما من كانوا يعلمون به أنه يريد الإيمان به.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Woe to you, … For you devour widows' houses, and for a pretense make long prayers. Therefore, you will receive greater condemnation.” For they were invited to pray in the houses of the those who suffered death at that time, so they prayed and hypocritically prolonged their prayers to get more money from the family of the dead in return for their prayers.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقول "ويل لكم ... لأنكم تأكلون بيوت الأرامل. ولعله تطيلون صلواتكم. لذلك تأخذون دينونة أعظم" وذلك أنهم كانوا يدعون إلى منازل الذين كانوا يموتون في ذلك الوقت فيصلون ويطلبون الصلاة رياء منهم لكي يعطيهم أهل الميت شيئاً كثيراً أجرة صلاتهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            What they earned in this way was taken from the share of the widows and the orphans. They will therefore be judged more severely.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فكان الذي يأخذونه في ذلك بريائهم هو من حق الأرامل والأيتام ولذا فإنهم يأخذون دينونة أعظم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! For you travel land and sea to win one proselyte, and when he is won, you make him twice as much a son of hell as yourselves.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله "تطوفون البحر والبر لتكسبوا دخيلاً واحداً. ومتى حصل تصنعونه ابنا لجهنم أكثر منكم مضاعفاً".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            For they would invite strangers, who are not descendants of Abraham, to become Jewish. And once he converts, they would teach him the Law and make him a source of collecting silver.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأنهم كانوا يدعون الغرباء عن نسل إبراهيم إلى التهود ومتى انقاد إلى رأيهم علموه الشريعة وجعلوه سبباً لجمع الفضة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He then subsequently loses faith in this Law, whose chiefs are so worldly, and turn into a son of hell; and so they become guilty on his behalf.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فيكفر ذاك بالشريعة التي رؤساؤها محبو الدنيا هكذا. وبهذا يصير ابناً لجهنم وهم به مدانون.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            St. Cyril said the Scribes and Chiefs used to travel everywhere and use every trick to stop every single one from worshipping idols.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقال القديس كيرلس أن الكتبة والأحبار كانوا يطوفون في كل موضع ويعملون كل حيلة لعلهم يقدرون أن يردوا واحداً من عبادة الأوثان.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            But once he does, they don’t teach him the Law or Moses’ teachings, but teach only their own teachings.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وإذا حصلوا عليه لا يعلمونه وصايا الناموس ولا ما أمر به موسى بل يعلمونه وصاياهم فقط ولذا قال:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He therefore said, “you make him twice as much a son of hell” putting further blame on their shoulders. He called them “blind guides” because the scribes and the Pharisees were the spiritual guides of the people.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "تصنعونه ابناً لجهنم" لذلك يصير ابناً لجهنم مثلهم فتضاعف دينونتهم وتسميته إياهم "بالقادة العميان “لأن الكتبة والفريسيين كانوا بمنزلة القادة للشعب باعتبار أنهم معلموهم الروحيون.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He called them blind because they were ignorant of the road to virtue and truth. He said, “'Whoever swears by the altar, it is nothing, etc.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ودعاهم بالعميان لجهلهم طريق الحق وعماهم عن سبيل الاستقامة. وقوله لهم "القائلون من حلف بالهيكل ... إلخ."         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            St Cyril also called them blind guides because they preferred the gold to the altar He said “For which is greater, the gold or the temple that sanctifies the gold?” For the offerings of the Jews were sanctified by the altar because the priest would sanctify the altar when it was built. The altar then sanctifies all offerings placed on it.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يقول أيضا القديس كيرلس أنه دعاهم بالقادة العميان لأنهم فضلوا الذهب على الهيكل قال: "أيهما أعظم القربان أم المذبح الذي يقدس القربان" لأن قربان اليهود كان يتقدس بالمذبح لأن الكاهن كان يقدس المذبح عند بنائه ويصير المذبح يقدس كل قربان يوضع عليه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As for the Christian offerings, the altar is neither greater than it, nor is it sanctified by the altar, but by the divinity of Christ who is unified with it, and is therefore sanctified because it turns into the true life-giving flesh and blood of God which are by all means more honorable than altars, angels and skies, because the creator is exalted above all of His creation.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأما قربان المسيحيين فليس المذبح أعظم منه ولا بالمذبح يتقدس بل بلاهوت المسيح الذي يتحد به فيتقدس ويصير حقاً جسد الرب ودمه المحبين اللذين هما أشرف بلا قياس من المذابح ومن الملائكة ومن السماء لأن الخالق أعلى من جميع خلقه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “For you pay tithe of mint and anise and cumin, etc. God has ordered the Jews to tithe their income to support the Levites and another tenth to give to the service of the temple and another tithe to support the poor every third year.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله "تعشرون النعنع والشبت والكمون ... إلخ." وذلك أن الله قد أمر اليهود أن يؤدوا عشر دخلهم نفقة على اللاويين وعشراً آخر منه لخدمة الهيكل وعشراً آخر على الفقراء كل سنة ثالثة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Jews disagreed on whether they should tithe mint, anise and cumin. Therefore the Pharisees and the scribes ruled that they should do so, but ignored the three virtues, justice, mercy and faith.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            واختلف اليهود في وجوب تأدية عشر هذه البقول أي النعنع والشبت والكمون فحكم الفريسيون والكتبة بوجوب تلك التأدية وغفلوا عن هذه الفضائل الثلاث أي الحق والرحمة والإيمان.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            For Justice upholds the truth, Mercy shows kindness, especially to those who are afflicted, and Faith is the faith in God, relying on Him. Jesus did not rebuke them for tithing mint, etc.,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويريد بالحق العد وبالرحمة الرفق وبالشفقة على الناس ولاسيما المصابون منهم. وبالإيمان الإيمان بالله والاتكال عليه ولم يلمهم السيد المسيح على حكمهم بتعشير النعنع ... إلخ.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            but for clinging to small matters and ignoring the Law and the great virtues which they must hold on to.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بل على تمسكهم بهذه الأشياء الدنيئة وتركهم أحكام الناموس والفضائل الجليلة التي كان يجب عليهم أن يتحلوا بها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Blind guides, who strain out a gnat and swallow a camel!” They used to strain water and wine before drinking to make sure there are free from gnats lest they become unclean but they ignore the salvation of their souls. God wants us not only to hold onto the easy commandments and ignore the more difficult ones, but to hold on to all. We must do this and not neglect that.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "يصفون عن البعوضة ويبلعون الجمل" أي أنكم تصفون الماء والخمر قبل الشرب لئلا يكون فيهما بعوضة التي تحسبونها نجسة وتتهاونون بخلاص نفسكم ويريد بذلك ألا نتمسك بالسهل من الوصايا ونترك صعبها والواجب أن نفعل هذه ولا نترك تلك.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “For you cleanse the outside of the cup and dish, but inside they are full of extortion and self-indulgence.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله "تنقون خارج الكأس والصحفة وهما من داخل مملوء اختطافا ودعارة".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He means the body by “outside the cup” and the soul by “inside the cup.” The Lord rebuked the scribes and the Pharisees because they pretended to be holy. But God knew they were full of sins on the inside.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أراد بخارج الكأس الجسد وبداخله النفس وقد وبخ السيد المسيح الكتبة والفريسين لأنهم يظهرون أمام الناس بمظهر الصديقين وداخلهم الذي يعلمه علام الغيوب هو ممتلئ من كل خطيئة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Those who keep their bodies from sin but their hearts are full of love for it and desire for it, will eventually fall in sin,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبما أن الذي يحفظ جسده من الخطيئة ولا يحفظ قلبه من محبتها والرغبة عليها فلابد له من فعلها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            in a like manner as a person with a skin disease. He can use a balm, but that won’t do him good unless he drinks a medicine. Only then does he benefit.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكما أن المصاب بالجرب إذا استعمل الدهان من الخارج لا ينفعه إن لم يشرب له من الداخل دواء لينقي من الأخلاط وحينئذ ينجح فيه الدواء ويحصل على الفائدة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Those who sin inside are bound to show it on the outside. That’s why God rebuked them saying: “Blind Pharisee, first cleanse the inside of the cup and dish, that the outside of them may be clean also.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كذلك الذي تعمل الخطيئة داخله لابد من أن تظهر خارجه ولذلك فإنه يبكتهم قائلاً "أيها الفريسي الأعمى نق أولاً داخل الكأس والصحفة لكي يكون خارجها أيضا نقياً".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            They pretended to be virtuous and holy before people, seeking their praise, when in reality they do the opposite.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولأنهم كانوا يتظاهرون للناس بالبر والقداسة ليمدحوهم. وهم في السر على عكس ذلك.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            God therefore likened them to, “whitewashed tombs which indeed appear beautiful outwardly, but inside are full of dead men's bones and all uncleanness.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فحسناً شبههم "بالقبور المبيضة تظهر من خارج جميلة وهي من داخل مملؤة عظام أموات وكل نجاسة".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He also said, “Even so you also outwardly appear righteous to men, but inside you are full of hypocrisy and lawlessness.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقال لهم: "هكذا أنتم أيضا من خارج تظهرون للناس أبراراً ولكنكم من داخل مشحونون رياء وإثماً"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said,” Woe to you, scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! Because you build the tombs of the prophets and adorn the monuments of the righteous, etc.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقال: "ويل لكم ... لأنكم تبنون قبور للأنبياء وتزينون مدافن الصديقين ... إلخ."         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            God wanted to show them that they admit they are the offspring of prophet killers. The Lord did not rebuke them for building tombs for prophets,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أراد بهذا أنهم يقرون على أنفسهم بأنهم أولاد قتلة الأنبياء. هذا وأن السيد المسيح لم يلمهم لبنائهم قبور الأنبياء.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            for this is a praiseworthy undertaking, but because they helped their fathers in killing the prophets through their evil intentions of crucifying Christ.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن هذا العمل ممدوح لكن لأنهم شاركوا آبائهم في قتل الأنبياء بما كانوا ينوونه من الشر الذي ارتكبه آبائهم بصلبهم السيد المسيح         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Once they were successful and satisfied their desire, they completed their father’s works and their evil became as complete as their fathers’.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            حتى إذا ظفروا بذلك وتمموه كشهوتهم فيكملون ما هو ناقص منهم عن آبائهم وحينئذ يصير شرهم كاملاً كآبائهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As He says, “Fill up, then, the measure of your fathers' guilt.” He likened them to serpents because they attack those who do not threaten them. Because the serpent is a reptile which glides on earth, God called those who think about nothing but their earthly desires serpents. John the Baptist also called them, “Brood of vipers,”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويتضح ذلك من قوله "فاملأوا أنتم مكيال آبائكم". وشبههم بالحيات لأنها تقتل من لا يسيء إليها ولأن الحية تزحف على الأرض دعا الله الذي لا فكر له إلا في الشهوات الأرضية حية. وهكذا دعاهم يوحنا المعمدان "أولاد الأفاعي".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            meaning the devils which are bad vipers tempt them with the love of carnal pleasures and they become their children and inherit hell like them. He clarifies, “How can you escape the condemnation of hell?”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يعني أن الشياطين أي الأفاعي الرديئة هم الذين يستميلونهم إلى حب الشهوات الأرضية لكي يصيروا لهم بنبأ ويرثون جهنم مثلهم وقد أوضح بقوله "كيف تهربون من دينونة جهنم".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Because those who accept thoughts of loving sin from the devils can’t escape the condemnation of hell.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            إن الذي يقبل من الشياطين أفكار محبة الخطية، لا فرار له من عقوبة جهنم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “Therefore, indeed, I send you prophets, wise men, and scribes: some of them you will kill and crucify, and some of them you will scourge in your synagogues and persecute from city to city,”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لذلك ها أنا أرسل إليكم أنبياء وحكماء وكتبة فمنهم تقتلون وتصلبون ومنهم تجلدون في مجامعكم وتطردون من مدينة إلى مدينة".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            For when the disciples received the Holy Spirit they obtained the gift of prophecy like Agabus who prophesied about Paul,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وذلك لأن التلاميذ لما حل عليهم الروح القدس نالوا روح النبوة كأغابوس الذي تنبأ عن بولس         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            And the gift of wisdom described by St. Paul as, “for to one is given the word of wisdom through the Spirit.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والحكمة وقال عنها بولس الرسول: "فإنه لواحد يعطي بالروح كلام حكمة".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The gift of knowledge described by St. Paul as “to another the word of knowledge through the same Spirit.” The apostle refers to those who accepted the grace, interpreted the divine books and taught it to people.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والعلم وقال عنه بولس الرسول: "ولآخر كلام علم" ويعني الرسول بالذين نالوا موهبة العلم عن الذين قبلوا النعمة وفسروا كتب الله وعلموها للناس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            They did not accept the apostles who were present during this age and did not listen to their evangelical message.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والرسل هم الذين كانوا في ذلك الزمان: الذين لما أتوا إليهم لم يقبلوهم ولا سمعوا منهم كلام بشارتهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Rather they prosecuted and killed them. They did not respond to their wonders or miracles.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأنزلوا بهم كل عقاب وكل موت. ولم يذعنوا لآياتهم ولا لمعجزاتهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            This is why He said, “that on you may come all the righteous blood shed on the earth, from the blood of righteous Abel to the blood of Zechariah, son of Berechiah, whom you murdered between the temple and the altar.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولأجل هذا قال لهم: لكي يأتي عليكم كل دم زكى سفك على الأرض من دم هابيل الصديق إلى دم زكريا بن براشيا الذي قتلتموه بين الهيكل والمذبح".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Some may ask why Jesus held the Jews who were living during the time of His crucifixion responsible for righteous Abel’s who preceded Christ over five thousand years.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولسائل أن يسأل. ما السبب في قول السيد لأولئك اليهود الذين كانوا في زمان صلبه أنه يوجب عليهم دم هابيل الصديق بينما أن هابيل قبل السيد المسيح بخمسة آلاف سنة وكسور.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            We know that the sins of the fathers are not visited upon the children from His saying: “The son shall not bear the guilt of the father, nor the father bear the guilt of the son. The righteousness of the righteous shall be upon himself, and the wickedness of the wicked shall be upon himself.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبينما نعلم أن الابن لا يؤخذ بإثم أبيه من قوله تعالى "الابن لا يحمل من إثم الأب. بر البار عليه يكون وشر الشرير عليه يكون".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The answer is God had inflicted some punishment on the Israelites for their sins when they committed them,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والجواب نقول أن الله تعالى قد عاقب الإسرائيليين على آثامهم في وقت ارتكابهم بعض العقاب.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            but left some of the punishment to be inflicted on their offspring who followed them in their sinful footsteps according to His saying: “visiting the iniquity of the fathers on the children to the third and fourth generations of those who hate Me.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأبقى إيقاع بعضه على أولادهم التابعين خطواتهم الأثيمة وفقاً لقوله تعالى "أفتقد ذنوب الآباء في الأبناء في الجيل الثالث والرابع من مبغضي".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Since the Jews wished and desired to take hold of the Lord to kill Him and because of the Lord’s foreknowledge of the death they will inflict upon Him and upon His guiltless disciples who will come to visit them after His resurrection, He told them this based upon their intentions.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبما أن اليهود كانوا يشتهون ويتمنون الظفر بالسيد ليقتلوه. ولأجل ما قد سبق في علمه بأنهم سيقتلونه ويقتلون التلاميذ الذين يأتون إليهم بعد قيامته بلا ذنب يأتونه معهم قال لهم هذا القول حسب نياتهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Scholars have researched the identity of Zechariah whom the Lord mentioned. Some said that he was one of the twelve minor prophets but other scholars have refuted this opinion on the pretext of lack of evidence.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبحث العلماء عمن هو زكريا الذي ذكره السيد. فقال بعضهم أنه أحد الإثني عشر نبياً الصغار. فرد عليهم غيرهم وقالوا أن هذا القول لا دليل عليه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Zechariah the prophet came from the land of the Chaldeans to Jerusalem at a young age and lived long. He died and was buried with great honor in the Holy House, in the tombs of the priests.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وذلك أن زكريا النبي جاء من أرض الكلدانيين إلى أورشليم وهو صغير وعاش زماناً طويلاً ومات ودفن بالبيت المقدس في قبور الكهنة بمجد عظيم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The one mentioned by the Lord is the father of John the Baptist. When Herod the First ordered the massacre of the innocent of all children of two years and younger, one of the soldiers informed him that Zacharias had a son named John, about two years of age,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأما الذي ذكره السيد فهو أبو يوحنا المعمدان. وذلك أن هيرودس الأول لما أمر بقتل الأطفال من ابن سنتين فما دون قال له واحد من الشرط أن لزكريا ابناً اسمه يوحنا تقدير سنة سنتان.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            and some of the Jews think he is the Christ. When Herod heard this, he sent messengers to Zechariah to bring the child. When Elizabeth heard this, she could not take it lightly.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وجماعة من اليهود يظنون أنه المسيح. فلما سمع هيرودس ذلك أرسل رسلاً إلى زكريا لإحضار الصبي. ولما بلغ اليصابات الخبر اشتد عليها الأمر.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            so she thought and said: “I have no place to take refuge and seek sanctuary except the temple where Zechariah received God’s promise. God will guide me to what is good.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وفكرت فكرة صالحة وقالت: ليس لي موضع ألتجئ إليه وأعتصم به أحسن من الهيكل الذي تسلمه زكريا منه بالموعد وفيه يرشدني الله إلى الخير.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            She hurried and took the child to the temple and claimed sanctuary. When Zechariah came with the messengers to his house he found no one.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأسرعت وأتت بالصبي إلى الهيكل واعتصمت به ، وأما زكريا فأتى مع الرسل إلى بيته فلم يجد أحداً فيه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He showed the messengers kindness and told them, here is the house. As you can see it is empty. The child’s mother must have felt what is about to happen, and ran away with the child.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فأكرم الرسل وقال لهم: هوذا البيت كما ترونه خالياً ولا شك أن أم الصبي شعرت بالقضية فهربت به من هنا.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            I beseech you to let me go to the temple to pray to God before I die at the Hands of Herod, who will sure kill me when he sees that I don’t have the boy.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأطلب منكم أن تدعوني أمضي إلى الهيكل لأصلي إلى الله قبل موتي لأن هيرودس لما يراني وليس الصبي معي يقتلني،         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When they agreed to his request, he went to the temple where he found the boy and his mother. He took the boy from his mother and dressed him in priestly clothes and took him to the altar where he ordained him a priest, so that if one of them is killed, the priesthood remains with the other.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما أجابوه إلى طلبه وتوجه إلى الهيكل ووجد الصبي وأمه به. فأخذ الصبي من أمه وألبسه ثياب الكهنوت وصعد إلى المذبح وسامه كاهناً حتى إذا قتل أحدهما بقى الكهنوت في الآخر،         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He then delivered him to his mother and asked her to run away with him. So she obeyed and took him to the desert of Ziphana.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وسلمه إلى أمه واشار عليها بأن تهرب به فأطاعته ومضت إلى برية الزيفانا.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When the priests heard that Zechariah has ordained his son a priest without their knowledge, they became very angry especially since they were jealous of him because of the vision that he saw in the temple, which gave him a lot of consideration and respect amidst the people.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما اتصل الخبر بكهنة اليهود أن زكريا قد سام ابنه كاهناً بغير علمهم اشتد حقدهم عليه مما كانوا يكتمونه في صدورهم من الحسد لأجل الرؤيا التي رآها في الهيكل التي صار له بها الاعتبار الفائق عند الشعب.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            They had evil plans for him but Zechariah took sanctuary in the temple and did not leave. Since Herod’s messengers could not go into the temple to get Zechariah. They informed Herod of this. Herod brought the chief priests and the elders and asked them about Zechariah. They advised him that Zechariah can be killed where he is so he killed him between the temple and the altar.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكانوا ينوون له الشر. أما زكريا فاعتصم بالمذبح ولم يخرج. ولما كان رسل هيرودس لا يمكنهم دخول الهيكل وإخراج زكريا وأعلموا هيرودس بذلك فجمع رؤساء الكهنة وشيوخ الشعب واستفتاهم في أمر زكريا فأفتوا بقتله في مكانه فقتل بين الهيكل والمذبح.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            His blood boiled and screamed for fifty-eight years until Jerusalem was conquered by Titus Vespasianus Caesar.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولم يزل دمه يغلي ويصرخ ثمان وخمسين سنة حتى فتح أورشليم تيطس بن واسباسيانوس قيصر.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When Titus found the blood boiling and screaming and inquired about the cause, he was told about what happened to Zechariah. He then ordered a large number of priests killed at the same spot where the blood was boiling and screaming. Immediately the blood stopped to boil and to scream.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما وجد الدم يغلي ويصرخ فحص عن الأمر فأعلموه بما جرى لزكريا. فأمر بذبح عدد عظيم من الكهنة في مكان الدم الصارخ. فبطل حالاً الغليان والصراخ.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “all these things will come upon this generation,” and it happened as He said because many of those who heard and saw Him endured great suffering during the days of Titus Vespasianus.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله "إن هذا كله يأتي على هذا الجيل" وقد تم قوله هذا لأن كثيرين من ناظريه وسامعي قوله قد نالتهم شدائد صعبة أيام تيطس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord pitied them saying: "O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, the one who kills the prophets and stones those who are sent to her! How often I wanted to gather your children together, as a hen gathers her chicks under her wings, but you were not willing!”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولذلك رثى لهم بقوله "يا أورشليم يا أورشليم يا قاتلة الأنبياء وراجمة المرسلين إليها كم مرة أردت أن أجمع أولادك كما تجمع الدجاجة فراخها تحت جناحيها ولم تريدوا".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When blaming them, The Lord addressed the city to show leniency. He repeated the word Jerusalem to show sorrow and mercy on the people living there.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وتوجيهه الخطاب هنا إلى المدينة ليكون لين في التوبيخ وتكرار لفظة أورشليم على سبيل الترثي والرحمة على الشعب الساكن فيها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He meant the prophets and the messengers whom He sent to them but they killed them and cast them out.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويعني بالأنبياء والمرسلين أنه كان يعظهم بالأنبياء فكانوا يقتلون منهم. وسيعظهم برسله فيقتلون منهم ويطردون.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He used the metaphor of the hen because it is very warm towards its chicks. He said, “but you were not willing” because man was created free to do good and abhor evil and vice versa.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وذكره للدجاجة لأنها شديدة الحنو على أولادها. وقوله "ولم تريدوا" يعني أن الإنسان خلق حراً في عمل الخير وترك الشر وبالعكس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Your house is left to you desolate.” The house is the temple which is desolate because it lacked the support of the Lord. It was destroyed at the hands the soldiers of Titus Vespasianus.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله "هوذا بيتكم يترك لكم خراباً" يعني بالبيت الهيكل وبخرابه خلوه من معونته وهدمه بيد عساكر تيطس بن واسباسيانوس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Even though He said “you shall see Me no more,” they saw Him again. It means that they won’t see Him rebuking them again, except in His second coming, where they will bless Him saying, Blessed is He who comes in the name of the Lord!         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله "إنكم لا ترونني من الآن" مع أنهم رأوه فيعني أنهم لا يرونه يوبخهم بعد ذلك إلا في مجيئه الثاني وبالرغم منهم يباركونه قائلين مبارك الآتي باسم الرب.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Glory Be To God Forever. Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي له المجد دائماً.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>       </Document>