<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" Consecration="true">   <Title>      <Language id="English">The Rite of Consecration of Women (First Rank)</Language>      <Language id="Arabic">طقس تكريس النساء (الرتبة الأولى)</Language>   </Title>      <Comment>      <Language id="English">         After Matins’ doxologies, and before the Raising of Incense      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         بعد ذكصولوجيات باكر وقبل رفع البخور      </Language>   </Comment>            <Comment>      <Language id="English">         The female candidate for consecration recites the following pledge, then stands before the sanctuary, bowing her head humbly.      </Language>      <Language id="Arabic">         تقرأ المُتقدمة للتكريس التعهد الآتي، وتقف أمام الهيكل مطأطئة الرأس في انسحاق.      </Language>   </Comment>    <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">Pledge of the Consecrated Woman</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">تعهد المكرسة</Language>      </Title>       <Role id="Sister">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               I (…), the weak, in requesting to be accepted in the way of consecration in the Coptic Orthodox Church, pledge before the altar of God, and before our father, His Holiness, Pope (...), and before our father, His Grace (His Eminence), the bishop (metropolitan), Abba (…),            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أنا الضعيفة (...) إذ ألتمس قبولي في طريق التكريس بالكنيسة القبطية الأرثوذكسية، أتعهد أمام مذبح الله وأمام أبينا قداسة البابا (...) وأمام نيافة أبينا الأسقف (المطران) الأنبا (...)،            </Language>         </Text>                        <Text>            <Language id="English">               to commit: to [abiding by] the commandments of the Holy Bible and the doctrine of the Coptic Orthodox [Church], and to partake of the mysteries of Confession and Communion, and to strive in spiritual life, and to be faithful in the responsibility [given to me], and to deal with others in a good manner, and to submit to the hierarchy of the Church represented by His Holiness, the Pope and Patriarch, and His Grace, the Bishop (His Eminence, the Metropolitan).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أن ألتزم بوصايا الكتاب المقدس، والعقيدة القبطية الأرثوذكسية، وممارسة الاعتراف والتناول، وجهادات الحياة الروحية، والأمانة في المسئولية، وحُسن التعامل مع الغير، والخضوع للرئاسة الكنسيَّة، مُمثلة في قداسة البابا البطريرك ونيافة أبينا الأسقف (المطران).            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               For as I receive the blessing of putting-on the attire of consecration on this day, (date) AD, (date) AM, I pledge that doing so at all times is a condition to my commitment to the way of consecration till the end, by the grace of God.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وإنِّي إذ أنال بركة ارتداء زي مكرسة  اليوم الموافق (...) م، (...) ش، أتعهد أن يكون استمراري في ارتدائه مشروطاً بالتزامي بطريق التكريس إلى النهاية بنعمة الله.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>   </Section>   <Role id="Sister">      <Comment>         <Language id="English">            She then bows her head and recites the following:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تحني رأسها وتقول ما يلي:         </Language>      </Comment>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            I ask you to pray for me. Behold, a prostration. Absolve me, and bless me, my master, Your Holiness, the Pope, and Your Grace, the Bishop (Your Eminence, the Metropolitan).         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أرجو أن تصلوا من أجلي. ها ميطانية. حاللني وباركني يا سيدي قداسة البابا ونيافة الأسقف (المطران).         </Language>      </Text>   </Role>   <Role id="Bishop">      <InsertDocument path="include/LordsPrayer"/>   </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/ThanksgivingPrayer"/>   <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The First Litanies</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">الطلبات الأولى</Language>      </Title>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O Lord, who is wise in His counsel and created mankind in His image and likeness—He created males and females in His image and likeness, and granted them blessing; we ask You, O Lord, to hear us and have mercy on us.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أيها الرب الحكيم في مشورته، الذي خلق الإنسان على صورته ومثاله، ذكراً وأنثى خلقهما على صورته ومثاله، ومنحهما البركة، نسألك يا رب: اسمعنا وارحمنا.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O Lord, who granted [the gift of] prophecy to Miriam, the sister of Moses and Aaron, and to Deborah, Huldah, and Anna, the daughter of Phanuel, and allowed Philip the evangelist to have virgin daughters who prophesy; we ask You, O Lord, to hear us and have mercy on us            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يا رب يا مَنْ منحت النبوة لمريم أخت موسى وهارون، ولدبورة وخلدة وحنة ابنة فنوئيل، وسمحت أن يكون لفيلبس المبشِّر بنات عذارى يتنبأن، نسألك يا رب: اسمعنا وارحمنا.            </Language>         </Text>       </Role>       <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>       <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O You who poured out Your Holy Spirit on men and women alike, and gave them the gifts of Spirit; we ask You, O Lord, to hear us and have mercy on us.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يا مَنْ أفضت روحك القدوس على الرجال والنساء معاً، وأعطيتهم مواهب الروح، نسألك يا رب: اسمعنا وارحمنا.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>   </Section>   <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">Prayers for Consecration</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">صلوات التكريس</Language>      </Title>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O Lord, who decided to send Mary Magdalene to inform Your holy Apostles of Your glorious Resurrection, and allowed Phoebe to become a deaconess in Your holy Church.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يا رب يا مَنْ سمحت أن تُرسل مريم المجدلية لتُخبر رسلك القديسين بقيامتك المجيدة، ويا مَنْ سمحت أن تكون فيبي شمَّاسة في كنيستك المقدسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               As You have allowed it in the past, O Lord, allow this woman (these women) who is (are) standing before You, today, to participate in Your service, and make us worthy to fulfill this service without falling into condemnation before You, and pour out the grace of Your Holy Spirit upon her (them).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               كما سمحت يا رب في القديم، اسمح أمامك اليوم، أن تشترك هذه (هؤلاء) في خدمتك، واجعلنا مستحقين ان نكمل هذه الخدمة بغير وقوع في دينونة أمامك، وأفض نعمة روحك القدوس عليها (عليهن).            </Language>         </Text>         <InsertDocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusion"/>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy3"/>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O Lord, God, who does not reject the women who present themselves to serve with good intention as it is according to the divine will, but You have decided to call them Your servants.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أيها الرب الإله الذي لا ترفض النساء اللاتي يقدمن أنفسهن باتفاق المشيئة الإلهية ليخدمن بنية صالحة، بل سمحت ان تدعوهن خادمات لك،            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Grant Your maidservant(s) the grace of the Holy Spirit, she (those) who desires to present herself (themselves) to You and fulfill Your service, as You have granted the grace of this service to Your servant Phoebe, whom You have called to do works in Your Church—she became a helper to Your servant Paul the Apostle.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أعطي نعمة الروح القدس (لإمائك هؤلاء/أمتك هذه) (اللاتي/التي) يرغبن في أن يقدمن أنفسهن لك، ليتممن خدمتك، كما منحت نعمة هذه الخدمة لعبدتك فيبي التي دعوتها للعمل في كنيستك، فكانت معينة لعبدك بولس الرسول.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Pour out Your holy gifts on her (them).            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أفض عليهن مواهبك المقدسة.            </Language>         </Text>         <InsertDocument path="include/SilentPriestConclusion"/>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy3"/>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O eternal Lord, the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, look now to Your maidservant(s) who is (are) called for the service of consecration. Give her the grace of the Holy Spirit and purify her from every defilement of body and spirit that she may be worthy to fulfill the work that You have pledged to her.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أيها الرب الأزلي أبو ربنا يسوع المسيح، أُنظر الآن إلى (إمائك هؤلاء/أمتك هذه) (اللاتي/التي) دعين لخدمة التكريس. أعطهن نعمة الروح القدس، وطهرهن من كل دنس الجسد والروح، لكيما باستحقاق يتممن العمل الذي تعهد به إليهن.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Glory and worship are due to You with Your only-begotten Son, and the Holy Spirit forever and ever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لك المجد والسجود مع ابنك الوحيد والروح القدس إلى أبد الأبدين. آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy3"/>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O Lord, God, the Holy and Almighty, who sanctified women by the birth of Your only Son from the Virgin St. Mary; we ask You, O Lord, to hear us and have mercy on us.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أيها الرب الإله القدوس القادر على كل شيء، يا مَنْ قدَّست النساء بميلاد ابنك الوحيد من العذراء القديسة مريم حسب الجسد.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O You who granted the grace of the Holy Spirit, not only to men but to women also. Now, O Lord, look to Your maidservant(s); call her to service and pour out the gift of Your Holy Spirit upon her. Keep her in the orthodox faith to fulfill Your service continually, without blame, according to Your will. For Yours is the glory, the honor, and the worship, O Father, Son, and the Holy Spirit.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يا مَنْ أعطيت نعمة الروح القدس ليس للرجال فقط وإنَّما للنساء أيضاً. الآن يا رب أُنظر إلى (إمائك هؤلاء/أمتك هذه)، أدعوهن للخدمة وأفض عليهن موهبة روحك القدوس. إحفظهن في الإيمان الأرثوذكسي متمِّمات خدمتك باستمرار بلا لوم حسب مسرتك، لأن لك كل المجد وكرامة وسجود أيها الآب والابن والروح القدس.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy3"/>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O God, the Holy and Most High, who looks upon the lowly, and who chose the strong and weak, and honored humble women. Send, O Lord, the grace of Your Holy Spirit on Your maidservant(s). Strengthen her with Your righteousness, so that if she abides by Your commandments and serves in Your holy house, she may become for You an honored vessel for glorification.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يا الله القدوس العلي الناظر إلى المتواضعات، يا مَنْ اختار الضعفاء والأقوياء وكرَّم اللواتي هنَّ في اتضاع. أرسل يا رب نعمة روحك القدوس على (إمائك هؤلاء/أمتك هذه). قوهن ببرك، فإذا عملن بوصاياك، وخدمن في بيت قدسك، كنَّ لك آوان مكرمة لتمجيدك.            </Language>         </Text>         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O Lord grant her power to joyfully abide by Your teachings that You have appointed for her service as a canon. O Lord give her the Spirit of meekness, power, praise, forbearance, and patience, so that if she carries Your yoke with joy and struggles patiently, she will be granted the crowns of service.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أعطهن يا رب قوة لكي يسلكن بابتهاج حسب تعاليمك التي رسمتها قانوناً لخدمتهن، هبهن يا رب روح التواضع والقوة والتسبيح والاحتمال والصبر، فإذا حملن نيرك بفرح وصبرن على الجهاد، تكون لهن أكاليل الخدمة.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy3"/>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O Lord, who knows our weakness, perfect Your maidservant(s) and may she serve women, visit females who are sick and those who are distant from church, serve the female poor and needy, assist adult females on their baptism day, teach the female catechumens, and organize females in church. Strengthen her for edification and to be a good example. Sanctify her, enlighten her, and give her wisdom. For You are blessed and glorified, O Father, Son and the Holy Spirit.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               نعم أيها الرب العارف بضعفنا، كمِّل (إمائك/أمتك) وليقمن بخدمة النساء، ويفتقدن المريضات والغائبات عن الكنيسة، ويقمن بخدمة الفقيرات والمحتاجات، ويساعدن في يوم عماد النساء الكبيرات، ويعلمن الموعوظات، ويرتبن النساء في الكنيسة. قوهن للبنيان والمثال الصالح. قدسهن، أنرهن، أعطيهن حكمة. لأنك مبارك وممجد، أيها الآب والابن والروح القدس.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy3"/>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               O Lord, listen to our prayers and send blessing on her from the Holy Spirit, that she may fulfill Your service without falling into condemnation, and become a role model for holy life. Bless her, O Lord, she whom You have purchased by Your precious Blood.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               إستمع يا رب صلواتنا وارسل عليهن بركة من الروح القدس، لكي يتمِّمن خدمتك بغير وقوع في دينونة، ويقدمن مثالاً للحياة المقدسة. باركهن يا رب، (هؤلاء اللاتي/هذه التي) اشتريتهن بالدم الثمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy3"/>   </Section>   <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">The Second Litanies</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">الطلبات الثانية</Language>      </Title>      <Role id="Deacon">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Let us ask the Lord.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               من الرب نطلب.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               For the peace of the holy, catholic, and apostolic Church, let us ask the Lord.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               عن سلام الكنيسة المقدسة الجامعة الرسولية، من الرب نطلب.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               For the service of women in Church, and the female poor, sick, and catechumens, let us ask the Lord.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               عن خدمة النساء في الكنيسة وعن الفقيرات والمريضات والموعوظات، من الرب نطلب.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               For her (those) who is (are) presented for the service of consecration by the nomination of those who nominated her, that the Lord may grant her grace and power, and bless her service as He blessed Phoebe in the past, let us ask the Lord.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               عن (هؤلاء/هذه) المتقدمات إلى خدمة التكريس بتزكية مَنْ قدموهن، لكيما يمنحهن الرب نعمة وقوة، ويبارك خدمتهن كما بارك خدمة فيبي من قبل، من الرب نطلب.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>      <InsertDocument path="include/LordHaveMercy"/>   </Section>   <Role id="Bishop">      <InsertDocument path="include/LordsPrayer"/>            <Comment>         <Language id="English">            Then the bishop makes the sign of the cross three times (without the laying of hands), saying each time:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثم يرشم الأسقف بالصليب الرشومات الثلاثة المعروفة (بدون وضع الأيدي) وهو يقول في كل مرة:         </Language>      </Comment>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            (...) a consecrated woman in the holy, Coptic, orthodox, Church of God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            (...) مكرسة في كنيسة الله المقدسة القبطية الارثوذكسية.         </Language>      </Text>   </Role>   <InsertDocument path="consecrations/ordinations/include/ThreeSignings"/>   <Role id="People">      <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Axia (3): tekbwki (...) ]selet n~te Pi,~rictoc.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Worthy (3), Your servant (...), the bride of Christ.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            مستحقة (3)، عبدتك (...) عروس المسيح.         </Language>      </Text>   </Role>   <Role id="Bishop">      <Comment>         <Language id="English">            Then the bishop blesses the service vestments with the three signs of the cross for her to dress in.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ثم يبارك الأسقف ملابس الخدمة بالثلاثة رشومات ليلبسنها.         </Language>      </Comment>   </Role>   <Section expanded="true">      <Title>         <Language id="English">Commandment</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">وصية</Language>      </Title>      <Role id="Bishop">         <Text>            <Language id="English">               Know, blessed daughter, that the Lord chose you for the service of consecration in the holy Church. Keep the commandment, and be alert to always be blameless and to keep the consecration vestments without blemish. Let praise be in your mouth, and always be full of grace through the holy Mysteries. Be obedient to your father, the bishop, and those who guide you in God’s way. Be faithful towards doctrine and the service to which you are entrusted with by the Church.  May the Lord grant you power by His grace, and count you with the wise virgins, who are the blessed brides of Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               إعلمي أيتها الابنة المباركة أن الرب قد اختارك لخدمة التكريس بالكنيسة المقدسة. فاحفظي الوصية، واحرصي أن تكوني بلا لوم وأن تحفظي ثوب التكريس بلا عيب. املئي فمك من التسبيح وكوني دائماً في ملء النعمة بوسائط الأسرار المقدسة. واسلكي في الطاعة لأبيك الأسقف ولمَنْ يرشدك في طريق الله. واحفظي الأمانة في العقيدة وفي الخدمة التي ائتمنت عليها من قِبَل الكنيسة، وليهبك الرب قوة بنعمته، ويحسبك مع العذارى الحكيمات عرائس المسيح المباركات.            </Language>         </Text>      </Role>   </Section></Document>