<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - John 8:21-29         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير – يوحنا 8: 21-29         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When our Lord Christ taught with authority in Jerusalem on Sunday and Monday and was surrounded by the Jews who believed that He is truly Christ, their awaited king,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لما علم ربنا يسوع المسيح في مدينة أورشليم في يومي الأحد والاثنين تعليماً بسلطان وكل اليهود مجتمعون حوله مؤمنون أنه بالحقيقة المسيح ملكهم الذي كانوا ينتظرونه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            it became very difficult for the Jewish elders and priests who hated Him. They decided to trick him and deliver Him to Pilates, the Roman governor to have Him killed.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            صعب ذلك جداً على مقدمي وكهنة اليهود الذين كانوا يبغضونه وتشاوروا أن ينصبوا له فخاً حتى يسلموه إلى بيلاطس الوالي الرومي ليقتله.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When He came on Tuesday to teach as usual, “So they watched Him, and sent spies who pretended to be righteous, that they might seize on His words, in order to deliver Him to the power and the authority of the governor.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما حضر يوم الثلاثاء للتعليم كعادته "أرسلوا جواسيس يتراءون أنهم أبرار لكي يمسكوه بكلمة حتى يسلموه إلى حكم الوالي وسلطانه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Then they asked Him, saying: "Teacher, we know that You say and teach rightly, and You do not show personal favoritism, but teach the way of God in truth: Is it lawful for us to pay taxes to Caesar or not?"         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فسألوه قائلين يا معلم نعلم أنك بالاستقامة تتكلم وتعلم ولا تقبل الوجوه بل بالحق تعلم طريق الله. أيجوز لنا أن نعطي جزية لقيصر أم لا"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            thinking that He will say “No” so they can go to the Roman governors and inform them and they would kill Him,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وظنوا أنه سيقول لهم لا. فيمضوا إلى ولاة الروم ويعلموهم بذلك ليقتلوه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            but the Lord who knows all said, “Why do you test Me, you hypocrites? Show Me the tax money. Whose image and inscription is this?" They said to Him, "Caesar's."         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فأجابهم علام الغيوب قائلا "لماذا تجربونني أروني ديناراً. لمن الصورة والكتابة. فأجابوا وقالوا لقيصر"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            And He said to them, "Render therefore to Caesar the things that are Caesar's, and to God the things that are God's." meaning that if the denarius carried Caesar’s picture then it should be given to him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فقال لهم: “اعطوا إذن ما لقيصر لقيصر وما لله لله". يعني بما أن الدنانير عليها صورة القيصر فيجب أن تُعطى له.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Likewise, the image of God drawn on man’s reasoning and talking soul must be given to Him. He thus revealed the honor and the pride of the soul         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وصورة الله التي رسمها على النفس العاقلة الناطقة يجب أن تُعطى له. وقد أوضح بهذا شرف النفس وكرامتها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            because God Himself drew His picture on it and He orders us to give it to Him by constantly loving, fearing and constantly thinking about Him and His commandments and Laws.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن الله تعالى رسم صورته عليها ولذا يأمرنا أن نعطيه إياها بدوامها في خوفه ومحبته والتفكر فيه وبوصاياه ونواميسه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            We Should always seek His help to obey His commandments and be delivered from all sin.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            والتضرع الدائم في طلب معونته على عمل وصاياه والخلاص من كل خطية.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Jews at the time were divided into two groups: the Pharisees and the Sadducees         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان اليهود في ذلك الزمان ينقسمون إلى فرقتين. الواحدة تسمى الفريسيين أي المعتزلة والأخرى تسمى الصدوقيين         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            who did not believe in resurrection as the bible testified. They had a leader whose name was Sadduc, who was responsible for ruining their beliefs in truth and swayed them towards not believing in the resurrection of the dead.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذين يقولون ليس قيامة للأموات كما شهد عنهم الإنجيل وكان لهم زعيماً يسمى صادوق قد أفسد رأيهم عن الحق وأمالهم إلى رأي من يعتقد أن الموتى لا يقومون.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            On Tuesday while the Lord was teaching in the temple. Some of the Sadducees came to Him desiring to show contempt for the resurrection and asked Him about a woman who was married to seven brothers, one after the other and then died. They left no offspring and the woman last of all died.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وفي يوم الثلاثاء بينما كان الرب يعلم في الهيكل حضر إليه قوم من الصدوقيين يقصدون التهزئة بالقيامة وسألوه عن امرأة تزوجت سبعة إخوة الواحد بعد الآخر وماتوا ولم يتركوا نسلاً وآخر الكل ماتت المرأة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            They asked him, “Therefore, in the resurrection, whose wife of the seven will she be? For they all had her."         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهنا سألوه قائلين "ففي القيامة لمن من السبعة تكون زوجة. فإنها كانت للجميع"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            What they were clearly saying is if she were to be to the first one that would be unjust and if she were to be to all of them they would be adulterers.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            يريدون أن يقولوا بأوضح عبارة إن كانت للأول فهذا ظلم وإن كانت لهم كلهم فيكونوا زناة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Viciously they said, she did not have any children because had she had any children, He may have told them she was to be to the one who fathered her children. But the Lord Christ shut them up by saying:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقالوا بمكر أنه لم يكن لهم نسلاً حتى لا يقول لهم تكون للذي له منها ولداً. ولكن السيد المسيح أبكم أفواههم بقوله:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            "You are mistaken, not knowing the Scriptures or the power of God. For in the resurrection they neither marry nor are given in marriage, but are like angels of God in heaven”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "تضلون إذ لا تعرفون الكتب ولا قوة الله لأنهم في القيامة لا يزوجون ولا يتزوجون بل يكونون كملائكة الله في السماء"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            which means that the marital relationship between husband and wife pertains to this earth only and will not apply in heaven. From Christ’s response we learn about the resurrection and how it will be.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أي أن النسبة بين الزوج والزوجة مختصة بهذه الدنيا ولا تكون في السماء ونتعلم من جواب السيد المسيح كيف تكون القيامة وعلى أي وجه هي.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            People will be spirits and will no longer have any of these physical needs such as food, drink, etc.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهو أن يكون الناس فيها روحانيين غير مفتقرين إلى شيء من هذه الأمور الجسمانية كالأكل والشرب وغيره.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When He says like the angels, he doesn’t mean without bodies like the angels but without the need for anything like them.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وليس يريد أن نكون كالملائكة بمعنى أن نكون بغير أجساد مثلهم لكننا لا نحتاج إلى شيء كما هم لا يحتاجون.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Since the Sadducees thought that Moses sayings about the above mentioned wife denies the resurrection, the Lord Christ cited a statement from this prophet’s sayings verifying the resurrection:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما كان الصدوقيون يظنون أن اقوال موسى في مسألة الزوجة المذكورة تبطل القيامة ذكر لهم السيد المسيح عبارة من أقوال هذا النبي تحقق القيامة فقال:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “But concerning the resurrection of the dead, have you not read what was spoken to you by God, saying: 'I am the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob'? God is not the God of the dead, but of the living."         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "أفما قرأتم ما قيل لكم من قبل الله القائد أنا إله إبراهيم وإله إسحق وإله يعقوب ليس الله إله أموات بل إله أحياء"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            God said that these people are alive which means that they are still there because their souls are immortal. After resurrection they move to a life that is prepared for them and for all the virtuous.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقال في هؤلاء أنهم أحياء بمعنى أنهم باقون أي نفوسهم خالدة ولأنهم يصيرون عند القيامة إلى الحياة المعدة لهم ولسائر الأبرار.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As for His saying: “God is not the God of the dead, but of the living” it verifies that the unrepentant sinners are dead in their sins and they have no God as John the Evangelist said, He who says, "I know Him," and does not keep His commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأما قوله "ليس الله إله أموات بل إله أحياء" فلكي يحقق أن الخطاة غير التائبين الذين هم موتى بخطاياهم ليس الله لهم إلهاً كما يقول يوحنا الإنجيلي "من قال إني قد عرفته ولم يحفظ وصاياه فهو كاذب".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “But when the Pharisees heard that He had silenced the Sadducees, they gathered together. Then one of them, a lawyer, asked Him a question, testing Him, saying: "Teacher, which is the great commandment in the Law?"         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "أما الفريسيون فلما سمعوا أنه أبكم الصدوقيين اجتمعوا معاً. وسأله واحد منهم وهو ناموسي ليجربه قائلاً: "يا معلم أية وصية هي العظمى في الناموس؟"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Jesus said to him: “You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, with all your soul, and with all your mind. This is the first and great commandment.” The love of God is to keep His commandments as the Lord said to His disciples:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فقال له يسوع: تحب الرب إلهك من كل قلبك ... إلخ." وحب الرب هو حفظ وصاياه والعمل بها كما قال السيد المسيح لتلاميذه:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “You are My friends if you do whatever I command you.” The Lord showed us the greatness of loving one another because He likened it to our love for Him saying:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "أنتم أحبائي إن فعلتم ما أوصيكم به" وقد أظهر عظم جلال محبة بعضنا لبعض إذ جعل ذلك شبه محبتنا له بقوله:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “You shall love your neighbor as yourself.” The neighbor that the Lord ordered us to love as ourselves is anyone in need of help or is suffering. I must help him as much as I could         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "والثانية مثلها تحب قريبك كنفسك" وقريبي الذي أمرني بحبه كنفسي هو من أراه في ضيقة أو محتاج إلى معونة مني وأعينه حسب طاقتي         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            and as I would help myself had I been in such a situation. My love for him is like my love for my creator as John the Evangelist said:         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كالذي قدر أن أعين به نفسي إذا كنت في مثل تلك الضيقة. فإن حبي إياه يشبه حبي لخالقي كما قال يوحنا الإنجيلي:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “If someone says, "I love God," and hates his brother, he is a liar; for he who does not love his brother whom he has seen, how can he love God whom he has not seen?” Thus the love of God can’t be except by the love of one’s brother.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "إن قال أحد أني أحب الله وأبغض أخاه فهو كاذب. لأن من لا يحب أخاه الذي أبصره كيف يقدر أن يحب الله الذي لم يبصره" وعليه فإن حب الله لا يصح إلا بمحبة الأخ.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When the Lord wanted to reveal His divinity and that He is equal to His Father, He said: "What do you think about the Christ? Whose Son is He?"         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولما أراد أن يوضح لهم لاهوته وربوبيته وأنه مساوٍ لأبيه في ذلك قال لهم: “ماذا تظنون في المسيح. ابن من هو"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He asked them to alert the minds of the Pharisees to believe in His divinity and that He is the one promised by the prophets.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أراد بقوله هذا أن ينبه عقول الفريسيين إلى الاعتقاد بربوبيته وأنه هو الذي وعد بمجيئه الأنبياء.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He asked them whose son is He. “They said to Him: "The Son of David." He said to them: "How then does David in the Spirit call Him 'Lord,' etc.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقال لهم: ابن من هو قالوا له ابن داود . قال لهم: فكيف يدعوه داود بالروح رباً ... إلخ."         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Because the Jews did not know that Christ is God incarnate in the flesh, the son of God and the son of David, they did not favor answering His question. And from that day forward, no one dared question Him anymore.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولكون اليهود لم يكونوا يعلمون أن المسيح هو إله متأنس وهو ابن الله وابن داود. لم يستحسنوا أن يجيبوه على سؤاله "ومن ذلك اليوم لم يجسر أحد أن يسأله بتة."         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Because it was difficult for them to hear Him talk about his divinity and they considered it heresy.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأنهم كانوا إذا سمعوه في بعض الأوقات يشير لهم عن لاهوته يصعب عليهم ذلك ويعتبروه تجديفاً.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He proved to them using David’s words that He is divine and the God of David, God of the seen and the unseen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            حيث أثبت لهم من قول داود أنه بلاهوته رب داود. وهو رب كل ما يرى وما لا يرى.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The son of God, born before all ages like the birth of the sun rays from its source while connected to it.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهو ابن الله المولود منه قبل كل الدهور كميلاد شعاع الشمس من قرصها. مولود منه وهو ثابت فيه كما أن شعاع الشمس مولود من قرصها وهو متصل بالقرص.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Paul, the apostle speaks about His birth from the father and His link to Him like the ray of the sun to its source. He said: “who being the brightness of His glory and the express image of His person” so that we may know that He is the true son complete in picture and hypostasis as His father and is not separate from His father’s hypostasis like the created children,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولكي يعرفنا بولس الرسول عن ميلاده من الآب واتصاله به كالشعاع بالشمس قال: "الذي وهو بهاء مجده ورسم جوهره" أبيه كالبنين المخلوقين.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            but He is connected to His Father’s hypostasis as the ray is connected to its source and as David has called Him God and His Father God saying: “The Lord said to my Lord Sit at My right hand.” and He did not call him God in His divinity only but also in His humanity too,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            بل هو متصل بأقنوم أبيه كالشعاع بالقرص كما دعاه داود رباً وأبيه رباً بقوله "قال الرب لربي اجلس عن يميني" ولم يدعه رباً بلاهوته فقط بل بلاهوته وناسوته.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            because the father’s saying sit by my right hand refers to his sitting in his humanity after His ascension to heaven. David demonstrated to us that His divinity and His humanity are one God and we don’t say that His divinity is a God and His humanity is another. Both are one.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن قول الآب له اجلس عن يميني هو عن جلوسه بناسوته بعد صعوده إلى السماء. وقد حقق لنا داود بذلك أنه بلاهوته وناسوته رب واحد وأنه واحد ولا نقول أن لاهوته رب وناسوته رب بل هو رب واحد         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As Paul the apostle has testified, “and one Lord Jesus Christ,” meaning He is one God with His Humanity and divinity because the union between the divinity and the humanity has become one hypostasis and one divine incarnation.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            كما شهد بذلك بولس الرسول بقول "ورب واحد يسوع المسيح" يعني أنه رب واحد بلاهوته وناسوته لأن اللاهوت باتحاده بالناسوت صار أقنوماً واحداً إلهاً متأنساً.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Trinity and monotheism were clarified by the divine inspiration, “Then God said, "Let Us make man in Our image, according to Our likeness;”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأما عن التثليث والتوحيد فقد أثبته الوحي بقوله "وقال الله نعمل الإنسان على صورتنا كشبهنا"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            which shows the presence of the Holy Spirit in His word “us” clarifying that the saying was not about the Son alone but about the three hypostasis together: The Father, the Son and the Holy Spirit.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولكون هذا القول يوضح وجود الروح القدس لقوله نخلق أوضح بهذا أن القول ليس للابن وحده بل للثلاثة أقانيم معاً الآب والابن والروح القدس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Also during building the Tower of Babel, He said: “Come, let Us go down and there confuse their language, that they may not understand one another's speech."         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهكذا قال أيضا أيام بناء البرج "هلم ننزل ونبلبل هناك لسانهم"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Moreover He said: "I am the God of your father – the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac, and the God of Jacob," speaking of the three hypostasis, otherwise there would have been no need to repeat the word God three times.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقال أيضا: "أنا إله أبيك إله إبراهيم وإله إسحق وإله يعقوب" ومراده بهذا القول الكلام عن الثلاثة أقانيم وإن لم يكن ذلك فما كانت حاجة إلى تكرير لفظ الجلالة         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He repeated the word God three times to show us that each of the three hypostasis is a true God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان القول هكذا أنا إله إبراهيم وإسحق ويعقوب وإنما كرر اسم الإله ثلاثة دفعات لكي نعلم أن كل واحد من الأقانيم الثلاثة إله حقيقي.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The father is a true God, the son is a true God and the Holy Spirit is a true God. If we know that each of the three hypostasis is a true God we should know that the three are one God and not three Gods.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فالآب إله حقيقي والابن إله حقيقي والروح القدس إله حقيقي. وإذا علمنا أن كل واحد من الأقانيم الثلاثة إله حقيقي. نعلم ايضا أن الثلاثة إله واحد وليس ثلاثة آلهة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            And every other thing followed Him, was created by Him, and limited, with a beginning and an end, in His image and in His presence.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وإن كل غيرة وبعده. ومخلوق منه ومحدود ومحصور وله بداية ونهاية في صورته وفي وجوده.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As for the Holy Trinity, each of its three hypostasis is without beginning or end, not in His image and not in His presence.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أما الثالوث الأقدس فكل واحد من أقانيمه لا بداية له ولا نهاية لا في صورته ولا في وجوده.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He IS from the beginning and is still being. He is unique and no one is like Him. Anyone who denies that the Father is God, the Son is God and the Holy Spirit is God         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            هو منذ الأزل ولا يزال وهو هو واحد لا شبه له ولا مثال. ومن أنكر علينا قولنا. أن الآب رب والابن رب والروح القدس رب         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            denies David’s words: “The Lord said to my Lord Sit at My right hand” and Moses words, “Then the Lord rained brimstone and fire on Sodom and Gomorrah, from the Lord out of the heavens” because the prophets and priests of the Jews testify for our Christian faith.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فلينكر على داود قوله "قال الرب لربي اجلس عن يميني" وعلى موسى قوله "فأمطر الرب ... من عند الرب" لأن إيماننا نحن المسيحيون قد شهدت به أنبياء اليهود وكهنتهم.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>       </Document>