<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Season id="Joyful29thOfTheMonthRaw">            <Title>               <Language id="English">Watos Exposition for the 29th day of each Coptic Month</Language>         <Language id="Arabic">طرح واطس اليوم التاسع والعشرون من كل شهر</Language>                  </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Amwini t/rou n~ten ]w~ou: m~Pen% I/#c# P,#c#:  v/etaumacf n~je ]paryenoc:   qen B/yleem n~te ]Ioudea~.          </Language>         <Language id="English">            Come all, to glorify / our Lord Jesus Christ / who was incarnate of the Virgin, / in Bethlehem of Judea.           </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تعالوا جميعكم لنمجد، ربنا يسوع المسيح، الذي تجسد من العذراء، ?ي بيت لحم اليهودية.          </Language>      </Text>               <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Nieuajjelion e#y#u#:   autamon e~pimuct/rion:   eybe p~jinmici m~Penc#w#r:#  e~bol qen Maria ]paryenoc.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            The holy Gospels / narrated the mystery / of the Birth of our Savior / from the Virgin Mary.            </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الأناجيل المقدسة? ، سردت  السر، الذي لميلاد مخلصنا، من مريم العذراء.         </Language>      </Text>            <Section expanded="true">         <Title>            <Language id="English">Watos Exposition</Language>            <Language id="Arabic">طرح واطس</Language>         </Title>                     <Text>            <Language id="English">               A luxurious praise and rich veneration is this honorable commemoration of the holy Annunciation, the glorious pure Nativity, and the honorable magnificent Resurrection of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.  To Him who is coessential with His good Father, and the Holy Spirit, the Life-Giver, be glory forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مديحاً ?اخراً. وتبجيلاً زاهراً: من أجل التذكار الشري? السيدي الذي للبشارة المقدسة والميلاد المجيد البتولي والقيامة الشري?ة المعظمة التي لسيدنا ومخلصنا يسوع المسيح له المجد دائماً مع أبيه الصالح المساوي له ?ي الجوهر و?ي الألوهية والأزلية والروح القدس المحيي إلى الأبد آمين.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Comment>            <Language id="English">               Explanation            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الت?سير            </Language>         </Comment>                  <Text>            <Language id="English">               Come today, O you believers and lovers of Christ, let us rejoice and be glad by singing spiritual and heavenly hymns on this great day, the twenty-ninth of this month.  On this day, the Lord sent the Archangel Gabriel to our Lady to announce the Incarnation of the eternal Word of God, our Savior Christ, the Son of God, who is begotten before all ages and one with the Father in eternity and divinity.              </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               تعالوا جميعكم اليوم أيها المؤمنون محبو المسيح لن?رح ونسر بالتماجيد الروحية والتراتيل السماوية ?ي هذا اليوم العظيم الذي هو التاسع والعشرون من هذا الشهر لأن ?يه أرسل الرب الملاك جبرائيل مبشراً الست السيدة بتجسد كلمة الله الأزلي الذي هو مخلصنا المسيح ابن الله المولود منه قبل كل الدهور الكائن معه والمساوي له ?ي الأزلية والألوهية.             </Language>         </Text>                     <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the miraculous Nativity of our Lord Jesus Christ from the pure Virgin; that is the Nativity of the King of Kings and Lord of Lords, our Lord Jesus Christ              </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?يه أيضاً كان الميلاد البتولي ذو الأمر العجيب من البتول الزكية الذي هو ميلاد ملك الملوك ورب الأرباب سيدنا يسوع المسيح.             </Language>         </Text>                     <Text>            <Language id="English">               On this day also was the honorable Resurrection of our Savior from among the dead, which He completed by His good Economy, that what the prophets had prophesied may be fulfilled. The pure evangelists witnessed to this and preached to all the regions of the earth.              </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               و?يه أيضاً كانت القيامة الشري?ة التي لمخلصنا من بين الأموات عندما أكمل تدبيره الصالح لتمام ما تنبأت به كتب الأنبياء الصادقين. وكما شهد بذلك الإنجيليون الأطهار الذين بشروا ?ي أقطار المسكونة.             </Language>         </Text>                     <Text>            <Language id="English">               Bethlehem was thus glorified from among the towns and cities, for in it was born our Savior, wrapped and placed in a manger.  All the luminous hosts worshipped His divinity and praised His glorious lordship.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هوذا بيت لحم قد ا?تخرت على المدن والقرى. لأنه قد ظهر منها مخلصنا مولوداً مل?و?اً موضوعاً ?ي مذود. سائر المراتب النورانية تسجد لعظمة لاهوته مسبحين لمجد ربوبيته.             </Language>         </Text>                     <Text>            <Language id="English">               We ought, our spiritual fathers and our elect brothers, to spiritually celebrate this feast of the twenty-ninth day of the month, chanting and praising heavenly hymns.  For on this day was salvation and joy for the human race on account of the life-giving Annunciation, the virginal Nativity, and glorious Resurrection which saved us from the hand of the enemy.  The glory of the divine Christ and the light of His Resurrection shone upon those who were in exile in Hades, and they were returned to Paradise once more.              </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?يجب علينا أيها الآباء الروحيون والأخوة النجباء المنتخبون أن نعيد عيداً روحياً بالتراتيل والتماجيد السمائية ?ي هذا اليوم العظيم الذي هو التاسع والعشرون من هذا الشهر الذي ?يه كان الخلاص وال?رح لجنس البشر بالبشارة المحيية، والميلاد البتولي ، والقيامة الشري?ة التي بها كان الخلاص من يد العدو. والمعتقلون ?ي الجحيم خلصوا وأشرق عليهم مجد لاهوت المسيح ونور قيامته وعادوا إلى ال?ردوس مرة أخرى.             </Language>         </Text>                     <Text>            <Language id="English">               Blessed are those who commemorate this glorious feast and may their offerings be elevated upon the holy altars.  Blessed is the one who visits the [poor] brethren of Christ on this day.  Blessed is the one who labors in freeing those in captivity on this day.  Blessed is the one who visits those in prison, as the Lord enables him.  Blessed is the one who consoles those who mourn: those in poverty.  Truly the Lord will save him from all the worldly troubles and he shall not lack anything from the Lord.  May the Lord multiply His grace and blessings upon him, that he may overflow unto others, and receive eternal blessings of non-perishable joy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?طوبى لمن يصنع هذا التذكار الشري? وترت?ع قرابينه ?وق المذابح المقدسة. ?طوبى لمن ي?تقد أخوة المسيح ?ي هذا اليوم العظيم. طوبى للذي يجتهد ?ي الا?راج عن المتضايقين. طوبى للذي ي?تقد المسجونين كقدر عطايا المسيح إليه. طوبى لمن يعزي الحزانى وذوي ال?اقة. بالحقيقة أن الرب يخلصه من سائر الأحزان والضوائق الحادثة ?ي هذا العالم وليس يعوزه الرب شيئاً: لكن تتضاع? عليه النعم والبركات حتى ي?ضل عنه لأخرين وينال الخيرات السرمدية التي لا أنقضاء ل?رحها.             </Language>         </Text>                     <Text>            <Language id="English">               Let us sing with a joyful voice saying, “Hail to Bethlehem, the city of the prophets, whence Christ our Savior was born of the Virgin Mary, the pride of all virgins, without seed of man!  Hail to Bethlehem, whence shone the light of Christ, before whose divine glory the luminous hosts tremble! Hail to Bethlehem, whence was born He who sits upon the cherubic throne!  Hail to Bethlehem, which became like heaven, for He whose greatness is praised by the heavenly, is now also praised by the earthly in Bethlehem!              </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ?لنقل بصوت ال?رح والتهليل:السلام لبيت لحم مدينة الأنبياء التي ظهر منها مخلصنا المسيح المولود من ?خر جميع العذارى القديسة مريم بغير زرع بشر. السلام لبيت لحم الذي أشرق منها نور ميلاد المسيح الذي ترتعد من مجد لاهوته الطقوس النورانية. السلام لبيت لحم الذي ولد ?يه الجالس على مركة الشاروبيم. السلام لبيت لحم الذي صارت شبيهاً بالسماء،  لأن الذي يسبحه السمائيون يسبحون عظمته الآن مع الأرضيين ببيت لحم.             </Language>         </Text>                     <Text>            <Language id="English">               “Hail to the city of God, Jerusalem, upon which the great throne was erected where Salvation came to our father Adam and his offspring through the Cross!  Hail to the Mount of Cranium, where our Savior was lifted up on the Cross and His holy hands were nailed to it!?  These revelations were revealed to the early fathers before the divine Incarnation.  Hail to the life-giving sepulcher where the pure Body of our Lord was laid, and to the holy cave where the wood of the Cross was hidden!              </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               السلام لمدينة الله أورشليم التي صار أعلاها الكرسي العظيم و?يها كان الخلاص بالصلبوت المحيي لأبينا آدم وذريته. السلام لجبل الأقرانيون الذي ر?ع مخلصنا أعلاه على الصليب وسمرت تلك اليدان الزكيتان. وظهرت الاعلانات للآباء الأولين من قديم الدهر قبل التجسد الإلهي. السلام للقبر المحيي الذي وضع ?يه الجسد الطاهر الذي لمخلصنا والمغارة المقدسة التي أخ?وا ?يها خشبة الصليب.             </Language>         </Text>                     <Text>            <Language id="English">               Hail to the holy Resurrection, when our Savior appeared to His own disciples after He rose from the dead on the third day after His crucifixion!  Hail to the city of God, Zion, where upon the Holy Spirit descended!  Hail to the holy wilderness of the Jordan upon which the pure feet of our Lord walked, and He was baptized by John the Baptist, the son of Zacharias.              </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               السلام للقيامة المقدسة التي ظهر ?يها مخلصنا لخواصه التلاميذ إذ قام من بين الأموات من بعد صلبوته بثلاثة أيام. السلام لمدينة الله صهيون التي هبط عليها روح القدس. السلام للبراري المقدسة التي هي براري الأردن التي استحقت أن تطأ عليها تلك الأقدام الإلهية و?يها تعمد من النبي العظيم يوحنا ابن زكريا.             </Language>         </Text>                     <Text>            <Language id="English">               Rejoice, O Virgin Mary, for you were worthy to receive that great Annunciation, of the Incarnation of the Word of God the Father, who was incarnated from you, and was born as a human.  You fed from your breast the One who sustains the whole creation.  Therefore, we magnify you with the Archangel Gabriel saying,  “Hail to you O full of grace, the Lord is with you!?  Intercede on our behalf before your beloved Son so that He may strengthen us in the true faith, have mercy on us according to His great mercy, save us from the troubles of this world and from our adversaries, soften the hearts of those having authority over us, and grant us the forgiveness of our sins.  Praise be to God forever. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               إ?رحي يا مريم العذراء لأنك استحقيتي هذه البشارة العظيمة بحلول كلمة الله الآب تجسد منك? وظهر مولوداً كالبشرية. وأرضعتيه من ثدييك? الذي يعول كل الخليقة. ?لأجل هذا نعظمك مع غبريال الملاك هكذا قائلين إ?رحي يا ممتلئة نعمة الرب معك?. إش?عي ?ينا أمام ابنك الحبيب لكي يثبتنا على الإيمان المستقيم ويرحمنا كعظيم رحمته ويخلصنا من ضوائق هذا العالم ويك?ينا شر أعدائنا المضادين لنا. ويعط? علينا قلوب المتولين علينا وينعم لنا بغ?ران خطايانا. والسبح لله دائماً آمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season></Document>