<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Isaiah 12:2-13:10         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير النبوات – من أشيعاء النبي 12: 2 – الخ و 13: 2 – 10         </Language>      </Title>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Behold, God is my salvation” meaning that when the believers saw Jesus on the great day of the crucifixion, and saw the signs and the miracles that took place, they were assured that He was the divine Savior of the world. Formerly, they had not understood Jesus’ explanation to them concerning His life giving passion. On another level, the prophet foresaw the crucifixion of the Lord as the father of all fathers, Abraham, had seen it and rejoiced. It was as if he had witnessed it and therefore he said, “Behold, God is my salvation.” He was assured that Jesus was the Savior of the world and therefore he said, “I will trust, and not be afraid,” which means that after the truth was revealed to the believers in His holy name, they left everything behind and relied upon Him fully fearing neither poverty nor death.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "هوذا الله خلاصي" يعني بهذا أن المؤمنين بالمسيح لما رأوه يوم الصلبوت العظيم والعلامات والآيات التي حدثت. تحققوا أنه الإله مُخلِّص العالم. وقد كانوا قبلاً غير فاهمين ما كان يُنذرهم به الرب عن آلامه المُحيية. ومعنى آخر وهو أن النبي رأى بعين بصيرته يوم صلب الرب كما رآه أبو الآباء إبراهيم وفرح. فكان كمن قد شاهده ولذا قال: "هوذا الله مُخلصي" إذ قد تحقق له أنه مُخلص العالم. قال: "الرب الذي أنا مُتكل عليه فلا أخاف" يعني أنه من بعد ما ظهر الحق للمؤمنين باسمه المقدس تركوا كل شيء عنهم وجعلوا اتكالهم عليه غير خائفين الفقر ولا الموت.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “'For Yah, the Lord, is my strength and song,” referring to the fact that those who rely upon the Lord, asking for His blessings and always praising Him are glorified in Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "مجدي وتسبيحي هو الرب" وقد أشار بهذا إلى أن المتَوكلين على الرب الطالبين رضاءه فإن تسبيحه يكون دائما في أفواههم وهو مُتمجد بهم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “He also has become my salvation” which means that our salvation came to us through the cross of our God the Word.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وقد صار لي خلاصاً" يعني بهذا أن خلاصنا صار لنا بصليب الإله الكلمة.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Therefore with joy you will draw water From the wells of salvation,” meaning that when the nations knew God and believed in Him, they relied upon Him and received His blessing. They were directed by Him to the life-giving well of His divine teachings, which is the living water as He had said, “He who believes in Me, as the Scripture has said, out of his heart will flow rivers of living water."         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "يَستَقون ماء بفرح من ينابيع الخلاص" يعني لما عرف الشعوب الإله وآمنوا به وتوكلوا عليه وحَلت بَركته عليهم أشار إليهم بأن يستقوا التعاليم المحيية المُخلصة لنفوسهم من الينبوع الإلهي الذي هو ماء الحياة كما قال له المجد: "من آمن بي كما قال الكتاب تجري من بطنه أنهار ماء حي".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            His saying, “with joy,” shows that, unlike the Jews, who accepted the law out of fear and terror when they saw the thunder, lightning, smoke and the sound of the trumpet, “Then they said to Moses, "You speak with us, and we will hear; but let not God speak with us, lest we die.", God now directed Christians to be joyful for they had been freed of the bondage of sin and they became sons after they had been slaves. The Savior has released the believers from the bitter enslavement of the devil and bought them with His precious blood, leaving no place for fear and terror but only everlasting joy.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله "بفرح" فليس كما قَبل بنو إسرائيل وصاياه ونواميسه بالخوف والارتعاب حيث كانوا يرَون الرعود والبروق وصوت البوق والدخان فقالوا لموسى: "تكلم أنت معنا فنسمع. ولا يتكلم معنا الله لئلا نموت". بل أشار لهم هنا بالفرح لأنهم صاروا بعد العبودية بنين. حيث قد عتق المُخلِّص المؤمنين باسمه من عبودية الشيطان المُرة واشتراهم بدمه المقدس فلم يبقَ خوف ولا رعب بل الفرح الدائم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            For this reason, Paul said, “Rejoice in the Lord always. Again I will say, rejoice!”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولذلك قال بولس الرسول: "افرحوا في الرب كل حين وأقول أيضا افرحوا".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            And in that day you will say: "Praise the Lord, call upon His name; Declare His deeds among the peoples,” indicating that the faith in Jesus Christ had spread among all nations and His name was being proclaimed in all areas.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وتقولون في ذلك اليوم سبحوا الرب وادعُوا باسمه وبشروا في الأمم بأعماله الكريمة" يعني بهذا أن الإيمان بالمسيح قد ذاع في كل الأمم وقد بشروا باسمه في كل الأصقاع.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Make mention that His name is exalted,” indicating that there was a huge number of people who had believed in Him and who praised and exalted Him day and night.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "اذكروا بأن اسمه قد تعالى" يعني بذلك كثرة الشعوب الذين آمنوا به حتى لم يخلُ مكانٌ في الأرض من المؤمنين باسمه يُسبحونه ويُمجدونه الليل والنهار.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Cry out and shout, O inhabitant of Zion, For great is the Holy One of Israel in your midst!" referring to the raising of the Lord on the life-giving cross. The believers rejoiced for their eternal salvation.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "تهلَلي وافرحي يا ساكنة صهيون لأنه قد ارتفع في وسطك قدوس إسرائيل" يعنى بهذا عن ارتفاع الرب في وسطهم على الصليب المُحيى وقد ابتهجت نفوس المؤمنين به بالخلاص الأبدي.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, "Lift up a banner on the high mountain” referring to the holy cross which was carried by kings who believed in Christ, like Constantine the righteous, on their easy walk to salvation. Although God has called the road leading to salvation, “difficult” this was in reference to those who did not have the right doctrines and therefore fell into sin and followed their desires in food, drink, etc. They suffer on the way to salvation because they find prayer, fasting, charity, love, and abstinence “difficult” whereas the true believers find these things as sweet as honey. God said on a different occasion, “For My yoke is easy and My burden is light”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ارفعوا راية على الجبال السهلة" يعني بهذا عن علامة الصليب المقدس التي حملها الملوك المؤمنون بالمسيح وساروا في طريقه السهل المؤدي إلى الحياة مثل البار قسطنطين وأشباهه. وإن كان الرب قد أسمى الطريق المؤدي إلى الحياة كرباً فهو بالقياس إلى الذين يكون إيمانهم غير صحيح. فيعملون الرذائل ويتَّبعون شَهواتهم في المأكل والمشرب وغيرهما وهؤلاء يكون عندهم طريق الحياة الذي هو الصوم والصلاة والصدقة والمحبة وترك اللذات كَرباً جداً. وهو عند المؤمنين الحقيقيين أحلى من الشهد. وقد قال الرب في. موضع آخر: "لأن نيري هين وحملي خفيف".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Raise your voice to them” referring to the pure disciples whom God had called upon to spread the Gospel without fear. He removed their fear by saying, “I am with you always, even to the end of the age” which means that he was with them, supporting them and with those whom they evangelized, who accepted the teachings of Jesus Christ and followed them.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ارفعوا أصواتكم ولا تخافوا" يعني بهذا عن التلاميذ الأطهار فأن الرب قد أمرهم أن ينادوا بالإنجيل غير خائفين وقد أزال خوفهم بقوله لهم: "ها أنا معكم كل الأيام إلى انقضاء الدهر" يعني أنه كان معهم بمعاضدته إياهم. ومع من آمن على أيديهم وقبل وصاياه من أفواههم المقدسة وعَمِلَ بها.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “I have commanded My sanctified ones; I have also called My mighty ones for My anger-- Those who rejoice in My exaltation” which means that when the truth will be revealed to the kings, the wise men and the rulers of all nations, they will follow God and be delivered from the darkness of their souls that anger and live with faith in Jesus Christ. Their hearts will rejoice when they receive the blessing of the Holy Spirit just like Cornelius the centurion and his household who accepted the Holy Spirit upon encountering the teachings of St. Peter. They rejoiced and were enlightened and realized that they had lived their lives until that moment in the darkness of anger, away from the faith in Christ, before they had accepted Jesus. When they believed and received the Holy Spirit, they rejoiced.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وأنا الآتي ومعي الجبابرة ليُكملوا غضبي. فيفرحون ويُخزون معاً" يعني بهذا أنه عندما يظهر الحق للملوك والحكماء والرؤساء من كل الأمم وينقادون إلى الرب. فيخرجون من الظلمة التي هي الغضب ويكملون بالإيمان بربنا يسوع المسيح وتفرح قلوبهم بحلول نعمة الروح المقدس عليهم. كما حصل لكرنيليوس القائد وجماعته لما قبِلوا الروح القدس بتعليم بطرس الرسول وفرحوا جداً واستنارت نفوسهم وعلموا أنهم كَمَلوا أيامهم إلى ذلك الوقت في الغضب المظلم الذي هو البعد عن الإيمان بربنا يسوع المسيح. ولما آمنوا وتكملوا بالروح القدس عَظم فرحهم وابتهاجهم.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            Likewise the Eunuch, the minister of Candace who served the Queen of Ethiopia when he accepted Christ at Philip’s hands. The eunuch walked on his way, happy and rejoicing with his newly acquired faith in God and his knowledge of the commandments as he was taught by Philip, the prophet.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكذلك الخصي وزير كنداكة ملكة الحبشة مع فيلبس وكيف كان سائرا في طريقه فرحاً مسروراً بإيمانه بالرب ومعرفته وصاياه من فم رسوله         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            All those aforementioned and others rejoiced at their knowledge of God and His teachings and regretted their old sinful days, spent in anger.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فجميع من ذكرنا وغيرهم "يفرحون" لمعرفتهم الله وإيمانهم به "ويخزون" إذ يتذكرون أيامهم السالفة التي أمضوها تحت الغضب.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “The noise of a multitude in the mountains, like that of many people! A tumultuous noise of the kingdoms of nations gathered! The Lord of hosts musters The army for battle. They come from a far country” which refers to the acceptance of the nations of the faith in Jesus through His holy disciples as we have already mentioned.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "صوت أمم كثيرة صوت ممالك وشعوب مجتمعة رب الصباؤوت أمر شعباً مسلحاً أن يأتي من أرض بعيدة" فهو كما تَقَدم القول عن إقبال الأمم والشعوب إلى الإيمان بدعوة التلاميذ الأطهار.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Therefore all hands will be limp, Every man's heart will melt, And they will be afraid. Pangs and sorrows will take hold of them; They will be in pain as a woman in childbirth; They will be amazed at one another; Their faces will be like flames,” which means that when the Israelites saw the blessings the disciples received through the gifts of the Holy Spirit in Zion, they were astonished and when the disciples started to evangelize to them, their hearts were moved as stated in the Book of Acts. Their faces burned shamefully for their sins. “Now when they heard this, they were cut to the heart, and said to Peter and the rest of the apostles, "Men and brethren, what shall we do?" Then Peter said to them, "Repent, and let every one of you be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ for the remission of sins; and you shall receive the gift of the Holy Spirit.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "فلذلك تسترخي كل يد. ويذوب قلب كل إنسان وتضطرب المشائخ. ويأخذهم المُخَلِّص ويتضورون كالتي تلد. وُيَنوح الواحد قبالة صاحبه ويَتحيَّرون وتَتغير وجوههم كاللهيب" يعني بهذا لمَّا رأى شعب إسرائيل والأمم النعمة التي حصلت للتلاميذ الأطهار لعطية الروح القدس في عليه صهيون ذهُلت عقولهم. ولما ابتدأ التلاميذ يبشرونهم باسم المسيح خفقت قلوبهم كما يشهد بذلك سفر الأعمال. وتغيرت وجوههم كاللهيب خجلاً على ما قد فعلوا "وقالوا لبطرس ولسائر الرسل ماذا نصنع أيها الرجال الأخوة. فقال لهم بطرس توبوا وليعتمد كل واحد منكم على اسم يسوع المسيح لغفران الخطايا فتَقبَلوُا عطية الروح القدس".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said,” Behold, the day of the Lord comes, cruel, with both wrath and fierce anger,” referring to the coming of the Lord on the last day when no one will be freely forgiven but each will be judged according to his/her deeds.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "هوذا يوم الرب يأتي بغير مغفرة" يعنى بهذا عن إتيان الرب جل اسمه في اليوم الأخير حيث لا يكون فيه لأحد مغفرة مجاناً ولكنه سيُجازي كل واحد كنحو أعماله.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, ‘And He will destroy its sinners from it.” referring to the apostates who followed the anti-Christ to the Judgment.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "قادم بسخط وغضب. ليجعل المسكونة كلها برية قاحلة ليبيد الخطاة منها" يعني بالخطاة إلى الكفار الذين يكونون قد تبعوا المسيح الكذاب الذي يأتي في آخر الزمان وقت مجيء سيدنا يسوع المسيح للمداينة.         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “For the stars of heaven and their constellations will not give their light; The sun will be darkened in its going forth, and the moon will not cause its light to shine.” All of this will happen when the Lord comes on the clouds as He said in the Holy Bible. “The sun will be darkened, and the moon will not give its light; the stars will fall from heaven, and the powers of the heavens will be shaken Then the sign of the Son of Man will appear in heaven.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "كوكب السماء والأوريون وكل زينتها لا تُعطي نورها. وتظلُم الشمس عند طلوعِها. والقمر لا يضيء بنوره" أي أن هذا جميعه يكون في يوم إتيان الرب له المجد على سحاب السماء كما قال في إنجيله المقدس: "تظلُم الشمس والقمر لا يعطي ضوءه والنجوم تسقط من السماء وقوات السموات تتزعزع. وحينئذ تَظهر علامة ابن الإنسان في السماء".         </Language>      </Text>      <Text>         <Language id="English">            May God grant us to be one of those who have faith and has done good deeds to avoid the terror of that great day. We ask our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ who gave Himself up for us and who bore the pains and death of the crucifixion to save us and who spilt His holy blood to redeem us, to accept our fasting, prayers, charitable deeds, offerings and help you in your fight and grant you good deeds in this world and in the next glorious halos… and cleanse your filth and forgive your sins, grant you patience and gratitude and strong faith in worshipping Him to strengthen your souls and bodies and bless what He has given you of His bounty and keep and increase your good deeds. I pray that He gives you obedience and helps you do what is pleasing to Him and keep you from what you fear of all trials and tribulations, sicknesses, tragedies, disabilities, needs, diseases, disasters, sin and evil and deliver you from every carnal and cunning thought and give you a spiritually blessed path and restore those who have lost their way and heal your sicknesses and give travelers safe returns, offer you solace in your grief with the power of the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ. Glory be to Him forever, Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            جعلَنا الله في ذلك اليوم مِمن له إيمان وأعمال صالحة يفوز بهما من هول ذلك اليوم العظيم. ونسأل ربنا يسوع المسيح الذي أتى لخلاصنا واحتمل الصلب والموت لأجلنا وسَفك دمه الأقدس الذي به اشترانا أن يَتقبَل أصوامكم وصلواتكم وصدقاتكم وتوبتكم وقرابينكم ومحرقاتكم. ويُعينكم في جهادكم. ويوهب لكم في هذه الحياة الدنيا أعمالاً زاهرة وفي الآخرة أكاليل فاخرة. ويَغسل أوساخكُم. ويُمحي ذنوبكم. ويُرزقكم الصبر. ويلهمكم الشكر وأن يُعطيكم إيماناً صادقاً يُثَبِتَكُمْ على عبادته. وتقوى به نفوسكم وأجسادكم. ويبارك فيما وهبه لكم من خيراته. وأسبغه عليكم من نعمائه. ويحفظكم في صالح الأعمال والإزدياد فيها. والتزود منها للعالم العتيد زاداً نافعاً. ويوفِقَكم للطاعة. ويُقربكم إلى مرضاته. ويُكفيكم هول ما تتخوفون منه. من سائر المِحن والتجارب. والنقمات والآفات. والمصائب والعاهات. والفقر والأسقام. ويُنقذكم من أمواج البلايا. وبحار المكاره والخطايا. وينزع منكم كل فكر جسداني. ويَهبكم سيرة روحانية. ويُرد ضاليكم. ويشفي أمراضكم. ويَرد مسافريكم إليكم سالمين. ويعطيكم عزاء في الأحزان التي تنالكم. بقوة صليب ربنا يسوع المسيح. له المجد دائما آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section></Document>