<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation – Isaiah 61:1-7         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير – أشعياء 61: 1-7           </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “The Spirit of the Lord God is upon Me, Because the Lord has anointed Me.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "روح الرب على لذلك مسحني".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            When God the Logos wanted to be incarnate of the Virgin’s blood, the Holy Spirit purified, sanctified and anointed her blood before it was unified with the Logos. That is why He is called anointed because His body was anointed with the Holy Spirit.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن الإله الكلمة لما شاء أن يتجسد من دم العذراء قدس له الروح القدس دمها ونقاه ومسحه وحينئذ اتحد به الكلمة ولذلك سمي مسيحاً لأجل أن جسده ممسوح مقدس بالروح القدس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            This also refers to the manifestation of the Holy Spirit during baptism.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ويشير بهذا الكلام أيضا إلى حلول الروح القدس عليه عند المعمودية.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “To preach good tidings to the poor” who were denied the riches of God because of their sins. Satan had them in his grip, inflicted poverty on them and denied them eternal life. They felt the need for a savior who would release them from their spiritual poverty.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "لأبشر المساكين بالروح" الذين تمسكنوا من غنى الله لأنهم لما أخطأوا وتسلط عليهم إبليس أفقرهم ومنعهم من النعيم المستديم. وقد شعروا باحتياجهم إلى من ينقذهم من فقرهم الروحي.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “He has sent Me to heal the brokenhearted” who were distraught because of their sins. The Lord heals them of their iniquities.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "وأرسلني لأشفي منكسري القلوب" الذين انسحقوا على خطاياهم فمثل هؤلاء يبرئهم المسيح من آثامهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “To proclaim liberty to the captives” to liberate their souls from the captivity of Satan and sin.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            و"لأنادي للمأسورين بالإطلاق" فيطلق نفوسهم من عبودية الشيطان والخطيئة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And the opening of the prison to those who are bound.” Not only does the Lord restore the sight to the blind in the flesh but also to those blinded by sin and ignorance.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "وللعمى بالبصر" فإنه له المجد يهب البصر للعميان بالجسد ويهب بالأخص البصيرة للعميان بالجهل والخطيئة"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He delivers those chained to idolatry and satanic practices, who are fettered by evil, astray from God’s knowledge. Because of their sins, they fell under a heavy weight which crushed them and remained there until Christ came and released them.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأرسل المنسحقين في الحرية" فهو ينقذ الذين كانوا مقيدين بقيود عبادة الأوثان والأغلال الشيطانية التي قيدهم بها عدو الخير فأبعدهم عن معرفة الله وقد صاروا من جراء خطاياهم كأنهم تحت حمل ثقيل وقع عليهم فسحقهم وظلوا هكذا حتى جاء المسيح وأطلقهم منها".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “To proclaim the acceptable year of the Lord.” The year in which the Lord was offered as a Holy sacrifice on the cross is the acceptable year to God for the salvation of mankind. The Jews referred to this year as the Jubilee: every fifty years they would blow their horns throughout the Jewish land, calling that every Jew enslaved because of debt or other is freed, and every plot of land taken from its original owner be returned to him again, so that all those of the house of Israel would continue to own what God gave them through Moses and Joshua.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأنادي بسنة مقبولة للرب "أن السنة التي رفع فيها سيدنا ضحية زكية على خشبة الصليب هو السنة المقبولة عند الله لخلاص البشر وكان يشار إليها عند اليهود بسنة اليوبيل وهي كل سنة تكمل الخمسين فقد كانوا في تلك السنة ينفخون في الأبواق في كل بلاد اليهودية وينادون بأن كل يهودي استعبد بسبب دين أو غيره يحرر وكل قطعة أرض انتقلت من ملك صاحبها الأصلي ترجع إلى ربها ليملك كل بيت من إسرائيل ما قسم الله له بيد موسى ويشوع.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The year of the Jubilee refers to the works of Christ because He delivered us from condemnation and enslavement to the enemy by His glorious coming and His humility towards the poor of His people and His invitation to them in particular. His great love has ended with His self-sacrifice and restoring our inheritance of the virtue, God’s acceptance and eternal heaven, which we had lost.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وما أحسن أن تكون سنة اليوبيل المشار إليها إشارة ورموزاً إلى عمل المسيح فإنه قد أنقذنا من الهلاك ومن سبي العدو بإتيانه المجيد وحسن تواضعه لفقراء شعبه ودعوته إياهم خواصه ومحبته العظيمة التي انتهى فيها أن يفدينا بنفسه وأرجع لنا ما فقدناه من ميراث البر ورضا الله والفردوس السماوي.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “And the day of vengeance of our God “`on His adversaries’”. He said, “To comfort all who mourn” for the suffering of the faithful in this life of persecution. Their mourning will turn into rejoicing when they inherit the kingdom of heaven.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وبيوم انتقام لإلهنا "من مبغضيه" قال: "وأعزي جميع النائحين" يعني بالنوح عن حزن المؤمنين في هذه الحياة الدنيا من جرى الاضطهادات التي تنتابهم ولكن هذا النوع سيتحول إلى فرح حيثما يرثون في المجد السمائي.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The disciples sorrowed and mourned when Christ was crucified. But their lamentation turned into joy when they saw the Lord after His resurrection from the dead. He had already told them, “Most assuredly, I say to you that you will weep and lament, but the world will rejoice; and you will be sorrowful, but your sorrow will be turned into joy…. Therefore you now have sorrow; but I will see you again and your heart will rejoice, and your joy no one will take from you.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقد حزن التلاميذ وناحوا وقت صلب السيد المسيح. ولكن هذا الحزن وهذا النواح قد تحولا إلى فرح حينما رأوا السيد بعد قيامته من بين الأموات. وقد سبق فقال لهم: "إنكم ستبكون وتنوحون والعالم يفرح. أنتم ستحزنون ولكن حزنكم يتحول إلى فرح … عندكم الآن حزن ولكني سأراكم أيضا فتفرح قلوبكم ولا ينزع أحد فرحكم معكم"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “To console those who mourn in Zion, to give them beauty for ashes.” The Jews used to express profound sorrow and mourning by sitting in ashes and covering their face with dust. When the reason for their grief ceases, they rejoice, wash, put on perfume and wear soft garments.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لأجعل لنائحي صهيون مجداً عوضاً عن الرماد" يعني بما أن علامة الحزن الشديد عند الإسرائيليين وغيرهم قديماً كانت بافتراش الرماد وتعفير الوجه بالتراب وعند زوال الحزن بزوال دواعيه، يصير لهم الفرح التام ويغنون ويتضمخون بالأطياب والثياب الناعمة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            The Lord will take away the grief of the faithful and dress them in everlasting garments of glory. “The oil of joy for mourning.” He compensated their tears with the oil of heavenly joy.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            هكذا يعني الرب أنه ينزع حزن المؤمنين ويسربلهم بثياب المجد السرمدي. قال: "ودهن فرح بدل النوح". يعني يعوضهم عن دموع النوح بدهن الفرح السمائي.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “The garment of praise for the spirit of heaviness.” Misery will be replaced by rejoicing in the kingdom of God “That they may be called trees of righteousness, The planting of the Lord.” The word ‘trees’ refers to those who believe in His holy name because they bear the fruits of virtue unlike the unfaithful who are barren and will be cast in hell as unfruitful trees are cast in fire.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وحلة التسبيح بدل الروح البائسة" يعني بدل ثياب البؤس حلل التهليل في ملكوته القدسية. قال: "فيدعون جيل الأبرار أغراساً للرب يتمجد بها" يعني عن المؤمنين باسمه القدوس ودعاهم بالأغراس المثمرة إشارة إلى ثمر الفضيلة المطلوب منهم بعكس الغير المثمرين فإنهم يطرحون في جهنم كما تطرح الأشجار الغير مثمرة في النار.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “That He may be glorified." He will be glorified by His saints who are a bearing vine on earth feeding the famished. “By this My Father is glorified, that you bear much fruit”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وقوله: "يتمجد بها" يعني أنه يتمجد في أفواه قديسيه الذين يكونون في الأرض كالكروم المثمرة يتغذى من ثمارها كل جائع. كما قال له المجد: "بهذا يتمجد أبي أن تأتوا بثمر كثير"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And they shall rebuild the old ruins They shall raise up the former desolations And they shall repair the ruined cities” The saints renewed the hearts of the nations which had been enslaved by Satan through idolatry until they neglected their maker and their hearts became barren of His holy name.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ويشيدون مدمرات القدم. ويجددون المدن الخربة" يعني أن الأمم الذين تملكهم الشيطان وآمالهم إلى عبادة الأوثان حتى صارت نفوسهم قفرة من معرفة خالقهم وأرض قلوبهم جدباء من ذكر اسمه تعالى         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            After they accepted faith in God they became like inhabited cities, full homes and fruitful lands. “Strangers shall stand and feed your flocks, And the sons of the foreigner Shall be your plowmen and your vinedressers.” The Gentiles knew God through the disciples and some of them became patriarchs, priests and shepherds to the flock, removing their thorns and planting the word of God in its place.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قد جدد الرسل قلوبهم وأصبحوا بعد الإيمان بالله جل اسمه يشبهون المدن العامرة والبيوت الآهلة. والأرض الخصبة" وتأتي الغرباء ويرعون غنمهم والقبائل الغريبة يكونون لهم حراثين وكرامين" يعني أنه بواسطة الرسل آمن الأمم وصار منهم بطاركة وقسوساً ورعاة يرعون رعيتهم فينزعون منك الشوك. ويزرعون عوضه الزرع الجيد الذي هو كلام الله.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “But you shall be named the priests of the Lord, they shall call you the servants of our God.” If the shepherds teach their flock as above, then they will truly be called the priests of the Most High and His servants.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أما أنتم فتدعون كهنة الرب وخدام الله" يعني إذا علم الرعاة الرعية وعلموا معها ما ذكرنا آنفاً فإنهم يدعون بحق كهنة الله وخدامه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “You shall eat the riches of the Gentiles, and in their glory you shall boast.” When the nations accepted faith they inherited the share of the Jews who did not believe. You will rejoice in reigning with Christ forever         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "عوضاً عن حزنكم وخزيكم تناولن ميراثاً دائماً في أرضهم وتأخذون نصيبهم" يعني إلى دخول الأمم إلى الإيمان وإرثهم نصيب الإسرائيليين الذين لم يؤمنوا. قال: "ويكون لكم الفرح" بملككم الدائم مع السيد المسيح         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Glory be to Him Forever Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي له المجد دائماً أبدياً. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>       </Document>