<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation – Job 27:1-28:13         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير – أيوب 27: 1-28: 1         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “As God lives, who has taken away my justice.” Job swears by the Lord who has inflicted these trials on him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "حي هو الرب الذي حكم علىَّ هكذا" أقسم الصديق بالرب الذي بلاه بهذه التجارب.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And the Almighty, who has made my soul bitter” because of his battles with the devils and the ideas that they put in his head, which saddened him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "والضابط الكل الذي أحزن نفسي" من جرى مقاتلة الشياطين له وما كانوا يوسوسون له من الأفكار التي تحزن نفسه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “As long as my breath is in me, And the breath of God in my nostrils,” despite all the calamities that befell him and which could have caused the death of another person, he will not use his mouth to utter profanities.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أنه مادامت نسمتي فيَّ وروح القدس في أنفي" رغم البلايا التي حاقت به التي بأقل منها بكثير جداً كان الإنسان يفارق الحياة الدنيا.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “My lips will not speak wickedness” He will not lie and will not renounce his faith in God whether in health or in disaster.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لن تنطق شفتاي إثماً" يعني لم يتكلم بغية كلاماً ردياً. ولم يكذب ولم يكفر بالله تعالى لا في حال الصحة ولا في حال البلوى.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Nor my tongue utter deceit.” Evil thought will not overpower him and the wile of the devil did not bring him close to sin.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ولا تتلو نفسي ظلماً" أي أن نفسه من نقاوتها لم تقو عليها الأفكار الشريرة ولا تمكنت حيل الشيطان أن تدنو منها لترميها في الخطيئة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Job did not utter this to show off but to teach those who come after him so if they hear or read about his calamities they would not think that it was a punishment from God for his sins. Unlike David, whose house was given to Absalom, his son, when he sinned.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولم يقل الصديق هذا افتخاراً بل تعليماً لمن هو يصده حتى إذا قرأ أحد أو سمع ببلواه لا يظن أنه بالخطيئة أبلاه الرب بهذا كما فعل بداود لما أخطأ إذ أسلم بيته في يد أبشالوم ابنه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Job prophesied about the incarnation of our God. His prophecy agreed with Peter’s description of the Lord, “Who committed no sin, Nor was deceit found in His mouth”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وأيضا أن النبوة سبقت فنطقت على فم الصديق لأجل تجسد الإله. وطابقت ما ذكره بطرس الرسول عن السيد المسيح بقوله: "الذي لم يفعل خطيئة ولا وجد في فمه مكر"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Far be it from me That I should say you are right” he said to those who want to do good seeking vainglory and wished Job to praise them.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "حاشاي أن أبرركم إلى الآن" يعني أن الذين يعملون الخير لطلب المجد الباطل وكانوا يريدون من الصديق أن يمدحهم على ذلك فكانت القوة التي فيه تعرفه أنهم ليسوا بأبرار.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Till I die I will not put away my integrity from me. My righteousness I hold fast, and will not let it go,” which means that he rebuked the sinners, but they did not accept it and ridiculed him calling him ignorant. As Solomon the Wise once said, “Do not correct a scoffer, lest he hate you” as if he is telling them you hate me because I rebuke you yet I will not cease and will not stop speaking the truth.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لا أقلع عن كمالي وقد تمسكت بالبر فلا أرخيه" يعني بهذا أنه كان يبكت الأشرار ولكنهم لم يقبلوا منه بل كانوا يستهزئون عليه ويسمونه جاهلاً كما قال سليمان الحكيم: "لا توبخ مستهزئاً لئلا يبغضك" فكأنه يقول لهم أنتم تبغضوني لتوبيخي لكم أما أنا فلا أقلع عن كمالي ولا أسكت عن الحق.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “My heart shall not reproach me as long as I live” I am not a hypocrite and I am not ashamed of rebuking those who do not follow the path of the Lord.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ولست أعرف أني فعلت شيئاً من الشر أو الظلم" أي أني لا أعرف المراءاة ولا أستحي من توبيخ الذين هم سائرون في غير طريق الله تعالى.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “May my enemy be like the wicked” referring to his adversaries the devils who asked the Lord that they may have power over his body, and hoping that he will not lose faith in God because of the weight of the disasters that befell him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "فليكن سقوط أعدائي الشياطين، فإنهم لما سألوا الله تعالى أن يسلطهم على جسده زعماً منهم أنه يكفر بالله من ثقل الشدة التي تحل به. فلما عاينوا منه ما هو عليه من الصبر الجميل والجهاد الحسن. سقطوا وافتضحوا وصاروا كالمنافقين.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            But when they observed his perseverance, they fell and revealed themselves as hypocrites. David described the hypocrites as the chaff which the wind drives away. The same happened to the devils; who were driven away like chaff.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وبما أن داود النبي قد شبه المنافقين بالعصافة التي تذريها الريح فهكذا اضمحلت الشياطين من أمام الصديق كالعصافة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “For what is the hope of the hypocrite.” If the sinner dies in his sins, he has no hope in Christ and does not deserve mercy, because he did not repent before death.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ما هو رجاء المنافق" يعني بهذا أن الخاطئ إذا مات في الخطايا فليس له رجاء بالرب ولا يستحق رحمة لأنه لم يرجع عن خطاياه قبل الموت.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Will God hear his cry When trouble comes upon him?  Will he delight himself in the Almighty?” God does not listen to those addicted to sin as He said through Isaiah, “But your iniquities have separated you from your God; And your sins have hidden His face from you, So that He will not hear.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أفيسمع الرب صلاته أو إذا نزل عليه ضيق هل يجد دالة أمامه" يعني أن الله لا يسمع للخطاة المدمنين على الخطيئة كما قال على لسان أشعياء النبي: "آثامكم صارت فاصلة بينكم وبين إلهكم وخطاياكم سترت وجهه عنكم حتى لا يسمع"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “I will teach you about the hand of God; What is with the Almighty I will not conceal” When he warned the sinners and they did not heed he warned them of their recompense before God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "بل إني أعرفكم بما في يدي الرب ولا أكذب بما هو عند الضابط الكل" يعني أنه لما نهى الأشرار ولم ينتهوا قال لهم ماذا يكون جزاؤهم قدام الله.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Surely all of you have seen it; Why then do you behave with complete nonsense? This is the portion of a wicked man with God” As long as the hypocrite insists on his ways he has no share in heaven. The share that he hopes for is false because he is alienated from God and will be eternally cast in Hades.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "هو ذا كلكم تعلمون أنه باطلاً هو نصيب الإنسان المنافق من قبل الرب" وبالحقيقة أنه مادام المنافق مصراً على نفاقه فلا نصيب له في النعيم والنصيب الذي يرجوه فهو باطل لأنه بعد من الله وخلود في الجحيم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And the heritage of oppressors, received from the Almighty” The oppressors are the atheist kings who are moved by God to take the sinners captive.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ونصيب الأقوياء يأتي عليه من الضابط الكل" ويعني بالأقوياء الملوك الكفرة الذين يسلطهم الله تعالى على الخطاة فيسبونهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “If his children are multiplied, it is for the sword.” The Lord throws his children in front of them to rebuke them.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "إن كثر بنوه فللذبح" يعني أنه يقصف أولادهم قدامهم ليبكتهم بهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Those who survive him shall be buried in death” God will kill the hypocrite, destroy his offspring and his cattle.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وبقيته تموت موتاً" يعني أن الله تعالى يرسل على المنافق موت الفجأة لأولاده ويحق ماشيته أيضا بالفناء.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And their widows shall not weep” God will harden the hearts of the people towards them until God’s wrath is spent.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وأراملهم لا يحرمهم أحد" يعني أن الله تعالى يقسي قلوب الناس عليهم حتى يبلغ منهم غضب الله.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Though he heaps up silver like dust, And piles up clothing like clay He may pile it up, but the just will wear it, And the innocent will divide the silver” The Lord will take away their riches and reward it to whom He loves as He ordered the Jews to take the Egyptians’ money when they fled from Egypt.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "جمعوا الفضة كالتراب وأعدوا الذهب كالطين هذه جميعها ينالها الصديقون. ويرث أهل البيت أمواله" يعني أن الله تعالى ينزع مالهم منهم ويعطيه لمن يحب وكذلك أمر بني إسرائيل أن يأخذوا أموال المصريين وقت خروجهم من مصر.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “The rich man will lie down, But not be gathered up; He opens his eyes, And he is no more,” describing the death of the stingy rich man who will not see the kingdom of God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "يضطجع ولا يعود يفتح عينيه ولا يكون" يعني بهذا عن موت الغني البخيل. فإنه من يعاين ملكوت الله.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Terrors overtake him like a flood;” when his late repentance torments him. He will continue in his suffering and sighing as a man drowned in the deep sea.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لتدركه الأهوال كالطوفان" يعني أنه بعد موته يكون معذباً بأفكاره نادماً على ما فاته منه ولات ساعة مندم. بل يبقى غاطساً في الآلام والتنهد كمن هو غارق في لجج المياه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “A tempest steals him away in the night, the east wind carries him away, and he is gone; It sweeps him out of his place.” ‘The tempest’ is the darkness of hell and the ‘East wind’ is the heat of his torture. “And shall hiss him out of his place” After death there is no mercy shown to sinners.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وفي الليل يحمله الضباب وتأخذه السموم فيذهب وتقتلعه من مقره مهاناً منبوذاً" ويعني بالضباب إلى ظلمة الجحيم. وبالسموم إلى شدة حرارة عذابات جهنم. قال: "ولا يشفق عليه" أي أنه لم يكن بعد الموت رحمة للخطاة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “He breaks open a shaft away from people; In places forgotten by feet They hang far away from men;” those who violated the law lose their humanity because they proceeded in animals’ footsteps.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "والذين نسوا البر ضعفوا من البشر" يعني أن الذين يخرجون من ناموس الشريعة فيسقطون من بشريتهم لأنهم تبعوا البهائم في سيرتها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “As for the earth, from it comes bread” The ‘earth’ refers to heaven and the ‘bread’ is the praise and glory as David said, “Men ate angels' food; He sent them food to the full.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "والأرض التي تأتي بالخبز" يعني بالأرض إلى الملكوت وبالخبز إلى التسبيح والتمجيد كما قال داود النبي: "أكل الإنسان خبز الملائكة"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “But underneath it is turned up as by fire,” the ‘fire’ refers to Hades where the sinners will reside.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ينقلب أسفلها كما بالنار" ويعني بالنار إلى الهاوية. موضع عذاب الخطاة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Its stones are the source of sapphires, And it contains gold dust,” referring to the honor of heaven as John the apostle has described the heavenly Jerusalem and its riches in the book of Revelation.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "حجارتها هي موضع الياقوت وفيها تراب الذهب" هذا على كرامة الملكوت كما قال يوحنا الإنجيلي في رؤياه على أورشليم السمائية وما فيها من الجواهر وغيرها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “That path no bird knows, Nor has the falcon's eye seen it.” The path is that of the virtuous, unknown to sinners because it is beyond their comprehension and their near sightedness.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "سبيل لم يعرفه طير ولم تنظره عين باشق" يعني بالسبيل إلى طريق الصديقين الذي لا يعرفه الأشرار لعلوه عن أفكارهم وقصر نظرهم عن رؤيته.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “The proud lions have not trodden it, Nor has the fierce lion passed over it.” Only the humble were informed of it. None of the kings of the earth will be able to achieve it with his army or his wealth for it can only be achieved through obedience and faithfulness to God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ولم يطأه بنو المتكبرين" فلم يخطر به إلا المتواضعون. قال: "ولم يسلكه الأسد" يعني أنه لا يستطيع أحد من ملوك الأرض أن يناله بقوة ماكرة ولا يبذل أمواله. بل بطاعة الله تعالى. والإيمان به.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “He puts his hand on the flint.” The ‘flint’ is Jerusalem where God extended his hand on the cross outside it.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "إلى الزاوية يمد يده" ويشير بالزاوية إلى أورشليم التي مد يده على الصليب خراجها.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “He overturns the mountains at the roots.” The ‘mountains’ are the unbelieving kings and leaders who, when they witnessed the miracles, the power of the devil within them was diminished and began to follow Christ.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ويهدم الجبال من أساساتها" يعني بذلك عن الملوك والحكام الغير المؤمنين الذي لما عاينوا الآيات والعجائب انكسرت قوة الشيطان التي فيهم وانصاعوا إلى الإيمان بالمسيح.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “He cuts out channels in the rocks.” The teachings of the Lord of the living water overturned the teachings of Satan to mankind; as a pitcher of foul water is emptied on the ground.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ويقلب قوة الأنهار" ويعني بذلك عن التعاليم النجسة التي سقاها الشيطان للبشر كالماء فإن تعاليم الرب المحيية قد قلبتها كما يقلب الإناء الملأ بالماء الأسن إلى الأرض.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And His eye sees every precious thing What is hidden he brings forth to light” the Lord revealed to the faithful all that was hidden of spiritual truths through the inspiration of the Holy Spirit.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وأظهر لهم كل فعل جليل ورأته أعينهم وكشف قوته نوراً" يعني بهذا أنه أظهر للمؤمنين به ما كان مخفياً عنهم من العلوم الروحانية بإلهام الروح القدس.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “But where can wisdom be found? And where is the place of understanding?” referring to the unbelievers who did not know the way of salvation and did not recognize the path to heaven. They were not born of light.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أما الحكمة فأين توجد وأين مقر الفهم. ولا يعرف الإنسان الطريق ولا وجود لهما في البشر" يعني بهذا عن الغير مؤمنين. فإنهم لم يعرفوا طريق الخلاص. ولم يسلكوا مسالك توصلهم إلى الملكوت. لأنهم لم يولدوا من النور.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Let us ask our Lord Jesus Christ to enlighten our minds so that we may walk in His ways.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فنسأل ربنا يسوع المسيح أن يضيء عقولنا لنسلك في طرقه         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Glory Be to God Forever Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            له المجد إلى الأبد. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>       </Document>