<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" pascha="true" fixeddatedocument="true">   <forceseason id="Fasts ^ PaschaWeek ^ WatosDays ^ Weekdays ^ Wednesdays ^ FuneralTune ^ SeasonOfAirAndFruits">      <Title>         <language id="English">Wednesday Eve (The Sixth Hour)</language><language id="Indonesian">Malam Hari Rabu (Jam Keenam )</language>         <language id="Arabic">ليلة الأربعاء (الساعة السادسة)</language>         <language id="Coptic">Pie~jwrh m~Pf~tou (}ajp 6)</language>      </Title>            <role id="Priest">         <insertdocument path="include/KhenEfranAmen"/>                  <text>            <language id="English">               The prophecies of the Sixth Hour of the eve of Wednesday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Nubuat-nubuat dari Jam Keenam  Malam Hari Rabu pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نبوات الساعة السادسة، من ليلة الأربعاء من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Jeremiah 13:9, 16:9-13</language><language id="Indonesian">Yeremia 13:9, 16:9-13</language>               <language id="Arabic">أرميا 13: 9, 16: 9-13</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/prophecyIntro/Jeremiah"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nai ne n/e~tefjw m~mwou n~je P[oic n~te nijom Vnou] n~te p~Icra/l:               </language>               <language id="English">                  "Thus says the Lord: 'In this manner I will destroy the insolence of Judah and that of Jerusalem.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Beginilah firman TUHAN: Demikianlah Aku akan menghapuskan kecongkakbongakan Yehuda dan Yerusalem.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  هذا ما يقوله رب القوات إله اسرائيل: هأنذا أفسد كبرياء يهوذا وكبرياء أورشليم               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je ich/ppe a~nok ]natako e~bolqen paima mpem~yo n~netenbal e~bol: ouoh n~h~r/iqen netene~hoou n~ne ouc~m/ n~ounof nem ouc~m/ n~rasi swpi: t~c~m/ n~oupatsel/t nem oucm/ n~selet:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Behold, before your eyes and in your days, I will bring to an end from this place the voice of joy and the voice of gladness, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebab beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam, Allah Israel: Sesungguhnya, di tempat ini, di depan matamu dan pada zamanmu, akan Kuhentikan suara kegirangan dan suara sukacita, suara pengantin laki-laki dan suara pengantin perempuan.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  العظيمة في هذا المكان أمام عيونكم وفي أيامكم لا يكون صوت سرور ولا صوت فرح ولا صوت عريس ولا صوت عروس،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh ece~swpi aksantame pai laoc e~nai caji t/rou ouoh eue~joc nak je eybeou a~P[oic caji e~h~r/i e~jwn n~nai pethwou t/rou.               </language>               <language id="English">                  "It shall come to pass that when you shall announce all these words to this people and they say to you, 'Why has the Lord pronounced all these evils against us?               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Apabila engkau memberitahukan kepada bangsa ini segala perkataan itu dan mereka berkata kepadamu: Mengapakah TUHAN mengancamkan segala malapetaka yang besar ini terhadap kami?               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ويكون إذا عرفت الشعب بجميع هذه الأقوال وقالوا: لماذا تكلم الرب علينا بكل هذه الشرور،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ie as pe pi[in~jonc: ie v~nobi e~tanaif m~pem~yo e~bol m~P[oic Pennou]:                </language>               <language id="English">                  What is our wrongdoing, and what sin did we commit before the Lord our God?'                </language><language id="Indonesian">Apakah kesalahan kami dan apakah dosa yang telah kami lakukan terhadap TUHAN, Allah kami?,                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وما الظلم أو الخطية التي صنعناها أمام الرب إلهنا؟                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eke~joc nwou: je eybe je a~netenio] ,at n~cwou peje P[oic:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then you shall say to them, 'Because your fathers forsook Me,' says the Lord,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  maka engkau akan berkata kepada mereka: Oleh karena nenek moyangmu telah meninggalkan Aku, demikianlah firman TUHAN,                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فتقول لهم، لأن أباءكم تركوني عنهم قال الرب،                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh aumosi cavahou n~ninou] n~semmwou auerbwk nwou                </language>               <language id="English">                  'For they went after foreign gods; and they served and worshiped them.               </language><language id="Indonesian">dan oleh karena mereka telah mengikuti allah lain dengan beribadah dan sujud menyembah kepadanya,               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وأتبعوا آلهة غريبة وعبدوها وسجدوا لها،                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh auouwst m~mwou a~nok de au,at n~cwou: ouoh panomoc m~poua~reh e~rof:               </language>               <language id="English">                  They forsook Me, and did not keep My law.               </language><language id="Indonesian">tetapi mereka meninggalkan Aku dan tidak berpegang pada Taurat-Ku.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وأما أنا فتركوني عنهم ولم يحفظوا ناموسي                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nywten hwten atetenerpethwou ehote netenio]. Ic h/ppe n~ywten hwten e~retenmosi v~ouai v~ouai cavahou n~niouws n~te netenh/t ethwou e~s~tem y~reten cwtem n~cwi:               </language>               <language id="English">                  But you acted in ways more evil than your fathers; for behold, you, each one of you, walk after the evil pleasures of your heart and do not obey Me.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan kamu sendiri berlaku lebih jahat dari pada nenek moyangmu! Lihat, kamu masing-masing mengikuti kedegilan hatinya yang jahat dari pada mendengarkan kepada-Ku.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وقد عملتم أنتم أيضاً الشر أكثر من أبائكم، فهوذا أنتم أيضاً تسلكون كل واحد وراء شهوات قلوبكم الشريرة غير مطيعين لي,               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh ]nahiy/nou e~bolqen pai kahi eoukahi e~retencwoun m~mof an n~ywten nem netenio] ouoh qen pima e~te m~mau: eretene~erbwk e~hankenou]: nai e~te n~cenanai nwten an.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Therefore I will cast you out of this land and into a land neither you nor your fathers know; and there you shall serve other gods, who will show you no mercy.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Maka Aku akan melemparkan kamu dari negeri ini ke negeri yang tidak dikenal oleh kamu ataupun oleh nenek moyangmu. Di sana kamu akan beribadah kepada allah lain siang malam, sebab Aku tidak akan menaruh kasihan lagi kepadamu.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فساطرد كم من هذه الأرض، إلي أرض لا تعرفونها أنتم ولا أبائكم, وفي ذلك الموضع تتعبدون لألهة أخري، هؤلاء الذين لا يرحمونكم.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ProphecyConclusion"/>         </section>      </role>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Introduction to the Paschal Praise</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Pendahuluan Pujian Paskah</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">مقدمة تسبحة البصخة</language>         </Title>               <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PropheciesConclusion"/>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The doxology of the Sixth Hour of the eve of Wednesday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi dari Jam Keenam  Malam Hari Rabu pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  تسبحة الساعة السادسة، من ليلة الأربعاء من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="include/LordsPrayerNoTitle"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/Doxology.2"/>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Psalm 102:1-2</language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur 102:1-2</language>               <language id="Arabic">مزمور 102: 1-2</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PsalmOfDavid"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  P[oic cwtem e~ta p~roceu,/: mare paq~rwou i~ e~p~swi m~pekm~yo.                </language>               <language id="English">                  Hear my prayer, O Lord, and let my cry come to You.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  TUHAN, dengarkanlah doaku, dan biarlah teriakku minta tolong sampai kepada-Mu.                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يارب استمع صلاتي وليصعد أمامك صراخي                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Qen pie~hoou e~]naws e~p~swi oub/k n~q/tf: ,wlem cwtem e~roi: all/louia.               </language>               <language id="English">                  In the day when I call upon You, hear me quickly. Alleluia.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sendengkanlah  telinga-Mu kepadaku; pada hari aku berseru, segeralah menjawab aku! . Alleluia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  في اليوم الذي أدعوك فيه أستجب لي سريعاً. الليلويا.               </language>            </text>         </section>      </role>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Matthew 25:1-13</language><language id="Indonesian">Matius 25:1-13</language>            <language id="Arabic">متى 25: 1-13</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/KeEperto"/>         <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroMatthew"/>         <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Tote c~o~ni n~je ]metouro n~te niv/oui m~m/] m~paryenoc nai e~tau[i n~noulampac aui~ e~bol e~h~ren pipatselet:               </language>               <language id="English">                  “Then the kingdom of heaven shall be likened to ten virgins who took their lamps and went out to meet the bridegroom.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Pada waktu itu hal Kerajaan Sorga seumpama sepuluh gadis, yang mengambil pelitanya dan pergi menyongsong mempelai laki-laki.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  حينئذ يشبه ملكوت السموات عشر عذارى اخذن مصابيحهن وخرجن للقاء العريس               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ne cuon t~iou de n~coj n~q/tou nem tiou n~cab/: Nicoj gar e~tau[i n~noulampac. mpouel neh nemwou. Nicabeu de auel neh n~q~r/i qen noumoki nem noulampac:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Now five of them were wise, and five were foolish. Those who were foolish took their lamps and took no oil with them, but the wise took oil in their vessels with their lamps.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Lima di antaranya bodoh dan lima bijaksana. Gadis-gadis yang bodoh itu membawa pelitanya, tetapi tidak membawa minyak, sedangkan gadis-gadis yang bijaksana itu membawa pelitanya dan juga minyak dalam buli-buli mereka.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكان خمس منهن جاهلات وخمس حكيمات اما الجاهلات فأخذن مصابيحهن ولم يأخذن معهن زيتا واما الحكيمات فأخذن زيتا فى انيتهن مع مصابيحهن               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Etafwck de n~je pipatselet auhi nim t/rou ouoh auenkot: E~ta t~vasi de mpie~jwrh swpi: a~ouq~rwou swpi je ic pipatselet afi~ teny/nou a~mwini e~bol e~h~raf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  But while the bridegroom was delayed, they all slumbered and slept. “And at midnight a cry was heard: ‘Behold, the bridegroom is coming; go out to meet him!’               </language><language id="Indonesian">Tetapi karena mempelai itu lama tidak datang-datang juga, mengantuklah mereka semua lalu tertidur. Waktu tengah malam terdengarlah suara orang berseru: Mempelai datang! Songsonglah dia!</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلما ابطا العريس نعسن كلهن ونمن ففى نصف الليل صار صوت: هوذا العريس قد اقبل فقمن اخرجن للقائه               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Tote autwounou n~je niparyenoc t/rou e~tem~mau ouoh aucolcel n~noulampac:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then all those virgins arose and trimmed their lamps.                </language><language id="Indonesian">Gadis-gadis itupun bangun semuanya lalu membereskan pelita mereka.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  حينئذ قامت اولئك العذارى وزين مصابيحهن،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Peje nicoj de n~nicabeu je moi nan ebolqen petenneh je nenlampac na[e~no:               </language>               <language id="English">                  And the foolish said to the wise, ‘Give us some of your oil, for our lamps are going out.’               </language><language id="Indonesian">Gadis-gadis yang bodoh berkata kepada gadis-gadis yang bijaksana: Berikanlah kami sedikit dari minyakmu itu, sebab pelita kami hampir padam.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فقالت الجاهلاتٍ للحكيمات: اعطينا من زيتكن فان مصابيحنا تنطفى               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Aue~rouw~ de n~je nicabeu eujwm~moc: je m/pote n~tefs~tem rasten nemwten: masenwten de mallon ha n/et] e~bol ouoh swp nwten.               </language>               <language id="English">                  But the wise answered, saying, ‘No, lest there should not be enough for us and you; but go rather to those who sell, and buy for yourselves.’               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tetapi jawab gadis-gadis yang bijaksana itu: Tidak, nanti tidak cukup untuk kami dan untuk kamu. Lebih baik kamu pergi kepada penjual minyak dan beli di situ.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فاجابت الحكيمات وقلن: لعله لا يكفينا واياكن فاذهبن بالاحرى الى الباعة وابتعن لكن               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Etausenwou de je n~touswp: afi n~je pipatselet ouoh n/etcebtwt ausenwou nemaf e~qoun e~ pihop ouoh aumasyam m~piro:               </language>               <language id="English">                  And while they went to buy, the bridegroom came, and those who were ready went in with him to the wedding; and the door was shut.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Akan tetapi, waktu mereka sedang pergi untuk membelinya, datanglah mempelai itu dan mereka yang telah siap sedia masuk bersama-sama dengan dia ke ruang perjamuan kawin, lalu pintu ditutup.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلما ذهبن ليبتعن جاء العريس ودخلت معه المستعدات الى العرس واغلق الباب               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ep~qae~ de aui n~je p~cwjp n~niparyenoc eujwm~moc: je Pen[oic Pen[oic aouwn nan:                </language>               <language id="English">                  “Afterward the other virgins came also, saying, ‘Lord, Lord, open to us!’                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Kemudian datang juga gadis-gadis yang lain itu dan berkata: Tuan, tuan, bukakanlah kami pintu!                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وأخيراً  جاءت بقية العذارى قائلات: ربنا ربنا افتح لنا                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  N~yof de aferouw~ pejaf je a~m/n ]jwm~mmoc nwten je ]cwoun m~mwten an: Rwic oun je tetencwoun an m~piehoou oude ]ounou.               </language>               <language id="English">                  But he answered and said, ‘Assuredly, I say to you, I do not know you.’ “Watch therefore, for you know neither the day nor the hour.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Tetapi ia menjawab: Aku berkata kepadamu, sesungguhnya aku tidak mengenal kamu. Karena itu, berjaga-jagalah, sebab kamu tidak tahu akan hari maupun akan saatnya."</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  اما هو فاجاب وقال: الحق اقول لكن اننى لا اعرفكن فاسهروا اذا لانكم لا تعرفون اليوم ولا الساعة.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/BowDownBeforeTheHolyGospel"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelConclusionEve"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Exposition</language><language id="Indonesian">Komentari</language>            <language id="Arabic">الطرح</language>         </Title>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The exposition of the Sixth Hour of the eve of Wednesday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Komentari dari Jam Keenam Malam Hari Rabu pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طرح الساعة السادسة، من ليلة الأربعاء من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  Behold these virtues and parables that our Lord of Glory Jesus the source of every grace and good—has told us; He who granted mankind to partake in His kingdom.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Perhatikanlah kebajikan dan</div><div>perumpamaan ini bahwa Raja</div><div>Kemuliaan kita, Yesus, sumber dari</div><div>setiap anugerah, kebaikan, dan kedamaian, telah  <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">memberitahukan kita. Dia </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">mengijinkan umat manusia untuk </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">mengambil bagian dalam</span></div><div>kerajaan-Nya. Dengarkanlah, <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">pikirkanlah,</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يا لهذه الفضائل وهذه الامثال التى قالها ملك المجد الذى هو يسوع ملك النعمة والخيرات المكمل السلام الذى انعم لجنس البشر بشركة ملكوته.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  Listen, think, and understand and know His blessed parables, for the sake of the prudent virgins who were mentioned in the Bible and were likened to his kingdom; full of joy and exultation.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>pahamilah dan ketahuilah mengenai <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">perumpamaan-Nya yang penuh </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">berkat. Gadis-gadis bijaksana yang </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">disebutkan Alkitab dan disamakan </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dengan kerajaan-Nya, penuh sukacita </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan kegembiraan.</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  اسمعوا وتأملوا وافهموا واعلموا أمثاله الطوباوية من اجل العذارى الحكيمات اللواتى نطق من أجلهن في الإنجيل  وشبههن بملكوته المملوء فرحا وسروراً.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  Ten virgins: five foolish and five wise, said the Lord. As He tells us, there was no distinction between them as virgins; but they differed in their deeds. Thus, He praised and blessed the wise five (virgins) because they were earnest and prudent.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div> "Ada sepuluh gadis, <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">lima bodoh dan lima bijaksana," kata Seperti yang Dia katakan kepada kita, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">tidak ada perbedaan di antara mereka </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">sebagai gadis; tetapi mereka berbeda</span></div><div>dalam perbuatan mereka. Karena itu <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Tuhan memuji dan memberkati lima </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">gadis yang bijak, tulus dan bijaksana.</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  عشر عذارى قال الرب خمس جاهلات وخمس حكيمات قال هؤلاء العشرة كن عذراى ولكنهن افترقن لاجل أعمالهن فطوب الحكيمات الفهيمات لانهن صنعن الحكمة بايجاد               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  They filled their lanterns with oil and kept the surplus in their containers. As for the foolish virgins, they were lackadaisical and did not prepare their lanterns.                </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Mereka mengisi lentera mereka</div><div>dengan minyak dan menyimpan</div><div>kelebihannya dalam wadah mereka.</div><div>Adapun gadis-gadis yang bodoh</div><div>mereka malas dan tidak menyiapkan <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">lentera mereka.</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وملأن مصابيحهن من الزيت واوعيتهن مما فضل عنهن فاما العذارى الجاهلات فتكاسلن ولم يفهمن قيمة مصابيحهن                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  When they all woke up at the given time to proceed with their procession ahead of the bridegroom, their lanterns became useless at the wedding time and were unable to accompany the bridegroom.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Ketika mereka semua bangun pada</div><div>waktu yang telah ditentukan untuk</div><div>berjalan dalam prosesi di depan</div><div>mempelai pria, lentera mereka</div><div>menjadi tidak berguna.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلما قمن جميعهن فى ساعة واحدة ليمشين قدام العريس تعطلت مصابيحهن وقت الفرح ولم يحضرن مع العريس               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  Those who were prepared, accompanied him to the wedding and the somnolent ones stayed outside.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>pada saat acara pernikahan dan</div><div>mereka tidak dapat <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">menemaninya.Mereka yang siap akan </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">menemaninya ke pesta pernikahan </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan orang-orang yang malas berdiri di </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">luar.</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  والمستعدات دخلن معه الى العرس والمتكاسلات وقفن خارجا.               </language>            </text>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ExpositionConclusion"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/EveningLitaniesAndConclusionLink"/>   </forceseason></document>