<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader" pascha="true" fixeddatedocument="true">   <forceseason id="Fasts ^ PaschaWeek ^ WatosDays ^ Weekdays ^ Wednesdays ^ FuneralTune ^ SeasonOfAirAndFruits">      <Title>         <language id="English">Wednesday Eve (The Third Hour)</language><language id="Indonesian">Malam Hari Rabu (Jam Ketiga )</language>         <language id="Arabic">ليلة الأربعاء (الساعة الثالثة)</language>         <language id="Coptic">Pie~jwrh m~Pf~tou (}ajp 3)</language>      </Title>            <role id="Priest">         <insertdocument path="include/KhenEfranAmen"/>                  <text>            <language id="English">               The prophecies of the Third Hour of the eve of Wednesday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Nubuat-nubuat dari Jam Ketiga Malam Hari Rabu pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نبوات الساعة الثالثة، من ليلة الأربعاء من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Amos 5:18-27</language><language id="Indonesian">Amos 5:18-27</language>               <language id="Arabic">عاموس 5: 18-27</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/prophecyIntro/Amos"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoi n~n/eter e~piyumin e~pie~hoou n~te P[oic: e~rou nwten e~pai. ehoou n~te P[oic: ouoh pai e~hoou n~ou,aki ouoh n~ouwini an pe: Mv~r/] afsanvwt n~je ourwmi e~bolha p~ho n~oumoui~ ouoh n~tec i~ ejwf n~je ou laboi:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Woe to you who desire the day of the Lord! What is the day of the Lord to you? It will be darkness and not light. It will be as though a man fled from a lion, and a bear met him!               </language><language id="Indonesian">Celakalah mereka yang menginginkan hari TUHAN! Apakah gunanya hari TUHAN itu bagimu? Hari itu kegelapan, bukan terang!  Seperti seseorang yang lari terhadap singa, seekor beruang mendatangi dia,              </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ويل للذين يشتهون يوم الرب ما بغيتكم في يوم الرب، فإن هذا اليوم ظلام لا نور, كما إذا هرب إنسان من وجه أسد فصادفته لبوة               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh n~tefvwt e~qoun e~pef/i ouoh n~teffai n~tef jij e~h~r/i e~jen ]joi n~tef jokhf n~je ouhof: M/ ou,aki an pe p~e~hoou m~P[oic: ouoh ououwinia~n pe oug~novoc pe m~mon tefmoue~.                </language>               <language id="English">                  As though he rushed into the house, leaned his hand on the wall, and a serpent bit him! Is not the day of the Lord darkness and not light? Is it not a deep darkness, with no brightness in it?                </language><language id="Indonesian">dan ketika ia sampai ke rumah, bertopang dengan tangannya ke dinding, seekor ular memagut dia! Bukankah hari TUHAN itu kegelapan dan bukan terang, kelam kabut dan tidak bercahaya?                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فيجيئ إلي بيته ويرفع يده علي الحائط فتلدغه حية، أليس يوم ظلام لا نور وضباب لا ضياء له؟                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Aimecte netensai ouoh ai,au n~cwi: oun~naswlem qen netennis] n~e~hoou n~sai:                </language>               <language id="English">                  "I hate, I reject your feast days. I do not savor your sacred assemblies.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Aku membenci, Aku menghinakan perayaanmu dan Aku tidak senang kepada perkumpulan rayamu.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لقد أبغضت أعيادكم ورذلتها ولست أشم رائحة في أيام أعيادكم العظيمة،                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je ou/i e~swp a~retensan i~ni n/i n~han[~lil nem hansouswousi n~]nasopou an: ouoh ]najoust an e~jen na pioujai n~te petenouwnh e~bol:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Though you offer Me burnt offerings and meat offerings, I will not accept them. I will not regard your fattened peace offerings.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sungguh, apabila kamu mempersembahkan kepada-Ku korban-korban bakaran dan korban-korban sajianmu, Aku tidak suka, dan korban keselamatanmu berupa ternak yang tambun, Aku tidak mau pandang.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إني إذا قربتم لي محرقاتكم وتقدماتكم لا أقبلها، ولست أنظر إلي فدية شكركم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Matacyo e~bolharoi mp~q~rwou n~nekhwd/: ouoh pi'almoc n~te nekorganon n~]nacwtem e~rof an:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Take away from Me the sound of your songs, for I will not hear your musical instruments.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Jauhkanlah dari pada-Ku keramaian nyanyian-nyanyianmu, lagu gambusmu tidak mau Aku dengar.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أبعد عني صوت تسابيحك، ومزمار أرغنك لست أسمعه،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh efe~c~kerker n~je ouhap m~v~r/] n~oumwou: ouoh ]meym/i m~v~r/] n~oumouncwrem n~aterjinior m~mof. M/ hanqolqel nem han souswousi a~retene~nou e~h~r/i n/i hip~safe nh~me n~rompi p~/i m~p~Icra/l peje P[oic:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Instead, let justice run swiftly as does water from the mountain, and let righteousness be as a stream that cannot be crossed. "O house of Israel, did you offer Me sacrifices and offerings those forty years in the wilderness? [Says the Lord.]               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tetapi biarlah keadilan bergulung-gulung seperti air dan kebenaran seperti sungai yang selalu mengalir. "Apakah kamu mempersembahkan kepada-Ku korban sembelihan dan korban sajian, selama empat puluh tahun di padang gurun itu, hai kaum Israel?               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وليجر القضاء كالماء والعدل كالوادي الذي لايعبر. هل قربتم لي ذبائح وتقدمات في البرية أربعين سنة يا بيت اسرائيل يقول الرب؟               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  A~reten[i n~]c~kun/ n~te Molo, nempiciou n~te petennou] Revan: nitupoc e~taretenyamiw~ou nwten.                </language>               <language id="English">                  You have carried the tabernacle of Moloch and the star of your god Raiphan, which you made for yourselves.                </language><language id="Indonesian">Kamu akan mengangkut Sakut, rajamu, dan Kewan, dewa bintangmu, patung-patungmu yang telah kamu buat bagimu itu,                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  بل حملتم خيمة ملوخ وكوكب إلهكم رافان التماثيل التي صنعتموها لكم,                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh eie~oue~teb y/nou e~bol cam~n/ n~Damackoc: peje P[oic Vnou] pipantokratwr pe pefran.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Therefore I shall exile you beyond Damascus," says the Lord—the Almighty God is His name.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div style="text-align: start;"><font color="#000000" face="Times New Roman">dan Aku akan membawa kamu ke dalam pembuangan jauh ke seberang Damsyik," firman TUHAN, yang nama-Nya Allah semesta alam.</font></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأسبيكم إلي ماوراء دمشق. قال الرب الإله الضابط الكل هو إسمه.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ProphecyConclusion"/>         </section>      </role>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Introduction to the Paschal Praise</language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Pendahuluan Pujian Paskah</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">مقدمة تسبحة البصخة</language>         </Title>               <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PropheciesConclusion"/>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The doxology of the Third Hour of the eve of Wednesday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi dari Jam Ketiga Malam Hari Rabu pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  تسبحة الساعة الثالثة، من ليلة الأربعاء من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="include/LordsPrayerNoTitle"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/Doxology.2"/>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Psalm 64:5</language><language id="Indonesian">Mazmur 65:5</language>               <language id="Arabic">مزمور 64: 5</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PsalmOfDavid"/>            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Wouniatf m~v/e~takcotpf ouoh aksopf e~rok: efe~swpi qen nekaul/ou sae~neh.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Blessed is he whom You choose and help; he shall dwell in Your courts.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Berbahagialah orang yang Engkau pilih dan yang Engkau suruh mendekat untuk diam di pelataran-Mu!               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طوبي لمن أخترته وقبلته ليسكن في ديارك إلي الأبد,               </language>            </text>            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  F~ouab n~je pekervei: ouoh foi n~s~v/ri qen oumeym/i: all/louia.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Holy is Your temple, wondrous in righteousness. Alleluia.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Kiranya kami menjadi kenyang dengan segala yang baik di rumah-Mu, di bait-Mu yang kudus. Alleluia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  قدوس هو هيكلك وعجيب بالبر. الليلويا.               </language>            </text>         </section>      </role>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Matthew 24:36-51</language><language id="Indonesian">Matius 24:36-51</language>            <language id="Arabic">متى 24: 36-51</language>         </Title>                  <insertdocument path="pascha/include/KeEperto"/>         <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroMatthew"/>         <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eybe pie~hoou de etem~mau nem ]ounou: m~mon hli e~mi e~rwou: oude niaggeloc n~te niv/oui: e~b/l e~Viwt m~mauatf:               </language>               <language id="English">                  “But of that day and hour no one knows, not even the angels of heaven, but My Father only.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tetapi tentang hari dan saat itu tidak seorangpun yang tahu, malaikat-malaikat di sorga tidak, dan Anakpun tidak, hanya Bapa sendiri."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وأما ذلك اليوم وتلك الساعة، فلا يعلمهما أحد ولا ملائكة السموات، إلا الآب وحده.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Mv~r/] gar n~nie~hoou n~te Nwe~: pair/] eynaswpi qen t~paroucia~ m~p~s/ri m~v~rwmi.               </language>               <language id="English">                  But as the days of Noah were, so also will the coming of the Son of Man be.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  "Sebab sebagaimana halnya pada zaman Nuh, demikian pula halnya kelak pada kedatangan Anak Manusia.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وكما كان في أيام نوح، كذلك يكون في ظهور إبن الإنسان،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                   Mv~r/] gar e~nausop qen nie~hoou etqajwf m~pikatak~lucmoc euouwm ouoh eucw: eu[ic~himi ouoh eu[ihai: sa pie~hoou e~ta Nwe~ senaf e~qoun e~]kubwtoc m~mof. Ouoh m~poue~mi satefi~ n~je pikatak~lucmoc ouoh n~tefel ouon niben: pair/] eynaswpi qen p~jini~ m~p~s/ri m~v~rwmi:               </language>               <language id="English">                  For as in the days before the flood, they were eating and drinking, marrying and giving in marriage, until the day that Noah entered the ark, and did not know until the flood came and took them all away, so also will the coming of the Son of Man be.                </language><language id="Indonesian">Sebab sebagaimana mereka pada zaman sebelum air bah itu makan dan minum, kawin dan mengawinkan, sampai kepada hari Nuh masuk ke dalam bahtera, dan mereka tidak tahu akan sesuatu, sebelum air bah itu datang dan melenyapkan mereka semua, demikian pulalah halnya kelak pada kedatangan Anak Manusia.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                   لأنه كما كانوا قبل أيام الطوفان يأكلون ويشربون ويتزوجون ويزوجون إلي اليوم الذي دخل فيه نوح إلي الفلك، ولم يعلموا حتي جاء الطوفان وغرق الجميع، كذلك يكون أيضاً مجيء إبن الإنسان.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Tote c~nau eu,/ qen t~koi: ouai eue~olf ouoh ouai eue~,af:               </language>               <language id="English">                  Then two men will be in the field: one will be taken and the other left.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Pada waktu itu kalau ada dua orang di ladang, yang seorang akan dibawa dan yang lain akan ditinggalkan;               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  حينئذٍ يكون إثنان في الحقل ويؤخذ الواحد ويترك الآخر               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                   Ouoh c~nou] eunout qen oueuni: oui~ eue~olc ouoh oui~ eue~,ac.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Two women will be grinding at the mill: one will be taken and the other left.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  kalau ada dua orang perempuan sedang memutar batu kilangan, yang seorang akan dibawa dan yang lain akan ditinggalkan.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وإثنتان تطحنان علي رحي، فتؤخذ الواحدة وتترك الأخرى.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Rwic oun je tetene~mi an je a~re peten[oic n/ou qen as n~ounou:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Watch therefore, for you do not know what hour your Lord is coming.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Karena itu berjaga-jagalah, sebab kamu tidak tahu pada hari mana Tuhanmu datang.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                   إسهروا إذا لأنكم لا تعلمون في أية ساعة يأتي ربكم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Vai de a~rie~mi e~rof: je e~nare pineb/i e~mi je a~re piconi n/ou naf qen as n~ounou: nafnarwic: hina n~tefstem,au e~[i m~pef/i:               </language>               <language id="English">                  But know this, that if the master of the house had known what hour the thief would come, he would have watched and not allowed his house to be broken into.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tetapi ketahuilah ini: Jika tuan rumah tahu pada waktu mana pada malam hari pencuri akan datang, sudahlah pasti ia berjaga-jaga, dan tidak akan membiarkan rumahnya dibongkar.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وإعلموا هذا، أنه لو علم رب البيت في أية ساعة يأتى السارق لسهر ولم يدع بيته ينقب،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Eybe vai hwten swpi e~retencebtwt: je qen ]ounou e~tetencwoun m~moc an e~re p~s/ri m~v~rwmi n/ou n~q/tc.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Therefore you also be ready, for the Son of Man is coming at an hour you do not expect.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Sebab itu, hendaklah kamu juga siap sedia, karena Anak Manusia datang pada saat yang tidak kamu duga."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلذلك كونوا انتم أيضاً مستعدين لأن إبن الإنسان يأتي في ساعة لا تعرفونها.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Nim hara pe pipictoc m~bwk ouoh n~cabe: v/e~te pef[oic na,af e~h~r/i e~jen nefe~biaik e~] nwou n~touq~re qen p~c/ou n~t/ic:                </language>               <language id="English">                  “Who then is a faithful and wise servant, whom his master made ruler over his household, to give them food in due season?                </language><language id="Indonesian">"Siapakah hamba yang setia dan bijaksana, yang diangkat oleh tuannya atas orang-orangnya untuk memberikan mereka makanan pada waktunya?                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فمن تري هو العبد الأمين الحكيم الذي يقيمه سيده علي عبيده ليعطيهم طعامهم في حينه؟                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Wouniatf m~pibwk e~tem~mau: eswp afsani~ n~je pef[oic n~tefjemf efi~ri m~pair/]: a~m/n ]jw m~moc nwten: je efe,af hijen peten~taf t/rf.               </language>               <language id="English">                  Blessed is that servant whom his master, when he comes, will find so doing. Assuredly, I say to you that he will make him ruler over all his goods.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Berbahagialah hamba, yang didapati tuannya melakukan tugasnya itu, ketika tuannya itu datang. Aku berkata kepadamu: Sesungguhnya tuannya itu akan mengangkat dia menjadi pengawas segala miliknya.</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طوبي لذلك العبد الذي إذا جاء سيده فيجده يفعل هكذا. الحق أقول لكم, إنه يقيمه علي جميع ماله.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  E~swp de afsanjoc n~je pibwk ethwou e~te m~mau qen pefh/t: je pa[oic nawck:               </language>               <language id="English">                  But if that evil servant says in his heart, ‘My master is delaying his coming,’               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Akan tetapi apabila hamba itu jahat dan berkata di dalam hatinya:               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولكن إن قال ذلك العبد الشرير في قلبه,               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh n~teferh/tc n~hioui~ n~nefs~v/r n~e~biaik: n~tef ouwm de ouoh n~tefcw nem n/etyaqi:                </language>               <language id="English">                  And begins to beat his fellow servants, and to eat and drink with the drunkards,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tuanku tidak datang-datang, lalu ia mulai memukul hamba-hamba lain, dan makan minum bersama-sama pemabuk-pemabuk,                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إن سيدي يبطئ قدومه فيبتدئ يضرب العبيد رفقاءه ويأكل ويشرب مع السكيرين،                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Efe~i~ de n~je P[oic m~pibwk e~tem~mau qen pie~hoou e~tefnajoust qajwf an: nem qen ]ounou e~ten~f~cwoun m~moc an:                </language>               <language id="English">                  The master of that servant will come on a day when he is not looking for him and at an hour that he is not aware of,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  maka tuan hamba itu akan datang pada hari yang tidak disangkakannya, dan pada saat yang tidak diketahuinya,                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فيأتي سيد ذلك العبد في يوم لا ينتظره، وساعة لا يعرفها                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh efevorjf tefm/] ouoh efe~,w n~teftoi nem nisobi: pima e~te v~rimi naswpi m~mof nem pic~yerter n~te ninajhi.               </language>               <language id="English">                  And will cut him in two and appoint him his portion with the hypocrites. There shall be weeping and gnashing of teeth.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  dan akan membunuh dia dan membuat dia senasib dengan orang-orang munafik. Di sanalah akan terdapat ratapan dan kertakan gigi."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فيشقه من وسطه ويجعل نصيبه مع المرائين هناك يكون البكاء وصرير الاسنان.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/BowDownBeforeTheHolyGospel"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>            <role id="Reader">         <insertdocument path="pascha/wednesday/interpretations/3rdHourEve/Matthew.24.36-51"/>      </role>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelConclusionEve"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Exposition</language><language id="Indonesian">Komentari</language>            <language id="Arabic">الطرح</language>         </Title>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The exposition of the Third Hour of the eve of Wednesday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Komentari dari Jam Ketiga Malam Hari Rabu  pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طرح الساعة الثالثة، من ليلة الأربعاء من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  Contemplate you who exalt the Lord, the kindness of Christ our God: observe how He calls His chosen who fulfill His will, prudent and honest servants.                </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Renungkanlah kebaikan Kristus Allah</div><div>kita, engkau yang memuliakan Tuhan. <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Amati bagaimana Dia memanggil hamba </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">pilihan-Nya, yang bijaksana dan jujur, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">yang memenuhi kehendak-Nya. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Khususnya,</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  تأملوا يا عابدي الإله إلي تحنن المسيح إلهنا، كيف يدعو أصفياءه الصانعين إرادته عبيداً حكماء وأمناء,                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  I mean those who preserve his commandments, and look forward to their awards; those who remain awake and alert, that they may receive the promised rewards.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>mereka yang memelihara <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">perintah-perintah-Nya yang </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">menantikan upah mereka, dan yang </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">akan tetap berjaga-jaga dan waspada, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">sehingga mereka dapat menerima upah </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">yang dijanjikan.</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أعني الذين يحفظون وصاياه المتوقعين أجراً صالحاً، الساهرين المتيقظين لكي ينالوا المواعيد                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  As the Bible asserts that those servants—whose master makes a surprise visit and finds them awake—are blessed. Assuredly I say: He will make His servant ruler over His property.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Sebagaimana Alkitab menegaskan bahwa </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">hamba yang saat tuannya membuat </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">kunjungan tiba-tiba dan menemukannya </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">sedang berjaga-jaga, akan diberkati. </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Sesungguhnya Aku berkata, Ia akan </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">memerintahkan pelayannya itu untuk </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">mengurus hartanya.</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  كما قال في الإنجيل إن ذلك العبد مغبوطاً، أعني الذي يأتي سيده بغتة فيجده يفعل هكذا أقول لكم إنه يقيمه وكيلاً على جميع ماله               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  So for He whom He finds derelict in his duties and neglecting them often, one day, his Master will make a surprise visit, repudiate him, and make his lot with the hypocrites, in the place of darkness and suffering.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Adapun siapa yang dia temukan <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">mengabaikan tugas-tugasnya pada hari </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">saat tuannya tiba-tiba datang, dia akan</span></div><div>mengusirnya, dan membuat nasibnya <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">serupa dengan orang munafik yang ada di </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">tempat kegelapan dan penderitaan.</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فأما ذلك الذي يجده متغافلاً فيطرد يوماً بيوم، فيجئ سيده في ساعة لا يعرفها فيشقه من وسطه ويجعل نصيبه مع المرائين في الظلمة وموضع العذاب،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                  Let us awake and be alert in anticipation of the day of the Lord so that we may rejoice with Him in His dwelling-place and receive His clemencies and mercies.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Marilah kita bangun dan waspada untuk <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">mengantisipasi hari Tuhan, sehingga </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">kita dapat bersukacita bersama-Nya di </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">kediaman-Nya dan menerima </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">pengampunan dan belas kasihan-Nya.</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فلنتيقظ من غفلتنا وننتظر يوم الرب لنفرح معه في دياره ونفوز بمراحمه ورافاته.               </language>            </text>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ExpositionConclusion"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/EveningLitaniesAndConclusionLink"/>   </forceseason></document>