<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Group>      <Season id="KoiahkSeason ^ MidnightPraises">         <Section>            <Title>               <Language id="English">                  Exposition on the First Saturday “Hail”               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  طرح واطس يقال علي الشرات الاولي               </Language>            </Title>                         <Text>               <Language id="Coptic">                  &lt;ere ne w~ }paryenoc: y/e~tacswpi ouy~ronoc: m~P,#c# pia~,writoc: p~s/ri m~V] a~l/yoc.               </Language>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to you, O Virgin, who became a throne for Christ, the uncontainable Son of God in truth.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ التي صارت كرسياً للمسيح الغير المحوي ابن الله بالحقيقة.               </Language>            </Text>                         <Text>               <Language id="Coptic">                  &lt;ere w~ }paryenoc: y/e~tacfai qen peca~m/r: m~v/e~te m~mon ma sopf e~rof: n~h~r/i qen t~ve nem hijen pikahi.               </Language>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to you, O Virgin, who bore in her womb Him whom no place can contain in heaven or on earth.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ التي حملت في احشاءها الذي لا يحويه مكان في السماء وعلى الارض.               </Language>            </Text>                         <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to you, O Virgin, from whom was incarnate the eternal Logos. Hail to you, O Virgin, who deserved to nurse the Son of God from her blessed paps. Hail to you, O Virgin, who became a ship bearing in her pure womb the Conductor of the whole universe.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ. التي أتي وتجسَّد منها الكلمة الازلية. السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ. التي استحقت ان ترضع ابن الله من ثدييها المباركين. السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ. التي قد صارت سفينة. حملت في بطنها الطاهر. مدبر سائر المسكونة.               </Language>            </Text>                         <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to you, O Virgin, who are higher than the Cherubim and more glorified than the Seraphim. Hail to you, O Virgin, the pure dove who announced to us peace and deliverance. Hail to you, O Virgin, of whom the prophets spoke, concerning your birth of the only-begotten Son.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ. التي هي ارفع من الكاروبيم.وممجدة اكثر من السارافيم. السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ. الحمامة النقية التي بشرتنا بالسلامة والنجاة. السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ. التي نطقوا من اجلها الانبياء. بميلادها الابن الوحيد.               </Language>            </Text>                         <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to you, O Virgin, who was raised in the temple of God, and deserved to receive divine food prepared for her from heaven. Hail to you, O Virgin, of the pure seed who brought forth the branch of life. Hail to you, O Virgin, whose perfume is greater than that of the trees of Paradise.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ. التي ربيت في هيكل الله. واستحقت ان تقبل اليها الطعام الإلهي المهيأ لها من السماء. السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ. ذات الاصل الطاهر التي اثمرت لنا عنقود الحياة. السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ. التي عطرها اعظم من اشجار الفردوس.               </Language>            </Text>                        <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to you, O Virgin, the aromatic flower whose scent emanated and was smelt by the saints. We ask you to remember us before your beloved Son on that great day, that He may forgive our sins and repose the souls of our departed in the paradise of joy. Amen.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لكِ ايتها العذراءَ. الزهرة الزكية التي ارتفع زكاها واشتموه القديسين. نسألك ان تذكرينا أمام ابنك الحبيب في ذلك اليوم العظيم. في غفران خطايانا. وينيح نفوس امواتنا في فردوس النعيم آمين الليلويا الخ...               </Language>            </Text>         </Section>      </Season>   </Group></Document>