<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Exposition on the Fourth Canticle         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            طرح آدام على الهوس الرابع         </Language>      </Title>             <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            {I qen netenjij: m~pim/t n~kap: kuyara n~te Dauid: piiero'alt/c.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            Take in your hands the ten stringed harp of David, the holy psalmist,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            خذوا بأيديكم العشرة اوتار القيثارة الذى لداود الملك.         </Language>      </Text>             <Text>         <Language id="Coptic">            Nem piorganon: n~te pimocikon: nem oucalpiggoc: m~p#n#a#tikon.         </Language>         <Language id="English">            along with the musical organ and the spiritual trumpet.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وارغن الموسيقى والبوق الروحاني.         </Language>      </Text>             <Text>         <Language id="English">            Cry out joyfully saying, “Bless the Lord from the heavens. Bless Him in the highest. Bless our Lord, O heaven of heavens, with sweet sounding cymbals. Glorify His name and praise Him.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            واصرخوا بتهليل قائلين: باركوا الرب من السموات. باركوه في الآعالى. باركوا الرب الهنا يا سماء السموات. بصنوج شجية الصوت. ومجدوا اسمه وسبحوه.         </Language>      </Text>             <Text>         <Language id="English">            To our God belongs the sound of the flute; it is good to chant to Him in Zion and take vows in Jerusalem. Chant to our God a new chant. Let Israel rejoice in the Lord his God.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فبالهنا يليق اصوات المزمار. ويحسن له النشيد في صهيون. والنذور في اورشليم. انشدوا للرب الهنا نشيداً جديداً وليفرح اسرائيل بالرب الهنا.         </Language>      </Text>             <Text>         <Language id="English">            Sing to Him in orderly harmony and spiritual glorification. Boast in Him all you His saints, and rejoice with Him in great glory. Enter His holy courts and thank Him joyfully. Sing to His exalted name, because He made us a free people and a pure nation. Let us praise Him unceasingly.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            رتلوا له باتفاق الصفوف وتماجيد روحانية. افتخروا به يا كل قديسيه. وسروا معه بمجد عظيم. ادخلوا الي ديار قدسه. واشكروه بالتهليل. رتلوا لاسمه العالي. لأنه جعلنا له شعباً مبرراً. وامة مطهرة فلنسبحه بغير فتور.         </Language>      </Text>             <Text>         <Language id="English">            We worship You, O Christ our God, with Your good Father and the Holy Spirit, for You have come and saved us.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            نسجد لك ايها المسيح الهنا مع أبيك الصالح والروح القدس. لأنك اتيت وخلصتنا.         </Language>      </Text>    </Section></Document>