<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Season id="Fridays">      <Section>         <Title>            <Language id="English">               Exposition on the Friday Theotokia            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               طرح واطس يقال علي تذاكية الجمعة            </Language>         </Title>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Tec~marwout n~yo qen nihio~mi: w~ Maria~ y~mau m~V]: f~c~marwout n~je pekarpoc: e~te vai pe I/#c# P,#c#.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Blessed are you among women, O Mary, the Mother of God, and blessed is your Fruit, Jesus Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مباركة انتِ في النساءَ يامريم ام الله. ومبارك هو ثمركِ الذي هو يسوع المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Tec~marwout e~hote t~ve: w~ Maria~ }paryenoc: je n~yo pe p~sousou m~pengenoc: a~non qa ni,~r/ctia~noc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               You are more blessed than heaven, O Virgin Mary, because you are the pride of our race, we the Christians.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مباركة اكثر من السماء يامريم العذراءَ لأنك انت فخر جنسنا نحن المسيحيين.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               Blessed are you, O Mary the queen, the mother of the King, because the eternal King came and dwelt in you. Many women received honors, but you are more exalted than them all, because the King of heaven and earth took flesh from you and drank milk from your breasts, until He split asunder Satan. He took what is ours and gave us what was His. Out of His abundant compassion, He was incarnate from this bride, and saved us from the hands of the unmerciful enemy.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مباركة انت يامريم الملكة ام الملك. لان الملك الدائم اتي وحلَّ فيكِ. نساء كثيرات نلن كرامات ارتفعت انتِ اكثر من جميعهن. لان ملك السماء والارض اخذ له جسداً منكِ. ورضع اللبن من ثدييك. حتي اشدخ الشيطان. هو اخذ الذي لنا واعطانا الذي له. من اجل كثرة رأفته. تجسَّدَ من هذه العروسة. حتي خلصنا من يد المضاد الغير الرحوم.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               Virgin Mary, the wise Theotokos, saved Adam through her beloved Son. Virgin Mary is the faithful intercessor for humanity before the Omnipotent. Virgin Mary cries out in the sanctuary before her beloved Son, that He may forgive our sins.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               العذراء مريم والدة الاله الحكيمة. التي خلصت آدم من قبل ابنها الحبيب. العذراء مريم الشفيعة الأمينة في جنس البشر. امام ضابط الكل. العذراء مريم تصرخ في الهيكل امام ابنها الحبيب. لكي يغفر لنا خطايانا.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               What shall I call you, O Saintly Virgin, who became a dwelling for the wisdom of God? You are the rational hook that catches Christians and raises them up to heaven. As the author (David) said, “You shone brighter than the sun, O Mary, the second heaven, because the One who created heaven came and was in your embrace.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بمنْ ادعوك ايتها العذراء القديسة. لأنك صرتي مسكناً لحكمة الله. لأنك أنتِ هي الصنارة العقلية التي تصيد المسيحيين. وتصعدهم الي السموات. كما قال الفاخوري اضأتِ أكثر من الشمس يامريم السماء الثانية. لأن الذي خلق السماء وصار في حضنكِ.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               You became for us an intercessor with Jesus Christ, the King who was baptized in the Jordan River, was lifted up upon the cross, was buried in the tomb, and rose on the third day from the dead, according to the Scriptures. Intercede for us before your beloved Son, that He may forgive us our sins.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               صرتِ لنا وسيلة عند يسوع المسيح. الملك الذي اعتمد في نهر الاردن. ورُفع علي الصليب. ودفن في القبر. وقام في اليوم الثالث من بين الأموات. كما في الكتب. اشفعي فينا عند ابنك الحبيب ليغفر لنا خطايانا.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season></Document>