<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Group>      <Season id="KoiahkSeason ^ MidnightPraises">         <Section>            <Title>               <Language id="English">                  Exposition on the Second Saturday “Hail”               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  طرح واطس يقال علي الشارات الثانية               </Language>            </Title>                         <Text>               <Language id="Coptic">                  &lt;ere pinis] n~Gabri/l: piaggeloc m~faisennoufi: e~jen Maria~ }paryenoc: eybe p~jinmici m~Pencwt/r.               </Language>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to Gabriel, the great angel of the Annunciation to Virgin Mary of the birth of our Savior.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لغبريال العظيم. ملاك البشارة لمريم العذراءِ من أجل ميلاد مخلصنا.               </Language>            </Text>                        <Text>               <Language id="Coptic">                  &lt;ere nak w~ Gabri/l: piaggeloc n~te pic~mou: v/e~tafhiwis n~Za,ariac: eybe pij~vo n~Iw#a#.               </Language>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to you, O Gabriel, angel of blessing, who announced to Zacharias the birth of John.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لك يا غبريال ملاك البركة. الذي بشر زكريا بميلاد يوحنا.               </Language>            </Text>                         <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Come all today, together, O beloved people of Christ, to worship the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit, one co-essential Trinity.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  فتعالوا اليوم كلكم معاً. ايها الشعب المحب للمسيح. لنسجد للآب والابن والروح القدس. الثالوث المقدس المساوي.               </Language>            </Text>                        <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Let us praise this stately angel, Gabriel, the great among the archangels, saying: Hail to Gabriel, the angel announcing joy and delight. Hail to Archangel Gabriel, whose name means the power of God.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  ونمدح هذا الملاك. الجليل العظيم في رؤساء الملائكة غبريال هكذا قائلين: السلام لغبريال الملاك المبشر بالفرح والسرور. السلام لغبريال رئيس الملائكة. الذي تفسير اسمه قوة الله.               </Language>            </Text>                        <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to Archangel Gabriel, who announced to Zacharias the birth of the great prophet, the anointing forerunner, the priest the son of the priest—John, the relative of our Lord Jesus Christ.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لغبريال رئيس الملائكة. الذي بشر زكريا بميلاد النبي العظيم. السابق الصابغ. الكاهن ابن الكاهن يوحنا. نسيب سيدنا يسوع المسيح.               </Language>            </Text>                        <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to Archangel Gabriel, who carried the message of the Father to the pure Virgin Mary concerning the incarnation of the eternal Word, who took flesh from her in a body that is beyond comprehension. A pure birth, by which He saved Adam and his descendants.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لرئيس الملائكة غبريال. الحامل رسالة الآب الي البكر الطاهرة. العذراءَ مريم بحلول الكلمة الازلي. وتجسد منها بجسد يفوق العقل. وميلاده الطاهر. الذي به خلص آدم ونسله.               </Language>            </Text>                        <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to Archangel Gabriel, who announced to the shepherds the birth of the Savior of the world. Hail to Archangel Gabriel, who was with the martyrs, saints, and the righteous until they completed their struggle which was pleasing to God. Hail to Archangel Gabriel, who comforts the hearts of the faithful.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لغبريال رئيس الملائكة. الذي بشر الرعاة بولادة مخلص العالم. السلام لغبريال رئيس الملائكة. الذي كان مع الشهداء والقديسين والابرار حتي كملوا جهادهم في مرضاة الله. السلام لغبريال رئيس الملائكة. معزي قلوب المؤمنين.               </Language>            </Text>                         <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Hail to Archangel Gabriel, who was sent to the Virgin, announcing to her the coming of the Logos saying, “Rejoice, O full of grace, the Lord is with you.”               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  السلام لغبريال رئيس الملائكة. المرسل الي العذراءَ. مبشراً لها بحلول الكلمة. قائلاً لها هكذا. افرحي يا ممتلئة نعمة الرب معكِ.               </Language>            </Text>                        <Text>               <Language id="English">                  Let us ask the Lord Almighty, through the intercession of the Immaculate Lady Virgin Mary, and this honorable archangel Gabriel, to grant us the forgiveness of our sins, to save all Christian people from temporal trials and tribulations, and to elate them with the eternal joy of salvation forever. Amen.               </Language>               <Language id="Arabic">                  فلنطلب من الرب بشفاعة الست السيدة الطاهرة البتول مريم. وهذا الملاك الجليل غبريال ان ينعم لنا بغفران خطايانا. ويخلص كافة الشعب المسيحي. من المحن والتجارب الزمانية. ويفرحهم ببهجة الخلاص السرمدي الي الآبد امين. الليلويا.               </Language>            </Text>         </Section>      </Season>   </Group></Document>