<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Season id="KoiahkSeason">      <Section>         <Title>            <Language id="English">               Exposition on the Third Canticle            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               طرح واطس علي الهوس الثالث            </Language>         </Title>                  <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Aftaho n~ouhukwn n~noub: n~je Nabou,odonocor p~ouro ouoh catotf afouahcahni: m~pair/] efjw m~moc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               King Nebuchadnezzar made a golden idol and immediately commanded saying:            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أقام الملك نبوخذنصر صنماً من ذهب. وأمر لوقته هكذا قائلاً.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Je aije e~rwten t/rou: qa nieynoc nem nilaoc: nivul/ niacpi n~lac: ,amasj mahy/ten e~nacaji.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               "I say to you all, peoples, nations, tribes, and tongues, listen and contemplate on my words.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               انى قلت لكم جميعاً يا معشر الشعوب والأمم والقبائل والألسن. انصتوا وتأملوا لكلامي.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Eswp a~resancwtem e~t~c~m/ n~]calpiggoc: caten y/nou hitou e~q~r/i: ouwst n~]hukwn n~noub.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               When the sound of the trumpet is heard, bow down immediately and worship the golden idol.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               اذا ما سُمع صوت البوق فخرٌوا لوقتكم. واسجدوا لصورة الذهب.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Eswp de a~retens~temi~ri m~vai: oude e~s~temcwtem e~nacaji: caten y/nou e~hioui~ m~mwten: e~q~r/i e~]h~rw n~,~rwm eymoh.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               If you do not do so, and you do not adhere to my commandment, you will be thrown into the lit fiery furnace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               واذا لم تصنعوا هكذا ولم تسمعوا لقولي. للوقت تلقون في اتون النار المتقد.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Etaucwtem e~naicaji n~je pis~lol t/rf n~te tefmetouro: auhitou e~q~r/i ouoh auouwst: m~pem~yo n~]hukwn n~noub.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               When these words were heard, all the tribes of the kingdom, kneeled and worshipped, before the golden idol,            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما سمع هذا الكلام جميع القبائل التي في مملكته خرٌوا وسجدوا أمام الصورة الذهبية.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Eb/l e~pig# n~a~lou n~a~gioc: Cedrak Micak Abdenagw: m~poucwtem n~ca p~ouro: oude m~pououwst n~]hukwn.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Except for the three saintly youth, Sedrak Misak and Abdenago. They did not obey the king, and did not bow to the idol.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ما عدا الثلاثة فتيه القديسين. سدراك و ميساك وابداناغو. فانهم لم يطيعوا الملك ولم يسجدوا للصورة.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Alla aujemnom] qen pouh/t: nem tou'u,/ nem poucwma: ouoh auo~hi qen pounah]: e~P% V] n~te t~ve.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               But they were strengthened, in their hearts, spirits and bodies, and stood firm upon their faith in the Lord, God of heaven.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بل تقووا في قلوبهم وفى نفوسهم وأجسادهم. وأقاموا على ايمانهم بالرب اله السماء.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Etafcwtem n~je p~ouro: afjwnt qen ounis] n~embon: afouahcahni eyrouconhou: ouohi e~hitou e~]h~rw n~,~rwm ecmoh.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               When the king heard, he was greatly enraged, and he decreed that the youths be tied and thrown into the fiery furnace.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فلما سمع الملك غضب غضباً عظيماً. وأمر أن يربطوا ويلقوا في اتون النار المتقد.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               h/ppe ic ouaggeloc n~te P%: afi~ e~pec/t e~bolqen t~ve: afneh pisah n~te pi,~rwm: Afaif m~v~r/] n~ouiw] efk/b.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Then the Angel of the Lord, descended from heaven, calmed the flames of fire and made it as cold dew.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               واذ بالرب قد نزل من السماء ونفض لهيب النار.وصيَّره كالندى البارد.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ouoh pig# n~a~lou n~a~gioc: aumosi qen y~m/] n~]h~rw: nauhwc e~V] qen ourasi: nem piaggeloc n~te P%.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The three saintly youth walked in the midst of the furnace, and they were praising God in joy with the Angel of the Lord.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               والثلاثة فتيه القديسين مشوا في وسط الاتون وكانوا يسبحون الله بفرح مع ملاك الرب.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Afo~hi n~je Azariac: qen y~m/] n~]h~rw n~,~rwm: afouwn n~rwf afc~mou e~V]: n~yof nem nefs~v/ri nemaf.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Then Azariah stood, in the midst of the fiery furnace, and opened his mouth and blessed God, he and his peers with him.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               ثم وقف عزريا في وسط اتون النار وفتح فاه وبارك الله هو ورفقته معه.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Je k~c~marwout P% V]: hwc e~rof a~rihouo~ [acf: f~c~marwout n~je piran e#y#u# n~te pefw~ou: sa e~neh n~te pie~neh.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Saying, "Blessed is the Lord God, praise Him and exalt Him above all, Blessed is the Holy name of His glory, unto the age of the ages."            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               قائلين مبارك ايها الرب الله. سبحوه وزيدوه علواً. مبارك هو اسم مجده القدوس الى ابد الابد.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Cmou e~P% Ananiac: c~mou e~P% Azariac: c~mou e~P% M/ca/l: nie~biaik n~te V] et[oci.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Bless the Lord O Hananiah, bless the Lord O Azariah, bless the Lord O Mishael, the servants of the Lord Most High.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بارك الرب يا حنانيا.بارك الرب ياعزاريا بارك الرب ياميصائيل. عبيد الله العلي.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Cmou e~P% n/e~tercebecye: m~P% V] n~te t~ve: hwc e~rof ouoh maw~ou naf: a~rihouo~ [acf sa nie~neh.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Bless the Lord, all you who fear the Lord God of heaven, praise Him, glorify Him, and highly exalt Him forever.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               باركوا الرب يا خائفى لرب اله السماء سبحوه ومجدوه وزيدوه علواً الى الآباد.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Afnah] e~V] n~je p~ouro: nem ni,aldeoc t/rou n~te tefmetouro: aftaho m~pig# n~a~lou na~gioc: e~jen hwb niben.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The king and all the Chaldeans in his kingdom believed in God. And he placed the three saintly youth over all that he had.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               قد أمن الملك بالله وكل الكلدانيين اللذين في مملكته وأقام الثلاثة فتية القديسين على كل ماله.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Twbh m~P% e~h~r/i e~jwn: w~ pig# n~a~lou n~a~gioc: Cedra, Micak Abdenagw.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Pray to the Lord on our behalf, O three saintly children, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-Nego, that He may forgive us our sins.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               اطلبوا من الرب عنا ايها الثلاثة فتية القديسين سدراك وميصاك وابداناغو.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season></Document>