<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.suscopts.org/CopticReader">   <Season id="Thursdays">      <Section>         <Title>            <Language id="English">               Exposition on the Thursday Theotokia            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               طرح واطس على تذاكية الخميس            </Language>         </Title>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Mwu~c/c piar,/p~rov/t/c: e~tafswpi qen pid~rumoc: afnau e~ou,~rwm qen oubatoc: oude m~pourwkh n~je nefk~latoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               When Moses the Archprophet was in the wilderness, he saw a fire in a bush, but its branches did not burn.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               موسي رئيس الأنبياء لما كان في البرية رأى ناراً في عوسجة ولم تحترق أغصانها.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Afers~v/ri e~masw: e~tafnau e~pi,~rwm qen pibatoc: afe~mi e~]meym/i: je n~yof pe peftupoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               He was greatly amazed when he saw the fire in the bush, so he understood that it was truly symbolic.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فتعجَّب جدا لما نظر النار في العليقة فعلم الحقيقة انها هي مثال.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Psousou n~niparyenoc t/rou: pe Maria~ ]macnou]: ]ramnoc n~a~/yinoc: eymoh e~bolqen Pip#n#a# e#y#u#.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               This is the pride of all virgins, Mary the Theotokos, the true bush aflame with the Holy Spirit.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               فخر كل العذارى مريم والة الاله. العليقة الحقيقية المتقدة من الروح القدس.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               As n~nouc ie as n~caje: ie jincwtem eynas~fai: efjw m~p~taio~ n~te taisel/t: Maria~ ]yeo~dokoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               What mind, what utterance, or what hearing can speak of the sayings and honor of this Virgin, the bride, Mary the Theotokos?            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أي عقل وأي نطق وأي سمعٍ يمكنه أن ينطق بقول وبكرامة هذه العذراءَ العروسة مريم والدة الاله.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               W ]tim/ n~te taijinerboki: n~te ]neji m~paryenik/: e~taf[icarx e~bol n~q/tc: pirefyamio~ n~hwb niben.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               O, the honor of this pregnancy of the virginal womb into which was incarnate the Creator of all.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يا لكرامة هذا الحَبَل الذي للبطن البتولي الذي تجسَّد منها خالق الكل.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               W ninakhi n~nou]: e~taf,/ qen B/yleem: y~baki m~p~ouro Dauid: nem pijinmici m~paryenikon.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               O, the divine pangs which were in Bethlehem, the city of King David, and the virginal birth.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يا للطلق الالهي الذي كان في بيت لحم مدينة الملك داود والميلاد البتولي.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               W ]nis] n~sv/ri: je v/e~tafyamio~ n~niv/oui~: afi~ e~pec/t hijen pikahi: ouoh af[icarx qen }paryenoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               O, the great mystery: He who created heaven came down to earth and was incarnate from the Virgin.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               يا لعظم الاعجوبة ان الذي خلق السموات نزل علي الأرض وتجسَّد من العذراءَ.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Afwrk n~je P% n~Dauid: ouoh n~nefouwm n~h~y/f: je e~bolqen p~outah n~te tekneji: ]na,w hijen peky~ronoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The Lord has sworn to David and will not relent: “Of the seed of your loins I will set upon your throne.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               أقسَمَ الرب لداود ولم يندم ان من ثمرة بطنك أجعل علي كرسيك.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ouoh kata v~r/] e~e~tafjoc eyb/tf: n~je Mi,eoc pip~rov/t/c: je n~yo hwi pe B/yleem: p~kahi n~Evraya.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Likewise, Micah the prophet said, “You also, O Bethlehem, the land of Ephrata,            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وهكذا قال ايضاً ميخاوس النبي وأَنتِ يا بيت لحم أرض افرتا.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Nyo oukouji an te e~bol: oute niourwou n~te Iouda: efe~i~ gar e~bol n~q/]: n~je ouhugoumenoc v/eta~reh e~Pic#l#.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               are not the least among the kings of Judah, for out of you shall come a ruler who will shepherd Israel.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               لستِ بصغيرة بين ملوك يهوذا لأن منكِ يخرج المدبر الذي يرعي اسرائيل.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Piouai e~bolqen ]t~riac: pio~mooucioc nem v~iwt: e~taui~ni naf n~handwron: n~je niourwou n~nimagoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The one of the Trinity, of one essence with the Father, to whom the magi presented the offerings,            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الواحد من الثالوث المساوي مع الآب. الذي قدموا له القرابين ملوك المجوس.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Afrek niv/oui~ n~te niv/oui~: afi~ e~pec/t saron: hina n~tefbwl e~bol: m~piparaptwma n~Adam.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               bowed the heaven of heavens and came down to us to undo the transgression of Adam.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               طأطأ سماَءَ السموات ونزل الينا لكي يحلَّ زلة آدم.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Niourwou n~te Yarcoc … aunau e~nim/ini qen t~ve: ic ouc~himi ecjolh m~v~r/: ouoh ecerouwini e~masw.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The kings from Tarsis and the Islands saw a sign from heaven: a woman clothed with the sun, she being greatly luminous,            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الملوك الذين من ترسيس والجزائر رأوا آية من السماء. اذ بامراءَة مشتملة بالشمس وهي مضيئة جداً.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ouoh piioh et qa nec[alauj: nem ib# n~,~lom e~jen teca~ve: ecmosi qen y~m/] n~t~ve: ecerouwini hijen pikahi.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               with the moon under her feet and twelve stars on her head, walking in the midst of heaven and her light shining on the earth.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               والقمر تحت أقدامها واثني عشر نجم علي رأسها تمشي في أفق السماء وضياءُها على الأرض.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Yai te ]ramnoc: e~tafnau e~roc: n~je Mwu~c/c qen pid~rumoc: ouoh pi,~rwm efmoh n~q/tc: pe Pen% I/#c# P,#c#.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               This is the bush which Moses saw in the wilderness with the fire aflame in it—our Lord Jesus Christ.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               هذه العليقة التي أبصرها موسي في البرية والنار المتقدة فيها هو ربنا يسوع المسيح.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               V] piats~nau e~rof: qajwou n~nie~wn t/rou: afnau e~rof n~je pip~rov/t/c: m~v~r/] m~pi,~rwm qen pibatoc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               The invisible God, before all ages, was seen by Moses as a fire in a bush,            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               الله الغير المنظور قبل كل الدهور نظر اليه موسي مثل نار في عوسج.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Ouoh ouc~m/ ecjw m~moc: je Mwu~c/c Mwu~c/c pe]mei m~mof: anok pe V] n~te nekio]: m~mon keouai e~b/l e~roi.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               with a voice saying to him, “Moses, Moses, whom I love, I AM the God of your fathers. There is none other but Me.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               وصوت يقول له ياموسي ياموسي الذي أنا أحبه. أنا هو إله ابائك وليس أحد سواي.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Bwl m~piywoui e~bol: v/etoi n~nek[alauj: je pima e~tako~hi e~ratk hijwf: oukahi efouab pe.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Loosen the sandals on your feet because the place on which you stand is holy ground.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               حِل الحذاء الذي في رجليك لأن الموضع الذي أنت واقف عليه أرض مقدسة.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Eybe vai tener,wreuin: nem Mwu~c/c enjw m~moc: je V] efnatounoc n~oup~rov/t/c: nwten par/] cwtem n~cwf.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Therefore we sing with Moses the prophet saying, “God will raise up for you, from among your brethren, a Prophet, so listen to Him.”            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               من أجل هذا نسبح مع موسي النبي قائلين أن الله يقيم لكم نبياً من اخوتكم مثلي فاسمعوا له.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season></Document>