<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">      <Season id="KoiahkSeason ^ AdamDays">      <Section>         <Title>            <Language id="English">               Exposition on "Your mercies, O my God"            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               طرح علي "مراحمك يا الهي"            </Language>         </Title>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Neknai w~ panou]: hanat[i/~pi m~mwou: neknai w~ panou]: m~v~r/] n~nimounhwou.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, are countless. Your mercies, O my God, are like the rain.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك يا الهي غير محصاة مراحمك يا الهي مثل الأمطار.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Neknai w~ panou]: cews e~masw: neknai w~ panou]: e~hote pisw.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, are very plenteous. Your mercies, O my God, are more than the sand.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك يا الهي كثيرة جدا. مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من الرمل.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Neknai w~ panou]: c~[oci e~niv/oui~: neknai w~ panou]: e~hote nimeui~.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, are higher than the heavens. Your mercies, O my God, are more than the thoughts.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك يا الهي تعلو علي السموات. مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من الأفكار.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="Coptic">               Neknai w~ panou]: cap~swi n~niaggeloc: neknai w~ panou]: m~v~r/] m~pi,~r/ctalloc.            </Language>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, are higher than the angels. Your mercies, O my God, are like snow.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك يا الهي تفوق الملائكة. مراحمك يا الهي مثل الجليد.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, are more than thousands. Your mercies, O my God, are myriads of myriads. Your mercies, O my God, are like the lights. Your mercies, O my God, are more than the raindrops. Your mercies, O my God, are more than the stars. Your mercies, O my God, flow more than the springs. Your mercies, O my God, are more than the clouds. Your mercies, O my God, are countless.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من الألوف. مراحمك يا الهي ربوات أضعاف. مراحمك يا الهي مثل الأنوار. مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من القطرات. مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من النجوم. مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من الينابيع. مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من السحاب. مراحمك يا الهي لا يحصي لها عددا.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, are more than the winds. Your mercies, O my God, are stronger than storms. Your mercies, O my God, go beyond nature. Your mercies, O my God, are beyond creation. Your mercies, O my God, are more than the plants of the field. Your mercies, O my God, are more than the dew. Your mercies, O my God, are more than the waterfalls. Your mercies, O my God, cover the high mountains.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من الرياح. مراحمك يا الهي أقوى من العواصف. مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من الطبايع. مراحمك يا الهي تفوق علي الخليقة. مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من نبات الأرض. مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من الأندية. مراحمك يا الهي اكثر من الأمطار الجارية. مراحمك يا الهي تغطي الجبال العالية.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, quicken the spirits. Your mercies, O my God, bring us good. Your mercies, O my God, take care of humans. Your mercies, O my God, rescue animals. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon our father Adam and our mother Eve. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon Abel the righteous, the first martyr. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon Enoch whom You took alive to heaven.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك يا الهي تحيي الأرواح. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا بالإنعام. مراحمك يا الهي تعول البشر. مراحمك يا الهي تعطي النجاة للبهائم. مراحمك يا الهي فلتأت علينا مثل ابينا آدم وأمنا حواء. مراحمك يا الهي فلتأت علينا مثل هابيل الصديق اول الشهداء. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل اخنوخ البار الذي رفعته الي السماء حيّا.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon Noah the righteous whom You saved from the flood waters. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon Melchizedek the king of Salem. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the rest of the pure prophets. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the saintly apostles.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل نوح البار الذي خلصته من ماء الطوفان. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل ملشيصاداق ملك سليم. مراحمك ياالهي تأتي علينا مثل إبراهيم واسحاق ويعقوب. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل سائر الأنبياء الاطهار. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل الرسل القديسين.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the martyrs who sacrificed their blood for the name of Christ. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the rest of the confessors. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the righteous cross-bearers. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the struggling ascetics. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the worshipping anchorites.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل الشهداء الذين سفكوا دماهم علي اسم المسيح. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل سائر المعترفين. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل لباس الصليب الابرار الصالحين. مراحمك ياالهي تأتي علينا مثل النساك المجاهدين. مراحمك ياالهي تأتي علينا مثل السواح العابدين.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the wise virgins. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the tax-collector whom You accepted. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the sinful women whom You forgave. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the thief who was crucified on Your right. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the people of Nineveh who repented.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل العذارى الحكيمات. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل العشار الذي قبلته إليك. مراحمك ياالهي تأتي علينا مثل الخاطية التي غفرت لها خطاياها. مراحمك ياالهي تأتي علينا مثل اللص الذي صلب عن يمينك. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل أهل نينوي الذين تابوا إليك.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the sinners who You forgave. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the blind whose eyes You opened. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the mute whom You allowed to speak. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the deaf whose ears You opened. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the paralytics whom You healed.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك ياالهي تأتي علينا مثل الخطاه الذين غفرت لهم خطاياهم. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل العميان الذين فتحت لهم اعينهم. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل الخرس الذين أطلقت لهم السنتهم. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل الصم الذين فتحت لهم آذانهم. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل المخلعين الذين أنهضتم.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, come upon us as upon the dead whom You raised. Your mercies, O my God, come upon us, we Your people who cry out to You. Your mercies, O my God, come and dwell upon the heads of the righteous priests. Your mercies, O my God, come and dwell upon the heads of the monastics and laypersons. Your mercies, O my God, come and dwell upon the heads of those who labored with us in this Psalmody.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك يا الهي تأتي علينا مثل الأموات الذين اقمتهم. مراحمك ياالهي تأتي علينا نحن شعبك الصارخين إليك. مراحمك ياالهي تأتي وتحل علي رؤوس الآباء الكهنة الاطهار. مراحمك يا الهي تأتي وتحل علي رؤوس الرهبان والعلمانيين. مراحمك ياالهي تأتي وتحل علي رؤوس الإخوة الذين تعبوا معنا في هذه الابصلمودية.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               Your mercies, O my God, come and dwell upon the heads of the Orthodox Christians, from east to west and from north to south. Your mercies, O my God, come and dwell upon the heads of those gathered in this church, from oldest to youngest, men and women, elders and youth, monastics and laypersons, visitors and locals. Disregard our sins which we have committed knowingly and unknowingly, willingly and unwillingly.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               مراحمك ياالهي تأتي وتحل علي رؤوس المسيحيين الارثوذكسيين من مشارق الشمس الي مغاربها ومن الشمال الي اليمين. مراحمك ياالهي تأتي وتحل علي رؤوس كل المجتمعين في هذه البيعة المقدسة من الكبار والصغار. الرجال والنساء. الشيوخ والشبان. الرهبان والعلمانيين الغرباء وأهل المكان. اترك واغفر لنا خطايانا التي صنعناها بمعرفة وبغير معرفة. والتي صنعناها بإرادتنا وبغير ارادتنا.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               God, please forgive our trespasses that are apparent and those that are hidden, and wash our filth. Purify us from all deception, hypocrisy, and all evil; from all envy and all temptations. Loose from us all bonds of sin, all doubts and arrogance. Cast away from us all dishonest action, all gossip, all evil blasphemes, all cursing, and all evil powers for the sake of Your holy name by which we are called.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               اللهم اغفر لنا أثامنا الظاهرة والخفية واغسل ادناسنا وطَهِّرْنا من كل غش ومن كل مراياه ومن كل شر. وكل حسد وتجربة.حل عنا كل وثاقات الخطية. وكل الشكوك والكبرياء واطرد عنا كل فعل خبيث وكل نميمة. وابعد عنا كل الأقسام الحانثة. وكل لعنة وكل القوات الردية. من اجل اسمك القدوس الذي دعينا به.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="English">               O Lord, please send to us the grace of Your Holy Spirit. Have compassion on us and have mercy on us according to Your mercy. Forgive our mistakes, repose the souls of our departed, heal our sick, and return our travelers.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               اللهم أرسل علينا نعمة روحك القدوس وتحنن علينا وارحمنا كعظيم رحمتك. سامحنا بهفواتنا. نيح نفوس أسلافنا. واشف أمراضنا. ورد غربة مسافرينا.            </Language>         </Text>                  <Text>            <Language id="English">               Keep for us the life of our father the Patriarch Pope (___) and his partners in the apostolic service, the metropolitans and bishops in all places. Keep the lives of the reverent fathers, the deacons, and all Christian people, from east to west, and from north to south, keeping us and them firm in the Holy Orthodox Apostolic Church,            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               واحفظ لنا حياة السيد البطريرك أنبا ( فلان) وكذلك شركائه في الخدمة الرسولية الآباء المطارنة والأساقفة بكل مكان واحفظ حياة الآباء الكهنة والاخوة الشمامسة وسائر الشعب المسيحي من مشارق الشمس الي مغاربها. ومن الشمال الي اليمين. ويثبتنا نحن واياهم في البيعة المقدسة الجامعة الرسولية.            </Language>         </Text>                   <Text>            <Language id="English">               through the intercessions of the ever-virgin St. Mary, St. Mark the Evangelist to the land of Egypt, the angels and archangels, the patriarchs, the prophets, the apostles, the martyrs, the saints, and all those who have pleased the Lord by their good works, and do please Him until the end of ages, from the seed of our father Adam until this moment, at all times and forevermore. Amen.            </Language>            <Language id="Arabic">               بشفاعة السيدة مرت مريم البتول الطاهرة الزكية. ومارمرقص الإنجيلي الرسول كاروز الديار المصرية والملائكة ورؤساء الملائكة. والاباء والانبياء والرسل والشهداء والقديسين. وكل الذين أرضوا الرب باعمالهم الصالحة. ويرضوه الي آخر الدهور من ذرية ابينا آدم الي الان وكل أوان والي دهر الداهرين. أمين.            </Language>         </Text>      </Section>   </Season></Document>