<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik" pascha="true" fixeddatedocument="true">   <forceseason id="Fasts ^ PaschaWeek ^ AdamDays ^ Weekdays ^ Tuesdays ^ FuneralTune ^ SeasonOfAirAndFruits">      <Title>         <language id="English">Tuesday Eve (The First Hour)</language><language id="Indonesian">Malam Hari Selasa (Jam Pertama)</language>         <language id="Arabic">ليلة الثلاثاء (الساعة الاولى)</language>         <language id="Coptic">Pie~jwrh m~Psomt (}ajp 1)</language>      </Title>            <role id="Priest">         <insertdocument path="include/KhenEfranAmen"/>                  <text>            <language id="English">               The prophecies of the First Hour of the eve of Tuesday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.            </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Nubuat-nubuat dari Jam Pertama Malam Hari Selasa pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.</div></language>            <language id="Arabic">               نبوات الساعة الاولى، من ليلة الثلاثاء من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.            </language>         </text>      </role>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Zechariah 1:1-6</language><language id="Indonesian">Zakharia 1:1-6</language>               <language id="Arabic">زكريا 1: 1-6</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/prophecyIntro/Zechariah"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  N~h~r/i de qen pia~bot m~mah s~m/n n~te ]rompi m~mahc~nou] hi darioc: a~oucaji n~te Vnou] swpi ha Za,ariac p~s/ri m~Bara,iac p~s/ri n~Addw pip~rov/t/c efjw m~moc: Afjwnt n~je P[oic e~jen netenio] e~fjwm~moc je eke~joc nwou:               </language>               <language id="English">                  In the eighth month of the second year of the reign of Darius, the word of the Lord came to Zechariah, son of Berechiah, son of Addo the prophet, saying, "The Lord has been very angry with your fathers, and you shall say to them,               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dalam bulan yang kedelapan pada tahun kedua zaman Darius datanglah firman TUHAN kepada nabi Zakharia bin Berekhya bin Ido, bunyinya:"Sangat murka TUHAN atas nenek moyangmu. Sebab itu katakanlah kepada mereka:</language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وفى الشهر الثامن من السنة الثانية لداريوس. كانت كلمة الرب إلى زكريا بن براشيا بن عدو النبى قائلاً. قد غضب الرب على آبائكم قائلاً قل لهم,               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je nai ne n/e~tefjw m~mwou n~je P[oic pi pantokratwr: je kety/nou haroi ouoh a~nok hw ]nakott harwten peje P[oic pipantokratwr.               </language>               <language id="English">                  'Thus says the Lord Almighty: "Return to Me, and I will return to you," says the Lord,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Maka datanglah firman TUHAN dengan perantaraan nabi Hagai, bunyinya: Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam: Kembalilah kepada-Ku, demikianlah firman TUHAN semesta alam, maka Akupun akan kembali kepadamu, firman TUHAN semesta alam.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  هكذا ما يقوله الرب الضابط الكل أرجعوا إلى وأنا أيضاً أرجع إليكم قال الرب الضابط الكل.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh m~perswpi m~v~r/] n~netenio] etauerkalin nwou n~je nip~rov/t/c icjen swrp eujw m~moc: je nai ne n/e~tefjwm~mwou n~je P[oic pipantokratwr:               </language>               <language id="English">                  "And do not become like your fathers, whom the former prophets accused, saying, 'Thus says the Lord Almighty:               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Janganlah kamu seperti nenek moyangmu yang kepadanya para nabi yang dahulu telah menyerukan, demikian: Beginilah firman TUHAN semesta alam:               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  ولا تكونوا كابائكم الذين خاطبهم الآنبياء الأولون قائلين. هذا ما يقوله الرب الضابط الكل               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je matacye y/nou e~bolha netenmwit ethwou: nem e~bolha netenh~b/oui~ ethwou: ouoh m~pou]h~y/ou e~cwtem n~cwi peje P[oic pipantokratwr:                </language>               <language id="English">                  "Turn from your evil ways and your evil practices.''' But they did not pay attention or heed Me," says the Lord.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Berbaliklah dari tingkah lakumu yang buruk dan dari perbuatanmu yang jahat! Tetapi mereka tidak mau mendengarkan dan tidak mau menghiraukan Aku, demikianlah firman TUHAN.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  أرجعوا عن طرقكم الرديئة وعن أعمالكم الشريرة فلم يصغوا قال الرب الضابط الكل.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Auywn netenio] nem nip~rov/t/c m/ aunawnq sae~neh.                </language>               <language id="English">                  "your fathers—where are they? And the prophets—will they live forever?                </language><language id="Indonesian">Nenek moyangmu, di mana mereka? Dan para nabi, apakah mereka hidup untuk selama-lamanya?                 </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فـأين هـم آباؤكم والآنبياء فهل يحيون إلى الأبد                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Pl/n nanomoc nem nacaji sopou e~rwten: n/ a~nok e~]honhen m~mwou qen oup~neuma n~te nae~biaik nip~rov/t/c n/e~tautahe netenio]:               </language>               <language id="English">                  But receive My words and My ordinances as I commanded by My Spirit to My servants the prophets who overtook your fathers."                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Tetapi segala firman dan ketetapan-Ku yang telah Kuperintahkan kepada hamba-hamba-Ku, para nabi, bukankah itu telah sampai kepada nenek moyangmu? Maka bertobatlah mereka serta berkata:                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لكن نواميسى وأقوالى إقبلوها تلك التى أمرت بـها روح عـبيدى الآنبياء الـذين أدركوا آباءكم وخـاطبوهم قـائـلين.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh aue~rouw~ pejwou: je kata v~r/] e~tafouah cahni n~je P[oic pipatokratwr e~i~ri kata netenmwit: nem kata neten h~b/oui pair/] afi~ri nwten.               </language>               <language id="English">                  And they answered and said, "As the Lord Almighty determined to deal with us, according to our ways and according to our practices, thus He dealt with us."               </language><language id="Indonesian">Sebagaimana TUHAN semesta alam bermaksud mengambil tindakan terhadap kita sesuai dengan tingkah laku kita dan perbuatan kita, demikianlah Ia mengambil tindakan terhadap kita!"               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  كما أمـر الرب الـضابـط الكـل أن يـصنع بكم بحسب طرقكم. وكأعمالكم هكذا صنع بكم.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ProphecyConclusion"/>         </section>      </role>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Introduction to the Paschal Praise</language><language id="Indonesian">Introduction to the Paschal Praise</language>            <language id="Arabic">مقدمة تسبحة البصخة</language>         </Title>               <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PropheciesConclusion"/>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The doxology of the First Hour of the eve of Tuesday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Doksologi dari Jam Pertama Malam Hari Selasa pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.</div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  تسبحة الساعة الاولى، من ليلة الثلاثاء من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="include/LordsPrayerNoTitle"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/Doxology.1"/>            <role id="Reader">         <section expanded="true">            <Title data-section-header="true">               <language id="English">Psalm 62:6-7</language><language id="Indonesian">Psalm 62:6-7</language>               <language id="Arabic">مزمور 62: 6-7</language>            </Title>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/PsalmOfDavid"/>                        <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Paoujai nem paw~ou auqen panou]: Vnou] n~te tabo/~yia~ ouoh tahelpic acqen Vnou]:                </language>               <language id="English">                  In God is my salvation and my glory; He is the God of my help, and my hope is in God.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Hanya pada Allah saja kiranya aku tenang, sebab dari pada-Nyalah harapanku.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  خلاصى ومجدي هما بإلهي إله معونتى ورجائى هو بالله.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Kegar n~yof pe Panou] pacwt/r: paref sopt e~rof n~nakim n~houo~: all/louia.               </language>               <language id="English">                  For [indeed] He is my God and my Savior, my protector; I shall never be moved. Alleluia.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Hanya Dialah gunung batuku dan keselamatanku, kota bentengku, aku tidak akan goyah.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  لأنه إلهي ومخلصى ناصرى فلا أتزعزع أبداً. الليلويا.               </language>            </text>         </section>      </role>                  <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Luke 13:23-30</language><language id="Indonesian">Lukas 13:23-30</language>            <language id="Arabic">لوقا 13: 23-30</language>         </Title>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/KeEperto"/>         <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelIntroLuke"/>         <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Peje ouai de naf je P[oic hankouji ne n/eynanohem: n~yof de pejaf nwou:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then one said to Him, “Lord, are there few who are saved?” And He said to them,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan ada seorang yang berkata kepada-Nya: "Tuhan, sedikit sajakah orang yang diselamatkan?"                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فقال له واحد يارب أقليل هم الذين يخلصون. فأما هو فقال لهم.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je a~ria~gwnizecye e~i~e~qoun e~bolhiten piro etj/ou je ne ouon oum/s ]jw m~moc nwten nakw] n~cai~e~qoun ouoh n~nous~jemjom:               </language>               <language id="English">                  “Strive to enter through the narrow gate, for many, I say to you, will seek to enter and will not be able.               </language><language id="Indonesian">Jawab Yesus kepada orang-orang di situ: "Berjuanglah untuk masuk melalui pintu yang sesak itu! Sebab Aku berkata kepadamu: Banyak orang akan berusaha untuk masuk, tetapi tidak akan dapat.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  اجتهدوا أن تدخلوا من الباب الضيق. فأنى أقول لكم أن كثيرين سيطلبون أن يدخلوا فلا يستطيعون.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Afsan voh etwnf n~je pin/b /i ouoh n~tefs~yam m~piro: ouoh n~te tennaerh/tc nohi e~raten y/nou cabol ouoh ekwlh epiro e~retenjw m~moc:                </language>               <language id="English">                  When once the Master of the house has risen up and shut the door, and you begin to stand outside and knock at the door, saying,                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Jika tuan rumah telah bangkit dan telah menutup pintu, kamu akan berdiri di luar dan mengetok-ngetok pintu sambil berkata:                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فإذا بلغ أن يقوم رب البيت ليغلق الباب. فتبدأون بأن تقفوا خارجاً وتقرعون الباب قائلين                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Je P[oic P[oic a~ouwn nan: ouoh n~tfe~rouw~ n~tefjoc nwten: je n~]cwoun m~mwten an je n~ywten han e~bol ywn.               </language>               <language id="English">                  ‘Lord, Lord, open for us,’ and He will answer and say to you, ‘I do not know you, where you are from,’               </language><language id="Indonesian">Tuan, bukakanlah kami pintu! dan Ia akan menjawab dan berkata kepadamu: Aku tidak tahu dari mana kamu datang.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  يارب يارب أفتح لنا. فيجيبكم قائلاً. أنى لست أعرفكم من أين أنتم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Tote e~reten erh/tc n~joc: je anouwm m~pekm~yo ouoh ancw: ouoh ak]c~bw qen nenp~latia~:                </language>               <language id="English">                  Then you will begin to say, ‘We ate and drank in Your presence, and You taught in our streets.’                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Maka kamu akan berkata: Kami telah makan dan minum di hadapan-Mu dan Engkau telah mengajar di jalan-jalan kota kami.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  حينئذ تبتدئون أن تقولوا. أكلنا قدامك وشربنا. وعلمت فى شوارعنا.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh f~najoc nwten je n~]cwoun m~mwten an je n~ywten han e~bolywn: masenwten e~bolharoi t/rou niergat/c n~te ]a~dikia~:               </language>               <language id="English">                  But He will say, ‘I tell you I do not know you, where you are from. Depart from Me, all you workers of iniquity.’               </language><language id="Indonesian">Tetapi Ia akan berkata kepadamu: Aku tidak tahu dari mana kamu datang, enyahlah dari hadapan-Ku, hai kamu sekalian yang melakukan kejahatan! </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فيقول لكم أنى لا أعرفكم من أين أنتم. أذهبوا عنى يا جميع فاعلى الأثم.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Pima e~tem~mau f~naswpi n~je v~rimi nem pic~yerter n~te ninajhi: hotan a~retensannau e~Abraam nem I~caak nem Iakwb nem nip~rov/t/c t/rou qen ]metouro n~te Vnou] n~ywten de eue~hioui~ m~mwten e~bol.               </language>               <language id="English">                  There will be weeping and gnashing of teeth, when you see Abraham and Isaac and Jacob and all the prophets in the kingdom of God, and yourselves thrust out.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Di sanalah akan terdapat ratap dan kertak gigi, apabila kamu akan melihat Abraham dan Ishak dan Yakub dan semua nabi di dalam Kerajaan Allah, tetapi kamu sendiri dicampakkan ke luar.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  هناك يكون البكاء وصرير الأسنان. إذا رأيتم إبراهيم وإسحق ويعقوب وجميع الأنبياء فى ملكوت الله وأنتم تطردون خارجاً.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh eue~i~ e~bol qen niman~sai nem niman~hwtp nem pemhit nem car/c ouoh eue~roybou qen ]metouro n~te Vnou]:                </language>               <language id="English">                  They will come from the east and the west, from the north and the south, and sit down in the kingdom of God.                </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan orang akan datang dari Timur dan Barat dan dari Utara dan Selatan dan mereka akan duduk makan di dalam Kerajaan Allah.                </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  وسيأتون من المشارق والمغارب والشمال والجنوب ويتكئون فى ملكوت الله.               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="Coptic">                  Ouoh h/ppe ouon hanqaeu eunaersorp ouoh hansorp eunaer qae~.               </language>               <language id="English">                  And indeed there are last who will be first, and there are first who will be last.”               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Dan sesungguhnya ada orang yang terakhir yang akan menjadi orang yang terdahulu dan ada orang yang terdahulu yang akan menjadi orang yang terakhir."               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  فهوذا آخرون يكونون أولين وأولون يكونون آخرين.               </language>            </text>                        <insertdocument path="pascha/include/BowDownBeforeTheHolyGospel"/>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="include/GloryBeToGodForever"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/GospelConclusionEve"/>            <section expanded="true">         <Title data-section-header="true">            <language id="English">Exposition</language><language id="Indonesian">Komentari</language>            <language id="Arabic">الطرح</language>         </Title>                  <role id="Priest">            <text>               <language id="English">                  The exposition of the First Hour of the eve of Tuesday of Holy Pascha. May its blessings be with us. Amen.               </language><language id="Indonesian">                  Komentari dari Jam Pertama Malam Hari Selasa pada Pekan Paskah Suci. Kiranya berkat-berkatnya beserta kita. Amin.               </language>               <language id="Arabic">                  طرح الساعة الاولى، من ليلة الثلاثاء من البصخة المقدسة بركته علينا. آمين.               </language>            </text>         </role>                  <role id="Reader">            <text>               <language id="English">                  On His way to Jerusalem with His disciples, some one asked our Savior, “are there few who are saved?”                </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Dalam perjalanan-Nya ke Yerusalem <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">bersama para murid-Nya, seseorang </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">berkomentar kepada Juruselamat kita, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">"Sedikit orang yang akan diselamatkan.</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                  إن مخلصنا جعل مسيره إلى أورشليم مع خواصه فقال له واحد من الجمع يارب قليلون هم الذين يخلصون.                </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                   Our Savior replied saying, “Strive to enter through the narrow gate, lest you should come and knock on the door and say, ‘O Lord open (the door) unto us’;               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>"Juruselamat kita menjawab, <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">"Berusahalah keras untuk masuk </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">melalui pintu gerbang yang sempit </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">agar kamu tidak datang dan mengetuk </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">pintu dan berkata, "Ya Tuhan, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">bukakanlah kami,</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                   فأجابه مخلصنا قائلاً إحرصوا على الدخول من الباب الضيق لئلا تأتوا وتقرعوا الباب وتقولون يارب أفتح لنا.                  </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                   And He shall answer from inside and say unto you, ‘I do not know you, where you are from. Depart away all you wrongful, peccants to the place of weeping and the gnashing of teeth.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>kami," dan Dia akan menjawab dari dalam <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan berkata, “Aku tidak mengenal kamu, </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dari mana kamu berasal? Enyahlah kamu </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">semua yang berbuat dosa dan pembuat </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">kejahatan ke tempat ratapan dan </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">kertakan gigi.</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                   فيجيب هو من داخل قائلاً لكم أنى ما أعرفكم من أين أنتم أذهبوا عنى خارجاً يا جميع فاعلى الإثم حيث يكون البكاء وصرير الأسنان معاً،               </language>            </text>                     <text>               <language id="English">                   Many of the Gentiles will come from the east and the west and will nestle into the bosom of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven, but you will be neglegated outside, dominated by your profanity. Repent and expiate, that your sins may be taken away.               </language><language id="Indonesian"><div>Banyak suku bangsa akan datang dari timur <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">dan barat dan akan duduk dalam pangkuan </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">Abraham, Ishak, dan Yakub di kerajaan</span></div><div>surga, tetapi engkau akan diabaikan di luar, <span style="color: var(--main-fg);">engkau yang hidup tercemar. Bertobat dan </span><span style="color: var(--main-fg);">mengakulah, agar dosa-dosamu diampuni.”</span></div></language>               <language id="Arabic">                   كثيرون من الأمم يأتون من المشرق والمغرب فيتكئون حضن إبراهيم وإسحق ويعقوب فى ملكوت السموات وأما أنتم فسيطردونكم خارجاً وتتسلط عليكم أثامكم. فأرجعوا عن طرقكم الرديئة لكى تمحى عنكم هفواتكم.               </language>            </text>         </role>      </section>            <insertdocument path="pascha/include/ExpositionConclusion"/>      <insertdocument path="pascha/include/EveningLitaniesAndConclusionLink"/>   </forceseason></document>