<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><Document xmlns="http://www.ortodokskoptik.id/BukuBacaanKoptik">   <Section>      <Title>         <Language id="English">            Interpretation - Proverbs 1:11-35         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            تفسير – أمثال 1: 11-35         </Language>      </Title>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “My son, if sinners entice you, do not consent”, referring to those who consented to kill the Lord Jesus Christ. Satan has darkened their minds, and they were deceived by their foolishness. They did evil and saw it as right.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "يا ابني لا يضلنك الرجال المنافقون" يعني بذلك عن القوم الذين اتفقوا على قتل السيد المسيح. حيث قد أظلم الشيطان عقولهم. وتغلب عليهم الهوى. وغشاهم عمى البصيرة والحسد حتى كانوا يعلمون الضلال ويرونه حسناً.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “Do not consent. If they say, come with us, let us lie in wait to shed blood; let us lurk secretly for the innocent without cause.” The wise Solomon warns us that if we know the truth, we must stand by it and not join the fools in their foolishness. Even if standing up for the truth results in oppression.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ولا تجبهم إذا دعوك قائلين: هلم شاركنا في الدم لنختفِ في الأرض للرجل البار لغير علة" يريد الحكيم من الإنسان العاقل أنه غذا ظهر له الحق فيتمسك به ولا يتركه ولا يشارك الجهال في جهلهم. ولو ناله من جراء تعلقه بالحق الأذى.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Pontius Pilate, who is not a Jew, knew the truth. He realized that Jesus Christ is innocent, saying: “I am innocent of the blood of this just person”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن بيلاطس البنطي وهو غريب الجنس لما عرف الحق، وإن في حكمه على السيد المسيح عندما ظهرت له براءته قائلاً: "إني برئ من دم هذا البار".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            How then would a believer who knows the truth be involved with another in his sins?         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فكم يجب على المؤمن الذي يعاين الحق أن يشارك الغير في خطاياه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Let us swallow them alive like Sheol and whole, like those who go down to the pit” the Jews thought that by killing Jesus they would also kill any mention of His name. Had they known that by His death, His name would spread all over the world, and that people will believe in Him from the East to the West, they would not have sentenced Him to death.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ونبيد ذكره من الأرض" وقد ظن اليهود أنهم عندما يقتلون السيد المسيح يباد ذكره. ولو علموا أنه بموته ينتشر اسمه في جميع المسكونة. ويؤمنون باسمه من مشارق الشمس إلى مغاربها لما حكموا عليه بالموت.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “We shall find all kinds of precious possessions, we shall fill our houses with spoil.” On this point, the Jewish priests debated on the Lord Jesus Christ and said, “Look the world has gone after Him!” They thought that they would lose their positions as leaders, if they allowed Him to stay;         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "فنظفر بقنينته الثمينة. ونملأ بيوتنا غنيمة ونصيبه يصير لنا" وعلى هذا النحو تشاور كهنة اليهود على السيد المسيح وقالوا: "هوذا العالم قد ذهب وراءه" وظنوا أنهم إن أبقوه تزول منهم الرياسة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            because people were drawn to Him and almost deserted them. They conferred on His death so as to get Him out of the way, and continue being the leaders.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            لأن الشعب كان متعلقاً به وكاد أن يتركهم. تشاوروا على موته ليخلو لهم الجو وتبقى لهم رياستهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            But the opposite happened: their teachings ceased and they lost their leadership.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وكان ذلك عليهم بالعكس. لأن تعليمهم بطل ورياستهم نزعت منهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “Do not walk in the way with them.” This is a warning for the believers that they should not walk in the way of doubting, the killers, if they saw Him crucified.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لا تمش معهم في الطريق". وهذا تحذير للمؤمنين بالمسيح أنهم غذا رأوه مصلوباً لا يسيرون في طريق الشك مع القتلة.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “The fall of sinners in evil,” referring to Judas Iscariot, for while he was with the Lord, saw all His deeds, and heard His words and warnings about sin, yet remained a hypocrite.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "سقوط المنافقين شرير" يعني بذلك عن يهوذا الإسخريوطي لأنه وهو مع الرب كان يشهد أعماله ويسمع اقواله وتحذيره عن الخطايا ومع ذلك كان منافقاً.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            For even though he was present with the Lord, his heart was far away from Him. Therefore, his greediness led him into the great fall, when he “hanged himself.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            أي أنه كان حاضراً مع الرب وقلبه مصروف عنه وقد انتهى به نفاقه إلى تلك السقطة المريعة التي سقطها عندما "خنق نفسه".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “And falling headlong, he burst open in the middle and his entrails gushed out.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            "وإذ سقط على وجهه انشق من الوسط فانسكبت أحشاؤه كلها".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “So are the ways of everyone who is greedy for gain; it takes away the life of its owners,” meaning they have ruined their life by their hypocrisy when they said, “We have no king but Caesar!” They sinned against God and followed the worship of idols.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "هكذا طرق كل مولع بالإثم وبالنفاق تنزع نفوسهم" يعني أنهم أهلكوا نفوسهم بنفاقهم عند قولهم: "ليس لنا ملك إلا قيصر" فنافقوا على الرب واتبعوا عبادة الأوثان.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “Wisdom calls aloud outside,” meaning God, the Word. And his saying: “calls aloud outside” meaning that the Lord Jesus Christ is the Way to righteousness for the believers. He became the role model of perfection to them, and encouraged them to follow Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "الحكمة تنادي في الطريق" يعني بالحكمة عن الإله الكلمة. وقوله: "تنادي في الطريق" يعني أن السيد المسيح نهج للمؤمنين به طرق البر. ولم يدع سبيلاً للكمال إلا أظهره لهم وحثهم على السير فيه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “She raises her voice in the open squares” signifying the spread of the disciples’ evangelism all over the world as David the prophet said,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "وفي الشوارع تطلق صوتها" وهذا إشارة إلى انتشار بشرى التلاميذ في جميع المسكونة كقول داود النبي:         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Their line has gone out through all the earth, and their words to the end of the world.” He said, “She cries out in the chief concourses.” Concourses means strong kings, for godly wisdom has affected their hearts, and replaced idol worship. And they praised and revered the name of Jesus Christ day and night         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            فِي كُلِّ الأَرْضِ خَرَجَ مَنْطِقُهُمْ، وَإِلَى أَقْصَى الْمَسْكُونَةِ كَلِمَاتُهُمْ. جَعَلَ لِلشَّمْسِ مَسْكَنًا فِيهَا." قال: "وفي مداخل الحصون ثابتة " يعني بالحصون الملوك الأقوياء. فإن الحكمة الإلهية ولجت مداخل قلوبهم. وحطمت منها قلاع العبادة الوثنية. وبقى اسم المسيح في أفواههم يسبحونه إناء الليل وأطراف النهار.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “How long, you simple ones, will you love simplicity?” Meaning that they have rejected knowledge, and have not tried to learn about the Messiah, so much that they became illiterate, not seeking knowledge.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "إلى متى أيها الجهال تحبون الجهل" يعني أنهم تركوا العلم ولم يفحصوا عن المسيح المنتظر حتى أصبحوا جهالاً لا يميلون إلى العلم لتغافلهم عنه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “For scorners delight in their scorning, and fools hate knowledge.” They are fools and follow their own desires. They don’t accept rebuking for their foolishness.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "والحمقى يبغضون العلم بالتوبيخ" يعني أنهم لحماقتهم وسيرهم حسب أهوائهم لا يقبلون التوبيخ على جهلهم.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said, “Surely, I will pour out my spirit on you; I will make my words known to you.” This was fulfilled when the disciples were gathered on Thursday and the Holy Spirit descended upon them. “And began to speak with other tongues, as the Spirit gave them utterance.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "أفيض عليكم من روحي وأعلمكم كلامي" وقد تم ذلك حينما كان التلاميذ مجتمعين في يوم الخمسين حيث حل الروح القدس على الجمع" وبدأوا يتكلمون بألسنة أخرى كما أعطاهم الروح أن ينطقوا".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            Fulfilling what was spoken, by the prophet Joel: “And it shall come to pass in the last days, says God that I will pour out My Spirit on all flesh.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وهذا ليتم "ما قيل بيوئيل النبي . يقول الله ويكون في الأيام الأخيرة أني أسكب من روحي على كل بشر".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “I have called, and you refused,” meaning that He called them to believe in Him, but they didn’t accept. He performed many miracles and amazing signs before them, but they would not believe in Him. For He used to say to them, “But if I do, though you do not believe Me, believe the works, that you may know and believe that the Father is in Me, and I in Him.” Because of the hardness of their hearts, they didn’t listen to His words.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "لأني دعوت فأبيتم" يعني أنه دعاهم إلى الإيمان به فلم يسمعوا له. وعمل قدامهم الآيات الباهرة فلم يؤمنوا به فآمنوا بالأعمال لكي تعرفوا وتؤمنوا أن الآب فيَّ وأنا فيه". ولكنهم لقساوة قلوبهم لم يذعنوا إلى قوله.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “I have stretched out my hand and no one regarded because you disdained all my counsel.” When the Lord stretched His arms on the cross,         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ومددت يدي فلم يكن من يلتفت وأطرحهم كل مشورة مني" يعني بهذا أن الرب لما يبسط يده على الصليب         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            And they witnessed the signs that occurred: the sun darkened, the dead were raised, the veil of the temple was torn and the earth trembled. Despite all these, they didn’t believe in Him. Their hearts became dull that even with all these signs, they blasphemed Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ورأوا العلامات التي حدثت من إظلام الشمس وقيام الموتى. وانشقاق حجاب الهيكل. وتشقيق الصخور. ومع هذا كله لم يهتدوا إلى الإيمان به. بل غلظت قلوبهم حتى أنهم مع وجود هذه العلامات. وكانوا يجدفون عليه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “Then they will call on me, but I will not answer,” because of their persistent disobedience for “God does not hear sinners.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "حينئذ يدعونني فلا أجب" لاستمرارهم في المعاصي لأن "الله لا يسمع للخطاة" يعني أنهم أبغضوا الإيمان بالرب ورفضوا أقواله.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            As our Lord had said: “They hated Me without a cause.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            ولذلك قال له المجد: "أنهم أبغضوني بلا سبب".         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He said: “They would have none of my counsel, and despised my every rebuke.” For the Lord used to say, “For if you do not believe that I am He, you will die in your sins.” They didn’t accept His rebuke, and rejected His words.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "ولم يقبلوا مشورتي واستهانوا بكل توبيخ مني" لأنه له المجد كان يقول لهم: "لأنكم لم تؤمنوا أني أنا هو تموتون في خطاياكم" فلم يقبلوا منه. بل رذلوا كلامه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            “Whoever listens to me will dwell safely, and will be secure, without fear of evil;” referring to those who believe in the Lord Jesus Christ, hear His word, follow and obey them. Then they will receive everlasting life, which He promised to all who believe in Him.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            قال: "والسامع لي يسكن دعة مطمئناً من كل شر" يعني أن الذي يؤمن بربنا يسوع المسيح ويسمع أقواله ويعمل بها فإنه ينال الحياة الدائمة التي وعد بها مؤمنيه.         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            For He said, “That everyone who see the Son and believes in Him may have everlasting life; and I will raise him up in the last day,” and will be “secure, without fear of evil.”         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            حيث قال: "أن كل من يرى الابن ويؤمن به تكون له حياة أبدية وأنا أقيمه في اليوم الأخير" ويكون "مطمئناً من كل شر"         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            He will take away the fear that will overshadow the wicked on the resurrection and the awful judgment day. He will forever be happy with His Christ and Savior.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            وينزع عنه الخوف الذي يكون مستولياً على الأشرار يوم القيامة والدينونة المفزعة. ويكون دائماً فرحاً بمسيحه وفاديه،         </Language>      </Text>            <Text>         <Language id="English">            To Him be glory forever, Amen.         </Language>         <Language id="Arabic">            الذي له المجد دائماً. آمين.         </Language>      </Text>   </Section>       </Document>